<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138647</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-25259</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Systematic Review of Reporting Tools Applicable to Sexual and Reproductive Health Programmes: Step 1 in Developing Programme Reporting Standards</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Systematic Review of SRH Programme Reporting Tools</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Kågesten</surname>
<given-names>Anna</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Tunçalp</surname>
<given-names>Ӧzge</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Ali</surname>
<given-names>Moazzam</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="econtrib001" ref-type="fn"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Chandra-Mouli</surname>
<given-names>Venkatraman</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="econtrib001" ref-type="fn"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Tran</surname>
<given-names>Nhan</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<xref rid="econtrib001" ref-type="fn"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Gülmezoglu</surname>
<given-names>A. Metin</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="econtrib001" ref-type="fn"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Population, Family and Reproductive Health, Johns Hopkins School of Public Health, Baltimore, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>WHO Department of Reproductive Health and Research, including UNDP/UNFPA/UNICEF/WHO/World Bank Special Programme of Research, Development and Research Training in Human Reproduction, World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Implementation Research Platform, Alliance for Health Policy and Systems Research, World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Deoraj</surname>
<given-names>Alok</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Florida International University, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AK ÖT. Performed the experiments: AK ÖT. Analyzed the data: AK ÖT. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AK ÖT MA VCM NT AMG. Wrote the paper: AK ÖT MA VCM NT AMG.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="econtrib001">
<p>‡ These authors also contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">akaagesten@jhu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>29</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<elocation-id>e0138647</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>10</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>1</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Kågesten et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138647" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Complete and accurate reporting of programme preparation, implementation and evaluation processes in the field of sexual and reproductive health (SRH) is essential to understand the impact of SRH programmes, as well as to guide their replication and scale-up.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Objectives</title>
<p>To provide an overview of existing reporting tools and identify core items used in programme reporting with a focus on programme preparation, implementation and evaluation processes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>A systematic review was completed for the period 2000–2014. Reporting guidelines, checklists and tools, irrespective of study design, applicable for reporting on programmes targeting SRH outcomes, were included. Two independent reviewers screened the title and abstract of all records. Full texts were assessed in duplicate, followed by data extraction on the focus, content area, year of publication, validation and description of reporting items. Data was synthesized using an iterative thematic approach, where items related to programme preparation, implementation and evaluation in each tool were extracted and aggregated into a consolidated list.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Out of the 3,656 records screened for title and abstracts, full texts were retrieved for 182 articles, out of which 108 were excluded. Seventy-four full text articles corresponding to 45 reporting tools were retained for synthesis. The majority of tools were developed for reporting on intervention research (n = 15), randomized controlled trials (n = 8) and systematic reviews (n = 7). We identified a total of 50 reporting items, across three main domains and corresponding sub-domains: programme preparation (objective/focus, design, piloting); programme implementation (content, timing/duration/location, providers/staff, participants, delivery, implementation outcomes), and programme evaluation (process evaluation, implementation barriers/facilitators, outcome/impact evaluation).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Over the past decade a wide range of tools have been developed to improve the reporting of health research. Development of Programme Reporting Standards (PRS) for SRH can fill a significant gap in existing reporting tools. This systematic review is the first step in the development of such standards. In the next steps, we will draft a preliminary version of the PRS based on the aggregate list of identified items, and finalize the tool using a consensus process among experts and user-testing.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The current study was funded by the Alliance for Health Policy and Systems Research (AHPSR), hosted by the WHO (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/alliance-hpsr/about/en/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.who.int/alliance-hpsr/about/en/</ext-link>). Nhan Tran at AHPSR contributed with materials and preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="1"/>
<table-count count="2"/>
<page-count count="19"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are included in the article text and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Reporting of the key implementation elements of programmes in the field of sexual and reproductive health (SRH) is essential to understand the impact of the programmes, as well as to guide the efforts for future replication and scale-up. Indeed, readers of a programme report or publication need clear and complete information about the programme components, their development, implementation and evaluation, to be able to assess its quality as well as replicate the programme model [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. However, the reality is that many programmes report on results and impacts without describing how, when, where and under what conditions programmes were developed and implemented [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In a systematic review on comprehensive adolescent health programmes inclusive of SRH services, Kågesten et al. [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] found substantial inconsistencies in the depth and scope of programme component descriptions. In both the peer-reviewed and grey literature, many publications and reports lacked a clear description of programme activities and their implementation. Consequently, programmes may demonstrate impact without providing details as to how results were obtained and how components can be replicated. The lack of an adequate description of implementation processes is not unique to program reporting, but widely recognized in relation to the reporting of clinical trials and other research designs. For example, Chalmers and Glasziou [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] estimated that over 30% of clinical trials and over 50% of planned study outcomes were not sufficiently described in publications, representing “billions of dollars” in avoidable reporting waste. Further analyses showed that between 40% and 89% of biomedical interventions were non-replicable because of inadequate description of intervention components [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p>
<p>The key underlying reason for varying quality and levels of details is the absence of standards for programme reporting in SRH. In 1996, the lack of adequate reporting on randomized clinical trials prompted the development of the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], and subsequent statements have been developed for reporting on study designs beyond randomized controlled trials such as non-randomized evaluations [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and qualitative studies [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. However, scholars increasingly emphasize the need for greater clarity on what and how to report in relation to programme preparation, implementation and evaluation processes to better facilitate replication and scale up irrespective of the study design used [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p>
<p>In response to this gap, the World Health Organization (WHO) Department of Reproductive Health and Research, including the UNDP/UNFPA/UNICEF/WHO/World Bank Special Programme of Research, Development and Research Training in Human Reproduction (HRP), in partnership with the Alliance for Health Policy and Systems Research hosted by the WHO, initiated a consultative process to develop Programme Reporting Standards (PRS) to be used by programme implementers and researchers in the field of SRH. The overall goal is to improve the quality of programme reporting in order to allow others to replicate the programme, as well as to better understand and document the success and barriers in its implementation. In line with recommendations for developing reporting guidelines provided by Moher et al [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], the current systematic review is the first step in the development of the PRS. The objectives of the systematic review are two-fold: 1) to provide an overview of available reporting guidelines and tools that have been used, or are suitable to use, for SRH programmes; and 2) identify core items used in programme reporting with a focus on programme preparation, implementation and evaluation processes, to be included in a draft tool.</p>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Defining key terms</title>
<p>Our primary interest for the present review is the reporting of programmes, whether by researchers or programmers. According to the Dictionary of Epidemiology [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], a programme is a “(formal) set of procedures to conduct an activity, e.g. control of malaria”, whereas an intervention study involves an “intentional change in some aspect of the status of subjects, e.g. introduction of a preventive or therapeutic regimen or an intervention designed to test a hypothesized relationship”. A programme may or may not be interventional in nature. However, because these terms are often taken to mean the same thing, we used the terms <italic>programme</italic> and <italic>intervention</italic> interchangeably to refer to a formal set of prevention, promotion and/or intervention activities. [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] We further used the term <italic>programme components</italic> in reference to the elements or activities that comprise a programme.</p>
<p>A key challenge in reviewing literature on reporting tools is the highly varying terminology used to describe programmes [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. When describing individual studies, we therefore strived to retain the terminology used in the original publications. Finally, we used the terms <italic>items</italic> and <italic>reporting items</italic> interchangeably to refer to items included in reporting checklists or other tools (for example, the CONSORT statement has 21 items). Our goal was to identify a set of core items for potential inclusion in a PRS tool focused on SRH.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>We used a modified version of the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) statement [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] to conceptualize and carry out the current systematic review. Each step of the review was specified in a protocol for the overall PRS project (the protocol was not published but it is available in <xref rid="pone.0138647.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Text</xref>).</p>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Eligibility criteria</title>
<p>For the purpose of this review, we included any study or article that described a reporting guideline or tool that has been used, or would be suitable to use, for reporting on programmes in the field of SRH. In line with Moher et al [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], we defined a reporting guideline as a “checklist, flow diagram, or explicit text to guide authors in reporting a specific type of research”. Because the focus of our review extended beyond research reporting, we also included checklists or guiding texts developed for programme reporting outside of academia (e.g. by implementing organizations and donors). For the purposes of simplicity, from hereon we refer to all guidelines, checklists and other guiding specifications as “tools”. Finally, we included articles that outlined narrative recommendations for programme reporting, even if these did not present official tools. All included articles had to describe a tool or provide unique recommendations relevant to programme reporting, and be published between January 2000 and September 2014. We chose not to limit the search by programme or study design in order to capture as many relevant tools as possible. No language restrictions were applied.</p>
<p>As mentioned above, reporting tools had to have been used, <italic>or be applicable to use</italic>, for reporting on programmes targeting SRH outcomes. In line with the WHO’s mandate on SRH [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], such outcomes include but are not limited to: maternal mortality and morbidity, abortion, sexually transmitted infections and HIV prevention and treatment including mother-to-child transmission, adolescent pregnancy, family planning, safe abortion care, pregnancy and childbirth care, postnatal care of mother and newborn, and prevention and management of gender-based violence. By the term ‘applicable to use’, we mean tools used in the wider field of public health and medicine that may be relevant or suitable for SRH programmes even though the tools were not developed specifically for such outcomes (given that many of the issues central to programme reporting are not unique to the field of SRH). Two reviewers (AK, ÖT) evaluated which tools were applicable for inclusion. Those excluded were 1) tools that were minor modifications of an already established tool; 2) studies that merely assessed the quality of reporting or reviewed existing reporting tools; and 3) comments or editorials about a tool (unless these elaborated on items not otherwise included in existing tools).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Information sources and search strategy</title>
<p>We searched six electronic databases: PubMed, Scopus, PsychInfo, Embase, MEDLINE and Global Health for the period January 2000 through September 2014. All database searches were run during the week of 1 September 2014. We developed a core search strategy combining MeSH terms with key words for use in PubMed. The strategy was built in three blocks: reporting tool/guideline AND programme/intervention AND SRH/Health, and further adapted according to the standards and relevant MeSH terms for each database. The full search strategy for each database is available in <xref rid="pone.0138647.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>.</p>
<p>For the grey literature, we conducted a focused search on identifying reporting tools used by donors. The selection of donors was based on those providing support to the HRP. Website searches of implementing organizations in the field of SRH were beyond the scope of the current review. Such organizations will, however, be included in the next steps of the PRS development. Other sources of data included reference lists of key articles and background documents [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], one example being a review about reporting guidelines in health research [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. We also searched the library for the Enhancing the QUAlity and Transparency of Health Research (EQUATOR) network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/library/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.equator-network.org/library/</ext-link>), a resource bank of reporting guidelines. The latter search was focused on tools for reporting on interventions and implementation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Study selection</title>
<p>Following the search process, two reviewers (AK, ÖT) divided all records and independently screened the titles and abstracts. Full texts were obtained for all articles that passed the initial screening. The same two reviewers (AK, ÖT) assessed all full texts, in duplicate, with inconsistencies resolved through discussion. Full texts were included if they met all inclusion criteria; all reasons for exclusion were recorded.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Data extraction</title>
<p>Data was extracted using a standardized template across the following domains (see <xref rid="pone.0138647.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref> for a detailed summary of the extracted data):</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Background details (author(s), year(s) of publication, journal(s) or other sources).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Focus of tool (e.g. for reporting on a specific study design).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Content area (e.g. for reporting in a specific field such as HIV).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Number and description of reporting items included in the tool, or a summary of the recommended items for reporting if described in narrative format.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Number and description of reporting items specific to programme preparation, implementation and evaluation.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Validation (piloting or other modes of testing or validating the tool).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Each tool could have one or more sources; that is, data concerning the same tool could be extracted from different journal publications. One person in the research team (AK) extracted data from each included article. A second reviewer (ÖT) verified the extracted data for a random sample of 20% of included tools; inter-rater consistency (proportion of agreement) was over 95%.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Synthesis of results</title>
<p>We applied an iterative, thematic approach to the synthesis of textual data from the included tools. Based on the number of items specific to programme preparation, implementation and evaluation, tools were initially ranked into high (all items or overall focus of tool), moderate (some items even if not the focus of the tool, or narrative discussion or relevant reporting themes) or low (one item or less, not the focus of the tool) relevance. In the first step, all extracted items were reviewed for their applicability to programme reporting and aggregated into a compiled list. This list included the original item, a brief description and its corresponding tool. In the next step, we used an inductive coding process where each item was coded according to its programme reporting domain (e.g. implementation outcome) and potential sub-domains (e.g. fidelity). We conducted iterative reviews of the extracted items to identify and refine domains and sub-domains, during which items and codes that were similar or redundant were merged. Items that were judged by the reviewers as inapplicable to programme preparation, implementation and evaluation processes were removed. This distinction was based on items already included in existing guidelines for reporting on study designs and results (e.g. CONSORT or non-randomized alternatives). The final list of items was organized according to their main corresponding domain and sub-domain. Because of the nature of the review, where the main focus was to provide a narrative description of items, the reporting of analytical comparative measures such as odds ratios were not applicable.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Assessment of quality</title>
<p>Similar to previous systematic reviews of reporting guidelines [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], we did not appraise the methodological quality of tools, including of risk of bias within and across studies. The rationale for this was that the review sought to describe existing programme reporting tools rather than assess the quality of reporting, or the effectiveness or impact of programmes. As part of the synthesis process, there was an assessment on whether existing tools had been piloted or used widely based on the reported use in different geographical settings or endorsement by organizations and/or journals.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Characteristics of included tools</title>
<p>We screened the title and abstract of 3,656 records. Full texts were retrieved for 182 articles of which 108 were excluded; all reasons for exclusion were recorded. In total, 74 full text articles were retained for data extraction (<xref rid="pone.0138647.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0138647.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138647.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>PRISMA 2009 Flowchart of screening and data extraction process.</title>
<p>The majority of articles (96%) were published in peer-reviewed journals, the most common being BMC Medical Education or BMC Medical Research Methodology (8%), PLoS Medicine (7%) and Journal of Clinical Epidemiology (7%). The included articles corresponded to 45 tools (<xref rid="pone.0138647.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) retained for synthesis.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138647.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pone.0138647.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138647.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Overview of included tools, by relevance to the current systematic review.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0138647.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138647.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>High Relevance</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tool (in alphabetical order)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Focus of tool</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Content area</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Nr of items</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Source</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Complexity spectrum checklist</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized controlled trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex intervention trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. CONSORT statement–proposed addition</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized controlled trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Implementation reporting</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. CONSORT–SPI statement (on-going development)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized controlled trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social and psychological intervention trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. CONSORT statement–unofficial extension</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized controlled trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavioural medicine intervention trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Reporting on development and evaluation of complex interventions in healthcare (CReDECI) guideline</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Development and evaluation of complex interventions in healthcare</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. Guidelines for reporting evidence-based practice educational interventions (GREET) statement (on-going development)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description of educational evidence-based practice strategies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7. Implementation research framework for health sciences</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Implementation research</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Framework for implementation research in health</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8. Oxford Implementation Index</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systematic reviews</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Implementation data in systematic reviews</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9. Program evaluation and monitoring system (PEMS)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Program evaluation and monitoring</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIV Prevention</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10. PROGRESS-Plus checklist</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Equity lens for reporting on interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11. Reporting of HIV interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality of study methods in HIV prevention interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12. Reporting of implementation for injury prevention initiatives</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systematic reviews</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Injury prevention implementation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13. Reporting of nursing interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content of complex nursing interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14. Reporting of public health interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public health interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15. Reporting of tailored interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tailored interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16. Structured assessment of feasibility (SAFE) checklist</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feasibility of complex interventions in mental health services</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17. Standards for quality improvement reporting excellence (SQUIRE) guidelines</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality improvement interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18. Integrated checklist for determinants of practice (TICD)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Determinants of practice</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health care and chronic disease</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19. Template for intervention description and replication (TIDieR) statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description of interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20. Transparent Reporting of Evaluations with Nonrandomized Designs (TREND) statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, non-randomized design</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evaluation of public health/behavioural interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21. Workgroup for intervention development and evaluation research (WIDER) statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Components of behaviour change interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Moderate Relevance</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tool (in alphabetical order)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Focus of tool</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Content area</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Nr of items</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Source</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22. CONSORT statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized controlled trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23. CONSORT statement–extension</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized controlled trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-pharmacological treatments</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24. CONSORT–EHEALTH statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evaluations of web-based and mobile health interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25. CONSORT statement–extension</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized controlled trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pragmatic trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26. Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ) statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative studies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interviews and focus groups</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27. Guidance for Reporting Involvement of Patients and Public (GRIPP) checklist</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients and public involvement in research</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health technology/health services</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28. Preferred reporting standards in systematic reviews and meta-analyses (PRISMA) statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systematic reviews</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29. PRISMA–Equity statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systematic reviews</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health equity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30. Reporting of internet interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internet</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31. Reporting of public health programs in Colorado</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Program reporting</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public health program reporting system</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32. Statement on reporting of evaluation studies in health informatics (STARE–HI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evaluation studies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evaluation of health informatics systems</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Low Relevance</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tool (in alphabetical order)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Focus of tool</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Content area</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Nr of items</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Source</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33. Checklist for systematic reviews of non-randomized studies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systematic reviews, non-randomized designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized studies of health care interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34. Consolidated Health Economic Evaluation Reporting Standards (CHEERS) statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, economic evaluations</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Economic evaluations of health care interventions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35. Checklist to evaluate report of non-pharmacological trials (CLEAR NPT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized controlled trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-pharmacological treatments</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36. Enhancing transparency in reporting the synthesis of qualitative research (ENTREQ)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systematic reviews</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative research synthesis</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37. International Society for Pharmacoeconomics and Outcomes Research checklist for cost-effectiveness analysis alongside clinical trials (ISPOR RCT-CEA)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized controlled trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cost-effectiveness alongside clinical trials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38. Reporting guidelines for observational longitudinal studies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observational studies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal health and medical research</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39. Reporting guidelines for survey research</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey research</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40. Reporting qualitative research in health informatics (REQ-HI) recommendations</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative research</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health informatics</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41. Rural and Remote Health Journal guideline</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural and remote health</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42. Standards for reporting on diagnostic accuracy studies (STARD) statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnostic accuracy studies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43. Strengthening reporting of genetic associations (STREGA) statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observational</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genetic association studies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44. STandards for Reporting Interventions in Clinical Trials of Acupuncture (STRICTA) statement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention research, all study designs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acupuncture</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45. STrengthening the Reporting of OBservational studies in Epidemiology (STROBE statement)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observational</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>Note: N/A means that the tool did not present an official list of items, but included a narrative description of important reporting elements.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The majority of tools were developed for reporting on intervention research (n = 15), randomized controlled trials (n = 8) and systematic reviews (n = 7). Other guideline focuses included observational studies (n = 3), diagnostic accuracy (n = 2), qualitative studies (n = 2), survey research (n = 1), general study designs (n = 1), determinants of practice (n = 1), patient/public involvement in research (n = 1), programme evaluation and monitoring (n = 1) programme reporting (n = 1), evaluation studies (n = 1) and implementation research (n = 1).</p>
<p>Reporting tools covered a wide range of content areas such as behaviour change, health informatics, mobile or e-health, equity, nursing and complex interventions. Of the included tools, three described reporting items specific to SRH (for example, details on sexual partners or HIV status) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The majority of tools presented a checklist of core items for reporting (ranging from 6–58 items), while others (n = 8) used a narrative description of essential reporting elements. About half the tools did not include items or topics specific to the description of programme preparation, implementation or evaluation. However, some tools listed items or included a narrative description of topics that could be indirectly related to these topics, such as a description of unexpected events that in turn may affect implementation.</p>
<p>Overall, 21 tools were ranked as having a high relevance to the present review, 11 were ranked as moderate and 13 as low relevance in line with the criteria described earlier. Four tools are especially worth mentioning because of their high relevance and recent publication. First, the template for intervention description and replication (TIDieR) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] published in 2014 provide an itemized checklist for reporting on intervention studies, including items such as the intervention name, rationale, materials, procedures (how, by whom, when and where delivery occurred), as well as the dose, modifications and fidelity to the intervention. Secondly, in 2013 the workgroup for intervention development and evaluation research (WIDER) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] outlined a number of recommendations for describing the development, content, setting, mode of delivery, intensity, duration, and fidelity of behavior change interventions. Thirdly, in 2013 Peters et al [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] proposed a set of guiding questions for reporting implementation research, including the description of implementation strategies, context, complexity and real-world conditions. The implementation terminology presented as part of this framework [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] was also used to organize the findings from the current review. Finally, in 2003, Davidson et al [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] provided eight recommendations for minimal detail in the reporting of behavioral medicine interventions, including content/elements, provider, format, setting, recipient, intensity, duration and fidelity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Description of items</title>
<p>A total of 226 items related to programme preparation, implementation and evaluation processes were extracted and further consolidated into 50 items for potential inclusion in a PRS tool for SRH programmes. Items that were similar across multiple tools were merged, and the wording of items was changed accordingly. Where applicable, the wording was also changed from <italic>intervention</italic> to <italic>programme</italic> to better correspond to the purposes of the current review. The final list of items, their descriptions, corresponding domains and sub-domains, and sources are presented in <xref rid="pone.0138647.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0138647.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138647.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Reporting items related to programme preparation, implementation and evaluation.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0138647.t002g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138647.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domain</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sub-domain</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Programme preparation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Objective/Focus</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Programme name</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name of programme [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Objectives and anticipated impact of programme (why)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anticipated short-term and long-term influences of programme on individual participants as well as wider implications [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Target population</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics of the target population planned to be reached and at what level (individual, group, wider population) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Organization/agency</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mention the name, credentials and affiliations of the organization(s) developing the programme [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Funding source</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name of programme donor/funding source(s) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. Programme design process</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description of the process of designing the programme [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7. Theoretical foundation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Underlying theory and/or logic model of the programme [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], with details for how this theory guided the programme design and messages [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8. Program manual</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whether a manual or protocol existed for the programme [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], and where this can be accessed [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9. Implementation strategy</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Details on whether an implementation strategy was developed [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], and if any research questions were specific to implementation [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10. Evaluation plans</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detail any evaluation plans, both to assess programme implementation/process and to evaluate the programme’s impact/results [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piloting</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11. Piloting of activities</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whether programme activities were piloted, and if so detail how, when, by whom and the results [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Programme implementation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12. Components/activities</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Define and describe the content of programme activities in enough detail to allow replication [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. If a control group was used, the content of any activities assigned to the control should also be described [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13. Complexity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Degree of complexity of the activities, such as whether single or multiple components were included [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14. Standardisation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whether the content of components/activities followed a standardised protocol or curriculum [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15. Innovation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Degree of innovation as part of the programme [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16. Materials</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of materials used [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and where these can be accessed if applicable [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Timing, duration, location</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17. Timing (when)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Timing and duration of the programme (start and finish) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18. Setting (where)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key aspects of the programme setting [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>], including geographical context (e.g. country, rural/urban) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], single/multiple locations [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], type of context [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] such as “real-world” or clinical [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], and any infrastructure required [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19. Dose and intensity (how much)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of sessions/activities, how often activities were delivered [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], whether the frequency of activities was predetermined or varying [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], and the intensity or duration of each activity [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Providers/staff</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20. Provider characteristics (Who)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organization(s)/agencies involved in delivering the programme activities [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] (name and type) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], number of staff and their responsibilities [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], staff characteristics including demographics, professions, experience, education and technical skills required [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21. Provider/staff training</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Details on how programme staff was recruited, trained and supervised to deliver activities (when, how and by whom) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22. Provider reflexivity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reflection about the relationship between providers and participants, such as whether participants knew the staff [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], influences of professional opinions and the self-efficacy of providers[<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23. Participant recruitment</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Process of recruiting programme participants [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24. Participants (to whom)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics of participants that actually received the programme [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Report subgroups by key demographic factors such as age, biological sex/gender, socioeconomic status, education level, religion [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], HIV status, and nr of sexual partners [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Note participant risk profiles, if any (e.g. disadvantaged populations) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25. Participant preparation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whether anything was done to prepare or brief participants prior to the start of the programme [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delivery</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26. Methods used to deliver activities (how)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific methods/channels used for delivering programme activities [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>], degrees of human interactivity [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], level of involvement [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], technology required [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27. Efforts to ensure fidelity of participants</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Efforts to ensure fidelity, increase participation, compliance or adherence, and reduce contamination [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], such as incentives or compensation [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28. Efforts to ensure fidelity of providers/staff</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Efforts to enhance adherence of providers [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] such as staff meetings [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], support [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], incentives [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], feedback [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], motivation [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and supervision [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Implementation outcomes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29. Acceptability</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perception and comfort among stakeholders about the programme, its relative advantage and credibility [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30. Appropriateness</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perceived fit or relevance of the intervention as judged by the implementers [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31. Feasibility/practicality</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The actual fit, utility or suitability of the programme for the everyday life of participants [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32. Adoption</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uptake/utilization of programme [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Difference in uptake by intervention or control groups, if applicable [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33. Coverage/Reach</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The spread or penetration of the programme components [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34. Attrition</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-participation and dropout of participants [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], along with reasons for why [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35. Unexpected end of programme</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whether the programme ended or stopped earlier than planned, along with reasons for why [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36. Reversibility</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whether it would be possible to stop the programme without negative or harmful effects [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37. Contamination of activities</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unanticipated spread of activities outside of the programme target population [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38. Fidelity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whether the programme was delivered as intended, e.g. discrepancies between the programme design and the actual implementation of components and methods in the "real life context" [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39. Reasons for low fidelity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reasons for any deviation from planned activities or others parts of the programme design [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40. Sustainability</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extent to which participants may be able to use the programme in their everyday life, for example whether any support structures are in place to maintain behaviour changes [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], what happened after the program [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], whether any follow-up sessions are planned [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41. Costs of implementation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Costs and required resources for implementation [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], including time, human resources, materials, set-up, administration [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], delivery strategy [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Programme evaluation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Process evaluation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42. Process or implementation evaluation methods</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method that was used to assess implementation outcomes [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. For example, how fidelity was monitored and measured [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43. Effect of implementation process on results</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whether the implementation process affected results and quality of the programme results [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44. External events affecting implementation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant external events occurring at the time of intervention (e.g. social political, economic and/or geographical), which might have affected the implementation [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45. Ethical considerations</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethical issues that might have affected the implementation [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Implementation barriers and facilitators</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46. Implementation barriers and facilitators</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detailed description of factors hindering and facilitating implementation of the programme [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47. Strengths and limitations</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Appraise weaknesses [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and strengths [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] in the programme design, what worked and what can be improved [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Impact/results evaluation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48. Outcome evaluation methods</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">How programme results/impact was evaluated [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], differentiating between effectiveness, efficacy and cost savings [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49. Unexpected/negative effects</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any unexpected and/or negative effects of the programme [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50. Differential effects</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whether the programme effects differed according based on characteristics such as biological sex/gender, ethnicity, socioeconomic status, age, geographic location [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>The items were organized according to three main domains: 1) programme preparation, 2) program implementation, and 3) programme evaluation processes. A number of corresponding sub-domains were also identified. The following section provides a brief description of each domain and sub-domain.</p>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Programme preparation</title>
<p>Three sub-domains were identified which related to programme preparation or planning. These include the programme’s <italic>objective/focus</italic> (overall goal, anticipated impact, and target population); how the programme was <italic>designed</italic> (organization(s) and donors involved in developing the program, theory of change or logic model, the process of designing programme activities, existence of a manual/protocol and implementation strategy); and <italic>piloting</italic> (whether and how activities were piloted, along with results from the pilot).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019">
<title>Programme implementation</title>
<p>Six sub-domains emerged related to programme implementation. <italic>Programme content</italic> refers to the actual content of programme activities described with enough detail to allow replication; the complexity, number, level and innovation of activities; materials used and where to locate these. <italic>Timing</italic>, <italic>duration and location</italic> include items describing when and where programme activities were delivered, and the dose and intensity of activities. <italic>Programme providers/staff</italic> refer to who conducted the activities, as well as the training, characteristics, responsibilities and reflexivity of delivering staff. <italic>Programme participants</italic> cover who the actual recipients were; how participants were recruited and any preparation prior to the start of activities. Furthermore, <italic>programme delivery</italic> items describe how the programme activities were delivered; materials used; and efforts to ensure fidelity of both participants and staff. Finally, <italic>programme implementation outcomes</italic> refer to the actual acceptability and adoption of the programme; its coverage/reach, feasibility, modification, fidelity and reasons for low fidelity; appropriateness, implementation costs, reversibility, sustainability and unexpected events among other items.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020">
<title>Programme evaluation</title>
<p>With regard to programme evaluation processes, three sub-domains were identified. <italic>Process or implementation evaluation</italic> includes items describing process evaluation methods; how the implementation process might have affected results; contextual/external events; and ethical considerations affecting implementation. <italic>Implementation barriers and facilitators</italic> relate to factors hindering or facilitating implementation, as well as appraised strengths and limitations of the overall programme. Finally, <italic>impact/outcome evaluation</italic> items describe the process of evaluating programme outcomes (differentiating between effectiveness, efficacy and cost savings) or any upcoming evaluation plans, and whether the programme had any unexpected negative or differential effects.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec021" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>While there is growing evidence about “what works” to improve SRH outcomes, less is known about “how-to” implement, replicate and scale-up programmes [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Many programmes describe outcomes and results but do not provide enough detail to allow others to understand what exactly was done, the evidence, and lessons learnt from implementation barriers and/or facilitators. The current systematic review sought to provide an overview of tools that may be used for reporting on SRH programmes, and to further identify core items for programme reporting.</p>
<p>We found that over the past decade a wide range of tools have been developed to improve the reporting of health research. Most of the identified tools were essentially guidelines for reporting on research study design and results and included none or few items relevant to programme reporting. A number of tools were, however, of greater relevance. In particular, recent tools such as TIDieR [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and WIDER [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] may substantially improve the reporting of interventions using both randomized and non-randomized designs. For example, the TIDieR checklist [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] is a comprehensive list of items for reporting on how, where, when, by whom and with what fidelity interventions were implemented, thus moving beyond the single item provision of “sufficient” details on the intervention in order to allow replication used in guidelines such as CONSORT.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, these tools were developed specifically for intervention <italic>research</italic> and reporting in peer-reviewed journals. Although there seem to be increasing numbers of programme evaluations published in peer-reviewed journals and the existence of journals for this purpose (e.g. <italic>Global Health</italic>: <italic>Science and Practice</italic>), it is probably fair to assume that a significant proportion of programme reports are published on the web or in print outside the peer-reviewed journals. Deficiencies remain in the above frameworks for programme reporting, specifically as it relates to reporting of implementation strategies and outcomes. As recently noted by Glasziou et al [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], there is need for improved reporting beyond peer-reviewed journals that focus “more broadly at the multiple and various forms in which research processes and findings are reported”. Many programmes operate under complex, real world conditions making it difficult to communicate exactly what is being done, and how, in a timely and consistent manner. Coordinators, implementers, managers as well as researchers thus need a standardized way of documenting and reporting implementation strategies and outcomes throughout the course of the programme so that others can learn from their experiences. As a result, there is need for guidance for complete and accurate reporting on programme preparation, implementation and evaluation processes in real world contexts.</p>
<p>The current systematic review is the first step in the development of PRS for SRH, where we sought to provide a consolidated list of the types of items included in existing tools. While there was substantial diversity in the focus, scope and relevance of the tools reviewed, we identified 50 items related to the description of programme preparation, implementation and evaluation processes. Additional items and themes may be identified and suggested during subsequent steps of the PRS development. Specifically, in line with the recommendations by Moher et al [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], we will conduct a Delphi consensus exercise with a panel of experts to review and add to the list of items. This will be followed by a face to face consultative meeting to further refine and discuss the items, finalize the PRS and plan for its implementation. Finally, the PRS will be pilot-tested for user feasibility via different SRH programmes supported by the WHO. The specific purpose of the final PRS will be to help programme staff and researchers write reports and communicate key elements about how the programme was prepared, implemented and evaluated. The intended users of the PRS include programme staff and implementers writing reports to donors or for dissemination to external audiences. The PRS may also serve as a guide on what to include in peer-reviewed publications about programmes and their implementation processes. Finally, the PRS tool may function as a guide for upfront programme planning and implementation by outlining the essential elements that need to be reported on.</p>
<p>While every effort was made to undertake a comprehensive, systematic search of relevant literature, there are some limitations to the review. Because the review was restricted to peer-reviewed literature and selected grey literature sources published in the last 15 years it is possible that we missed relevant programme reporting tools that were published before or after this timeframe, or that may not be available to the public. One example is the Standards for Reporting Implementation Studies of Complex Interventions (StaRI) [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>], which was recently published (2015) and therefore not captured by the current systematic search. We attempted to minimize this risk of bias by piloting our search strategy and implemented this in a number of databases relevant to SRH. We also searched the EQUATOR database, which provides a comprehensive listing of available reporting tools. Despite the use of a structured, piloted data extraction form it is possible that we overlooked some items. Finally, frameworks on developing a scale-up strategy, such as the WHO ExpandNet tool [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>] and the SURE checklist for identifying factors affecting the implementation of a policy option [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>], were beyond the scope of the current review based on its inclusion and exclusion criteria. We acknowledge the importance and utility of these tools and frameworks for programmes and therefore they may inform the subsequent steps of the PRS development.</p>
<p>As far as we know, this is the first systematic review of tools and items relevant to reporting of SRH programmes. The review thus fills an important gap in the literature on programme reporting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec022" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Over the last decade a number of tools for reporting of research have been published. Recent initiatives have focused on improving the reporting of intervention research through guidelines such as TiDiER [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and WIDER [<xref rid="pone.0138647.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. However, few tools include specific elements related to the description of programme preparation and implementation, and we could not locate any standardized tools for reporting of programmes in the field of SRH. Development of PRS for SRH programmes can therefore fill a significant gap in existing reporting tools. Specifically, the availability of PRS can help improve descriptions of programme preparation, implementation and evaluation processes, which in turn can guide replication and scale-up of successful models. This systematic review is the first step in the development of such standards; in the next steps, we will draft a preliminary version of the PRS based on the aggregate list of identified items, and finalize the tool using a consensus process among experts and user-testing.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec023">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0138647.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138647.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Search strategies.</title>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0138647.s002" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138647.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Data extraction overview.</title>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0138647.s003" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138647.s003" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Text</label>
<caption>
<title>Systematic Review Protocol.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors wish to thank Ms Dina Khan for assisting with the quality check process of extracted data and Ms Annette Peters for editing assistance.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Durlak</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DuPre</surname> <given-names>EP</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Implementation matters: a review of research on the influence of implementation on program outcomes and the factors affecting implementation</article-title>. <source>Am J Community Psychol</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10464-008-9165-0" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10464-008-9165-0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18322790</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michie</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fixsen</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grimshaw</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eccles</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Specifying and reporting complex behaviour change interventions: the need for a scientific method</article-title>. <source>Implement Sci</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1748-5908-4-40" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1748-5908-4-40</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19607700</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kågesten</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parekh</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tuncalp</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turke</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive adolescent health programs that include sexual and reproductive health services: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>e23</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2014.302246" xlink:type="simple">10.2105/AJPH.2014.302246</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25320876</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chalmers</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasziou</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Avoidable waste in the production and reporting of research evidence</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>374</volume>: <fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(09)60329-9" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0140-6736(09)60329-9</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19525005</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glasziou</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boutron</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Julious</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Reducing waste from incomplete or unusable reports of biomedical research</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source> <volume>383</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eastwood</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horton</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olkin</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Improving the quality of reporting of randomized controlled trials. The CONSORT statement</article-title>. <source>Jama</source> <volume>276</volume>: <fpage>637</fpage>–<lpage>639</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8773637</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Des Jarlais</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyles</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crepaz</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Improving the reporting quality of nonrandomized evaluations of behavioral and public health interventions: the TREND statement</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14998794</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sainsbury</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ): A 32-item checklist for interviews and focus groups</article-title>. <source>International Journal for Quality in Health Care</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17872937</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adam</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alonge</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agyepong</surname> <given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Implementation research: what it is and how to do it</article-title>. <source>Bmj</source> <volume>347</volume>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.f6753" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/bmj.f6753</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24259324</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simera</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Guidance for developers of health research reporting guidelines</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1000217</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000217" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000217</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20169112</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Last</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spasoff</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name>, editors (<year>2000</year>) <chapter-title>A dictionary of epidemiology</chapter-title>. <edition>4th ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liberati</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tetzlaff</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulrow</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gotzsche</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannidis</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The PRISMA statement for reporting systematic reviews and meta-analyses of studies that evaluate health care interventions: explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1000100</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000100" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000100</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19621070</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weeks</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ocampo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seely</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sampson</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Describing reporting guidelines for health research: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>718</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.09.013" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.09.013</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21216130</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">WHO Sexual and Reproductive Health. The Department of Reproductive Health and Research including HRP.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adam</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <chapter-title>Implementation Research in Health: A practical guide</chapter-title>. <source>Alliance for Health Policy and Systems Research</source>, <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Treweek</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coyle</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Intervention description is not enough: evidence from an in-depth multiple case study on the untold role and impact of context in randomised controlled trials of seven complex interventions</article-title>. <source>Trials</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1745-6215-13-95" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1745-6215-13-95</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22742939</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayo-Wilson</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Reporting implementation in randomized trials: proposed additions to the consolidated standards of reporting trials statement</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>630</fpage>–<lpage>633</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17329641</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayo-Wilson</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hopewell</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macdonald</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Developing a reporting guideline for social and psychological intervention trials</article-title>. <source>Trials</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>242</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1745-6215-14-242" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1745-6215-14-242</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23915044</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hopewell</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macdonald</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michie</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Protocol for CONSORT-SPI: An extension for social and psychological interventions</article-title>. <source>Implementation Science</source> <volume>8</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>KW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufmann</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knatterud</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orleans</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Evidence-based behavioral medicine: what is it and how do we achieve it?</article-title> <source>Ann Behav Med</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14644692</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Möhler</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartoszek</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Köpke</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Proposed criteria for reporting the development and evaluation of complex interventions in healthcare (CReDECI): Guideline development</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Nursing Studies</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2011.08.003" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2011.08.003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21924424</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohler</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartoszek</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Quality of reporting of complex healthcare interventions and applicability of the CReDECI list—a survey of publications indexed in PubMed</article-title>. <source>BMC medical research methodology</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2288-13-125" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2288-13-125</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24138207</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McEvoy</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galipeau</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasziou</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammick</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Protocol for development of the guideline for reporting evidence based practice educational interventions and teaching (GREET) statement</article-title>. <source>BMC Medical Education</source> <volume>13</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McEvoy</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galipeau</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasziou</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammick</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>A systematic review of how studies describe educational interventions for evidence-based practice: Stage 1 of the development of a reporting guideline</article-title>. <source>BMC Medical Education</source> <volume>14</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McEvoy</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galipeau</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasziou</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammick</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>A Delphi survey to determine how educational interventions for evidence-based practice should be reported: stage 2 of the development of a reporting guideline</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Educ</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1472-6920-14-159" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1472-6920-14-159</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25081371</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Underhill</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Operario</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayo-Wilson</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The Oxford Implementation Index: a new tool for incorporating implementation data into systematic reviews and meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>874</fpage>–<lpage>882</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jclinepi.2013.03.006" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2013.03.006</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23810026</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright-DeAgüero</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The Program Evaluation and Monitoring System: A Key Source of Data for Monitoring Evidence-Based HIV Prevention Program Processes and Outcomes</article-title>. <source>AIDS Education and Prevention</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16987090</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Neill</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tabish</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petticrew</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pottie</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Applying an equity lens to interventions: using PROGRESS ensures consideration of socially stratifying factors to illuminate inequities in health</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jclinepi.2013.08.005" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2013.08.005</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24189091</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kavanagh J, S O, Lorenc (2008) Reflections in developing and using. PROGRESS-Plus. Equity Update.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crepaz</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Quality of study methods in individual- and group-level HIV intervention research: critical reporting elements</article-title>. <source>AIDS Educ Prev</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15342336</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arai</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Popay</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Extending systematic reviews to include evidence on implementation: methodological work on a review of community-based initiatives to prevent injuries</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>1060</fpage>–<lpage>1071</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16574289</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conn</surname> <given-names>VS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Groves</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Protecting the power of interventions through proper reporting</article-title>. <source>Nurs Outlook</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>318</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.outlook.2011.06.003" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.outlook.2011.06.003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21840555</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riggs</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuervo</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lumbiganon</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Improving the reporting of public health intervention research: Advancing TREND and CONSORT</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Health</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/pubmed/fdm082" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/pubmed/fdm082</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18204086</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrington</surname> <given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noar</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Reporting standards for studies of tailored interventions</article-title>. <source>Health Education Research</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>342</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/her/cyr108" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/her/cyr108</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22156230</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bird</surname> <given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Boutillier</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leamy</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bradstreet</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slade</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Evaluating the feasibility of complex interventions in mental health services: Standardised measure and reporting guidelines</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychiatry</source> <volume>204</volume>: <fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1192/bjp.bp.113.128314" xlink:type="simple">10.1192/bjp.bp.113.128314</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24311549</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chalmers</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bracken</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Djulbegovic</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garattini</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gülmezoglu</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>How to increase value and reduce waste when research priorities are set</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source> <volume>383</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidoff</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Batalden</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogrinc</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mooney</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Publication guidelines for quality improvement in health care: evolution of the SQUIRE project</article-title>. <source>Qual Saf Health Care</source> <volume>17</volume> <issue>Suppl 1</issue>: <fpage>i3</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/qshc.2008.029066" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/qshc.2008.029066</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18836063</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogrinc</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mooney</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estrada</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldmann</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname> <given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The SQUIRE (Standards for QUality Improvement Reporting Excellence) guidelines for quality improvement reporting: explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source>Qual Saf Health Care</source> <volume>17</volume> <collab xlink:type="simple">Suppl 1</collab>: <fpage>i13</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/qshc.2008.029058" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/qshc.2008.029058</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18836062</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Quality improvement research: Utilization of the SQUIRE Guidelines</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Psychiatric Nurses Association</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flottorp</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oxman</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Musila</surname> <given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wensing</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Godycki-Cwirko</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A checklist for identifying determinants of practice: a systematic review and synthesis of frameworks and taxonomies of factors that prevent or enable improvements in healthcare professional practice</article-title>. <source>Implement Sci</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1748-5908-8-35" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1748-5908-8-35</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23522377</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasziou</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boutron</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milne</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perera</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Better reporting of interventions: Template for intervention description and replication (TIDieR) checklist and guide</article-title>. <source>BMJ (Online)</source> <volume>348</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albrecht</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Archibald</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arseneau</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Development of a checklist to assess the quality of reporting of knowledge translation interventions using the Workgroup for Intervention Development and Evaluation Research (WIDER) recommendations</article-title>. <source>Implement Sci</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>52</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1748-5908-8-52" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1748-5908-8-52</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23680355</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Bruin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luszczynska</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Enhancing reporting of behavior change intervention evaluations</article-title>. <source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source> <volume>66</volume> <issue>Suppl 3</issue>: <fpage>S293</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/QAI.0000000000000231" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/QAI.0000000000000231</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25007199</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davidoff</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elbourne</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The revised CONSORT statement for reporting randomized trials: explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>663</fpage>–<lpage>694</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11304107</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hopewell</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montori</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gotzsche</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devereaux</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>CONSORT 2010 Explanation and Elaboration: Updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trials</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>e1</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.03.004" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.03.004</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20346624</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The CONSORT statement: revised recommendations for improving the quality of reports of parallel-group randomized trials</article-title>. <source>Jama</source> <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>1987</fpage>–<lpage>1991</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11308435</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>CONSORT 2010 Statement: Updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trials</article-title>. <source>Trials</source> <volume>11</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jüni</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlett</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Value of flow diagrams in reports of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source> <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>1996</fpage>–<lpage>1999</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11308437</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Improving the reporting of randomised trials: The CONSORT Statement and beyond</article-title>. <source>Statistics in Medicine</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>2985</fpage>–<lpage>2997</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/sim.5402" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/sim.5402</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22903776</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutron</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ravaud</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Methods and processes of the CONSORT group: Example of an extension for trials assessing nonpharmacologic treatments</article-title>. <source>Annals of Internal Medicine</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>W-60</fpage>–<lpage>W-66</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18283201</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eysenbach</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>CONSORT-EHEALTH: Improving and standardizing evaluation reports of web-based and mobile health interventions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Medical Internet Research</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gustafson</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pingree</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Relevance of CONSORT reporting criteria for research on eHealth interventions</article-title>. <source>Patient Educ Couns</source> <volume>81</volume> Suppl: <fpage>S77</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pec.2010.07.040" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.pec.2010.07.040</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20843621</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwarenstein</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Treweek</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gagnier</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tunis</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haynes</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Improving the reporting of pragmatic trials: an extension of the CONSORT statement</article-title>. <source>Bmj</source> <volume>337</volume>: <fpage>a2390</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.a2390" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/bmj.a2390</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19001484</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Staniszewska</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brett</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mockford</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barber</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The GRIPP checklist: strengthening the quality of patient and public involvement reporting in research</article-title>. <source>Int J Technol Assess Health Care</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0266462311000481" xlink:type="simple">10.1017/S0266462311000481</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22004782</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liberati</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tetzlaff</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>151</volume>: <fpage>264</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>, w264. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19622511</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petticrew</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tugwell</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Neill</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>PRISMA-Equity 2012 Extension: Reporting Guidelines for Systematic Reviews with a Focus on Health Equity</article-title>. <source>PLoS Medicine</source> <volume>9</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petticrew</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueffing</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benkhalti</surname> <given-names>Jandu M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dhaliwal</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Does consideration and assessment of effects on health equity affect the conclusions of systematic reviews? A methodology study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e31360</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0031360" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0031360</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22427804</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petticrew</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Neill</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhutta</surname> <given-names>ZA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Health equity: evidence synthesis and knowledge translation methods</article-title>. <source>Systematic reviews</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/2046-4053-2-43" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/2046-4053-2-43</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23799964</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burford</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tugwell</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Neil</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Testing the PRISMA-Equity 2012 Reporting Guideline: The Perspectives of Systematic Review Authors</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>8</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Proudfoot</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barak</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carlbring</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuijpers</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Establishing guidelines for executing and reporting internet intervention research</article-title>. <source>Cognitive Behaviour Therapy</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/16506073.2011.573807" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/16506073.2011.573807</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25155812</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernald</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deaton</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weister</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pray</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baumann</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A standardized reporting system for assessment of diverse public health programs</article-title>. <source>Preventing Chronic Disease</source> <volume>9</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigby</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Talmon</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brender</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ammenwerth</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Keizer</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nykanen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <chapter-title>Linking informaticians and end users—Using the STARE-HI evaluation reporting framework as a unifying design approach</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Adlassnig</surname> <given-names>KP</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Medical Informations in a United and Healthy Europe</source>: 2009 <publisher-name>European Federation for Medical Informatics</publisher-name>. pp. <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Talmon</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ammenwerth</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brender</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Keizer</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nykanen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rigby</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>STARE-HI—Statement on reporting of evaluation studies in Health Informatics</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Inform</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2008.09.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2008.09.002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18930696</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shea</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname> <given-names>JPT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sterne</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tugwell</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reeves</surname> <given-names>BC</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Checklists of methodological issues for review authors to consider when including non-randomized studies in systematic reviews</article-title>. <source>Research Synthesis Methods</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jrsm.1077" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/jrsm.1077</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26053540</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Husereau</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petrou</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carswell</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenberg</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Consolidated Health Economic Evaluation Reporting Standards (CHEERS)—explanation and elaboration: a report of the ISPOR Health Economic Evaluation Publication Guidelines Good Reporting Practices Task Force</article-title>. <source>Value Health</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>250</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2013.02.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jval.2013.02.002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23538175</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Husereau</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petrou</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carswell</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenberg</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Consolidated Health Economic Evaluation Reporting Standards (CHEERS) statement</article-title>. <source>Value Health</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>e1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2013.02.010" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jval.2013.02.010</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23538200</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutron</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tugwell</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giraudeau</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poiraudeau</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nizard</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A checklist to evaluate a report of a nonpharmacological trial (CLEAR NPT) was developed using consensus</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>1233</fpage>–<lpage>1240</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16291467</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flemming</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McInnes</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Enhancing transparency in reporting the synthesis of qualitative research: ENTREQ</article-title>. <source>BMC Medical Research Methodology</source> <volume>12</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramsey</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willke</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Briggs</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buxton</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chawla</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Good Research Practices for Cost-Effectiveness Analysis Alongside Clinical Trials: The ISPOR RCT-CEA Task Force Report</article-title>. <source>Value in Health</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>533</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16176491</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tooth</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ware</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Purdie</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Quality of reporting of observational longitudinal research</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>161</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15671260</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khangura</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brehaut</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Potter</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Reporting guidelines for survey research: an analysis of published guidance and reporting practices</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1001069</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001069" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001069</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829330</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niazkhani</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pirnejad</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aarts</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bal</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Reporting qualitative research in health informatics: REQ-HI recommendations</article-title>. <source>Stud Health Technol Inform</source> <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>881</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21893872</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowman</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Worley</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A guide to reporting studies in rural and remote health</article-title>. <source>Rural Remote Health</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>2312</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22950574</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reitsma</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruns</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gatsonis</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasziou</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irwig</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Towards complete and accurate reporting of studies of diagnostic accuracy: The STARD Initiative</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12513043</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reitsma</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruns</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gatsonis</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasziou</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irwig</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The STARD statement for reporting studies of diagnostic accuracy: explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>W1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12513067</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simel</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rennie</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The STARD statement for reporting diagnostic accuracy studies: application to the history and physical examination</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>768</fpage>–<lpage>774</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11606-008-0583-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11606-008-0583-3</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18347878</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smidt</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rutjes</surname> <given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Windt</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostelo</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reitsma</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Reproducibility of the STARD checklist: an instrument to assess the quality of reporting of diagnostic accuracy studies</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Res Methodol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16539705</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannidis</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gagnon</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Elm</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Strengthening the reporting of genetic association studies (STREGA): an extension of the strengthening the reporting of observational studies in epidemiology (STROBE) statement</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>608</lpage>.e594. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jclinepi.2008.12.004" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2008.12.004</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19217256</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacPherson</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammerschlag</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Revised STandards for Reporting Interventions in Clinical Trials of Acupuncture (STRICTA): extending the CONSORT statement</article-title>. <source>Acupunct Med</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/aim.2009.001370" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/aim.2009.001370</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20615861</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacPherson</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jobst</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niemtzow</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Standards for reporting interventions in controlled trials of acupuncture: The STRICTA recommendations. STandards for Reporting Interventions in Controlled Trails of Acupuncture</article-title>. <source>Acupunct Med</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11926601</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenbroucke</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Elm</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gotzsche</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulrow</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE): explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e297</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17941715</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Elm</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gotzsche</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenbroucke</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e296</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17941714</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacPherson</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jobst</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Improving the Reporting of Interventions in Clinical Trials of Acupuncture: The Updated and Revised STRICTA</article-title>. <source>Journal of Alternative and Complementary Medicine</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>929</fpage>–<lpage>930</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinnock</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Epiphaniou</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sheikh</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eldridge</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Developing standards for reporting implementation studies of complex interventions (StaRI): a systematic review and e-Delphi</article-title>. <source>Implementation Science</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s13012-015-0235-z" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/s13012-015-0235-z</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25888928</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">WHO, ExpandNet</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <chapter-title>Beginning with the end in mind</chapter-title>. <source>Planning pilot projects and other programmatic research for succesful scaling up</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138647.ref086"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">The SURE Collaboration (2011) SURE Guides for preparing and using evidence-based policy briefs. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://global.evipnet.org/SURE-Guides/" xlink:type="simple">http://global.evipnet.org/SURE-Guides/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>