<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-02196</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035776</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Behavioral ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Evolutionary processes</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Coevolution</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Population biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population dynamics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Zoology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal behavior</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Computer science</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computerized simulations</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Mathematics</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Applied mathematics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Complex systems</subject>
              <subject>Game theory</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Physics</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Interdisciplinary physics</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Sociology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Social networks</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Ecology</subject>
          <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
          <subject>Computer Science</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
          <subject>Physics</subject>
          <subject>Mathematics</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evolution of Cooperation Driven by Reputation-Based Migration</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Reputation-Based Migration</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cong</surname>
            <given-names>Rui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Bin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Qiu</surname>
            <given-names>Yuanying</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Long</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>MOE Key Laboratory of Electronic Equipment Structure Design, School of Mechano-Electronic Engineering, Xidian University, Xi' an, China</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Center for Systems and Control, State Key Laboratory for Turbulence and Complex Systems, College of Engineering, Peking University, Beijing, China</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Perc</surname>
            <given-names>Matjaž</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Maribor, Slovenia</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">congrui0000@126.com</email> (RC); <email xlink:type="simple">bin.wu@evolbio.mpg.de</email> (BW)</corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RC BW YQ LW. Performed the experiments: RC BW YQ LW. Analyzed the data: RC BW YQ LW. Wrote the paper: RC BW YQ LW.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e35776</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cong et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>How cooperation emerges and is stabilized has been a puzzling problem to biologists and sociologists since Darwin. One of the possible answers to this problem lies in the mobility patterns. These mobility patterns in previous works are either random-like or driven by payoff-related properties such as fitness, aspiration, or expectation. Here we address another force which drives us to move from place to place: reputation. To this end, we propose a reputation-based model to explore the effect of migration on cooperation in the contest of the prisoner's dilemma. In this model, individuals earn their reputation scores through previous cooperative behaviors. An individual tends to migrate to a new place if he has a neighborhood of low reputation. We show that cooperation is promoted for relatively large population density and not very large temptation to defect. A higher mobility sensitivity to reputation is always better for cooperation. A longer reputation memory favors cooperation, provided that the corresponding mobility sensitivity to reputation is strong enough. The microscopic perception of the effect of this mechanism is also given. Our results may shed some light on the role played by migration in the emergence and persistence of cooperation.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC) under Grant No. 51175397, No. 61020106005, and No. 10972002 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsfc.gov.cn/Portal0/default106.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nsfc.gov.cn/Portal0/default106.htm</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="7"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Cooperation has been a puzzling problem to biologists, sociologists and economists since Darwin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Axelrod1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Nowak1">[3]</xref>, because it benefits the defectors at costs to cooperators. In particular, it is interesting to investigate how cooperative behavior emerges in our human societies. Evolutionary game theory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-vonNeumann1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-MaynardSmith1">[5]</xref> is a powerful framework for understanding the emergence of cooperation. Up to now, a number of mechanisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Nowak2">[6]</xref> have been proposed to address this issue, including kin selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Hamilton1">[7]</xref>, group selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-MaynardSmith2">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Traulsen1">[9]</xref>, direct reciprocity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Trivers1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Axelrod2">[11]</xref>, indirect reciprocity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Alexander1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Saavedra1">[16]</xref>, and network reciprocity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Nowak5">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Perc2">[21]</xref>. Particularly, indirect reciprocity and network reciprocity have attracted intensive attention in the study of human cooperative behaviors, because our societies are well captured by networks, and that indirect reciprocity, which means “helpful ones will be helped by others”, is more powerful in shaping our cooperative behaviors in human communities than in other animals.</p>
      <p>Mobility, as an important characteristic of individuals in social network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Gonzlez1">[22]</xref> and also a way to realize the coevolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Perc3">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Zhang1">[27]</xref>, has recently received considerable attention in the study of cooperation. The population structure is often captured by spatial lattices <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Szab2">[28]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Perc5">[31]</xref>. Apart from population structures, the effects of mobility on the evolution of cooperation vary with movement patterns as well. To the best of our knowledge, there have been two types of forces that drive the migration. One is “random driven”. In this context, each individual is allowed to migrate to a nearby place randomly with a uniform probability on lattices <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Vainstein1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Sicardi1">[33]</xref> or to move in random directions on continuous plane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Meloni1">[34]</xref>. Further, moving individuals can be distinguished <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Traulsen2">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Perc6">[36]</xref> and endowed with different migration probabilities. The criteria of discrimination could be their strategies (cooperators or defectors) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Cheng1">[37]</xref>, or their influences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Droz1">[38]</xref>. The other is “payoff driven”. In these situations, an individual finds an empty site within some region that promises the highest payoff and then jumps to it (also called “success-driven”) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Helbing1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Yu1">[40]</xref>, or an individual will leave his current place if the payoff obtained does not meet the aspiration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Yang1">[41]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Perc7">[43]</xref> or expectation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Lin1">[44]</xref>. In our human societies, reputation, as the fuel for the engine of indirect reciprocity, plays an important role in shaping our migration decisions. Yet it is still unclear how this “fuel”-driven migration affects cooperation. Considering this, we propose a “reputation-based migration” model to address this issue.</p>
      <p>Reputation is a kind of social information by which individuals' past behaviors can be assessed. It has greatly contributed to evolution of cooperation in games of indirect reciprocity. The reputation can be simply evaluated by “image score” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Nowak3">[13]</xref> or other criterions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Nowak4">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Ohtsuki1">[45]</xref>. In spatial games, individuals are distributed on the nodes of the networks, and the edges represent who plays with whom. An individual interacts with his direct neighbors and acquires the reputations of them. In reality, people tend to interact with those with good reputations that potentially benefit themselves, but leave those with bad ones to avoid being exploited in the future. Besides, individuals often have the information of their neighbors' reputations with the rest unknown. Inspired by these, we propose a model where migration is driven by the reputation. Therein, individuals evaluate the environments by the reputation scores of neighbors and themselves. An individual has a larger probability to leave his current place and to migrate to a random nearby site if his reputation is high comparing to his neighbors, revealing the fact that individuals favor a preferable environment but repel a nasty one <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Santos2">[46]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Szolnoki3">[50]</xref>. For the updating of reputation, we incorporate memory effect <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Volstorf1">[51]</xref> to the image scoring. To address how the reputation-based migration affects the evolution of cooperation, we consider how the two intrinsic parameters in the model affects the cooperation level: the reputation decaying rate, which depicts a cumulative effect of previous actions on reputation, and the mobility sensitivity to reputation, which characterizes how sensitively reputation influences the decisions of migration.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p>In our model, the prisoner's dilemma game (PDG) is adopted as the paradigm to study the evolution of cooperation. For a typical PDG, each of the two players either cooperates (C) or defects (D). They both receive a reward <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> upon mutual cooperation and punishment <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> upon mutual defection. When confronted with a cooperator, the defector gains a temptation to defect <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, while the exploited cooperator acquires a sucker's payoff <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The ranking of the four payoff values is <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. By setting <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, A simplified version of PDG <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Nowak5">[17]</xref> is obtained such that the game is controlled by a single parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> indicates the temptation to defect. For the network of social contacts, we assume that players are located on a square lattice of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> sites with periodic boundary conditions. Each site can be either empty or occupied by one individual. Empty sites represent spatial regions individuals can migrate to. We denote by <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the density of population, defined as the ratio of population size to the number of all sites.</p>
      <p>Initially, an equal percentage (50%) of cooperators (Cs) and defectors (Ds) are randomly distributed in the population. Individuals play PDG with their direct neighbors, and are updated asynchronously in a random sequential order. In each round, an individual is randomly picked up for updating. One round consists of two successive processes: <italic>migration</italic> and <italic>imitation</italic>. During the migration process, a randomly chosen individual <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> explores all the empty sites within the Moore neighborhood with distance <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (the 8 neighboring sites). With probability <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which is governed by the reputations of neighbors and himself, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> migrates to a random place among those empty sites. For the sake that <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> has neighbors to interact with, those empty sites who have neighbors (non-empty neighboring sites) will preferentially be chosen from at random. If there is no empty site within <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>'s neighborhood, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> just stays where he is placed. In the imitation stage, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> interacts with all his neighbors (von Neumann neighborhood). The payoffs are accumulated. Meanwhile, payoffs of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>'s neighbors are calculated in the same way. Then <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> imitates the strategy of the neighbor who has the highest payoff (including himself), i.e., following a “best-take-over” rule. The reputation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is updated at the same time. If <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> has no neighbor to interact with in his current place, both his strategy and his reputation remain unchanged during this round. A time step is defined as many rounds of games such that each individual will on average be chosen once. Therefore, the real number of rounds played in one time step varies with population density <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. A key quantity that specifies the behavior of the system is the normalized fraction of cooperators <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> attained by averaging over many steps after the stationary phase is achieved, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the number of cooperators and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of all sites.</p>
      <p>In order to account for the reputation effect in mobility, we define an individual <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>'s reputation at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is 1 if <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> cooperates at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, otherwise being 0, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes the decaying rate. Thus an individual's reputation value is the weighted sum of the times he cooperated in the past games <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Fu1">[52]</xref>. For <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the memory effect vanishes and the reputation relies mainly on his current action; for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, reputation value is accumulated since the outset of the evolution.</p>
      <p>By comparing his reputation with those of his neighbors, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> evaluates the environment and tends to leave when the environment is not so good. Thus the influence of reputation on mobility is implemented through determining the probability of an individual <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to leave his current site, namely<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> represents <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>'s neighbors and himself. The parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> specifies an individual's mobility sensitivity to reputation. For <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, movement is insensitive to reputation and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> leaves with a probability equal to the inverse of the number of elements in set <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, while <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> leads to the deterministic rule where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> leaves with certainty if he is the one with the highest reputation among <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, but stays still otherwise. For the case that <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is isolated, we make a compulsory move by setting <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Considering that initially each individual has a reputation of zero, and thus no reputation records are available for guiding individuals' migration activities, we set <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> if all the members in <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> have a reputation equal to zero (and setting <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to be other constants in this case does not change the results qualitatively). Unlike models in ref <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Helbing1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Yu1">[40]</xref>, where migration relies on information on strategies of all individuals in a large area, migration here requires local information only. Note that in our model, reputation takes effect in the migration process only, and thus no influence of reputation on strategy updating is involved.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0035776-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Effects of temptation to defect and population density on cooperation.</title>
          <p>(a) Fraction of cooperators <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of temptation to defect <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for population density <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and (b) fraction of cooperators <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of population density <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for temptation to defect <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, for different combinations of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The cases without migration are plotted in dotted lines for comparison. Simulations are performed on a lattice of size <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The quantity <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is obtained by averaging over 2000 time steps after 18000 time steps. Each data point results from an average over 100 independent realizations. We have checked that after 18000 time steps, the value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is stabilized.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>In what follows, we present the results of numerical simulations. We first consider the influence of temptation to defect <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> on the fraction of cooperators <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In the presence of reputation-based migration, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is promoted for low temptation to defect (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g001">Fig. 1(a)</xref>). For <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, cooperation is promoted. For <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, depending on the specific <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, cooperation can be enhanced or suppressed. For <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, cooperation level plummets to zero, lower than that in the absence of migration, regardless of the values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. It is shown that <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> displays discontinuous transitions and the value remains constant between two transition points with increasing <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The phase transitions are due to the deterministic “best-take-over” rule we adopt in updating, where a strategy change occurs only if one individual in a C-D pair imitates the other who has a larger payoff (which is also the largest among the neighbors of the former one). Thus phases are altered at the points where C and D have identical payoffs. Considering all equal payoffs of C and D, potential transition points could be: <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, just as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g001">Fig. 1(a)</xref>, where a sharp drop of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is observed. Altogether, in an environment relatively favorable for cooperators, reputation-based migration enhances cooperation, while in a harsh environment, migration splits the surviving C clusters, accelerating the dying out of cooperators.</p>
      <p>The population density <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> has a notable impact on the dynamical process of evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Vainstein2">[53]</xref>, since it determines the number of empty sites that serve as destinations of migration, and eventually the characteristics of the network of real interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Lozano1">[54]</xref>. The influence of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g001">Fig. 1(b)</xref>. In the case of no migration, cooperators survive throughout the whole range of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> displays a U-shaped curve. By contrast, under our migration mechanism, there exists a threshold of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> below which <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In other words, cooperation can not persist for relatively low population density. However, as <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> increases, cooperation begins to emerge and flourish. For <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> approaching 1, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> declines sharply to the same value as the no migration case. These phenomena can be intuitively interpreted. For a low density population without mobility, the isolated individuals (also called “frozen sites” that never have the chances to make interactions or strategy changes) and occasionally formed C clusters to a certain extent maintain the cooperation level. Once mobility is introduced, the potential C clusters may be devastated. In our model, migration is based on local information. An individual leaves the dissatisfactory place and moves to a random one. In fact, there is no guarantee that the new place be better than the current one. This is quite unlike the pattern in ref <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Helbing1">[39]</xref> that intentionally searches for the best position globally, which facilitates the getting together of cooperators far between. Consequently, in a sparsely distributed population, migration destroys the positive assortment of cooperators brought by spatial structure, rendering local interactions more like a well-mixed scenario, and cooperators vanish rapidly. This is similar to the results obtained in refs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Sicardi1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Jiang1">[55]</xref> for low population density cases, where although different mobility patterns are adopted, likewise, destinations do not rely on nonlocal information but are actually random. For larger population densities, spatially larger C clusters can be formed initially, and migration helps to expand C clusters, thus enhancing the cooperation. As for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, due to the lack of empty sites, migration is almost impossible, and hence the result.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0035776-g002" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Influences of memory decaying rate and migration sensitivity on cooperation.</title>
          <p>(a) Fraction of cooperators <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for different values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and (b) fraction of cooperators <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in a logarithmic scale for small, medium, and large values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Other parameters are: <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We have excluded the case for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in all simulations because it is unrealistic and it takes infinitely long time for the system to converge as a result of the unlimited growth of reputation value. Other specifications for the simulations are the same as in Fig. 1.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Now we focus on the role of the two important parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which together govern the motion of individuals. The effect of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> on cooperation is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g002">Fig. 2(a)</xref>. On the one hand, for not very large values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (e.g., <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and smaller), neither small nor large value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> favors cooperation best, but intermediate values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> do, although the optimal <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> varies with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. On the other hand, if <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is very large, larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> always promotes cooperation. Just as demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g002">Fig 2(a)</xref> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and larger, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> increases monotonously with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Furthermore, as a common trait for all these <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>s, a sharp rise in <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is observed when <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> grows slightly larger than zero. The parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, as a decaying factor in reputation scoring, reflects the memory length of the reputation. In our study, we only consider the interval of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> because it is unrealistic to have an infinitely long memory about reputations in society. All the above results indicate that, reputation effect in migration (i.e., a memory length <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) is essential for the establishment of cooperation, but for a limited mobility sensitivity to reputation, memory should not be too long.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0035776-g003" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.g003</object-id>
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Cooperation levels and migration rates in contour forms.</title>
          <p>(a) Color-coded values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e124" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> parameter space and (b) corresponding equivalent migration probability. To obtain a data point in (b), the number of migration events is divided by the number of game rounds over a sufficiently long time after the stationary regime is achieved. In both panels, the scale of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e125" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is linear while <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e126" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> logarithmic, and certain contour lines are labeled. Other parameters are: <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e127" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Each data point results from an average over 10 independent realizations.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The influence of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e129" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> on <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e130" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g002">Fig. 2(b)</xref>. Generally speaking, larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e131" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>s are better for cooperation for any value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e132" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For small and moderate values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e133" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e134" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> grows monotonously and tardily with increasing <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e135" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For large values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e136" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (e.g., 0.95), <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e137" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> becomes more strongly dependent on <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e138" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the curve displays a sigmoid-like shape. A sufficiently large <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e139" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is needed for cooperation to establish, after which <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e140" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> increases dramatically, far exceeding those for lower <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e141" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>s. The parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e142" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can also be perceived as the capability to distinguish different reputation values. When <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e143" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is small, individuals with close reputations are treated alike, and they have similar probabilities to migrate. When <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e144" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is large, those with higher reputations have larger probability to move but those with lower reputations barely have the chance to move. With larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e145" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>s, individuals' actions are more reasonable or accurate, which favors the evolution of cooperation.</p>
      <p>To get a holistic view of the interplay of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e146" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e147" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we plot <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e148" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e149" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e150" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the contour form (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g003">Fig. 3(a)</xref>). It is obvious that for any non-zero value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e151" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e152" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> increases with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e153" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We also find that when <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e154" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> rises, the maximum of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e155" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> appreciates. Moreover, for relatively small <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e156" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>s, the <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e157" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> value requisite to sustain the same level of cooperation increases with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e158" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, just as demonstrated by the contour line for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e159" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This has led to the non-monotonous behavior of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e160" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e161" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> increases for a fixed <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e162" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g002">Fig. 2(a)</xref>. This phenomenon implies that: For larger values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e163" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, individuals' reputations are established through longer accumulation of previous actions. In these cases, an individual's decision to move or not should be made more accurately, rather than hastily in order to find a better environment for cooperation. However, if <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e164" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is sufficiently large, to obtain the same <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e165" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e166" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> increases, the required <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e167" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> declines(e.g., see the contour line for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e168" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g003">Fig. 3(a)</xref>). The cooperation level is maximized at the top right corner of the plane, which corresponds to <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e169" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the largest <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e170" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. To sum up, we conclude that, larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e171" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> promotes cooperation, as long as the corresponding <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e172" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is large enough.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0035776-g004" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.g004</object-id>
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Illustrations of some microscopic properties.</title>
          <p>(a) Snapshots of distributions of cooperators and defectors at different time steps in the absence of migration. <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e173" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is 0.5, 0.26, and 0.27 for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e174" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e175" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e176" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, respectively. (b) Snapshots of strategy (left and middle panels) and reputation (right panel, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e177" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e178" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e179" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e180" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is 0.39 for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e181" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and 0.52 for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e182" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. (c) Snapshots of strategy (left and middle panels) and reputation (right panel, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e183" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e184" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e185" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e186" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is 0.44 for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e187" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and 0.71 for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e188" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. (d) Time evolution of the ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e189" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of migration probability of boundary Cs to that of interior Cs. The dotted line <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e190" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is shown in the figure as a baseline. We have checked that by the time <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e191" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for (a) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e192" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for (b) and (c), the system has reached the equilibrium state. The color coding for strategy snapshots is as follows: blue or green represents a cooperator; red or yellow represents a defector; white represents an empty site. Particularly, green and yellow ones are those who will migrate to new places in this time step. For all the above panels, simulations are carried out for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e193" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e194" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and one realization, starting from the same initial strategy distribution shown in Fig. 4(a) the left panel (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e195" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Reputation induces diversity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Perc1">[20]</xref> in migration rates, and the combination of parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e196" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e197" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> changes the migration probability of individuals as a whole. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g003">Figure 3(b)</xref> shows the equivalent migration probability as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e198" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e199" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the contour form after the system has reached the equilibrium. Notably, the migration probability reaches a local minimum at the upper right corner of the plane, which coincides with the highest <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e200" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g003">Fig. 3(a)</xref>. Roughly, a larger cooperation level corresponds to a lower migration probability, and otherwise leading to the opposite. However, some exceptions appear near the lower boundary of the parameter plane, where both the <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e201" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the migration probability are low. This is due to the constraint in our model that an individual in an all-zero reputation neighborhood (including himself) just stays still. Within this parameter region, population is mainly composed of defectors. Their reputations quickly fall to zero and hence they no longer move, reducing the migration probability.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0035776-g005" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.g005</object-id>
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Influences of migration range and the order of migration and imitation.</title>
          <p>Fraction of cooperators <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e202" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of population density <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e203" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is shown in the figure for 4 different cases. For the first two cases, the migration range is enlarged to the Moore distance of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e204" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e205" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, respectively. For the other two cases, the order of migration and imitation is reversed such that migration comes after the strategy imitation. For all the above cases, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e206" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>For better understanding the mechanism of migration based on reputation and the varying effects of different parameters, it is useful to probe into spatio-temporal properties of the evolution process. We first consider the case that migration is not allowed. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g004">Figure 4(a)</xref> shows the snapshots of spatial configurations of strategies and empty sites at different time steps. Initially, owing to the randomly distributed strategies, those solitary cooperators sparsely scattered among defectors rapidly die out, and only those small C clusters survive (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e207" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Then these small C clusters expand to the limit, a state both Cs and Ds can resist the invasion of each other on the basis of payoff advantages, and the system quickly reaches a frozen state where no further strategy changes occur (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e208" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). However, if the reputation-based migration is incorporated, the limitation for strategy propagation is broken (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g004">Fig. 4(b)</xref>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e209" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), C clusters disperse and occupy larger areas, resulting in a remarkable rise in cooperation level. Meanwhile, C clusters become looser, with many empty sites in them. Eventually, system reaches a dynamic equilibrium (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e210" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), where part of individuals still tend to move. While expanding, some C clusters may split into smaller ones or vanish by chance, thus keeping <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e211" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> stable on average. If the parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e212" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is further increased (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g004">Fig. 4(c)</xref>), the C clusters become more compact, with less holes in them. Besides, less individuals tend to move in one step, partially because of the direct influence of parameter itself on migration probability, and partially because of the less empty sites inside the more densely assembled C clusters. Therefore, the real migration rate gets reduced, just as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g002">Fig. 2(b)</xref>. Moreover, there are some filament-like Ds separating or along the edge of C clusters. With almost zero reputation values, these Ds enjoy staying with reputation-high Cs and never move away. This also constitutes a reason that further expansion of Cs is inhibited.</p>
      <p>We have also plotted the snapshots of reputations when system is stabilized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g004">Fig. 4(b)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g004">Fig. 4(c)</xref> (the right panels). We see that the high-reputation areas coincide with the C clusters. Moreover, when <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e213" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is larger, there will be more individuals with medium values of reputation. Actually, the parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e214" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> also determines the maximum reputation value. For an individual that always cooperates, his reputation approaches <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e215" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, just as illustrated in the snapshots. For a larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e216" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, reputations show a more smooth transition from the highest to zero centering on C clusters. This is crucial for stabilizing cooperation, because the hierarchies in reputation values deter individuals in the vicinity of high-reputation ones from moving away, and this “viscosity” spreads by layers, leading to more compact C clusters.</p>
      <p>Cooperators at the boundary of C clusters may have different migration probabilities from those in the interior of C clusters. We say a cooperator is at the boundary if he is adjacent to at least one defector, or in the interior otherwise. By <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e217" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> we define the ratio of the average migration probability of boundary Cs to that of interior Cs, and the time evolution of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e218" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g004">Fig. 4(d)</xref>. It is found that large <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e219" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e220" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> correspond to small <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e221" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In turn, a decrease in either <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e222" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e223" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> results in a larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e224" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We should stress that a relatively low boundary migration probability is essential in promoting cooperation under our mechanism. If a cooperator at the boundary moves too frequently, it is quite likely that he jumps into a sea of defectors and finally dies out. Nevertheless, a high migration rate makes clusters looser, thus more susceptible to defectors. Therefore, the ideal mode is that: Cs at the boundary hold the position and defense the frontier, waiting for the reinforcement of Cs from the interior. When local advantages are formed, they strike back and expand the territory. In our model, high reputation individuals are more likely to be dissatisfied and tend to move. By contrast, low reputation ones will be pleased to stay next to the high ones. Consequently, to make C clusters stable and compact, on one hand, reputation hierarchy is needed, and on the other, migration can not be made too frequently or blindly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Vainstein1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Meloni1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Cheng1">[37]</xref>. Both of them require a large <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e225" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and a large <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035776.e226" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
      <p>We also investigate the robustness of the results by reversing the order of migration and imitation (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g005">Fig. 5</xref>), and find that the results are qualitatively unchanged. However, the cooperation level is slightly reduced and it requires larger population density for cooperation to establish. The reduction of cooperation should be ascribed to the fact that, if the strategy imitation precedes migration, an individual will not be able to avoid the bad environment in advance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Vainstein1">[32]</xref>. Additionally, we have checked the case in which the migration range is enlarged and find that cooperation is not further promoted (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035776-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). The results simply imply that, without a knowledge of the information on destinations of migrations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Yang1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Wu1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Jiang1">[55]</xref>, a long range move could be more risky, or sometimes disastrous, because the movement may be from a bad place to an even worse one.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>To sum up, we propose a new model to investigate how mobility affects the evolution of cooperation. In this model, individuals evaluate their environments by the reputations of neighbors and themselves. An individual tends to leave his current place and to migrate to a random nearby site if his reputation is higher than those of neighbors. We explore the effects of the two intrinsic parameters: reputation memory length and mobility sensitivity to reputation. It is found that both the memory length and the mobility sensitivity to reputation significantly change the dynamical process of evolution. We conclude that this migration mechanism enhances cooperation for relatively large population density and not very high temptation to defect. For any given reputation memory length, a higher mobility sensitivity to reputation is always better for cooperation. As reputation memory length increases, cooperation can be maximized at a higher level given that the corresponding sensitivity is large enough. We also provide a microscopic perception of the effect of this mechanism.</p>
      <p>In agreement with previous studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Vainstein1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Sicardi1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Cheng1">[37]</xref>, our results show that high probabilities of mobility inhibit cooperation. The reputation-based migration mechanism also induces diversity in migration probabilities, which have been shown to promote cooperation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Cheng1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035776-Droz1">[38]</xref>. Different from theirs, the diversity in mobilities in our model is not a prescribed assumption, but a consequence of the reputation-based migration. Thus it is more reasonable. Our work may shed some light on how migration affects the evolution of cooperation.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>Discussions with Te Wu are gratefully acknowledged.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Axelrod1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Axelrod</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1984</year>             <article-title>The Evolution of Cooperation.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Sigmund1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sigmund</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Games of Life: Explorations in Ecology, Evolution and Behaviour.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Nowak1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Evolutionary Dynamics: Exploring the Equations of Life.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-vonNeumann1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Neumann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgenstern</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1944</year>             <article-title>Theory of Games and Economic Behavior.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-MaynardSmith1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maynard Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1982</year>             <article-title>Evolution and the Theory of Games.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Nowak2">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Five rules for the evolution of cooperation.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>314</volume>             <fpage>1560</fpage>             <lpage>1563</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Hamilton1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1964</year>             <article-title>The genetical evolution of social behaviour i and ii.</article-title>             <source>J Theor Bio</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>52</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-MaynardSmith2">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maynard Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1976</year>             <article-title>Group selection.</article-title>             <source>Q Rev Biol</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>277</fpage>             <lpage>283</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Traulsen1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Traulsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Evolution of cooperation by multilevel selection. Proc 10.</article-title>             <source>Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>103</volume>             <fpage>10952</fpage>             <lpage>10955</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Trivers1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivers</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1971</year>             <article-title>The evolution of reciprocal altruism.</article-title>             <source>Q Rev Biol</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>35</fpage>             <lpage>57</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Axelrod2">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Axelrod</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>The evolution of cooperation.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>211</volume>             <fpage>1390</fpage>             <lpage>1396</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Alexander1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>The Biology of Moral Systems.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Aldine de Gruyter</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Nowak3">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sigmund</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Evolution of indirect reciprocity by image scoring.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>393</volume>             <fpage>573</fpage>             <lpage>577</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Wedekind1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wedekind</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Cooperation through image scoring in humans.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>288</volume>             <fpage>850</fpage>             <lpage>852</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Nowak4">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sigmund</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Evolution of indirect reciprocity.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>437</volume>             <fpage>1291</fpage>             <lpage>1298</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Saavedra1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saavedra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed-Tsochas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Cooperation under indirect reciprocity and imitative trust.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>e13475</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Nowak5">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1992</year>             <article-title>Evolutionary games and spatial chaos.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>359</volume>             <fpage>826</fpage>             <lpage>829</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Santos1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Scale-free networks provide a unifying framework for the emergence of cooperation.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev Lett</source>             <volume>95</volume>             <fpage>098104</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Szab1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabó</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fáth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Evolutionary games on graphs.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rep</source>             <volume>446</volume>             <fpage>97</fpage>             <lpage>216</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Perc1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szolnoki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Social diversity and promotion of cooperation in the spatial prisoner's dilemma game.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>77</volume>             <fpage>011904</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Perc2">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Evolution of cooperation on scale-free networks subject to error and attack.</article-title>             <source>New J Phys</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>033027</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Gonzlez1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lind</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>System of mobile agents to model social networks.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev Lett</source>             <volume>96</volume>             <fpage>088702</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Perc3">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szolnoki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Coevolutionary games – a mini review.</article-title>             <source>Biosystems 99:</source>             <volume>109 – 125</volume>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Poncela1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poncela</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez-Gardenes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Floría</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Complex cooperative networks from evolutionary preferential attachment.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>e2449</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Szolnoki1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szolnoki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Coevolution of teaching activity promotes cooperation.</article-title>             <source>New J Phys</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>043036</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Szolnoki2">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szolnoki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Resolving social dilemmas on evolving random networks.</article-title>             <source>EPL</source>             <volume>86</volume>             <fpage>30007</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Zhang1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Evolution of interactions and cooperation in the spatial prisoner's dilemma game.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>e26724</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Szab2">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabó</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tőke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Evolutionary prisoner's dilemma game on a square lattice.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>58</volume>             <fpage>69</fpage>             <lpage>73</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Szab3">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabó</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vukov</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szolnoki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Phase diagrams for an evolutionary prisoner's dilemma game on two-dimensional lattices.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>72</volume>             <fpage>047107</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Perc4">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Chaos promotes cooperation in the spatial prisoner's dilemma game.</article-title>             <source>EPL</source>             <volume>75</volume>             <fpage>841</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Perc5">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Coherence resonance in a spatial prisoner's dilemma game.</article-title>             <source>New J Phys</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>22</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Vainstein1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vainstein</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>ATC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arenzon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Does mobility decrease cooperation?</article-title>             <source>J Theor Bio</source>             <volume>244</volume>             <fpage>722</fpage>             <lpage>728</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Sicardi1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sicardi</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vainstein</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arenzon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Random mobility and spatial structure often enhance cooperation.</article-title>             <source>J Theor Bio</source>             <volume>256</volume>             <fpage>240</fpage>             <lpage>246</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Meloni1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meloni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buscarino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortuna</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frasca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez-Gardenes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Effects of mobility in a population of prisoner's dilemma players.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>79</volume>             <fpage>067101</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Traulsen2">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Traulsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Chromodynamics of cooperation in finite populations.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>e270</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Perc6">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szolnoki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabó</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Restricted connections among distinguished players support cooperation.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>78</volume>             <fpage>066101</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Cheng1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Motion depending on the strategies of players enhances cooperation in a co-evolutionary prisoner's dilemma game.</article-title>             <source>New J Phys</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>123014</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Droz1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Droz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szwabiński</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabó</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Motion of influential players can support cooperation in prisoner's dilemma.</article-title>             <source>Eur Phys J B</source>             <volume>71</volume>             <fpage>579</fpage>             <lpage>585</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Helbing1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Helbing</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>The outbreak of cooperation among success-driven individuals under noisy conditions.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>106</volume>             <fpage>3680</fpage>             <lpage>3685</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Yu1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Mobility enhances cooperation in the presence of decision-making mistakes on complex networks.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>83</volume>             <fpage>026105</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Yang1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Role of aspiration-induced migration in cooperation.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>81</volume>             <fpage>065101</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Roca1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roca</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helbing</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Emergence of social cohesion in a model society of greedy, mobile individuals.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>108</volume>             <fpage>11370</fpage>             <lpage>11374</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Perc7">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Heterogeneous aspirations promote cooperation in the prisoner's dilemma game.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>e15117</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Lin1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shuai</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Cooperation among mobile individuals with payoff expectations in the spatial prisoner's dilemma game.</article-title>             <source>Chaos Soliton Fract</source>             <volume>44</volume>             <fpage>153</fpage>             <lpage>159</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Ohtsuki1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohtsuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>How should we define goodness? – reputation dynamics in indirect reciprocity.</article-title>             <source>J Theor Bio</source>             <volume>231</volume>             <fpage>107</fpage>             <lpage>120</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Santos2">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenaerts</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Cooperation prevails when individuals adjust their social ties.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>e140</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Wu1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Moving away from nasty encounters enhances cooperation in ecological prisoner's dilemma game.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>e27669</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Wu2">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Evolution of cooperation on stochastic dynamical networks.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>e11187</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Wu3">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Evolutionary dynamics on stochastic evolving networks for multiple-strategy games.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>84</volume>             <fpage>046111</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Szolnoki3">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szolnoki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danku</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Making new connections towards cooperation in the prisoner's dilemma game.</article-title>             <source>EPL</source>             <volume>84</volume>             <fpage>50007</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Volstorf1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volstorf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rieskamp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>The good, the bad, and the rare: Memory for partners in social interactions.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>e18945</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Fu1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Reputation-based partner choice promotes cooperation in social networks.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>78</volume>             <fpage>026117</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Vainstein2">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vainstein</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arenzon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Disordered environments in spatial games.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>64</volume>             <fpage>051905</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Lozano1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arenas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Mesoscopic structure conditions the emergence of cooperation on social networks.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>e1892</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035776-Jiang1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Role of adaptive migration in promoting cooperation in spatial games.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>81</volume>             <fpage>036108</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>