<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-10-04965</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biogeography</subject>
              <subject>Macroecology</subject>
              <subject>Spatial and landscape ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Zoology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Ornithology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Ecology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Elevational Gradients in Bird Diversity in the Eastern Himalaya: An Evaluation of Distribution Patterns and Their Underlying Mechanisms</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Elevational Distribution of Birds in Himalaya</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Acharya</surname>
            <given-names>Bhoj Kumar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
            <sup>¤</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sanders</surname>
            <given-names>Nathan J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Vijayan</surname>
            <given-names>Lalitha</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Chettri</surname>
            <given-names>Basundhara</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
            <sup>¤</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Division of Conservation Ecology, Sàlim Ali Centre for Ornithology and Natural History, Anaikatty, Coimbatore, India</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, Tennessee, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Nogues-Bravo</surname>
            <given-names>David</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Copenhagen, Denmark</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">acharya2skm@gmail.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: BKA NJ LV BC. Performed the experiments: BKA BC. Analyzed the data: BKA NJS. Wrote the paper: BKA NJS LV BC. Obtained the permission for fieldwork: BKA LV BC.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="fn1">
          <label>¤</label>
          <p>Current address: Department of Zoology, Sikkim Government College, Tadong, Gangtok, Sikkim, India</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e29097</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Acharya et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Understanding diversity patterns and the mechanisms underlying those patterns along elevational gradients is critically important for conservation efforts in montane ecosystems, especially those that are biodiversity hotspots. Despite recent advances, consensus on the underlying causes, or even the relative influence of a suite of factors on elevational diversity patterns has remained elusive.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods and Principal Findings</title>
          <p>We examined patterns of species richness, density and range size distribution of birds, and the suite of biotic and abiotic factors (primary productivity, habitat variables, climatic factors and geometric constraints) that governs diversity along a 4500-m elevational gradient in the Eastern Himalayan region, a biodiversity hotspot within the world's tallest mountains. We used point count methods for sampling birds and quadrats for estimating vegetation at 22 sites along the elevational gradient. We found that species richness increased to approximately 2000 m, then declined. We found no evidence that geometric constraints influenced this pattern, whereas actual evapotranspiration (a surrogate for primary productivity) and various habitat variables (plant species richness, shrub density and basal area of trees) accounted for most of the variation in bird species richness. We also observed that ranges of most bird species were narrow along the elevation gradient. We find little evidence to support Rapoport's rule for the birds of Sikkim region of the Himalaya.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions and Significance</title>
          <p>This study in the Eastern Himalaya indicates that species richness of birds is highest at intermediate elevations along one of the most extensive elevational gradients ever examined. Additionally, primary productivity and factors associated with habitat accounted for most of the variation in avian species richness. The diversity peak at intermediate elevations and the narrow elevational ranges of most species suggest important conservation implications: not only should mid-elevation areas be conserved, but the entire gradient requires equal conservation attention.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was funded by MoEF, Government of India, through CISMHE, University of Delhi. NJS was supported by DOE-PER DE-FG02 a grant from the Danish National Research Foundation to the Center for Macroecology, Evolution and Climate. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="14"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Biodiversity varies geographically, and understanding why is one of the fundamental questions in biogeography, macroecology, and conservation ecology. Perhaps the best- studied pattern in species richness is the latitudinal gradient in diversity - the decline (for most taxa) in richness with increasing distance from the equator <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rosenzweig1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Gaston1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Hillebrand1">[3]</xref>. Elevational gradients, though perhaps not studied as intensively as the latitudinal gradient, provide equally striking patterns in diversity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Sanders1">[4]</xref>. The most common patterns seem to be either decreasing richness with increasing elevation or a hump-shaped pattern, in which diversity peaks at mid-elevations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rahbek1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain1">[6]</xref>. While many studies have documented patterns in diversity along elevational gradients and have attempted to describe the mechanisms underlying those patterns, the consensus on the generality of pattern and processes is still a topic of discussion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Sanders1">[4]</xref>. Understanding such patterns and their underlying mechanisms is critically important for conservation efforts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Hunter1">[7]</xref>, especially in biodiversity hotspots, montane regions which are likely to be especially threatened by climate change, and regions that have been generally un- or under-explored by biologists.</p>
      <p>Patterns in diversity along elevational gradients might vary among taxa, regions, and spatial scales <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Patterson1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Sanders2">[11]</xref>. Though the hump-shaped pattern is the most commonly reported pattern, its ubiquity might depend on the methods employed, sampling effort, taxa and gradient considered <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rahbek1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kattan1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Terborgh1">[12]</xref>. Moreover, whether the entire gradient is sampled can also influence the apparent pattern <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-NoguesBravo1">[13]</xref>. With some exceptions, studies on elevational diversity gradients are restricted to either low, mid or high elevation, in essence covering only a part of the gradient or on a smaller mountain with narrow elevational breadth. Data that span over the entire gradient or data from the highest elevations where life occurs, especially when the gradient itself is extensive, likely provide more opportunities for better understanding patterns of species richness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kattan1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Hawkins1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Blake1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Naniwadekar1">[16]</xref>. For instance, the extensive elevational gradient of Himalaya (from 200 m to &gt;8000 m) provides an ideal test bed for a broader understanding of the pattern of diversity with elevation and the underlying causes of the pattern <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Krner1">[17]</xref>. Our study, for example, covers 4500 m in elevation (300–4700 m) in the hitherto under-explored Eastern Himalayan Mountains. To our knowledge, this is the most extensive elevational gradient for birds ever examined.</p>
      <p>The most frequently documented correlates and drivers of elevational patterns of diversity include contemporary climate (temperature, rainfall; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kluge1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain2">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Sanders3">[20]</xref>), biological processes (mass effects, productivity, habitat heterogeneity, interspecific interactions; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rosenzweig1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kattan1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rosenzweig2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Whittaker1">[22]</xref>), evolutionary and historical processes (niche conservatism, isolation, speciation, endemism, and evolutionary diversification; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Heaney1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Machac1">[26]</xref> and spatial factors (area and the mid-domain effect; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rahbek2">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain3">[30]</xref>).</p>
      <p>One idea that has persisted in the literature is Rapoport's rule, which, as originally formulated, posited that the mean latitudinal range of species is smaller at low latitudes than at high latitudes because species at high latitudes are adapted to a broad spectrum of climatic conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Stevens1">[31]</xref>. A ‘rescue effect’ then would lead to higher species richness at lower latitudes than at higher latitudes if those species at high latitudes ‘spill’ down to lower latitudes. Some empirical support exists for Rapoport's rule, though the idea is still contentious <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Gaston2">[32]</xref>. Stevens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Stevens2">[33]</xref> extended Rapoport's rule to apply to elevational gradients as well, such that the ranges of species might be greater at high elevations than at low elevations, and the rescue effect would suggest that richness should decline with elevation. And indeed, there is some empirical support for Rapoport's elevational rule <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Sanders4">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Flieshman1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Bhattarai1">[35]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Another relatively controversial idea is that geometric constraints or mid-domain effects (MDE) are important drivers for such a pattern <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Colwell1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Colwell2">[36]</xref>. MDE results from random placement of species ranges within a bounded geographical domain creating a mid-elevation peak of species richness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Colwell1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Colwell3">[37]</xref>. Though critics argue that the MDE does not provide biological explanations for elevational richness patterns <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain4">[38]</xref> and some MDE patterns might be spurious <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Currie1">[39]</xref>, the MDE at a minimum provides appropriate null models and should be evaluated in combination with biotic, abiotic and historical factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain3">[30]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In this study, we examine the elevational gradient in bird diversity in the Sikkim region of the Eastern Himalaya, home to the tallest mountains in the world. In particular, our aims are to document, describe, and explain the elevational gradient in bird diversity in the Eastern Himalaya. First, we describe the pattern along this extensive gradient (we note that we did not sample the entire gradient due to logistical reasons but this might not influence overall pattern as there are very few plants or birds above the highest elevation we have sampled). Then, we evaluate a suite of biotic and abiotic factors that might be correlated with bird diversity, focusing on geometric constraints, temperature, precipitation, potential evapotranspiration (PET), actual evapotranspiration (AET), plant species richness, tree density, shrub density and basal area of tree. These parameters broadly represent MDE, energy, productivity and habitat diversity. Finally, we assessed the range size distribution pattern of birds along the elevation gradient by examining the elevational range size of each bird species and the applicability of Rapoport's rule.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Study area</title>
        <p>The study area is in the Eastern Himalayan Mountains (the state of Sikkim in India; 27° 03' to 28° 07' N and 88° 03' to 88° 57' E). Elevation in this region ranges from c.300 m to above 8000 m. The study sites were located in the Teesta Valley which consists of rough hilly terrain and varies in elevation from 300–5500 m. Both climate (tropical to temperate) and vegetation type (tropical forest to alpine meadows) vary with elevation, within a distance of ∼150 km. The lower and middle valleys (&lt;2000 m) are hot and humid with annual precipitation exceeding 2500 mm, while elevations above 2500 m are relatively drier and colder with substantially less rainfall (&lt;1000 mm). At the high elevation sites, precipitation is in the form of snowfall, and most of the alpine region remains under snow for almost 7–8 months a year.</p>
        <p>Six major vegetation zones occur in the study area. These are Tropical semi-deciduous forests (&lt;900 m), Tropical moist and broad-leaved forests (900–1800 m), Temperate broad-leaved forests (1800–2800 m), Temperate coniferous and broad-leaved forests (2800–3800 m), Sub-alpine (3800–4500 m) and Alpine vegetation (&gt;4500 m) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Haribal1">[40]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Bird sampling</title>
        <p>To quantify variation in the richness and abundance of birds along this elevational gradient, at 22 sites, we used the open width point count method along transects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Bibby1">[41]</xref>. The open width point count method is particularly effective for rapid assessment of bird assemblages, especially when large areas are sampled <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Bibby1">[41]</xref>. The transects varied in length from 600–1000 m, depending on vegetation type and accessibility, and were distributed among six vegetation types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g001">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029097-t001">Table 1</xref>). We avoided sites with clear evidence of disturbance by humans. Elevational distance between two consecutive sites was 150 m to 350 m depending upon the accessibility and availability of the sites. Within each transect at each site, we established permanent points (6–10 points depending upon the length of the transect) for bird sampling, keeping a minimum of 100 m distance between two adjacent sampling points along the transect. We conducted a count at each point for five minutes and recorded the identities and abundance of all birds seen or heard. All points were replicated 1–3 times each during winter (Dec-Feb), summer (Mar-May), monsoon (Jun-Aug) and post monsoon (Sept-Nov) during 2003–2006. Thus, a total of 2428 point counts were conducted during entirety of this study. Prior to the field study, we obtained the permission from the Forests, Environment and Wildlife Management Department, Government of Sikkim (Permit Nos. 07/GOS/FEWD and 54/GOS/FEWD).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029097-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Map of Sikkim showing sampling locations in different elevations.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0029097-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Details of transects laid along the elevation gradient of Sikkim, Eastern Himalaya.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0029097-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Transect</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Elevation (m)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vegetation Types</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Latitude(° ′N)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Longitude(° ′E)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Effort</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">300</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TrSDF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 12.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 28.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">450</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TrSDF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 14.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 27.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TrSDF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 14.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 28.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">750</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TrSDF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 15.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 26.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">900</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TrSDF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 29.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 30.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1050</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TrMBF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 29.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 30.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1200</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TrMBF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 29.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 30.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1350</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TrMBF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 33.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 38.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1500</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TrMBF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 34.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 39.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T10</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1650</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TrMBF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 36.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 38.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1900</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TBF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 37.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 36.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T12</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2150</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TBF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 37.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 42.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T13</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2400</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TBF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 39.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 36.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T14</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2650</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TBF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 39.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 43.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T15</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2850</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TCF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 41.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 45.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T16</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3050</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TCF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 45.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 43.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3250</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TCF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 46.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 42.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T18</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3450</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TCF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 48.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 42.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T19</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3650</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TCF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 49.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 42.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T20</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4000</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SAV</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 51.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 41.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T21</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4350</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SAV</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 52.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 41.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T22</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4700</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AV</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 54.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 41.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>TrSDF - Tropical semi-deciduous forests; TrMBF - Tropical moist and broad-leaved forests; TBF - Temperate broad-leaved forests; TCF - Temperate coniferous forests; SAV - Sub Alpine vegetation and AV - Alpine vegetation. Effort - No. of times each transect was repeated for sampling birds.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Vegetation sampling</title>
        <p>We also sampled the trees and shrubs at each of the 22 sites. Along each transect used for sampling birds at each site, we placed 10 20 m × 10 m quadrats for enumeration of trees. Plants with GBH (girth at breast height) &gt;20 cm were considered as trees. For estimating shrub density, two 5 m × 5 m sub-quadrats were placed diagonally within each of the 20 × 10 m quadrats. Thus, for each site, we recorded the richness and density of trees, the richness and density of shrubs, and the GBH of trees. We also estimated basal area of trees for each site using the formula: Basal Area  =  (GBH)<sup>2</sup>/4Л, where Л  = 3.14.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Climate and climatic variables</title>
        <p>We obtained rainfall and temperature data from seven locations at different elevations in the study region from Indian Meteorological Department. Based on these data, rainfall and temperature were estimated for all locations using regression equations, as is often done in these types of analyses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kluge1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Sanders3">[20]</xref>. The equations used for estimation were</p>
        <p>rainfall =  -0.7909(elevation) + 4046.1, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.975, p&lt;0.01</p>
        <p>temperature  = -0.0062(elevation) + 29.85, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.983, p&lt;0.01.</p>
        <p>We calculated potential evapotranspiration (PET) using the formula [PET =  mean annual bio-temperature (i.e. temperature &gt; 0°C) x 58.93] (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Bhattarai2">[42]</xref>). PET is an estimate of the potential amount of water released through transpiration and surface evaporation from vegetation that is well supplied with water <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Currie2">[43]</xref> and is considered as a surrogate of energy. We used actual evapotranspiration (AET) as surrogate of productivity. We calculated AET using the Turc's formula, AET = P/ [0.9 + (P/L)<sup> 2</sup>]<sup>1/2</sup> with L = 300 + 25T + 0.05T<sup>3</sup>, where P = mean annual precipitation and T = mean annual temperature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kluge1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Turc1">[44]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Data Analysis</title>
        <sec id="s2e1">
          <title>How does richness vary with elevation?</title>
          <p>We examined how observed species richness, estimated richness had sampling gone to completion, rarefied richness and density of birds varied with elevation for the 22 sampling sites. Observed species richness was the total count of species detected across all seasons at each site. We followed Reynolds et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Reynolds1">[45]</xref> to estimate density as D = n *10000/ Л r<sup>2</sup>C, where D = bird density (numbers/ha), n = total number of birds observed in all counts within the specific radius, r = specific radius (m) (specific radius is the average radial distance of birds from the observer), C = total number of counts conducted and Л = 3.14. We also estimated individual-based rarefied richness, which accounts for variation in the number of individuals sampled. We rarefied to the lowest number of individuals detected in any one survey (n = 260). Because some sites were more frequently sampled than others, we also used sample-based rarefaction (rarefied to lowest number of counts conducted (n = 72 point counts) for any site. Since the individual and sample-based rarefaction results were qualitatively similar, we report only the results from the individual-based rarefaction (but the results from sample-based rarefaction are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029097.s001">Figures S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029097.s002">S2</xref>).</p>
          <p>Additionally, we used two other approaches to assess whether our sampling protocol introduced any potential biases. First, we used a two-step rarefaction approach by using only six sampling points (the lowest number of points sampled) at each site from one season (summer) and rarefied to lowest number of individuals detected at any one site (n = 15). We found that the pattern of this two-step rarefaction procedure did not differ qualitatively from either total bird species richness (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">results</xref>) or the more standard individual- or sample-based rarefaction procedures described above (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g002">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029097.s003">Figure S3</xref>). Second, because the number of species in a sample rarely asymptotes, either because of missed species or because of unequal sampling, we estimated the Chao2 estimated species richness of each site using EstimateS, version 7 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Colwell4">[46]</xref>. While non-parametric estimators have their own biases and levels of precision, we selected the Chao2 because this estimator is less sensitive to patchiness of species distributions and variability in the probability of encountering species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Hortal1">[47]</xref>.</p>
          <fig id="pone-0029097-g002" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g002</object-id>
            <label>Figure 2</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Elevational distribution pattern of birds.</title>
              <p>Elevational variation of bird species richness (observed and Chao 2), rarefied richness (rarefied to 260 individuals) and density (birds/ha) in Sikkim, Eastern Himalaya.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
          </fig>
          <p>To describe the pattern of observed species richness, the Chao2 estimate of species richness, rarefied richness and density along the elevational gradient, we used ordinary least squares (OLS) regressions. Because the relationship between any estimate of richness and elevation need not be linear, we also used a quadratic term (elevation<sup>2</sup>) in each model to relate each of the response variables (observed richness, Chao2 estimated species richness, rarefied richness and density) to elevation. We compared AIC values to determine whether the linear or quadratic model best accounted for variation in each of the response variables. Because spatial autocorrelation can inflate errors in the statistical analyses of ecological data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-DinizFilho1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Bini1">[49]</xref>, we also used spatial regressions. We generated spatial correlograms for observed bird species richness and density using Moran's <italic>I</italic> coefficients with the software SAM version 4.0 (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rangel1">[50]</xref> for application and analytical procedure).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2e2">
          <title>Is there evidence of a mid-domain effect?</title>
          <p>We used Monte Carlo simulations programme, mid-domain effect null model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain3">[30]</xref> for testing geometric constraints or mid-domain effects on species ranges. This programme uses empirical range sizes or range midpoints within the elevational range and simulates species richness curves based on analytical-stochastic models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Colwell1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Colwell3">[37]</xref>. To test the impact of spatial constraints on species richness, 95% prediction curves were produced based on 50,000 simulations (without replacement) using empirical range sizes. Simulations using range mid-points arbitrarily show better fit to null model because midpoint simulations are too constrained by the empirical data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain3">[30]</xref>. Hence, range size simulation rather than range midpoint simulations are better for assessing fit to MDE null models for geometric constraints of species richness. The empirical species richness curves were compared with the 95% confidence intervals generated from species range sizes. Species richness data were generated at 100 m elevational increments. We then regressed the average of the predicted number of species against the observed empirical values to assess whether geometric constraints could contribute to the pattern of bird species richness in this system. In addition, we also used MDE predicted richness as predictor variable in the multiple regression model (see below).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2e3">
          <title>What factors are correlated with richness?</title>
          <p>We first used several simple linear regression models to explore the potential of individual environmental factors to predict observed bird species richness, Chao2 estimated species richness, rarefied species richness and density. We then performed stepwise multiple regressions to identify the factors that were related with the species richness and density of birds. Among the set of factors, we selected six variables - AET, MDE predicted richness, plant species richness, tree density, shrub density and basal area of trees. Since temperature, rainfall and PET were highly correlated with one another and with AET, we dropped these factors from the model and used only AET. In each step, the factor with lowest AIC and sums of squares was dropped until we found no significant difference between the model with or without that particular factor. This analysis was performed using statistical package R version 2.11.0. As discussed above, we also generated spatial correlograms for AET, MDE predicted richness, plant species richness, tree density, shrub density and basal area of trees using software SAM version 4.0 (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rangel1">[50]</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2e4">
          <title>Are range size and elevation correlated?</title>
          <p>We estimated the range of each species as the difference between the lowest and highest elevation at which that species was recorded during the study. The assumption then is that the species occurs at all intermediate elevations between lowest and highest elevation (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Patterson1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-MdNor1">[51]</xref>). We then asked whether there was a relationship between range size and elevation by regressing range size of each species against the lower and upper limits of its elevational range, as would be predicted if Rapoport's rule holds in this system.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>How does richness vary with elevation?</title>
        <p>We observed a total of 297 bird species over the course of the study from the 22 sites along this elevational gradient. The number of species observed at a single site varied from 27 to 89. Bird species richness exhibited a mid-elevation peak: the highest number of species was observed at approximately 2000 m (quadratic r<sup>2</sup> = 0.55, P &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g002">Figure 2</xref>) in the eastern Himalaya.</p>
        <p>Although the species accumulation curves approached a plateau for each of the sites, richness did not completely plateau for several of them (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g003">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029097.s001">Figure S1</xref>). Hence, we also examined the Chao2 estimate of the number of species had sampling gone to completion. Similar to the pattern for observed richness, the Chao2 estimated species richness also peaked at mid-elevations (r<sup>2</sup> = 0.55; p &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Because the number of individuals varied among sites, we also examined whether rarefied species richness varied systematically with elevation. The pattern of rarefied richness along the elevational gradient was best explained by a quadratic regression (r<sup>2</sup> = 0. 66; p &lt; 0.01). However, the pattern was not clearly hump-shaped. Instead, below about 2000 m, there was no systematic variation in rarefied richness with elevation, but above 2000 m, rarefied richness declined with elevation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029097-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Species accumulation curves of birds.</title>
            <p>Curves based on number of individuals detected in different elevational transects in Sikkim, Eastern Himalaya. Numbers in the figures indicate elevation (m) of the sampling site.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The total number of birds encountered varied from 260 to 1964 per site, and the mean number of individuals per point along each transect at each site ranged from 3.31 to 12.87. The density of birds ranged from 5.1 to 56.3 birds ha<sup>-1</sup> with the maximum density recorded at 2400 m and the minimum at 4350 m. Both the mean number of individuals per point (r<sup>2</sup> = 0. 46; p &lt; 0.01) and density (r<sup>2</sup> = 0. 45; p &lt; 0.01) peaked at mid-elevations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Vegetation along elevation gradient</title>
        <p>We recorded a total of 216 species of woody plants from the 22 sites. Of the total species observed, 170 were trees and 135 shrubs with 89 species common between trees and shrubs. Species richness of both trees and shrubs followed a hump-shaped relationship with elevation peaking at approximately 1500 m (Tree, r<sup>2</sup> = 0.71, p&lt;0.05; Shrubs, r<sup>2</sup> = 0.44, p&lt;0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Combined richness of trees and shrubs peaked at approximately1000 m. Shrub density also followed unimodal pattern with a peak at 1500 m, but tree density did not vary systematically with elevation. Basal area of trees was greatest at 1900 m elevation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029097-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Scatter plot showing the relationship between elevation and vegetation parameters in Sikkim, Eastern Himalaya.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Is there evidence of a mid-domain effect?</title>
        <p>We found, at best, limited support for a mid-domain effect. The curves were asymmetrical, and thus differed from mid-domain predictions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g005">Figure 5</xref>). A comparison of the empirical data with the 95% prediction curves obtained from 50,000 simulations using range sizes showed that 80% (35/44) of the empirical points occurred outside the predicted range of the null model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Empirical species richness was correlated with the mean of the predicted richness, but only weakly (r<sup>2</sup> = 0.18; p = 0.003). Additionally, bird species richness did not correlate with the MDE predicted richness (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029097-t002">Table 2</xref>) and MDE predicted richness (when used as predictor variable for observed bird species richness) fell out of the stepwise regression model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029097-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029097-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Mid-domain effect null model.</title>
            <p>Bird species richness curve (line with squares) along the elevation gradient of Sikkim, Eastern Himalaya with 95% simulation curves (lines without markers) obtained using empirical range sizes through the programme mid- domain null <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain3">[30]</xref>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0029097-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title>The r<sup>2</sup> values and associated <italic>P</italic>-values for simple linear regression between observed species richness, Chao2 estimated richness, rarefied richness and density of birds as a measure of six environmental factors.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0029097-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Parameters</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Observedbird species</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chao2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rarefied richness</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bird density</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MDE richness</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">r<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AET</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">r<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.25</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.29</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.35</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.06</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.28</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Plant species</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">r<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.47</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.45</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.52</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.30</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.008</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tree density</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">r<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.54</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.53</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.54</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Shrub density</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">r<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.42</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.38</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.37</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.44</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BA</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">r<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.18</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.11</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.18</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.32</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.006</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label/>
              <p>MDE - Mid-domain effect; AET - Actual evapotranspiration; BA - Basal area of trees. Significant (<italic>P</italic>≤0.05) r<sup>2</sup> values are shown in bold font.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0029097-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
            <title>Result of stepwise multiple regressions with bird species richness and bird density as response variable and MDE predicted richness, AET, plant species richness, tree density, shrub density and BA of trees as predictor variable.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0029097-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Model: Bird species ∼ AET + Shrub density</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&lt;none&gt;</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Df</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sum of Sq</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RSS</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AIC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2569.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110.73</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">AET</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2037.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4606.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121.57</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Shrub Density</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3336.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5905.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">127.04</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Residuals</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Min</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1Q</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3Q</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-7.078</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-5.486</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1.185</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.414</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.487</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Coefficients</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Estimate</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Std. Error</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">t value</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pr (&gt;|t|)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">(Intercept)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.843</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.395</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.881</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.009**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">AET</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0198</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0051</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.882</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Shrub Density</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000828</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000166</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.967</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00008***</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Model: Bird density ∼ Plant richness + Shrub density + BA</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&lt;none&gt;</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Df</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sum of Sq</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RSS</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AIC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1796.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104.86</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Plant</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">762.06</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2558.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110.63</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Shrub Density</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">597.03</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2393.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">109.17</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">BA</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">505.85</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2302.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108.31</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Residuals</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Min</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1Q</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3Q</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-13.8160</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-6.2631</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1712</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.6711</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.8234</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Coefficients</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Estimate</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Std. Error</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">t value</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pr (&gt;|t|)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">(Intercept)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0883</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.669</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.019</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9851</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Plant</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4119</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.149</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.763</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0128 *</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Shrub Density</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0004</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.446</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0250 *</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">BA</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0049</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0021</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.251</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0371 *</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label/>
              <p>MDE - Mid-domain effect; AET- Actual evapotranspiration; BA- Basal area of trees.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label/>
              <p>Only final model is presented here. Significant codes: ≤0 ‘***’ ≤0.001 ‘**’ ≤0.01 ‘*’.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>What factors are correlated with richness?</p>
        <p>The r<sup>2</sup> values and associated p-values for simple linear regression between bird species richness (observed and the Chao2 estimate), rarefied richness and density as a function of six environmental factors are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029097-t002">Table 2</xref>. AET, plant species richness, and shrub density were all positively correlated with bird species richness (observed, estimated and rarefied), whereas bird density was correlated with plant species richness, shrub density and basal area. In the stepwise regression model, AET and shrub density remained as the most important factors for bird species richness along the elevational gradient (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029097-t003">Table 3</xref>). Plant species richness, shrub density and basal area were most strongly correlated with bird density.</p>
        <p>The spatial correlogram for species richness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g006">Figure 6</xref>) indicated that richness was positively spatially autocorrelated up to 10 distance classes. Moran's I decreased beyond that point with negative or no correlation but the values were not statistically significant. Bird density also followed similar trend. For the suite of environmental variables, positive spatial autocorrelation appeared up to a few distance classes in all the cases with decline in Moran's I index towards higher distance classes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g006">Figure 6</xref>). For MDE predicted richness, tree density, and tree basal area, positive autocorrelation reappeared in the largest distance classes but for AET and plant species richness the Moran's I index declined towards larger distance classes with a negative autocorrelation coefficient.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029097-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Spatial correlograms for birds, AET and habitat variables along the elevation gradient of Sikkim, Eastern Himalaya.</title>
            <p>Correlograms represents (A) observed bird species richness, (B) bird density, (C) mid-domain effect predicted richness, (D) actual evapotranspiration, (E) plant species richness, (F) tree density, (G) shrub density and (H) basal area of trees.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Are range size and elevation correlated?</title>
        <p>Elevational range profiles of the birds of Eastern Himalaya showed that most species occupied very narrow elevational ranges along the gradient (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g007">Figure 7</xref>). Ninety bird species were restricted within 1800 m elevation, whereas 200 species occurred below 2600 m, and 40 species occurred only above 3000 m (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g007">Figure 7</xref>). Approximately 42% (125) of the bird species had elevational ranges of &lt;500 m, and 30% (90 species) were detected at only a single elevation. Thirty five species had range sizes of more than 2000 m (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g008">Figure 8</xref>). Only one species (White-capped Water Redstart Chaimarrornis leucocephalus) occurred at each site in the gradient (elevational range = 4500 m). The range sizes of low elevation species (especially those occurring below 1800 m elevation) tended to decrease with elevation (r = -0.34, p &lt; 0.01), whereas range sizes of high elevation species tended to increase with elevation (r = 0.37, p &lt; 0.01).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029097-g007" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Elevational range profiles of birds of Sikkim, Eastern Himalaya.</title>
            <p>Vertical bars indicate maximum and minimum elevational limits of each species.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0029097-g008" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g008</object-id>
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Elevational range-size distribution of birds of Sikkim, Eastern Himalaya.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.g008" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Along one of the most extensive elevational gradients in the world, we found that the species richness of birds in Eastern Himalaya displayed a distinct mid-elevation peak in species richness and density. Such a pattern is frequently documented in birds (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain1">[6]</xref>), small mammals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Patterson1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Heaney1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain3">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Graham1">[52]</xref>, herpetofauna <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Hofer1">[53]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Fu1">[54]</xref>, invertebrates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Olson1">[55]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Sanders5">[56]</xref> and plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kluge1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-VzquezG1">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Oommen1">[58]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Grau1">[59]</xref>. Other taxa in the Himalayas and nearby regions also exhibit mid-elevation peaks in species richness: plant diversity in the Central Himalaya, Nepal and Western Himalaya, India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Bhattarai2">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Oommen1">[58]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Grytnes1">[60]</xref> and small mammal diversity in the Mt. Qilian, China <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Li1">[61]</xref>. Clearly, the pattern is common, but what causes it?</p>
      <p>One idea is that perhaps the geometry of bounded domains or available area accounts for the mid-elevation peak in richness found here <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rahbek2">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Colwell1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Dunn1">[62]</xref>. However, we found little support for the MDE: only about 20% of the observed values of species richness occurred within the 95% prediction curve of the null model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029097-g005">Figure 5</xref>) and MDE predicted richness was not correlated with avian richness (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029097-t002">Table 2</xref>). In some cases, the MDE can account for most of the variation in species richness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kluge1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Colwell1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Jetz1">[63]</xref>. But in others it accounts for very little, or no variation in species richness (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Dunn1">[62]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Hawkins3">[64]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Hawkins4">[65]</xref>). Determining the circumstances for when the MDE does, and does not, account for variation in species richness is an important challenge for biogeographers and macroecologists <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Dunn1">[62]</xref>. We also think that available area is likely not important here. Furthermore, the most recent synthetic analysis at global scales found no support for the idea that area influences avian species richness along elevational gradients (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-McCain1">[6]</xref>).</p>
      <p>Various processes such as climate, productivity, habitat heterogeneity and mass effects have been proposed to explain elevational distributions of species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rosenzweig1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kattan1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Whittaker1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rahbek3">[66]</xref>. Though we did not test the entire suite of possible factors that could shape the pattern of bird diversity in the Eastern Himalaya, we found strong support for climatic and habitat variables. In particular, when we examined the potential correlates of species richness in isolation of one another using simple linear regressions, we found that both species richness and density of birds were positively and strongly correlated with AET, plant species richness and shrub density. Habitat heterogeneity and productivity are often correlated with bird species richness at various geographical scales <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-MacArthur1">[67]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kessler1">[71]</xref>. The diverse habitat with complex vegetation structure at mid-elevations in the Eastern Himalaya has relatively higher productivity, which would have caused peaks in species richness and abundance of birds.</p>
      <p>Many studies have examined how productivity might influence diversity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Gaston1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Whittaker1">[22]</xref>, and even in eastern Asia, there appears to be a relationship between primary productivity and bird species richness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Ding1">[72]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Ding2">[73]</xref>. However, some contention persists about both the shape of the relationship between diversity and productivity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Whittaker1">[22]</xref> and how exactly more productivity might lead to higher species richness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Evans1">[74]</xref>. The most frequently posited mechanism linking productivity to diversity is something like the ‘More Individuals Hypothesis’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Srivastava1">[75]</xref> or ‘species-energy’ theory. The basic idea is that more productivity leads to more individuals, and with more individuals, species richness is also higher, either because of reduced extinction probabilities or simply because of the sampling effect. However, it is unclear exactly why more energy should lead to more individuals of different species rather than simply more individuals of the same species. Indeed, in our study, when we removed the effect of ‘more individuals’ by rarefaction, there was still a strong and positive correlation between rarefied richness and AET.</p>
      <p>Evolutionary and historical events such as geographic isolation, dispersal, speciation and endemism could shape elevational diversity in montane regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Lomolino1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kessler1">[71]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Fjeldsa1">[76]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kozak1">[80]</xref>. It is hypothesized that several speciation events and subsequent dispersal into Himalayas occurred due to the formation of new habitats by climatic changes in the past <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Johansson1">[79]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Zhisheng1">[81]</xref>. Endemism appears to be lower in the Himalayas relative to other montane regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rasmussen1">[82]</xref> and indeed in all other global hotspots <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Orme1">[83]</xref>. Furthermore, recent work argues that speciation alone is not likely to drive the pattern we describe here because speciation is low within the Himalaya due to an apparent lack of potential barriers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Johansson1">[79]</xref>. Since Eastern Himalaya is located at the transition belt of Oriental and Palaearctic zoogeographical realms and Indian, Indochinese and Indomalayan regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Olson2">[84]</xref>, the avifauna in the study region could consist of immigrants from these realms and regions due to dispersal of species. While it would be unwarranted at this stage to discard endemism and speciation due to a dearth of empirical studies, further work could address these issues. In particular, applying phylogenetic analyses for the birds in the Eastern Himalayan region would clearly allow for a better evaluation of how (or whether) historical and evolutionary factors influence species richness (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Machac1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Kozak1">[80]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Graham2">[85]</xref>). However, the lack of robust phylogenetic hypotheses for many of these taxa examined here prevented us from pursuing this line of research.</p>
      <p>Variation in species richness and density are rarely, if ever, wholly explained by a single factor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Oommen1">[58]</xref>. And species richness varies in peculiar ways among taxa, even on the same elevational gradient <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Sanders2">[11]</xref>. In our case, we found that climatic and habitat factors accounted for most of the variation in the density and species richness of birds. It is of course not surprising that multiple factors can shape diversity gradients, and perhaps that is to be expected. What is somewhat surprising, however, is that these same factors accounted for variation in every attribute of the avian communities examined here – observed richness, the Chao2 estimate of diversity, rarefied richness and density.</p>
      <p>The decline in both species richness and density of birds above 2500 m is striking, and suggests an abrupt change in some factor or suite of factors that limits birds. The stature of the forest decreases dramatically at about this point, and the climatic conditions become increasingly severe beyond 2500 m in the region; both of these changes could cause declines in abundance and size distribution of invertebrates and scarcity of other food items for birds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Blake1">[15]</xref>. One potential criticism of our study is that we did not continue to sample avian communities above 4700 m elevation. However, we note that the decline in avian richness from 3000 m to 4700 m is very low (32 species at 3050 m and 27 species at 4700 m). While there are essentially a very few bird species above this elevation in this part of the Himalayas and, even if a few transient species were detected, their presence would not have qualitatively changed the overall patterns we document here.</p>
      <p>Rapoport's rule (extended to elevational gradients by Stevens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Stevens2">[33]</xref>) suggests that range size of species should increase with increasing elevation. Although range size of high elevation species in our case tended to increase with elevation, the relation was weak, and the ranges of low-elevation species actually decreased with increasing elevation. Hence, we find little evidence to support Rapoport's rule for the birds of Sikkim region of the Himalaya, indicating that Rapoport's rule does not explain the elevational pattern of birds in the eastern Himalaya. Rapoport's rule has invited criticisms and whether this rule is a general phenomena is an open question in biogeography <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Rohde1">[86]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Hernandez1">[87]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Most bird species in this study exhibited very narrow elevational ranges. Interestingly, of 297 species, only one species (White-capped Water Redstart Chaimarrornis leucocephalus) occurred at all 22 sites. Most occurred at only a few sites, suggesting that range sizes are extremely limited in this system, probably by a combination of dispersal ability, particular habitat associations, competition, or environmental tolerance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Gaston3">[88]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Orme2">[89]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Harris1">[90]</xref>. Most species here appear to be habitat specialists, either restricted to a handful of sites or a single vegetation zone. Those species with larger elevational ranges tended to be omnivores. For example, the omnivorous birds Blue Whistling Thrush (Myophonus caeruleus) and White-capped Water Redstart occupied extensive ranges along the gradient, whereas a true frugivore Pin-tailed Green Pigeon (Treron apicauda) was present at only a single elevation site. Playback experiments, coupled with physiological tolerance and behavioral observations about the degree of specialization among species would help elucidate the factors that limit the ranges of species along this extreme elevational gradient <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Jankowski1">[91]</xref>. However, in the absence of such exhaustive studies, incorporating phylogenetic analyses as a short cut to understanding the interplay between interspecific interactions and climatic tolerance (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029097-Graham2">[85]</xref>) would clearly be an important next step.</p>
      <p>In sum, along one of the longest elevational gradients in the world, we found that bird species richness and density showed hump-shaped relationship with elevation, peaking at approximately 2000 m, in the Eastern Himalayan region. The variation in richness and density was correlated strongly with both productivity and habitat rather than geometric constraints. The small elevational ranges of species along the gradient suggest that conservation efforts should consider the entire gradient rather than just portions of it.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0029097.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Species accumulation curves of birds.</bold> Curves based on number of point counts in different elevational transects in Sikkim, Eastern Himalaya. Numbers in the figures indicate elevation (m) of the sampling site.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0029097.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Elevational variation of rarefied bird species richness.</bold> Species richness observed when rarefied to 72 point counts along elevational transects in Sikkim, Eastern Himalaya.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0029097.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0029097.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Elevational variation of rarefied bird species richness.</bold> Species richness observed when rarefied to 15 individuals from six point counts from each site along elevational transects in Sikkim, Eastern Himalaya.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank the Department of Forests, Environment and Wildlife Management and Department of Home, Government of Sikkim for necessary permits and cooperation to carry out field work. We thank the Directors of SACON (V. S. Vijayan, Ravisankaran and P. A. Azeez) for facilities to work, and Ajith Kumar, S. Bhupathy, J. P. Tamang, Namrata Tamang, Ghanashyam Sharma, Jaya, Ranjini and SACON family for their support during field study and comments on the manuscript. Suhel Quader and Shiva Sharma helped us in stepwise regression analysis. Hospitality of local communities and yak herders, and support of field assistants Narayan, Bel, Ram Tiwari and Binod made field work enjoyable.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Rosenzweig1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenzweig</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Species diversity in space and time.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">436</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Gaston1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaston</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Global patterns in biodiversity.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>405</volume>             <fpage>220</fpage>             <lpage>227</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Hillebrand1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillebrand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>On the generality of the latitudinal diversity gradient.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>163</volume>             <fpage>192</fpage>             <lpage>211</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Sanders1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahbek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <article-title>The patterns and causes of elevational gradients.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Ecography</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>in press</publisher-name>             <comment>(In press)</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Rahbek1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahbek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>The role of spatial scale and the perception of large-scale species-richness patterns.</article-title>             <source>Ecol Lett</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>224</fpage>             <lpage>239</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-McCain1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCain</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Global analysis of bird elevational diversity.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>346</fpage>             <lpage>360</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Hunter1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>ML</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yonzon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Altitudinal distributions of birds, mammals, people, forests, and parks in Nepal.</article-title>             <source>Conserv Biol</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>420</fpage>             <lpage>423</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Patterson1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stotz</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Contrasting patterns of elevational zonation for birds and mammals in the Andes of southeastern Peru.</article-title>             <source>J Biogeogr</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>593</fpage>             <lpage>607</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Kattan1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kattan</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Bird diversity along elevational gradients in the Andes of Colombia: area and mass effects.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>451</fpage>             <lpage>458</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Rowe1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lidgard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Elevational gradients and species richness: do methods change pattern perception?</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>163</fpage>             <lpage>177</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Sanders2">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlton</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pogue</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Diverse elevational diversity gradients in great smoky mountains national park, USA.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Körner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spehn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Data mining for global trends in mountain biodiversity</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>75</fpage>             <lpage>87</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Terborgh1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Terborgh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1977</year>             <article-title>Bird species diversity on an Andean elevational gradient.</article-title>             <source>Ecology</source>             <volume>58</volume>             <fpage>1007</fpage>             <lpage>1019</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-NoguesBravo1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nogues-Bravo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romdal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahbek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Scale effects and human impact on the elevational species richness gradients.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>453</volume>             <fpage>216</fpage>             <lpage>218</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Hawkins1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>AFA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Altitudinal and latitudinal distribution of East Malagasy forest bird communities.</article-title>             <source>J Biogeogr</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>447</fpage>             <lpage>458</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Blake1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loiselle</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Diversity of birds along an elevational gradient in the Cordillera Central, Costa Rica.</article-title>             <source>Auk</source>             <volume>117</volume>             <fpage>663</fpage>             <lpage>686</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Naniwadekar1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naniwadekar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasudevan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Patterns in diversity of anurans along an elevational gradient in the Western Ghats, South India.</article-title>             <source>J Biogeogr</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>842</fpage>             <lpage>853</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Krner1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Körner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Why are there global gradients in species richness? Mountains might hold the answer.</article-title>             <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>513</fpage>             <lpage>514</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Kluge1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kluge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>What drives elevational patterns of diversity? A test of geometric constraints, climate, and species pool effects for pteridophytes on an elevational gradient in Costa Rica.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>358</fpage>             <lpage>371</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-McCain2">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCain</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Could temperature and water availability drive elevational species richness patterns? A global case study for bats.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>13</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Sanders3">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lessard</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Temperature, but not productivity or geometry, predicts elevational diversity gradients in ants across spatial grains.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>640</fpage>             <lpage>649</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Rosenzweig2">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenzweig</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1992</year>             <article-title>Species diversity gradients: we know more and less than we thought.</article-title>             <source>J Mammal</source>             <volume>73</volume>             <fpage>715</fpage>             <lpage>730</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Whittaker1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Meta-analyses and mega-mistakes: calling time on meta-analysis of the species richness–productivity relationship.</article-title>             <source>Ecology</source>             <volume>91</volume>             <fpage>2522</fpage>             <lpage>2533</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Heaney1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heaney</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Small mammal diversity along elevational gradients in the Philippines: an assessment of patterns and hypothesis.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>15</fpage>             <lpage>39</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Lomolino1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lomolino</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Elevational gradients of species density: historical and prospective views.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>3</fpage>             <lpage>13</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Hawkins2">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diniz-Filho</surname><given-names>JAF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soeller</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Climate, niche conservatism, and the global bird diversity gradient.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>170</volume>             <fpage>S16</fpage>             <lpage>S27</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Machac1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Machac</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Elevational gradients in phylogenetic structure of ant communities reveal the interplay of biotic and abiotic constraints on diversity.</article-title>             <source>Ecography</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>364</fpage>             <lpage>371</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Rahbek2">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahbek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>The relationship among area, elevation and regional species richness in Neotropical birds.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>149</volume>             <fpage>875</fpage>             <lpage>902</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Sanders4">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Elevational gradients in ant species richness: area, geometry, and Rapoport's Rule.</article-title>             <source>Ecography</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>25</fpage>             <lpage>32</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Colwell1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahbek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gotelli</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>The mid-domain effect and species richness patterns: what have we learned so far?</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>163</volume>             <fpage>E1</fpage>             <lpage>E23</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-McCain3">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCain</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>The mid-domain effect applied to elevational gradients: species richness of small mammals in Costa Rica.</article-title>             <source>J Biogeogr</source>             <volume>31</volume>             <fpage>19</fpage>             <lpage>31</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Stevens1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>The latitudinal gradient in geographical range: how so many species coexist in the tropics.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>133</volume>             <fpage>240</fpage>             <lpage>256</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Gaston2">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaston</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackburn</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spicer</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Rapoport's rule: time for an epitah.</article-title>             <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>70</fpage>             <lpage>74</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Stevens2">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1992</year>             <article-title>The elevational gradient in altitudinal range: an extension of Rapoport's latitudinal rule to altitude.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>140</volume>             <fpage>893</fpage>             <lpage>911</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Flieshman1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flieshman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>An empirical test of Rapoport's rule: Elevational gradients in montane butterfly communities.</article-title>             <source>Ecology</source>             <volume>79</volume>             <fpage>2482</fpage>             <lpage>2493</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Bhattarai1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattarai</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vetaas</surname><given-names>OR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Can Rapoport's rule explain tree species richness along the Himalayan elevation gradient, Nepal?</article-title>             <source>Divers Distrib</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>373</fpage>             <lpage>378</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Colwell2">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurtt</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>Nonbiological gradients in species richness and a spurious Rapoport effect.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>144</volume>             <fpage>570</fpage>             <lpage>595</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Colwell3">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>The mid-domain effect: geometric constraints on the geography of species richness.</article-title>             <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>70</fpage>             <lpage>76</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-McCain4">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCain</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>North American desert rodents: a test of the mid-domain effect in species richness.</article-title>             <source>J Mammal</source>             <volume>84</volume>             <fpage>967</fpage>             <lpage>980</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Currie1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Tests of the mid-domain hypothesis: A review of the evidence.</article-title>             <source>Ecol Monogr</source>             <volume>78</volume>             <fpage>3</fpage>             <lpage>18</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Haribal1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haribal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1992</year>             <article-title>The butterflies of Sikkim Himalaya.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Gangtok</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Sikkim Nature Conservation Foundation</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">217</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Bibby1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bibby</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mustoe</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Bird census techniques.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">302</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Bhattarai2">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattarai</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vetaas</surname><given-names>OR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grytnes</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Fern species richness along a central Himalayan elevational gradient, Nepal.</article-title>             <source>J Biogeogr</source>             <volume>31</volume>             <fpage>389</fpage>             <lpage>400</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Currie2">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Energy and large-scale patterns of animal-and plant-species richness.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>137</volume>             <fpage>27</fpage>             <lpage>49</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Turc1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turc</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1954</year>             <article-title>Le bilan d'eau des sols: relation entre les precipitation, l'evaporation et l'ecoulement.</article-title>             <source>Ann Agron</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>491</fpage>             <lpage>596</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Reynolds1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nussbaum</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1980</year>             <article-title>A variable circular-plot method for estimating bird numbers.</article-title>             <source>Condor</source>             <volume>82</volume>             <fpage>309</fpage>             <lpage>313</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Colwell4">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <comment>EstimateS (data analysis software system and user's guide), version 7. Published at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://viceroy.eeb.uconn.edu/estimates" xlink:type="simple">http://viceroy.eeb.uconn.edu/estimates</ext-link>. (Accessed 2008 11 March)</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Hortal1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hortal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>PAV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaspar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Evaluating the performance of species richness estimators: sensitivity to sample grain size.</article-title>             <source>J Anim Ecol</source>             <volume>75</volume>             <fpage>274</fpage>             <lpage>287</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-DinizFilho1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diniz-Filho</surname><given-names>JAF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bini</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Spatial autocorrelation and red herrings in geographical ecology.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>53</fpage>             <lpage>64</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Bini1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bini</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diniz-Filho</surname><given-names>JAF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rangel</surname><given-names>TFLVB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akre</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albaladejo</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Parameter estimation in geographical ecology: an empirical evaluation of spatial and non-spatial regression.</article-title>             <source>Ecography:</source>             <volume>32</volume>             <fpage>193</fpage>             <lpage>204</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Rangel1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rangel</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diniz-Filho</surname><given-names>JAF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bini</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>SAM: a comprehensive application for Spatial Analysis in Macroecology.</article-title>             <source>Ecography</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>46</fpage>             <lpage>50</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-MdNor1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Md Nor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Elevational diversity patterns of small mammals on Mount Kinabalu, Sabah, Malaysia.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>41</fpage>             <lpage>62</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Graham1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Bats versus birds: comparisons among Peruvian volant vertebrate faunas along an elevational gradient.</article-title>             <source>J Biogeogr</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>657</fpage>             <lpage>668</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Hofer1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bersier</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borcard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Spatial organization of a herpetofauna on an elevational gradient revealed by null model tests.</article-title>             <source>Ecology</source>             <volume>80</volume>             <fpage>976</fpage>             <lpage>988</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Fu1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Elevational gradients of diversity for lizards and snakes in the Hengduan Mountains, China.</article-title>             <source>Biodivers Conserv</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>707</fpage>             <lpage>726</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Olson1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>The distribution of leaf litter invertebrates along a Neotropical altitudinal gradient.</article-title>             <source>J Trop Ecol</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>129</fpage>             <lpage>150</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Sanders5">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Patterns of ant species richness along elevational gradients in an arid ecosystem.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>77</fpage>             <lpage>100</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-VzquezG1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vàzquez G</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Givnish</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Altitudinal gradients in tropical forest composition, structure, and diversity in the Sierra de Manantlàn.</article-title>             <source>J Ecol</source>             <volume>86</volume>             <fpage>999</fpage>             <lpage>1020</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Oommen1">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oommen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Elevational species richness patterns emerge from multiple local mechanisms in Himalayan woody plants.</article-title>             <source>Ecology</source>             <volume>86</volume>             <fpage>3039</fpage>             <lpage>3047</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Grau1">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grau</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grytnes</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birks</surname><given-names>HJB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>A comparison of altitudinal species richness patterns of bryophytes with other plant groups in Nepal, Central Himalaya.</article-title>             <source>J Biogeogr</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>1907</fpage>             <lpage>1915</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Grytnes1">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grytnes</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vetaas</surname><given-names>OR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Species richness and altitude: a comparison between null models and interpolated plant species richness along the Himalayan altitudinal gradient, Nepal.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>159</volume>             <fpage>294</fpage>             <lpage>304</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Li1">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Elevational gradients of small mammal diversity on the Northern slopes of Qilian, China.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>449</fpage>             <lpage>460</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Dunn1">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCain</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>When does diversity fit null model predictions? Scale and range size mediate the mid-domain effect.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>305</fpage>             <lpage>312</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Jetz1">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jetz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahbek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Geometric constraints explain much of the species richness pattern in African birds.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>98</volume>             <fpage>5661</fpage>             <lpage>5666</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Hawkins3">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diniz-Filho</surname><given-names>JAF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>The mid-domain effect cannot explain the diversity gradient of Nearctic birds.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>419</fpage>             <lpage>426</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Hawkins4">
        <label>65</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diniz-Filho</surname><given-names>JAF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>The mid-domain effect and diversity gradients: is there anything to learn?</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>166</volume>             <fpage>E140</fpage>             <lpage>E143</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Rahbek3">
        <label>66</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahbek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gotelli</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Entsminger</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rangel</surname><given-names>TFLVB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Predicting continental-scale patterns of bird species richness with spatially explicit models.</article-title>             <source>Proc Roy Soc B</source>             <volume>274</volume>             <fpage>165</fpage>             <lpage>174</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-MacArthur1">
        <label>67</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacArthur</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Recher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cody</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1966</year>             <article-title>On the relation between habitat selection and species diversity.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>100</volume>             <fpage>319</fpage>             <lpage>332</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Willson1">
        <label>68</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willson</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Comet</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Bird communities of northern forests: ecological correlates of diversity and abundance in the understory.</article-title>             <source>Condor</source>             <volume>98</volume>             <fpage>350</fpage>             <lpage>362</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Cuerto1">
        <label>69</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuerto</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Casenave</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Determinants of bird species richness: role of climate and vegetation structure at a regional scale.</article-title>             <source>J Biogeogr</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>487</fpage>             <lpage>492</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Freifeld1">
        <label>70</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freifeld</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Habitat relationships of forest birds on Tutuila Island, America Samoa.</article-title>             <source>J Biogeogr</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>1191</fpage>             <lpage>1213</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Kessler1">
        <label>71</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fjeldsa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Species richness and endemism of plant and bird communities along two gradients of elevation, humidity and land use in the Bolivian Andes.</article-title>             <source>Divers Distrib</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>61</fpage>             <lpage>77</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Ding1">
        <label>72</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>T-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>P-F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Energy flux, body size and density in relation to bird species richness along an elevational gradient in Taiwan.</article-title>             <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>299</fpage>             <lpage>306</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Ding2">
        <label>73</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>T-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>C-N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>P-F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Macro-scale bird species richness patterns of the East Asian mainland islands: energy, area and isolation.</article-title>             <source>J Biogeogr</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>683</fpage>             <lpage>693</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Evans1">
        <label>74</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaston</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Species-energy relationships at the macroecological scale: a review of the mechanisms.</article-title>             <source>Biol Rev</source>             <volume>80</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>25</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Srivastava1">
        <label>75</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Why more productive sites have more species: an experimental test of theory using tree-hole communities.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>52</volume>             <fpage>510</fpage>             <lpage>529</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Fjeldsa1">
        <label>76</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fjeldsa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mertens</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Correlation between endemism and local ecoclimatic stability documented by comparing Andean bird distributions and remotely sensed land surface data.</article-title>             <source>Ecography</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>63</fpage>             <lpage>78</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-DeKlerk1">
        <label>77</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Klerk</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fjeldsa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Biogeographical patterns of endemic terrestrial Afrotropical birds.</article-title>             <source>Divers Distrib</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>147</fpage>             <lpage>162</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Smith1">
        <label>78</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calsbeek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wayne</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holder</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Testing alternative mechanisms of evolutionary divergence in an African rain forest passerine bird.</article-title>             <source>J Evol Biol</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>257</fpage>             <lpage>268</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Johansson1">
        <label>79</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alström</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ericson</surname><given-names>PGP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Build-up of the Himalayan avifauna through immigration: a biogeographical analysis of the Phylloscopus and Seicercus warblers.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>61</volume>             <fpage>324</fpage>             <lpage>333</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Kozak1">
        <label>80</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozak</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiens</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Niche conservatism drives elevational diversity patterns in Appalachian salamanders.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>176</volume>             <fpage>40</fpage>             <lpage>54</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Zhisheng1">
        <label>81</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhisheng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kutzbach</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prell</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Evolution of Asian monsoons and phased uplift of the Himalaya-Tibetan plateau since late Miocene times.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>411</volume>             <fpage>62</fpage>             <lpage>66</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Rasmussen1">
        <label>82</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderton</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Birds of South Asia.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Washington, DC and Barcelona</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>The Ripley Guide. Smithsonian Institution and Lynx Edicions</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Orme1">
        <label>83</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orme</surname><given-names>CDL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eigenbrod</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickup</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Global hotspots of species richness are not congruent with endemism or threat.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>436</volume>             <fpage>1016</fpage>             <lpage>1019</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Olson2">
        <label>84</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinerstein</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wikramanayake</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>GVN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Terrestrial ecoregions of the worlds: a new map of life on Earth.</article-title>             <source>BioScience</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>933</fpage>             <lpage>938</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Graham2">
        <label>85</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahbek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Phylogenetic structure in tropical hummingbird communities.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>106</volume>             <fpage>19673</fpage>             <lpage>19678</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Rohde1">
        <label>86</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Rapoport's rule is a local phenomenon and cannot explain latitudinal gradients in species diversity.</article-title>             <source>Biodivers Lett</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>10</fpage>             <lpage>13</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Hernandez1">
        <label>87</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rozbaczylo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Biogeographical patterns and Rapoport's rule in southeastern Pacific benthic polychaetes of the Chilean coast.</article-title>             <source>Ecography</source>             <volume>28</volume>             <fpage>363</fpage>             <lpage>373</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Gaston3">
        <label>88</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaston</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Species-range-size distributions: patterns, mechanisms and implications.</article-title>             <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>197</fpage>             <lpage>201</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Orme2">
        <label>89</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orme</surname><given-names>CDL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>T-S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Global patterns of geographic range size in birds.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>1276</fpage>             <lpage>1283</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Harris1">
        <label>90</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pimm</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Range size and extinction risk in forest birds.</article-title>             <source>Conserv Biol</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>163</fpage>             <lpage>171</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029097-Jankowski1">
        <label>91</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jankowski</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levey</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Squeezed at the top: Interspecific aggression may constrain elevational ranges in tropical birds.</article-title>             <source>Ecology</source>             <fpage>1877</fpage>             <lpage>1884</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>