<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-21617</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051494</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Enzymes</subject>
              <subject>Glycobiology</subject>
              <subject>Proteins</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Immunology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Immunologic techniques</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Immunoassays</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Oncology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cancers and neoplasms</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genitourinary tract tumors</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Renal cell carcinoma</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Basic cancer research</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Urology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Renal cancer</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Immunology</subject>
          <subject>Urology</subject>
          <subject>Oncology</subject>
          <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Clinical Significance of Heparanase Splice Variant (T5) in Renal Cell Carcinoma: Evaluation by a Novel T5-Specific Monoclonal Antibody</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Significance of Heparanase Splice Variant in RCC</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Barash</surname>
            <given-names>Uri</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Arvatz</surname>
            <given-names>Gil</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Farfara</surname>
            <given-names>Roy</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Naroditsky</surname>
            <given-names>Inna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Doweck</surname>
            <given-names>Ilana</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Feld</surname>
            <given-names>Sari</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ben-Izhak</surname>
            <given-names>Ofer</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ilan</surname>
            <given-names>Neta</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Nativ</surname>
            <given-names>Ofer</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Vlodavsky</surname>
            <given-names>Israel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Cancer and Vascular Biology Research Center, Rappaport Faculty of Medicine, Technion, Haifa, Israel</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Urology, Bnai-Zion Medical Center, Haifa, Israel</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Pathology, Rambam Health Care Campus, Haifa, Israel</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, Carmel Medical Center, Haifa, Israel</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cukierman</surname>
            <given-names>Edna</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Fox Chase Cancer Center, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">Vlodavsk@cc.huji.ac.il</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: NI ON IV. Performed the experiments: UB GA SF. Analyzed the data: UB RF IN OBI NI ON. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RF ID ON. Wrote the paper: NI IV.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <elocation-id>e51494</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Barash et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>T5 is a novel splice variant of heparanase, an endo-β-D-glucuronidase capable of cleaving heparan sulfate side chains at a limited number of sites. T5 splice variant is endowed with pro-tumorigenic properties, enhancing cell proliferation, anchorage independent growth and tumor xenograft development despite lack of heparan sulfate-degrading activity typical of heparanase. T5 is over expressed in the majority of human renal cell carcinoma biopsies examined, suggesting that this splice variant is clinically relevant. T5 is thought to assume a distinct three-dimensional conformation compared with the wild type heparanase protein. We sought to exploit this presumed feature by generating monoclonal antibodies that will recognize the unique structure of T5 without, or with minimal recognition of heparanase, thus enabling more accurate assessment of the clinical relevance of T5. We provide evidence that such a monoclonal antibody, 9c9, preferentially recognizes T5 compared with heparanase by ELISA, immunoblotting and immunohistochemistry. In order to uncover the clinical significance of T5, a cohort of renal cell carcinoma specimens was subjected to immunostaining applying the 9c9 antibody. Notably, T5 staining intensity was significantly associated with tumor size (p = 0.004) and tumor grade (p = 0.02). Our results suggest that T5 is a functional, pro-tumorigenic entity.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by grants from the Israel Science Foundation (grant 593/10); National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health (grant CA106456); the Israel Cancer Research Fund (ICRF); the US-Israel Binational Science Foundation (BSF), and the Rappaport Family Institute Fund to I. Vlodavsky. I. Vlodavsky is a Research Professor of the ICRF. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="7"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Heparanase is an endo-β-glucuronidase that cleaves heparan sulfate (HS) side chains of heparan sulfate proteoglycans (HSPGs) presumably at sites of low sulfation, releasing saccharide products with appreciable size (4–7 kDa) that can still associate with protein ligands and facilitate their biological potency <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Dempsey1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Vlodavsky1">[3]</xref>. Mammalian cells express primarily a single dominant functional heparanase enzyme (heparanase-1). A second heparanase (heparanase-2) gene has been cloned based on sequence homology but apparently lacks HS degrading activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-LevyAdam1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-McKenzie1">[5]</xref>. Enzymatic degradation of HS leads to disassembly of the extracellular matrix (ECM) underlying endothelial and epithelial cells and is therefore involved in fundamental biological phenomena associated with tissue remodeling and cell migration, including inflammation, angiogenesis and metastasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Dempsey1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Parish1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Ilan1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Vreys1">[7]</xref>. While a decisive role of heparanase in cellular invasion and tumor metastasis is well documented <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Dempsey1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Parish1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Vreys1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Casu1">[8]</xref>, the function that heparanase plays in primary tumor progression is largely unknown, but likely involves angiogenic and signaling aspects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Arvatz1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Ramani1">[13]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Alternative splicing increases the coding capacity of the genome, generating multiple proteins from a single gene. The resulting protein isoforms frequently exhibit different biological properties that may play an essential role in tumorigenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Cooper1">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-vanAlphen1">[16]</xref>. We have recently reported the identification and characterization of a novel spliced form of human heparanase, termed T5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>. In this splice variant, 144 bp of intron 5 are joined with exon 4, resulting in a truncated, enzymatically inactive protein. T5 splice variant is endowed with pro-tumorigenic properties, enhancing cell proliferation, anchorage independent growth and tumor xenograft development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>. These features were observed in several tumor-derived cell lines over expressing T5, while T5 gene silencing was associated with reduced cell proliferation, suggesting that its function is relevant to multiple tumor types <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>. Notably, T5 mRNA expression is up-regulated in 75% of human renal cell carcinoma (RCC) biopsies examined, implying that this splice variant is clinically relevant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>. T5 is thought to assume a distinct three-dimensional conformation compared with the wild type (<italic>wt</italic>) heparanase protein. We sought to exploit this presumed feature by generating monoclonal antibodies that will recognize the unique structure of T5 without, or with minimal recognition of heparanase, thus enabling more accurate assessment of the clinical relevance of T5. Here, we provide evidence that such a monoclonal antibody (mAb), 9c9, preferentially recognizes T5 compared with heparanase by ELISA, immunoblotting and immunohistochemistry. A cohort of renal cell carcinoma specimens was subjected to immunostaining applying mAb 9c9. Notably, T5 staining intensity was significantly associated with tumor size (p = 0.004) and tumor grade (p = 0.02), suggesting that T5 is a functional, pro-tumorigenic entity.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Cloning and Purification of Maltose Binding Protein (MBP)-T5</title>
        <p>T5 was amplified by PCR using the following primers: forward 5' <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">GGAATTCATGCTG CTGCGCTCG</named-content> 3′ and reverse 5′AACTGCAGTCATTTCTTACTTGAGTAGG 3' and was inserted into bacterial expression vector (pMal-c2; NEB). The expression and purification of MBP and MBP-T5 was carried out according to the manufacture's (NEB) instructions. Briefly, MC1061 bacteria culture was grown in the presence of isopropyl-β-D-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG; 0.07 mM) for 5 h at 16°C. Bacteria were then harvested by centrifugation (5,000 g; 10 min at 4°C); the pellet was re-suspended in column buffer [80 mM Na<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 20 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> pH 7.5, 100 mM NaCl, 20 mM 4-(2-Aminoethyl) benzenesulfonyl fluoride hydrochloride (AEBSF)] and incubated with lysosyme (1 mg/ml; Sigma) for 30 min on ice. Following sonication and centrifugation, (20,000 g<italic>;</italic> 30 min), the supernatant was mixed gently with 1/10 volume of amylose resin (20 h; 4°C). The resin was then packed in a column, washed, and MBP-T5 was eluted with column buffer containing 10 mM maltose. Elution fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and protein concentration was determined by the Bradford assay (Bio-Rad).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Generation of Anti Human T5 Monoclonal Antibodies</title>
        <p>BALB/c mice were immunized with 50 µg of MBP-T5 fusion protein in complete Freund's adjuvant (CFA; Sigma), followed by five injections of MBP-T5 (50 µg) in incomplete Freund's adjuvant (IFA) every 2 weeks. Splenocytes were then isolated, fused with NSO myeloma cells and hybridomas were screened for their ability to bind MBP-T5 or heparanase but not MBP by ELISA, essentially as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-LevyAdam1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-GingisVelitski1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Shafat1">[19]</xref>. Positive hybridomas were selected, expanded and cloned. Hybridoma subclass was determined by isotyping kit according to the manufacturer's (Serotec, Oxford, UK) instructions. Monoclonal antibodies were purified from the cell supernatant by protein-G chromatography.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Cell lysates and Protein Blotting</title>
        <p>Preparation of cell lysates and immunoblotting analyses were carried out as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Patients</title>
        <p>The study included 66 patients with renal cancer (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051494-t001">Table 1</xref>) that were diagnosed in the Department of Urology, Bnai-Zion Medical Center, Haifa, Israel, whose archival paraffin-embedded pathological material was available for immunohistochmical analysis. The study protocol was approved by the Bnai-Zion Medical Center Helsinki Committee Institutional Review Board (IRB). Being a retrospective study that include data retrieval from medical records and paraffin blocks, the local IRB do not require individual patients approval by signing a written inform consent. It should be mentioned that some patients have died during follow up. All patients underwent surgical removal of the renal tumor (radical nephrectomy or partial nephrectomy). The follow-up protocol included physical examination, imaging studies of the chest and abdomen, renal function tests, and urine analysis. Patients were seen every 4 months during the first 2 years after surgery; every 6 months 2–5 years postoperatively and yearly thereafter. The clinical and pathological data of all patients was reviewed and patients were re-staged according to the 2009 Americam Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) revision of the tumor-node-metastasis (TNM) staging system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Edge1">[20]</xref>. The following information was recorded: demographics, site of tumor, histological subtype, Fuhrman's nuclear grade, TNM stage, treatment modality, and status at the end of the study.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0051494-t001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Demographic and clinical description of patients.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0051494-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of patients (%)</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Gender</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (65)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (35)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Grade</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (12)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (35)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (33)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (20)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Histology</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clear cell</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (75)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">papillary</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sarcomatoid</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (12)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">other</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Tumor size</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (40)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (30)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (30)</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>Data on 6 patients was missing.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Immunostaining</title>
        <p>Staining of formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded 5 micron sections was performed essentially as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-CohenKaplan1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Doweck1">[22]</xref>. Briefly, slides were deparaffinized, rehydrated, and subjected to antigen retrieval by boiling (20 min) in 10 mM citrate buffer, pH 6.0. Following washes with phosphate buffered saline (PBS), slides were incubated with 10% normal goat serum (NGS) in PBS for 60 min to block non specific binding and incubated (20 h, 4°C) with mAb 9c9, diluted 1∶100 in blocking solution. Slides were extensively washed with PBS containing 0.01% Triton X-100 and incubated with a secondary reagent (Envision G/2 system/AP) according to the manufacturer's (Dako, Glostrup, Denmark) instructions. Following additional washes, color was developed with the permanent red reagent (Dako), sections were counterstained with hematoxylin and mounted, as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-CohenKaplan1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-CohenKaplan2">[23]</xref>. Immunostained specimens were examined by senior pathologist (IN) who was blind to clinical data of the patients. Staining was scored according to the intensity of staining (0: none, +1: weak-moderate; +2: strong), and the percentage (extent staining) of tumor cells that were stained. The extent of staining was further categorized as low (0: &lt;10%), moderate (+1∶10–50%) and high (+2&gt;50% of the cells). Specimens that were similarly stained with mouse IgG, or applying the above procedure but lacking the primary antibody, yielded no detectable staining.</p>
        <p>Immunofluorescent double staining of heparanase and T5 applying antibody #733 and mAb 9c9 was carried out essentially as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-CohenKaplan1">[21]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Univariate association between T5 staining intensity and clinical and pathological findings as well as patients outcome, were analyzed using Chi Square tests (Pearson, Fisher exact test).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Generation and Characterization of T5-specific mAb</title>
        <p>We have recently reported the cloning of T5, a functional splice variant of heparanase endowed with pro-tumorigenic properties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>. In order to advance T5 research we developed a panel of monoclonal antibodies (mAb) against bacterially-expressed MBP-T5 fusion protein and compared their capacity to recognize T5 vs. heparanase by ELISA (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051494.s003">Table S1</xref>). We have noticed that some mAbs recognize heparanase and T5 to a similar extent (i.e., 7c4) while others (i.e., 9c9) preferentially recognized T5 vs. heparanase (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051494.s001">Fig. S1</xref>). Likewise, while antibody 7c4 recognized the latent 65 kDa heparanase and T5 to a similar extent by immunoblotting, antibody 9c9 preferentially reacts with T5 (15 and 17 kDa protein bands representing unglycosylated and glycosylated T5, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). Notably, mAbs 7c4 and 9c9 did not recognize the 8 kDa and 50 kDa heparanase subunits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>), nor the single chain constitutively-active enzyme (GS3; not shown), suggesting that the epitope of both antibodies is localized in the linker region of heparanase which is removed by proteolytic processing and is not present in the 8 and 50 kDa subunits or the GS3 variant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Arvatz1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Nardella1">[24]</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051494.s002">Fig. S2A</xref>). These results suggest that the generation of T5-specific monoclonal antibodies is feasible.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0051494-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Characterization of anti T5 mAb.</title>
            <p><bold>A</bold>. Immunoblotting. HEK 293 cells were transfected with heparanase (Hepa) or T5 gene constructs and lysate samples were subjected to immunoblotting applying mAb 7c4 (upper panel), mAb 9c9 (middle panel) or pAb 1453 (lower panel). Cells transfected with an empty vector (Vo) were used as control. Note that mAb 9c9 preferentially recognizes T5 vs. heparanase. <bold>B</bold>. Immunohistochemistry. Five micron sections of tumor xenografts produced by control CAG myeloma cells (Vo) or CAG cells over expressing heparanase (Hepa) or T5 were subjected to immunostaining applying mAb 9c9 as described under 'Materials and Methods'. Note that mAb 9c9 only reacts on sections derived from CAG cells over expressing T5. <bold>C</bold>. Human placenta. Placenta specimens were subjected to double immunofluorescent staining applying rabbit (pAb 733, green) and mouse (mAb 9c9, red) anti-heparanase antibodies. Merged image is shown in the lower panel. Note distinct expression pattern of heparanase (cytotrophoblasts) and T5 (villus stromal cells).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In order to reveal whether our antibodies are suitable for immunohistochemical analysis, and to explore their specificity, tumor xenografts were subjected to immunostaining. Remarkably, the specificity observed by ELISA and immunoblotting was also seen in immunostaining. Thus, antibody 7c4 reacted similarly with tumor xenografts generated by CAG human myeloma cells over-expressing heparanase or T5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>, left). In contrast, antibody 9c9 only reacted with tumor xenografts produced by CAG cells over-expressing T5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>, right lower panel). Encouraged by these results, we next examined the performance of antibody 9c9 on human specimens. We first employed placenta tissue which exhibits high levels of heparanase expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Dempsey2">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-HaimovKochman1">[26]</xref>. Heparanase staining was most intense in cytotrophoblasts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>, green), in agreement with previous results <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-HaimovKochman1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Zetser1">[27]</xref>. Importantly, mAb 9c9 did not stain the cytotrophoblasts but rather the villus stromal cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>, red). This result clearly demonstrates the specificity of mAb 9c9 staining towards T5 vs. heparanase and illustrates the tight control of heparanase mRNA alternative splicing, resulting in the generation of T5 in a discrete, cell-specific manner.</p>
        <p>We have next examined the capability of mAb 9c9 to detect T5 in tumor biopsies. In head and neck cancer, mAb 9c9 stained positively the epithelial compartment of some carcinomas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>); in other specimens, cells of the tumor microenvironment, predominantly mononuclear cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g002">Fig. 2F</xref>), rather than carcinoma cells stained positively for mAb 9c9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>). In addition, mAb 9c9 nicely decorated endothelial cells lining blood vessels and adjacent pericytes in the tumor vasculature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g002">Figs. 2D, E</xref>; 3D), in agreement with pro-angiogenic properties of T5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>. T5 staining at higher frequency and intensity was noted in renal cell carcinoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g003">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0051494-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>T5 staining in head and neck tumor biopsies.</title>
            <p>Tumor specimens were subjected to immunohistochemical analyses applying mAb 9c9 as described under 'Materials and Methods'. Shown are representative images of head and neck T5 negative (<bold>A</bold>) and positive tumors expressing T5 in tumor cells (<bold>B</bold>), tumor microenvironment (<bold>C, F</bold>), and tumor-associated blood vessels (<bold>D, E</bold>).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0051494-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>T5 staining in RCC.</title>
            <p>Tumor specimens were subjected to immunohistochemical analyses applying mAb 9c9 as described above. Shown are representative images of RCC T5 negative (<bold>A</bold>) and positive specimens of low grade clear cell carcinoma (<bold>B</bold>) and high grade sarcomatoid tumors (<bold>C</bold>). Staining of tumor-associated blood vessels is shown in (<bold>D</bold>).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Clinical Relevance of T5 for RCC</title>
        <p>We employed mAb 9c9 to examine T5 expression in specimens collected from RCC patients. Sixty six patients (43 male; 23 female) were included in the study (median age at diagnosis was 60.3±13.3), predominantly classified as clear cell carcinoma (75%). Demographic and clinical description of patients is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051494-t001">Table 1</xref>. T5 staining was observed in 67% of the cases (44/66; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g003">Fig. 3B, C</xref>), close in magnitude to T5 expression in RCC evaluated by RT-PCR (75%; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>), whereas 33% (22/66) of the specimens were negative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). T5 staining was associated with tumor grade (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051494-t002">Table 2</xref>). Here, 32% of the cases scored negative for T5 were categorized as advanced grade (3+4) compared with 63% of the cases with high grade tumors that stained positively for T5 (p = 0.02). Notably, T5 staining was associated with tumor size (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051494-t003">Table 3</xref>). Thus, 32% of the cases that were scored negative for T5 had tumors larger than 4 cm; in contrast, 73% of the cases that were stained positive for T5 had large tumors (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051494-t003">Table 3</xref>), differences that are statistically highly significant (p = 0.004). There was no association between T5 and histological subtype, stage at presentation, or patients’ outcome.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0051494-t002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>T5 staining associates with tumor grade in RCC.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0051494-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Tumor grade</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1+2 (%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+4 (%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (68)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (32)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (37)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (63)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label/>
              <p>P = 0.02.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>Data on 6 patients was missing.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0051494-t003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.t003</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>T5 staining associates with tumor size in RCC.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0051494-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Tumor size</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;4 cm(%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;4 cm(%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (68)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (32)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (27)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (73)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label/>
              <p>P = 0.004.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>Data on 6 patients was missing.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Alternative splicing considerably expands the information content of the transcriptome and proteome through the expression of different mRNAs from a single gene. Splicing abnormalities are a common characteristic of cancer, including genes associated with cell growth, motility, apoptosis, and response to chemotherapy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Skotheim1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Srebrow1">[29]</xref>. Alternative splicing closely affects also the tumor microenvironment. For example, alternative splicing of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) generates protein variants capable or incapable of interacting with HS, exerting diverse angiogenic properties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Neufeld1">[30]</xref>. Similarly, HSPG (i.e., CD44) and other constituents of the ECM (i.e., fibronectin) are alternatively spliced, decisively mediating cell proliferation and tumor metastasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Weidle1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-White1">[32]</xref>. Splice variants of xenopus, mole rat (Spalax), and human heparanase have been described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Bertolesi1">[33]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Sato1">[36]</xref>, commonly lacking HS-degrading activity typical of heparanase and exerting as yet uncharacterized biological function.</p>
      <p>We have recently described a human heparanase splice variant termed T5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>. T5 is composed of the 8 kDa subunit and linker segment of heparanase but lacks the 50 kDa subunit which contains the substrate (HS)-binding domains and catalytic residues (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051494.s002">Fig. S2A</xref>). T5 is thus incapable of cleaving HS, yet endowed with pro-tumorigenic features thought to be mediated by Src activation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>. Here, we expand the notion that T5 expression is associated with tumor progression. T5 expression was enhanced in most (67%) RCC specimens, correlating with larger tumors and higher histological grade (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051494-t002">Tables 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051494-t003">3</xref>), two parameters that closely associate with patients' outcome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Cheville1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Zisman1">[38]</xref>, thus providing a clinical relevance for T5. A key reagent that enabled the clinical evaluation of T5 is mAb 9c9. This unique antibody preferentially recognizes T5 vs. heparanase by ELISA, immunoblotting, and immunostaining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g001">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051494.s003">Table S1</xref>). Immunohistochemical analysis applying mAb 9c9 is therefore expected to predominantly detect T5. It should be noted that unlike heparanase, T5 is not subjected to proteolytic processing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Barash2">[17]</xref>. Thus, lack of reactivity cannot be attributed to the loss of mAb 9c9 epitope but rather directly reflects T5 expression levels. Notably, distinct clinical associations were found for heparanase and T5. Hence, while heparanase staining in RCC was associated with histological subtype, distant metastasis, and patients' survival <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Mikami1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Ren1">[40]</xref>, T5 staining was not associated with these parameters but rather with tumor size and tumor grade (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051494-t002">Tables 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051494-t003">3</xref>). This suggests that heparanase and T5 affect different aspects of RCC tumor progression which complement each other. Interestingly, mAb 9c9 as well as mAbs 7c4, 2G7 and 5F8 did not recognize the 8 or 50 kDa heparanase subunits and their epitope was therefore concluded to be localized to the linker segment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051494.s003">Table S1</xref>). In contrast, mAbs 9D5 and 5B5 recognized the 8 kDa subunit, and further deletion mutagenesis analyses localized their epitope to the protein N-terminus (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051494.s003">Table S1</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051494.s002">Fig. S2B</xref>). This is in agreement with the three-dimensional structure predicted for heparanase in which the protein N-terminus appears unstructured, exposed, and likely immunogenic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051494-Fux2">[41]</xref>. The model, however, was predicted for the constitutively-active variant (GS3) lacking the linker segment. In the context of T5, the linker region appears to be exposed on the outer portion of the molecule, eliciting strong immunogenic reaction and antibody production. Thus, while the linker segment is thought to be inert in the context of wild type heparanase, it appears as a functional entity in the context of the T5 splice variant.</p>
      <p>Taken together, we provide evidence that T5 is a clinically relevant splice variant which may complement the pro-tumorigenic function of heparanase. T5 likely assumes a distinct three-dimensional folding other than that of heparanase, a notion that is now supported by our mAb 9c9. Expression of T5 in blood vessels and immune cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051494-g002">Figs. 2C–E</xref>; 3D) may suggest that T5 function is not restricted to cancer but may well be involved in other pathological disorders (i.e., inflammation). Clearly, more research is required to resolve the crystal structure of T5 and to appreciate its contribution to the progression of other types of cancer and non-cancerous disorders. Studies aimed at these directions are ongoing.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0051494.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>ELISA.</bold> 96-well plate was coated with MBP (▪), MBP-T5 (▪), or heparanase (▪) proteins (1 µg/ml) and incubated with the indicated mAb for 2 h at room temperature. Following washes, anti-mouse IgG HRP-conjugated secondary antibody (Jackson Immunoresearch; West Grove PA) was applied and mAb binding was visualized by colorimetric reaction (TMB/H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). Shown are representative OD values obtained.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0051494.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>A</bold>. <bold>Schematic diagram of heparanase/T5 structure.</bold> Heparanase is first synthesized as a pre-proenzyme, harboring 35 amino acids signal peptide (SP, Met<sup>1</sup>–Ala<sup>35</sup>) which is removed upon entering the ER. The protein is then subjected to glycosylation and secreted as a ∼65 kDa latent protein (upper panel). Proteolytic processing removes the linker domain (Ser<sup>110</sup>–Gln<sup>157</sup>), resulting in 8 kDa (Gln<sup>36</sup>–Glu<sup>109</sup>), and 50 kDa (Lys<sup>158</sup>–Ile<sup>543</sup>) protein subunits (second panel) that heterodimerize to yield an active enzyme. Replacement of the linker segment with three pairs of glycine (G)-serine (S) results in a constitutively-active single chain enzyme (GS3; third panel). The SP, 8 kDa and linker fragments are retained in T5, but the 50 kDa subunit is excised except for 9 amino acids, which are followed by the addition of three unique amino acids (SKK, lower panel). <bold>B</bold>. Epitope determination. HEK 293 cells were transfected with wild type 8 kDa gene construct or 8 kDa deleted at its C-terminus (Gln<sup>36</sup>–Ser<sup>77</sup>; 8ΔC) or N-terminus (Leu<sup>65</sup>–Glu<sup>109</sup>; 8ΔN). Control cells were transfected with an empty plasmid (Vo). Lysate samples were then subjected to immunoblotting applying mAb 5B5 (upper panels) or mAb 9D5 (second panels). Equal protein loading is exemplified by actin immunoblotting (fourth panel); Myc-tag immunoblotting confirms comparable expression levels of gene constructs (third panel). The epitope of both antibodies is localized at the protein N-terminus.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0051494.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051494.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Performance of anti-T5 monoclonal antibodies.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Dempsey1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunn</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Heparanase, a potential regulator of cell-matrix interactions</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Parish1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parish</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hulett</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Heparanase: a key enzyme involved in cell invasion</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1471</volume>: <fpage>M99</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Vlodavsky1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedmann</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Molecular properties and involvement of heparanase in cancer metastasis and angiogenesis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-LevyAdam1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy-Adam</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen-Kaplan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shteingauz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Heparanase 2 interacts with heparan sulfate with high affinity and inhibits heparanase activity</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>28010</fpage>–<lpage>28019</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-McKenzie1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tyson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stamps</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Cloning and expression profiling of Hpa2, a novel mammalian heparanase family member</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source> <volume>276</volume>: <fpage>1170</fpage>–<lpage>1177</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Ilan1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Regulation, function and clinical significance of heparanase in cancer metastasis and angiogenesis</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>2018</fpage>–<lpage>2039</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Vreys1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vreys</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mammalian heparanase: what is the message?</article-title> <source>J Cell Mol Med</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Casu1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Non-anticoagulant heparins and inhibition of cancer</article-title>. <source>Pathophysiol Haemost Thromb</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Arvatz1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arvatz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shafat</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy-Adam</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The heparanase system and tumor metastasis: is heparanase the seed and soil?</article-title> <source>Cancer Metastasis Rev</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Barash1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barash</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen-Kaplan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dowek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Proteoglycans in health and disease: new concepts for heparanase function in tumor progression and metastasis</article-title>. <source>FEBS J</source> <volume>277</volume>: <fpage>3890</fpage>–<lpage>3903</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Fux1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fux</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Heparanase: busy at the cell surface</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>519</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-LevyAdam2">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy-Adam</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Tumorigenic and adhesive properties of heparanase</article-title>. <source>Semin Cancer Biol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Ramani1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramani</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Heparanase plays a dual role in driving hepatocyte growth factor (HGF) signaling by enhancing HGF expression and activity</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>6490</fpage>–<lpage>6499</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Cooper1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>RNA and disease</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>793</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Tazi1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tazi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bakkour</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stamm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Alternative splicing and disease</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1792</volume>: <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-vanAlphen1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Alphen</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wiemer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eskens</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The spliceosome as target for anticancer treatment</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>228</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Barash2">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barash</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen-Kaplan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arvatz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gingis-Velitski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy-Adam</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A novel human heparanase splice variant, T5, endowed with protumorigenic characteristics</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1239</fpage>–<lpage>1248</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-GingisVelitski1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gingis-Velitski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishai-Michaeli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Anti-heparanase monoclonal antibody enhances heparanase enzymatic activity and facilitates wound healing</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>3986</fpage>–<lpage>3993</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Shafat1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafat</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zcharia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nisman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nadir</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakhoul</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>An ELISA method for the detection and quantification of human heparanase</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source> <volume>341</volume>: <fpage>958</fpage>–<lpage>963</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Edge1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Edge SB, Byrd DR, Compton CC, Fritz AG, Greene FL, Trotti A (Eds.) (2010) AJCC Cancer Staging Manual. 7th Edition, New York, NY, Springer.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-CohenKaplan1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen-Kaplan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naroditsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zetser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Heparanase induces VEGF C and facilitates tumor lymphangiogenesis</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>2566</fpage>–<lpage>2573</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Doweck1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doweck</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan-Cohen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naroditsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sabo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Heparanase localization and expression by head and neck cancer: correlation with tumor progression and patient survival</article-title>. <source>Neoplasia</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1055</fpage>–<lpage>1061</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-CohenKaplan2">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen-Kaplan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doweck</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naroditsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Heparanase augments epidermal growth factor receptor phosphorylation: correlation with head and neck tumor progression</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>10077</fpage>–<lpage>10085</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Nardella1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nardella</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lahm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pallaoro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vannini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mechanism of activation of human heparanase investigated by protein engineering</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>1862</fpage>–<lpage>1873</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Dempsey2">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coombes</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Heparanase expression in invasive trophoblasts and acute vascular damage</article-title>. <source>Glycobiology</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>475</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-HaimovKochman1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haimov-Kochman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedmann</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman-Wohl</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenfield</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Localization of heparanase in normal and pathological human placenta</article-title>. <source>Mol Hum Reprod</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>566</fpage>–<lpage>573</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Zetser1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zetser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy-Adam</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gingis-Velitski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bashenko</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Processing and activation of latent heparanase occurs in lysosomes</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>2249</fpage>–<lpage>2258</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Skotheim1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skotheim</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nees</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Alternative splicing in cancer: noise, functional, or systematic?</article-title> <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1432</fpage>–<lpage>1449</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Srebrow1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srebrow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kornblihtt</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The connection between splicing and cancer</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>2635</fpage>–<lpage>2641</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Neufeld1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gengrinovitch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poltorak</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) and its receptors</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Weidle1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weidle</surname><given-names>UH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maisel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klostermann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Differential splicing generates new transmembrane receptor and extracellular matrix-related targets for antibody-based therapy of cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Genomics Proteomics</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-White1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baralle</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muro</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>New insights into form and function of fibronectin splice variants</article-title>. <source>J Pathol</source> <volume>216</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Bertolesi1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertolesi</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michaiel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dueck</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hehr</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Two promoters with distinct activities in different tissues drive the expression of heparanase in Xenopus</article-title>. <source>Dev Dyn</source> <volume>240</volume>: <fpage>2657</fpage>–<lpage>2672</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Nasser1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasser</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avivi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shushy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nevo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Cloning, expression, and characterization of an alternatively spliced variant of human heparanase</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source> <volume>354</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Nasser2">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasser</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nevo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shafat</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Adaptive evolution of heparanase in hypoxia-tolerant Spalax: Gene cloning and identification of a unique splice variant</article-title>. <source>PNAS</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>15161</fpage>–<lpage>15166</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Sato1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amemiya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munakata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Subcellular localization of human heparanase and its alternative splice variant in COS-7 cells</article-title>. <source>Cell Biochem Funct</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>683</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Cheville1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheville</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zincke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blute</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Comparisons of outcome and prognostic features among histologic subtypes of renal cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>612</fpage>–<lpage>624</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Zisman1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zisman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pantuck</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wieder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dorey</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Risk group assessment and clinical outcome algorithm to predict the natural history of patients with surgically resected renal cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>4559</fpage>–<lpage>4566</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Mikami1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimoda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Expression of heparanase in renal cell carcinomas: implications for tumor invasion and prognosis</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>6055</fpage>–<lpage>6061</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Ren1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Microvessel density and heparanase over-expression in clear cell renal cell cancer: correlations and prognostic significances</article-title>. <source>World J Surg Oncol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>158</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051494-Fux2">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fux</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feibish</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen-Kaplan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gingis-Velitski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Structure-function approach identifies a COOH-terminal domain that mediates heparanase signaling</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1758</fpage>–<lpage>1767</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>