<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-02262</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097021</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic networks</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Gene regulatory networks</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Neural networks</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Computer and information sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Network analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Social networks</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Engineering and technology</subject><subj-group><subject>Management engineering</subject><subj-group><subject>Management planning and control</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Identifying and Characterizing Key Nodes among Communities Based on Electrical-Circuit Networks</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Key Nodes and Electrical-Circuit Network</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Fenghui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Wenxu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di</surname><given-names>Zengru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><addr-line>School of Systems Science, Beijing Normal University, Beijing, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marinazzo</surname><given-names>Daniele</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Universiteit Gent, Belgium</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">wenxuwang@bnu.edu.cn</email> (WXW); <email xlink:type="simple">yfan@bnu.edu.cn</email> (YF)</corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YF WXW ZRD. Performed the experiments: YF WXW. Analyzed the data: FHZ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: FHZ WXW. Wrote the paper: FHZ WXW YF.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>e97021</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Zhu et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Complex networks with community structures are ubiquitous in the real world. Despite many approaches developed for detecting communities, we continue to lack tools for identifying overlapping and bridging nodes that play crucial roles in the interactions and communications among communities in complex networks. Here we develop an algorithm based on the local flow conservation to effectively and efficiently identify and distinguish the two types of nodes. Our method is applicable in both undirected and directed networks without a priori knowledge of the community structure. Our method bypasses the extremely challenging problem of partitioning communities in the presence of overlapping nodes that may belong to multiple communities. Due to the fact that overlapping and bridging nodes are of paramount importance in maintaining the function of many social and biological networks, our tools open new avenues towards understanding and controlling real complex networks with communities accompanied with the key nodes.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>Funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China under Grant No. 61174150, NCET-09-0228 and the Doctoral Fund of the Ministry of Education (20110003110027); the major project of National Social Science Fund (12&amp;ZD217); MOE (Ministry of Education in China) Youth Fund Project of Humanities and Social Sciences (Project No. 11YJC840006) and NSFC under Grant No. 11105011, CNNSF under Grant No. 61074116 and the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Many real networks typically contain components in which the nodes are of much denser connections to each other than to the rest of the network. The sets of such nodes are usually called communities or modules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Albert1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Boccaletti1">[3]</xref>. Communities indicate the existence of different groups that perform specific roles in social and biological networks. Exploring network communities is an important task in the sense that they provide graphical clues to the specific functions of groups of nodes and allows us to explore a network at a coarse level, which is much more helpful for understanding dynamical processes taking place on a network rather than inspect a network as a whole without any a priori knowledge about the similarity and functions of nodes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Lancichinetti1">[4]</xref>. Thus many methods have been developed for community detection, such as progressively removing the edges with maximum betweenness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Girvan1">[5]</xref>, optimizing the strength of the community by merging nodes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Newman2">[6]</xref>, the extremal optimization method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Duch1">[7]</xref>, and approaches based on the dynamical processes taking place on networks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Almendral1">[8]</xref>.</p>
<p>Despite the algorithms developed for detecting communities in complex networks, precisely partitioning communities in many real scenarios is still a challenging problem because of the existence of special nodes that belong to different communities simultaneously, namely, overlapping nodes. Some approaches have been presented attempting to solve the community detection problem associated with overlapping nodes. For example, Palla <italic>et al.</italic> proposed a method based on clique percolation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Palla1">[9]</xref>. A community is defined by a set of nodes that can be visited by rolling a <italic>k</italic> clique over the network through other cliques with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> common nodes. Lancichinetti <italic>et al.</italic> proposed an algorithm to detect overlapping and hierarchical structures using a fitness function <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Lancichinetti2">[10]</xref>. In contrast, fuzzy modularity concentrated on the probabilities of each node belonging to different modules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Nepusz1">[11]</xref>. Guimera <italic>et al.</italic> classified nodes based on their roles within communities, using their within-module degree and their participation coefficient to reflect their positions in their own module and with respect to other modules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Guimer1">[12]</xref>. Nonetheless, to the best of our knowledge, we still lack an efficient method to identify “connectors” among communities without relying on accurate partition of communities. Here we classify connectors into two categories: overlapping node and bridging node. Overlapping nodes refer to the nodes that belong to two or more communities with a number of edges connecting to each community, e.g., node 12 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. Whereas bridging nodes refer to the nodes that belong to a single community but has a few connections to the other communities; in other words, their edges bridge their own communities and the others, e.g. node 16 and 24 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. The two types of nodes play key roles in the communications and interactions among different communities and server as “messengers”. Although we may find the two types of nodes in terms of partitioning communities by using the established methods, it is computational exhausted and considerably depends on the accuracy of detecting communities that has yet not been fully resolved. Despite some interesting methods based on synchronization processes to locate overlapping nodes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Almendral1">[8]</xref>, they are not available for bridging nodes. Moreover, algorithms and tools for tackling overlapping communities in directed networks are still lacking.</p>
<fig id="pone-0097021-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Schematic network composed of 32 nodes and separated into 3 parts.</title>
<p>Certain nodes connect the separate parts.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>In this paper, we propose a method to detect and distinguish overlapping nodes and bridging nodes based on the current flow in the electrical circuits. The current-flow-based methodology has been exploited for studying complex networks, for instance, for exploring transportation dynamics of resistor networks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Li1">[13]</xref> and modeling information flow in biological networks and finding nodes with significant biological function <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Borgatti1">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Missiuro1">[17]</xref>. Inspired by the insightful approaches, we map an arbitrary network into an electrical-circuit network in which all the edges are resistors with a specific electrical conductance, and a pair of nodes can be set as the source and sink (target) of the current flowing through the network. By combining Kirchhoff's law and Ohm's law, we can calculate the flow of each edge for a given source and target of flow. It is intuitive that overlapping and bridging nodes usually have high current flows as measured by the current-flow centrality <italic>C</italic>, because of their specific positions. Thus the two types of nodes can be distinguished from the other nodes by their high values of <italic>C</italic>. Meanwhile, we offer an imbalance index <italic>D</italic> that captures the imbalance of current flows along the edges of nodes to separate the two types of nodes. In particular, the bridging edges of bridging nodes are of much high current flows than the rest of their edges. In contrast, the current flows along the edges of an overlapping node are relatively balanced because of the fact that the current flow passing through it is shared by its edges densely connecting to both communities. The main advantage of our method is that overlapping and bridging nodes can be identified without knowing the exact community partition of the network, accounting for its high efficiency and feasibility in detecting the key nodes. Moreover, our method can be applied to directed networks in a similar fashion. We substantiate our method in terms of a number of model and empirical networks, including the Lancichinetti-Fortunato-Radicchi (LFR) benchmark with tunable community structure and a power-law degree distribution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Lancichinetti3">[18]</xref>, Zachary's Karate Club (ZK) network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Zachary1">[19]</xref>, the scientific collaboration network in Santa Fe Institute (SFI) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Available1">[20]</xref> and the neural network of C. elegans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-White1">[21]</xref>. The two types of nodes in all the networks are detected with high probability and efficiency. We finally discussed the shortage of our method rooted in the implicit definition of communities.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Electrical-circuit method for undirected and directed network</title>
<p>In an electrical-circuit network generated by placing a resistor with a specific electrical conductance on each edge of the network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Newman3">[22]</xref>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, a given pair of nodes will serve as the source and target nodes, where current is injected into the network at the source node and leaves at the target node. In fact, any arbitrary network can be represented as a resistor network.</p>
<fig id="pone-0097021-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>An electrical-circuit network with an electrical conductance on each edge.</title>
<p>Current flows through the network from the source node <italic>s</italic> and leaves at the target node <italic>t</italic>, each edge has a fixed conductance.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Current flows from the source node <italic>s</italic> to the target node <italic>t</italic>, which causes a voltage difference between node <italic>s</italic> and node <italic>t</italic>. Ohm' s law states that the current through a conductor between two points is directly proportional to the potential difference across the two points; thus, for a given source-target pair, the current flowing through an arbitrary edge(<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) is<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e002"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e002" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is an element of the adjacency matrix, and <italic>I</italic> represents the current between nodes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> when the current is injected into the source node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and leaves at the target node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>We consider the general case: node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> connects to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> neighbors, and for an arbitrary node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, Kirchhoff's law states that the total current flow into or out of any node is zero. Combining Kirchhoff' s law with Ohm's law, implies that the voltages satisfy the equation<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e011"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e011" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>Physically, the source node maintains a constant potential,and the target is chosen to be the preferred node by which it connects to the ground. For a network with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> nodes, there are <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> linear equations, which can be written as follows:<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e014"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e014" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the sum is over all neighbors of node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The potential of each node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can be solved using an iterative method such as the Jacobi method.</p>
<p>The method can be extended to a directed network as long as we replace the resistors with an electrical circuit of diodes, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g003">Fig. 3</xref>, in this equivalent electrical circuit, all the nodes are connected to a universal sink (ground) whose potential value is zero <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Kaul1">[23]</xref>. The voltages of the nodes need be adjusted to satisfy Kirchhoff's law, which states that the sum of all currents entering node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> must be equal to the sum of all currents leaving node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; if the node receives more current than the sum of the outgoing currents, the node must increase in voltage to decrease the incoming currents and increase the outgoing currents, and vice versa. This updating process will continue until all nodes satisfy Kirchhoff's law.</p>
<fig id="pone-0097021-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>A simple network with four nodes and its equivalent circuit network.</title>
<p>Edges are represented by electrical-circuit diodes and nodes are connected to a universal sink.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Similar to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0097021.e002">Eq. (1)</xref>, the current flowing from node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is given by Ohm's law for a given source <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and universal sink (ground):<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e023"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e023" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the conductance of an ideal diode representing the edge from node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e027"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e027" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>The voltage of node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is determined by Kirchhoff's law that the sum of the currents one node supplies to its neighbors must be equal to the sum of the currents it receives.<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e029"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e029" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>When <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0097021.e023">Eqs. (4)</xref>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0097021.e027">(5)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0097021.e029">(6)</xref> are combined, the result can be expressed in terms of the potentials of the neighboring nodes:<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e030"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e030" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>Just as in the undirected case, the potential of each node is the weighted average potential of its neighbors. To compute the current flow, we need to enumerate all nodes, which takes the amount of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time. We consecutively update a node's voltage to the average voltage of its neighbors, according to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0097021.e030">Eq. (7)</xref>. It takes the amount of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time to update the voltage in one loop, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the average degree of nodes. The updating process converges in a small number of steps, say, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Thus the total computational time is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Wu1">[15]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Method of finding and distinguishing two types of key nodes</title>
<p>The overlapping and bridging nodes are located at conjunction positions, and the removal of these nodes will disable the interactions and communications among communities. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g001">Fig. 1</xref>, for example, node 16 and 24 are bridging nodes. They have edges with most of the nodes within their respective groups and a few edges that connect outside the groups. In the fields of community-network analysis and information dissemination, a bridging node controls information flow and diffusion; it has strong internal control within the community and strong connections among communities. Meanwhile, node 12 is an overlapping node between two communities. It connects the communities.</p>
<p>To identify the two types of nodes, the first task is to establish an index to distinguish them from the other nodes in a network. Considering an electrical-circuit network, nodes within a community are connected densely, and therefore their voltages may be similar to each other, while a large potential gap is present between two communities where the connecting edges are sparse and the local resistance is large. Thus, the current through the nodes or edges that connect the two communities can be significantly greater than the current through the nodes or edges within a community. Thus, a higher current value for a node indicates that it is more likely to be subject to the two types of nodes. As a second step, we note that overlapping nodes belong to more than one community and are usually associated with relatively denser connections to each community. We thus introduce the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> index to measure the imbalance of the current value on the edges of a node to separate the two types of nodes. The current-flow centrality <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to measure the significance of a node, which takes into account the contributions of all paths to the node. For a given node, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> measures the current flow that passes through the node when a unit of current is injected into a source node and removed from a target node, averaged over all source-target pairs. Given a source <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and a target <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the absolute current flow through the edge(<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>,<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) is given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0097021.e002">Eq. (1)</xref>. By Kirchhoff's law, the current that enters a node is equal to the current that leaves the node. Hence, the current flow through a node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> other than the source nodes and target nodes is half of the absolute flow on the edges incident to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e045"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e045" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula>Moreover, the current flows through both <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are set to fixed values. We give a precise definition of the current-flow centrality of a node:<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e048"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e048" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the total number of source-target pairs. When extended to a directed network, there is little difference from the present case for an arbitrary node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> between the source node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the universal sink (ground). Due to the fact that<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e052"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e052" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula>we define the directed current-flow centrality <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as:<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e054"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e054" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the size of the network. When choosing pairs of nodes as the source and target each time, we obtain the current flow of the edge(<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>,<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the summed current flow through the edge(<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>,<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) when the source and target nodes are changed. The <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> index of node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> measures the difference between the max and median value of node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="pone.0097021.e064"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e064" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula>Note that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where the sum is over all the neighbors of node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We normalize this <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> index by dividing by the maximum value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For a directed network, we merge each pair of in- and out-edges into one edge, and for node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, by adding the two current values, we can obtain the undirected and the directed <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> index.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Performance on artificial networks</title>
<p>Prior to applying our method to real-world networks, we discuss the inherent limits of the betweenness-based method for inferring the two types of nodes. In principle, the index of betweenness centrality is exclusively determined by shortest paths but omitting the other longer paths, accounting for the missing of some critical nodes in some scenarios. In contrast, our current-flow-based method takes the sharing of current flow according to the conservation into account, giving rise to a more comprehensive characterization of the statues of nodes in the network with inapparent communities. Take a sample network as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g004">Fig. 4</xref> as an example. There are two communities, each of which consists of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> nodes. As <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0097021-t001">table 1</xref> shows, both of index rank nodes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of highest, however, the betweenness fails to give a higher score to the topological central position node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in this simple network. In contrast, our current-flow centrality <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> gives a relatively higher score of node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This explicitly indicates that the critical node 7 that bridges the two communities is missed by using the betweenness-centrality-based method.</p>
<fig id="pone-0097021-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Example network with two groups.</title>
<p>Each group contains six nodes, the central node 7 connects the two groups.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0097021-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Centrality indices of the example sketched in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g004">Fig. 4</xref>.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0097021-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Node Label</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current-flow centrality</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Betweenness centrality</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.308</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.655</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.538</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.353</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,4,9,12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.279</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,2,10,11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.238</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap>
<p>To obtain a preliminary assessment of the underlying network characteristics identified by the indices <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we apply them to an artificial network consisting of the nodes and edges shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. The network is constructed by joining <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> parts with bridging nodes and overlapping nodes. The small network size enables that any pattern present could be easily detected by visual inspection. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g005">Fig. 5(a)</xref>, we artificially define the top 10% of nodes in terms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to be key nodes. In other words, the threshold of distinguishing the two types of key nodes from the other nodes is determined by the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of top 10% of nodes. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g005">Fig. 5(b)</xref>, the results reveal that the highest values of current flow occur in the nodes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. These nodes connect different communities of the network and plays important roles in the network. Despite their high values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, they differ in their <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> indices considerable. As stated before, a high <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> value and a low <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> value of node <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> indicate that the node acts as an overlapping node that belongs to both the two communities that it connects. In contrast, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> have high <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and high <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values simultaneously, indicating that they more likely to be bridging nodes.</p>
<fig id="pone-0097021-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>The usage of our method in the schematic network.</title>
<p>(a) The cumulative distribution function of the <italic>C</italic> index. One can obtains a corresponding value of the <italic>C</italic> index when <italic>F</italic>(<italic>C</italic>) reaches 0.9. The dash line indicates the threshold. Nodes of higher value than the threshold are key nodes. (b) The scatter plot of indices <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. A high <italic>C</italic> value and a low <italic>D</italic> value of 12 indicate that it could be considered as overlapping node, while 16 and 24 behave as bridging nodes.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We test our method on the LFR benchmark introduced by Lancichinetti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Lancichinetti3">[18]</xref>. In the LFR benchmark, the node degrees follow a power-law distribution with the exponent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and the sizes of the communities follow another power-law distribution with then exponent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. To ensure a clear community structure, we set <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. It can be intuitively understood that some nodes that connect two or more communities have large current values, corresponding to bridging nodes or overlapping nodes, as discussed before. Thus we need to introduce the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> index to distinguish these two types of nodes by using the current-distribution information for each node. The results demonstrate that some nodes whose current values are significantly larger than those of other nodes may be regarded as the two types of key nodes. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g006">Fig. 6</xref>, the network can be well separated into two categories. The nodes at the upper right of the scatter plot have relatively high values of both <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which indicates they have more internal edges than external edges. The nodes at the lower left are contained within communities and have few edges outside their communities. It can be claimed that there are no obvious overlapping nodes in this LFR benchmark, but it may contain some bridging nodes.</p>
<fig id="pone-0097021-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>The usage of our method and in the LFR benchmark network.</title>
<p>(a) The network is generated according to the rules of LFR benchmark. Nodes diameters indicate the current-flow centrality <italic>C</italic>, the color of each node is proportional to the index <italic>D</italic>. (b) The cumulative distribution function is used to identify the threshold of the <italic>C</italic> index. (c) the network can be separated by two categories according to the scatter plot, the upper right nodes can be considered as bridging nodes with high value of <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. There are no overlapping nodes in this network.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Real-world networks</title>
<p>We test our method by using a number of real-world networks: the ZK network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Zachary1">[19]</xref>, the SFI network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Available1">[20]</xref>, and the C. elegans neural network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-White1">[21]</xref>. All the data are available for the Open Access. In each case, we find that our method reliably detects the important nodes and ideally distinguishes the two types of nodes.</p>
<p>First, we consider ZK club network. In fact, Zachary observed 34 members of a karate club over 2 years. The nodes labeled as 1 and 34 correspond to the club instructor and the administrator, respectively. During the course of the study, a disagreement developed between the administrator of the club and the club's instructor, which ultimately led to the instructor leaving and starting a new club, taking approximately half of the original club's members with him. From the results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g007">Fig. 7</xref>, nodes 1, 34, and 3 have the highest <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values and can be considered to be key nodes. Furthermore, node 3 is considered to be an overlapping node between the communities and displays a high value of current flow but a smaller <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> value. Our identified bridging node 3 is consistent with the overlapping nodes identified in ref <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Li2">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-Wang1">[25]</xref>. Nodes 1 and 34, which are known to be the administrator and instructor of the karate club, are more likely to be bridging nodes because they have high current values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and high values of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, as discussed before. The visualization of the ZK network is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g007">Fig. 7(a)</xref>. The size of each node is proportional to the value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This visual perspective reveals that there are only a few nodes of large diameter, which means that few important nodes exist in this network. Additionally, a yellow color indicates a high value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. That is to say, large yellow nodes are more likely to be bridging nodes, while large red nodes are more likely to be overlapping nodes.</p>
<fig id="pone-0097021-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>The usage of our method in ZK network.</title>
<p>(a) The network consists of 34 nodes. The size of each node represents its <italic>C</italic> index value. The color of each node is proportional to its <italic>D</italic> index. (b) The cumulative distribution function of the <italic>C</italic> index and the threshold. In (c), nodes 1 and 34 act as bridging nodes because they have high value of <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic> indices, in contrast, node 3 can be considered as overlapping node with a high <italic>C</italic> value and a low <italic>D</italic> value.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Applying the directed electrical-circuit network paradigm, we investigate the SFI scientific collaboration network. We convert it to be a directed network by randomly a direction to each of the edges. The result shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g008">Fig. 8(c)</xref> indicates that node 72, 87, 106, and 2 have high values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, all these nodes act as connection points among communities. Due to the fact that node 106 has a high value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and a large value of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, it can be considered to be a bridging node. In fact, from visual inspection of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g008">Fig. 8(a)</xref>, we find that it has primarily inward-directed edges and only a few edges directed toward other communities, which means that this node transfers information that is received from the outside and spread in communities. Nodes 72 and 87 have similar characteristics, while node 2 behaves more like an overlapping node.</p>
<fig id="pone-0097021-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>The usage of our method in the directed SFI scientist collaboration network.</title>
<p>(a) Schematic of the SFI scientist collaboration network. Node diameters indicate the <italic>C</italic> index value, the color of each node is proportional to the index <italic>D</italic>. (b,c) The current-flow centrality <italic>C</italic> and index <italic>D</italic> for the directed SFI scientist collaboration network.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We also apply our method to another directed network: the C. elegans neural network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0097021-White1">[21]</xref>. The network contains 302 nodes and 2359 edges and is divided into 3 communities, with each node representing a neuron and each edge representing a synaptic connection between neurons. The C. elegans neural network is composed of sensory neurons, inter-neurons and motor neurons. The neurons with high centrality indices often have the most important functions, and all of them are inter-neurons. Applying our method to this network (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097021-g009">Fig. 9</xref>) demonstrates that a fairly large number of nodes have high values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which indicates that there exists a significant proportion of neurons that are connected to different parts of the brain. Upon further investigation of these connection nodes, we find that the node named ‘SAADL’ has relatively low <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values, meaning that they are more likely to act as overlapping nodes rather than bridging nodes.</p>
<fig id="pone-0097021-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption>
<title>The usage of our method in the C. elegans directed neural network.</title>
<p>(a,b) The current-flow centrality <italic>C</italic> and index <italic>D</italic> are calculated in the C. elegans neural network.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0097021.g009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>We have offered an electrical-circuit-based method to ascertain and distinguish overlapping and bridging nodes that play key roles in the communications and interactions among communities in complex networks without the need to partition all communities explicitly. The two types of critical nodes can be distinguished from the other nodes within communities by the relatively high current flow passing through them, as captured by the centrality of current flow. Further, the two types of nodes can be distinguished from each other via the imbalance of flows along their edges. In particular, the bridging edges of bridging nodes exhibit much high current flows than the other edges of the nodes. Whereas for the overlapping nodes, due to their dense connections to two communities and the absence of bridging edges, the current flows along their edges are relatively balanced. Thus the combination of the centrality of current flow passing through nodes and the imbalance of current flows along the edges of nodes offers a criterion for identifying the two types of nodes with high probability. In contrast, we have shown that the method for community partition based on the betweenness centrality cannot be used to address this problem. We have applied our method to a number of artificial and real networks with certain community structure, finding that the two types of nodes discovered by our method are in good agreement with the inspection of small visualized networks. Another advantage of our method is that it is available for both undirected and directed networks, accounting for its broad application scope in real situations.</p>
<p>Despite the advantages of our method compared to previously established methods in the literature, there are still some open questions pertaining to explicitly inferring overlapping and bridging nodes. For example, although our method is capable of finding these nodes with high probability, we continue to lack a reasonable threshold so as to exactly distinguish the two types of nodes. The challenge is rooted in the fact that there is only the measurement for the strength of communities rather than the exact definition of a community, accounting for the difficulty in exactly defining and recovering overlapping and bridging nodes. Nevertheless, our approach offers an alternative avenue for addressing the fundamental problem in complex networks and it is indeed effective and more efficient than existent methods in the literature based on the shortest paths and the betweenness centrality. Taken together, our approach could motivate further effort towards detecting the key nodes pertaining to ubiquitous community structures in complex networks.</p>
</sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Albert1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barabási</surname><given-names>A-L</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Statistical mechanics of complex networks</article-title>. <source>Rev Mod Phys</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Newman1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MEJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The structure and function of complex networks</article-title>. <source>SIAM Review</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Boccaletti1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boccaletti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Latora</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chavez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>DU</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Complex networks: structure and dynamics</article-title>. <source>Physics Reports</source> <volume>424</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Lancichinetti1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lancichinetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kivela</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saramaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fortunato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Characterizing the community structure of complex networks</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e11976</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Girvan1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Girvan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MEJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Community structure in social and biological networks</article-title>. <source>PNAS</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>7821</fpage>–<lpage>7826</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Newman2"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MEJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Fast algorithm for detecting community structure in networks</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>066133</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Duch1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arenas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Community detection in complex networks using extremal optimization</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>027104</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Almendral1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almendral</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leyva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sendina-Nadal</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Havlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Dynamics of overlapping structures in modular networks</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>016115</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Palla1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Derényi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vicsek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Uncovering the overlapping community structure of complex networks in nature and society</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>435</volume>: <fpage>814</fpage>–<lpage>818</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Lancichinetti2"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lancichinetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fortunato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kertész</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Detecting the overlapping and hierarchical community structure in complex networks</article-title>. <source>New J Phys</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>033015</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Nepusz1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nepusz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petróczi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Négyessy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bazsó</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Fuzzy communities and the concept of bridgeness in complex networks</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>016107</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Guimer1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guimerà</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes Amaral</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Functional cartography of complex metabolic networks</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>433</volume>: <fpage>895</fpage>–<lpage>900</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Li1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>SDS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Havlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Towards design principles for optimal transport networks</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>018701</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Borgatti1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgatti</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Centrality and network flow</article-title>. <source>Social Networks</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Wu1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huberman</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Finding communities in linear time: a physics approach</article-title>. arXiv:cond-mat/0310600.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Kim1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Przytycki</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wuchty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Przytycka</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Modeling information flow in biological networks</article-title>. <source>Phys Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>035012</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Missiuro1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Missiuro</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Information flow analysis of interactome networks</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000350</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Lancichinetti3"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lancichinetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fortunato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radicchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Benchmark graphs for testing community detection algorithms</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>046110</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Zachary1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zachary</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>An information flow model for conflict and fission in small groups</article-title>. <source>Journal of Anthropological Research</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>452</fpage>–<lpage>473</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Available1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/mejn/netdata/" xlink:type="simple">http://www-personal.umich.edu/mejn/netdata/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-White1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Southgate</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>The structure of the nervous system of the nematode caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soclondon B</source> <volume>314</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Newman3"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MEJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A measure of betweenness centrality based on random walks</article-title>. <source>Social Networks</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Kaul1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaul</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S-G</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Ranking billions of web pages using diodes</article-title>. <source>Commun ACM</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Li2"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leyva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Almendral</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sendina-Nadal</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buldú</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Synchronization interfaces and overlapping communities in complex networks</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>168701</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0097021-Wang1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Identifying and characterizing nodes important to community structure using the spectrum of the graph</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e27418</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>