<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-35869</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067672</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome analysis tools</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene prediction</subject><subject>Genetic networks</subject><subject>Trait locus analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microarrays</subject><subject>Regulatory networks</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics</subject><subj-group><subject>Biostatistics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>An Integrative Framework for Bayesian Variable Selection with Informative Priors for Identifying Genes and Pathways</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Integrative BVS Framework with Informative Priors</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Bin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Dianwen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ander</surname><given-names>Bradley P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiaoshuai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Fuzhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>Frank R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Xiaowei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Health Statistics, Chongqing Medical University, Chongqing, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Division of Biostatistics, Bayessoft, Inc., Davis, California, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Hunter College–School of Public Health, City University of New York, New York, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Medical Investigation of Neurodevelopmental Disorders (MIND) Institute, University of California Davis, Sacramento, California, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>School of Public Health, Shandong University, Jinan, Shandong, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Xinping</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of California Riverside, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">dyang@bayessoft.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: BP DZ XY. Performed the experiments: BP DZ XY. Analyzed the data: BP DZ BA XZ XY. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: BA FX FS. Wrote the paper: BP DZ BA XY.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<elocation-id>e67672</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Peng et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The discovery of genetic or genomic markers plays a central role in the development of personalized medicine. A notable challenge exists when dealing with the high dimensionality of the data sets, as thousands of genes or millions of genetic variants are collected on a relatively small number of subjects. Traditional gene-wise selection methods using univariate analyses face difficulty to incorporate correlational, structural, or functional structures amongst the molecular measures. For microarray gene expression data, we first summarize solutions in dealing with ‘large p, small n’ problems, and then propose an integrative Bayesian variable selection (iBVS) framework for simultaneously identifying causal or marker genes and regulatory pathways. A novel partial least squares (PLS) g-prior for iBVS is developed to allow the incorporation of prior knowledge on gene-gene interactions or functional relationships. From the point view of systems biology, iBVS enables user to directly target the joint effects of multiple genes and pathways in a hierarchical modeling diagram to predict disease status or phenotype. The estimated posterior selection probabilities offer probabilitic and biological interpretations. Both simulated data and a set of microarray data in predicting stroke status are used in validating the performance of iBVS in a Probit model with binary outcomes. iBVS offers a general framework for effective discovery of various molecular biomarkers by combining data-based statistics and knowledge-based priors. Guidelines on making posterior inferences, determining Bayesian significance levels, and improving computational efficiencies are also discussed.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This research is supported in part by a grant from Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health &amp; Human Development, NIH, USA (5R01HD061404). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. No additional external funding was received for this study.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Biomarkers play a central role in the development and conduct of translational and personalized medicine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Jain1">[1]</xref>. They are used in predicting the progression of disease (prognosis markers), selecting treatment regimes (predictive markers), screening diseases (diagnostic markers), and assisting with other forms of health related tasks. Genomic biomarkers have already been applied for making critical decisions, e.g., the Oncotype Dx test for quantifying risk of disease recurrence in women with early-stage breast cancer and for assessing the likely benefit from certain types of chemotherapy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Paik1">[2]</xref>. The most notable challenge in molecular biomarker discovery is caused by high-dimensionality of the data sets. There are thousands of genes in microarray data analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Mallick1">[3]</xref> and millions of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in genome-wide association studies (GWAS) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Guan1">[4]</xref> from which biomarkers are identified.</p>
<p>Traditionally, discovery of differential genes was achieved by univariate analyses where each gene is considered individually, e.g., the weighted voting scheme of Golub et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Golub1">[5]</xref>, the partial least squares of Nguyen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Nguyen1">[6]</xref>, and the Wilcoxon test statistic of Dettleing et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Dettling1">[7]</xref>. Such gene-wise comparison methods have to deal with the multiple comparison problem. Although schemes have been proposed in adjusting the study-wise type-1 error or restraining false positive rates, there lacks an effective way to explicitly incorporate correlational or functional relationships between the genes. Without studying the interactions of genes and their joint impacts on phenotype, the traditional gene-wise methods barely offer any biological interpretation. An earlier trial to link gene-wise tests together was seen in LIMMA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Smyth1">[8]</xref> using the idea of empirical Bayes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Casella1">[9]</xref>. It makes the analysis stable by borrowing information across genes via Bayesian hierarchical modeling and shrinkage estimator <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Beaumont1">[10]</xref>. Similar to gene-wise analyses, LIMMA still treats gene expressions as outcome variables and compares them across experimental conditions.</p>
<p>A more straightforward approach is to treat disease status or phenotype as the outcome variable while setting genes as predictors. This arrangement is not only meaningful, but allows for studying multiple genes’ joint impact on the outcome variable. Thereby, the task of biomarker identification naturally becomes a problem of variable selection in fitting regression models. Standard frequentist or likelihood-based variable selection schemes via criterion assessment such as BIC and AIC or stepwise subset selection algorithms become infeasible when the number of variables <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> becomes large; see an extensive discussion in Miller <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Miller1">[11]</xref>. As an alternative solution, Bayesian variable selection (BVS) not only provides intuitive probabilistic interpretation, but also explores the model space efficiently in a stochastic way to ensure that the models with high probabilities would show up earlier and more frequently during a simulation process. This is the reason that the first satisfactory scheme of BVS was called ‘stochastic search variable selection (SSVS)’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-George1">[12]</xref>. The theory of SSVS was further developed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-George2">[13]</xref> and many other stochastic searching schemes have been proposed, e.g., the simplified method of Kuo and Mallick <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Kuo1">[14]</xref>, the Gibbs variable selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Dellaportas1">[15]</xref>, Geweke’s BVS with block-updates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Geweke1">[16]</xref>, and the reverse jump MCMC algorithm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Green1">[17]</xref>. BVS algorithms were also extended to much wider settings, e.g., generalized linear models (GLMs) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Nott1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Chen1">[19]</xref>; multivariate regression models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Brown1">[20]</xref>; and even mixed-effects models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Meuwissen1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Cai1">[22]</xref>; see O’Hara and Sillanpää <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-OHara1">[23]</xref> for a detailed review.</p>
<p>The first applications of BVS in the setting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> arose from analyzing genetic data in the early 2000s. Examples include Bayesian model selection in gene mapping studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Sillanp1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Hoti1">[25]</xref> and SSVS for identifying multiple quantitative trait loci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Yi1">[26]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Yi2">[28]</xref>. Most of the methods use hierarchical Bayesian modeling to enable borrowing information from neighbors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Baldi1">[29]</xref>. It is especially noteworthy that BVS has been successfully applied to GWAS data that contains millions of genetic variants or SNPs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Hoggart1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Wakefield1">[31]</xref>. As stated by Guan and Stephens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Guan1">[4]</xref>, “even using relatively simple MCMC algorithms, BVS can indeed produce useful inferences in problems of this size (with thousands of SNPs)." For genomic data, including genome sequencing and gene expression microarray data, biomarker identification with full BVS strategies is becoming popular. BVS resorts to hierarchical modeling to control the model size while as much as possible allowing data structures to be complex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Ibrahim1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Ishwaran1">[33]</xref>. A fair number of BVS applications have been demonstrated in the previous decade <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Lee1">[34]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Gupta1">[36]</xref>.</p>
<p>A recent focus in BVS development is on how to model biological processes that involve gene or protein groups functioning in concert. A comprehensive understanding of such processes would help to unravel disease mechanisms and to design more effective therapeutical products <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Shahbaba1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Stingo1">[38]</xref>. Recent studies demonstrate that evaluating changes in expression across pre-defined gene sets often increases statistical power and produces more robust results <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Smyth1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Mootha1">[39]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Mller1">[42]</xref>. Therefore, an appropriate approach eliciting biologically meaningful and informative priors for BVS is a worthy pursuit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Stingo1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Li1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Wei1">[44]</xref>.</p>
<p>Following the above review of BVS development history, a generalized strategy called integrative BVS (iBVS) for biomarker discovery is presented in the Methods section. We propose an iBVS strategy with a novel prior called PLS g-prior for handling covariance matrices with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and incorporating gene pathways into the selection procedure. In the Simulation section, the above iBVS for gene expression data with binary disease status is validated using simulated data and compared with other standard BVS routine. In the Application section, the strategy of iBVS is illustrated using a practical Affymetrix microarray data set for patients with stroke. Remarks and discussions are given in the Discussion section.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Notations</title>
<p>Suppose that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> independent observations of the outcome variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which could be binary, count or continuous. Each outcome is associated with a set of predictor variables <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> whose values form the matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e009"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>In microarray data, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes the normalized level of expression for the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> gene on the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> subject. The outcome variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is said to have a distribution in the <italic>exponential family</italic> if its probability density function can be written in the general form, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Most of the distributions that we know such as Gamma, Beta, Poisson, and Gaussian distributions are all members of the exponential family. When <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> follows an <italic>exponential family</italic> distribution, the GLM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-McCullagh1">[45]</xref> is introduced in studying the relationship between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> via<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e018"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e018" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is a <italic>link function</italic> after which the expected value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, is predicted by the linear combination of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Bayesian Variable Selection in GLMs</title>
<p>A fundamental task of regression analysis is to select which subset of the predictors are used to predict or explain the variance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. When other features of the GLMs such as the choice of link function are determined, the problem of variable selection is equivalent to the task of model selection. This paper focuses on the explicit way of Bayesian variable/model selection in which an indicator vector <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is introduced where<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e025"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>Then the equation of GLM can be rewritten as<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e026"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e026" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>By specifying prior distribution of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (and possibly other parameters such as residual variance in a linear regression model), one applies Bayes rule to derive the posterior distribution <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from which to obtain the posterior probabilities <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for model selection (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Within the scope of this article, we define BVS as a procedure of variable selection based on the posterior marginal selection probabilities,<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e032"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e032" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>which has the form of Bayesian model averaging (BMA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Hoeting1">[46]</xref>. This BVS selection probability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> calibrates the overall strength of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in predicting <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> across various models.</p>
<p>Depending on the specification the prior distribution, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, many schemes of BVS have been proposed, e.g., independent prior distributions (i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Kuo1">[14]</xref> and Gibbs variable selection where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is set as a ‘pseudo-prior’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Dellaportas1">[15]</xref>. The most influential scheme is the SSVS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-George1">[12]</xref>, which assumes that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e040"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e040" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>a mixture of a concentrated Gaussian distribution (when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and a diffused one (when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Alternatively one may specify <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which has a natural interpretation and can be further extended to the multivariate setting, i.e., the g-prior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Zellner1">[47]</xref>,<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e045"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e045" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the sub-matrix of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> consisting of columns with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can be fixed at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or estimated via empirical Bayes. The g-prior is a conjugate prior; one may analytically integrate out <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to obtain <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>'s, which are of primary interest in BVS.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, g-prior has an undesirable feature: as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the Bayes factor in favor of the null model (i.e., the one with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). It is because of this Bayes factor paradox that Jeffreys <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Jeffreys1">[48]</xref> rejected normal priors, and later Zellner and Siow (ZS) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Zellner2">[49]</xref> proposed the Cauchy prior,<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e059"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e059" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>From the viewpoint of objective Bayes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Berger1">[50]</xref>, ZS-prior satisfies six of the seven desirable features (e.g., consistency, predictive matching, and invariance) for the choice of model prior, but it does not lead to closed-form answers. It was then further extended to the so-called ‘robust prior,’ which is formulated as the scale mixture of normal distributions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Liang1">[51]</xref>. Please see Bayarri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Bayarri1">[52]</xref> and the reference therein for recent development of objective BVS priors, e.g., intrinsic priors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Berger2">[53]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-OHagan1">[55]</xref>, expected posterior priors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Prez1">[56]</xref>, and integral priors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Cano1">[57]</xref>.</p>
<p>The prior <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can be naturally set as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. When there is no preference, we can simply let <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can be set to control the number of selected variables a priori. For a data set with 100 variable, setting <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> implies that only one variable be selected before observing the data. We do not recommend using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> because it indicate equal probabilities (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) for all models and does not induce any multiplicity adjustment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Scott1">[58]</xref>. Alternatively, one may introduce a hyper prior distribution for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which could provide automatic multiplicity adjustment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Do1">[59]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Newton2">[61]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>BVS When <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></title>
<p>Note that most of the above discussion assumes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. When BVS is applied to biomarker identification for genomic data where it is often seen that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we face many challenges. First, since the size of model space (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) increases exponentially with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, it becomes an intimidating task for a thorough search among all genes. Even with stochastic searching strategy, the MCMC sampling algorithm has a large computational burden at the level <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Second, among the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> genes, many of them are ‘noisy’ variables in the sense that they either have low quality such as missing or censored values or do not participate the biological processes under study. Blindly including them into the analysis would make the modeling procedure time consuming or end up with invalid conclusions. Third, the rank of matrix, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, would be much smaller than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the number of selected genes, making the matrix inversion impossible. Fourth, there are many genes whose expressions are highly correlated, easily leading to singularities in setting priors as well as deriving the posterior distributions. These between-gene correlation or causal structures, on the other hand, cannot be simply ignored.</p>
<p><bold>iBVS–A Generalized Framework of BVS.</bold> To solve the above problems, we could have two options: (1) to restrain the size of model space to a level that BVS can be accomplished within acceptable amount of time; and (2) to apply the principle of parsimony to reduce the number of model parameters via regularization and shrinkage estimators. In this article, we provide a generalized 2-step procedure called iBVS.</p>
<p><bold>Step One</bold> is a ‘robust’ screening process aiming to directly reduce the dimension <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> by removing genes with little useful signal or those having no known biological relationship to the target disease or phenotype. By ‘robust’ screening, we mean to use the combination of various criteria jointly to ensure that enough genes are included for Step Two. For example, we can first conduct gene-wise t-tests to remove genes with p-values larger than a pre-specified cut-off level (e.g., 0.01) that is much higher than the level after a multiplicity adjustment. Among the excluded genes, we may conduct gene-wise Wilcoxon test to further verify that no gene has a p-value smaller than 0.05; otherwise the genes will be moved back into the gene set. We may also move back those genes that have been discovered to be functionally or structurally related to the target disease or phenotype in the study. By curating public data bases, we can generate a list of proteins that are functionally related to the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and then find all the genes that code them. All these genes would be moved back to the gene set for consideration. We should also further move back additional genes that are connected to any genes in the current set according to a specific way of defining gene-gene networks, e.g., metabolic pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Romero1">[62]</xref> and protein-protein interaction networks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Phizicky1">[63]</xref>. The final retained set of genes is termed as the ‘signature set’ and used for Step Two. The screening process may also allow investigators' subjective preferences and other methods such as the <italic>topological analysis of co-expression network</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Zhang1">[64]</xref> and <italic>bagged gene shaving</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Hastie1">[65]</xref>. Here, we emphasize that the screening is not purely just for dimension reduction based on testing statistics. It is rather a key component of iBVS for biomarker identification, which aims to create a broad enough but biologically meaningful signature set for further conducting BVS in the next step.</p>
<p><bold>Step-Two</bold> of iBVS focuses on variable selection within the framework of Bayesian hierarchical modeling (BHM) that aims to investigate the joint distribution of genes in the signature set in predicting phenotype or disease status. BHM offers a flexible way in modeling complex structured data while restraining the number of parameters. To reduce the computation burden of BVS for large <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (number of signature genes), various strategies are conceived. As seen in Godsill <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Godsill1">[66]</xref>, and Yi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Yi3">[67]</xref>, we can adopt the ‘composite model selection’ principle and restrict that in each MCMC iteration, only models with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are allowed to be selected. This can be done by creating a special proposal distribution in the Metropolis-Hastings (M-H) algorithm. Using the idea of ‘Leaps and Bounds’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Furnival1">[68]</xref>, Annest and Bumgarner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Annest1">[69]</xref> proposed the iterative model selection algorithm that first orders all variables with a univariate selection method and then moves a 30-variable window down the ordered variables. To handle the problem of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, a direct solution is by Yang and Song's <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-prior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Yang1">[70]</xref>, which is the generalized inverse of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in Zellner's g-prior. Ridge regression is also originated to handle the problem of inverting a nearly singular matrix and Cholesky decomposition is usually adopted to speed up the matrix inversion. Some high-performance Gibbs samplers and M-H sampling algorithms have been developed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Wu1">[71]</xref>. A straightforward solution is to run multiple chains simultaneously (see Gelman and Rubin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Gelman1">[72]</xref>) on multiple virtual machines in computer clusters or using Cloud Computing platforms. Some approximation methods are also introduced trying to improve the computing speed, e.g., the Matching Pursuit method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Mallat1">[73]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Chen2">[74]</xref>.</p>
<p>In this paper, we proposed an iBVS with novel prior called PLS g-prior in dealing with large <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> problems and with informative prior on variable selection that reflect the gene-gene networks using Markov random field (MRF).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Incorporate Informative Priors</title>
<p>Meaningful prior information may come from different sources, including published literature, online knowledge bases, and empirical experience of the investigators. However, it is still not completely clear how to best use them or relate them effectively in variable selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Hill1">[75]</xref>. The most convenient way for informative prior elicitation is to incorporate the relative frequencies of identified biomarkers from published literature or from investigators' subjective preference. For example, Kitchen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Kitchen1">[76]</xref> used results from the scientific literature when constructing several informative exchangeable subset selection priors.</p>
<p>A more comprehensive approach is by adopting the view of systems biology, which studies biological processes as whole systems instead of isolate parts. For many diseases, expression-based classification alone do not achieve high accuracy because changes in expression of the few genes causing disease can be subtle compared to those of the downstream effectors, which vary considerably from patient to patient. A more effective means of marker identification is to combine expression measurements over pathways and identify which pathways act as markers in predicting or explaining phenotypes. Here pathway refers to a group of functionally or structurally related genes that jointly form a network. Several pathway- or network-based marker identification approaches have been proposed recently, e.g., Chuang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Chuang1">[77]</xref> integrates expression profiles with pathways extracted from protein interaction networks and Lee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Lee2">[78]</xref> does so by adopting pathways curated from literature. Large protein-protein interaction networks have recently become available for human, enabling new opportunities for elucidating pathways involved in major diseases and pathologies. This network-based marker discovery approach has shown success in diagnosis of metastatic breast cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Chuang1">[77]</xref> as well as classification of cell fate decisions during development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Ravasi1">[79]</xref>.</p>
<p>In this article, we combine the idea of gene- and network-based marker discovery and provides an iBVS framework for identifying contributive genes and important pathways. Informative priors on pathway definition could come from publicly available literature and databases: (1) DNA-sequence data (e.g., GeneBank and EBI); (2) RNA sequence data (e.g., NCBI and Rfam); (3) GWAS data (e.g., dbSNP and HapMap); (4) protein sequence data (e.g., UniProt, PIR and RefSeq); (5) protein class and classification (e.g., Pfam, IntDom, and GO); (6) gene structural (e.g., ChEBI, KEGG ligand Database, and PDB); (7) genomics (e.g., Entrez Gene, KEGG, and MetaCyc); (8) Signaling pathway (e.g., ChemProt and Reactome); (9) metabolomics (e.g., BioCycy, HMDB, and MMCD); (10) protein-protein interaction (e.g., IntAct, DIP, MiMI). These databases could help us define pathways or networks upon which to map our gene expression data under analysis. Using the available biological information on inter-connectivities and interactions between genes, we aim to discover pathways that are associated with a specific biological process. Srivastava et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Srivastava1">[80]</xref> have employed the GO information into their priors, and Stingo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Stingo1">[38]</xref> have used KEGG network information.</p>
<p>There are also many other types of public data that may not be used directly to construct pathways, but could be used directly for deriving prior distributions for the current model. For example, by searching literature (PubMed and Google Scholar) or reanalyzing older gene expression data from GEO, ArrayExpresss, and Oncomine, we could have some insights in determining the size and form of the model before analyzing the data set at hand. Many available clinical (e.g., OMIM, GeneCards, and CancerGenes) or drug databases (e.g., DrugBank and SuperTarget) could also provide structural or semi-structural information for us to restrain model space and parameters.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Posterior Inference</title>
<p>As was mentioned in section 1, when the posterior space is huge, we usually use the MCMC simulation to fit the posterior distribution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Robert1">[81]</xref>, instead of trying to obtain the exact values via complicated calculations. The Gibbs sampler, and M-H sampler are some of the well known Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithms. If possible, one should first analytically integrate out the nuisance parameters (e.g., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which is not of our main interest). This can significantly speed up the MCMC simulation procedure. As seen later, there are other ways to enhance the speed and efficiency of MCMC, including various means to define the proposal function in an M-H algorithm.</p>
<p>Once we obtain the samples from a MCMC procedure, we can summarize them to estimate the posterior probabilities of selecting genes and selecting pathways. In practice, certain guidelines should be followed for making posterior inferences. The setting of a cut-off for the important genes and pathways should adopt the cross-validation strategy. As many research papers have shown, in comparison to choosing one single best model, Bayesian model averaging (BMA) would provide a better performance in prediction problems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Madigan1">[82]</xref>. It is also possible that different models be used for variable selection and for making prediction or classifying samples using the selected variables; model selecting and making predictions are often viewed as two different goals.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>iBVS for Biomarker Identification with Binary Outcome</title>
<p>In this section, we illustrate our iBVS method for biomarker identification for gene expression data with binary outcomes. Here we employ Bayesian hierarchical modeling approach to do gene selection and pathway selection simultaneously and the PLS g-prior is introduced.</p>
<p>Suppose our gene expression data have up to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathways, we denote the pathway membership by the matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> if the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> gene belongs to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> otherwise), and denote gene-gene network by the matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> if there is a direct edge between the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> genes; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> otherwise). In addition to using the indicator <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for gene selection, we introduce another indicator <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for pathway selection, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) if the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway is selected (or excluded). When the outcome variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is binary, the Probit model of Albert and Chib <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Albert1">[83]</xref> is applied,<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e116"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where the latent variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is assumed to have the standard normal distribution, i.e.,<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e118"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e118" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes the number of selected pathways in predicting <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e124" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes the vector of first PLS component of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e125" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Note that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e126" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the sub-matrix of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e127" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, consisting of only the columns that correspond to selected genes in the selected <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway. Here, we use <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e129" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e130" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) to index the number of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e131" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> selected pathway (i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e132" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>); e.g., when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e133" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e134" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the pathway selection result, we have <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e135" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e136" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e137" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<sec id="s2f1">
<title>Prior specification for regression parameters</title>
<p>Note that since observation data <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e139" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and expression data <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e140" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are usually standardized, we'll assume <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e141" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e142" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is usually chosen as a large number to indicate that we have little prior information on the value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e143" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. As for the prior on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e144" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, some commonly used priors include a mixture distribution of a two normals, one normal and one point mass, or one point mass and one uniform; Zellner's <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e145" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>priors, Zellner-Siow's Cauchy priors, or equivalently a mixture of infinitely many normals. Yang and Song <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Yang1">[70]</xref> generalized <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e146" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-prior to the so called <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e147" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-prior.</p>
<p>For our hierarchical model, we propose a generalized g-prior called PLS g-prior,<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e148"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e148" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e149" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> represents the Moore-Penrose generalized inverse of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e150" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, similar to Yang and Song <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Yang1">[70]</xref>. The name comes from the fact that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e151" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the first PLS component of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e152" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Note that this generalized inverse is well-defined for any matrix.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f2">
<title>Prior specification for variable selection indicators</title>
<p>Following the principles in setting priors on variable selection indicators, we assume that the pathway selection indicators <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e153" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are independently Bernoulli distributed,<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e154"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e154" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e155" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> indicates the proportion of pathways expected a priori in the model. One may assume that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e156" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> follows a mixture distribution of a Dirac Delta distribution and a Beta distribution: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e157" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. If we integrate out the hyper-parameters, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e158" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e159" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, to get the marginal distribution of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e160" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we will end up with a product of Bernoulli distributions with parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e161" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Later on, we will omit the “new” in superscript and still denote it as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e162" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>To take into account the pathway membership information for each gene as well as the biological relationships between genes within pathways as indicated by the matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e163" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we follow Li and Zhang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Li1">[43]</xref> and Stingo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Stingo1">[38]</xref> and use a MRF to describe the prior on each component of the gene selection indicator <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e164" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>,<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e165"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e165" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e166" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e167" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are tuning parameters that will be specified later, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e168" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the set of neighbors of gene <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e169" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> within the selected pathway. This is equivalent to the multivariate form <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e170" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; here the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e171" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the vector consisting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e172" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> 1's. There are other ways to take advantage of the MRF information too, e.g., Wei and Li <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Wei2">[84]</xref> took a form similar to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e173" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to take into account the possible down-regulating effect from neighbors.</p>
<p>In the above hierarchical model, we also need to include constraints on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e174" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> so that (a) no empty pathways will be included; (b) no gene will be selected unless the pathway containing it is already selected; (c) adding or removing genes will not cause two selected pathways having identical sets of selected genes. Any violation to these three constraints will lead to an invalid configuration. Thus, we end up with the joint distribution of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e175" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the following form, except for invalid configurations where 0 probability will be assigned:<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e176"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e176" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula></p>
</sec><sec id="s2f3">
<title>Derivation of posterior distributions</title>
<p>The joint posterior distribution of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e177" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> given <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e178" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is.<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e179"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e179" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e180" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the indicator function and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e181" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is either <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e182" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> corresponding to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e183" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e184" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are the nonzero eigenvalues of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e185" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>We integrate out <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e186" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e187" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to obtain the joint posterior distribution of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e188" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as follows (See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0067672.s001">Text S1</xref> for detailed derivation):<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e189"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e189" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(13)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e190" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Computation with MCMC Algorithms</title>
<p>To sample the posterior distribution, we use a hybrid Gibbs and Metropolis-Hastings MCMC sampling technique, which consists of the following:</p>
<p>(a) Sampling <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e191" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> given <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e192" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> We can see from (13) that<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e193"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e193" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(14)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>In this article, we follow the method given in Devroye (1986) to sample each element <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e194" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from its univariate truncated normal distribution <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e195" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e196" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the vector of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e197" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> without the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e198" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> element.</p>
<p>(b) Sampling <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e199" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e200" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula><disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e201"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e201" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(15)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>The parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e202" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are updated using a Metropolis-Hastings algorithm in a two-stage sampling scheme. The pathway-gene relationships are used to structure the moves and account for the constraints specified earlier. Details of the MCMC moves to update <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e203" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are similar to that given in Stingo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Stingo1">[38]</xref> and consist of randomly choosing one of the following random move types that will not give rise to invalid configurations as seen earlier.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Simulation Studies</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Study Design</title>
<p>To verify the performance of iBVS and compare it with other methods, we mainly conducted simulation studies using KEGG pathways. First, we simulated gene expression data for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e204" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> genes that involves in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e205" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathways as defined in the KEGG database. From the pathway structures defined, we obtained the pathway membership matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e206" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (i.e., a <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e207" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> matrix; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e208" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> if the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e209" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> gene belongs to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e210" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e211" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> otherwise) and gene-gene connection matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e212" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (i.e., a <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e213" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> matrix; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e214" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> if there is a direct edge between the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e215" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e216" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> genes, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e217" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> otherwise). Then we simulated the binary outcome variable, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e218" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which was generated using the probit model with a latent variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e219" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. By applying iBVS algorithm with PLS g-prior to these synthesized data with know causal genes, we aimed to assess its sensitivity and specificity for gene selection. To further verify that iBVS could be applied in a practical setting with large number of genes, we also synthesized data with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e220" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Finally, we also compared iBVS to a BVS strategy that does not employ informative priors.</p>
<p>Each KEGG pathway can be approximately viewed as a Bayesian Network (BN), as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067672-g001">Figure 1</xref>. For the case of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e221" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we first merged all pathways into one large 315-gene BN to take into account the genes on multiple pathways. Then we simulated expression values for all the ‘root genes’ (those without parental genes directing to them in the BN) using independent standard normal distributions. Then, the expression values of their child nodes were simulated using the idea of structural equation modeling, i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e222" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e223" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e224" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>'s were random weights to ensure that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e225" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Repeating this procedure, we created 100 samples of expression values for the 315 genes. Then we standardized all the genes' expression values to ensure <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e226" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0067672-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>An Example of KEGG Pathway.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>To simulate binary outcomes, latent variables <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e227" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>'s were first simulated according to the equation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e228" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e229" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e230" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e231" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Then, the binary outcome <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e232" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is set to be 1 if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e233" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, otherwise it is set to be 0. Four scenarios of simulation are conducted based on the number of causal genes and number of total genes.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Scenario 1</title>
<p>For <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e234" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we chose only 8 causal genes: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e235" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e236" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e237" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e238" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e239" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e240" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway; and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e241" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is shared by the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e242" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e243" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathways. More specifically, we have.<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e244"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e244" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(16)</label></disp-formula><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e245" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e246" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was fixed, while two levels of gene effect size (i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e247" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> ) were considered: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e248" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> vs. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e249" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. To evaluate the impact of correlation structure on gene/pathway selection, the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e250" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway was pre-specified with highly correlated member genes (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e251" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> gene-gene correlation coefficients were larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e252" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or smaller than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e253" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e254" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway with lowly correlated members (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e255" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> gene-gene correlation coefficients were between -0.20 and 0.20), and the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e256" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway with mixed high and low correlations.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Scenario 2</title>
<p>Still for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e257" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, all 19 genes in the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e258" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway and all 9 genes in the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e259" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway were set as causal genes, i.e.,<disp-formula id="pone.0067672.e260"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e260" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(17)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e261" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was fixed and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e262" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> were set as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e263" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e264" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. As mentioned above, the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e265" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway mainly contains genes that are weakly correlated. The <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e266" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway has both strong and weak correlations (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e267" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> gene-gene correlation coefficients with absolute value larger than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e268" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e269" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> smaller than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e270" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Scenario 3</title>
<p>To consider the much higher dimensional situation, we extended our simulation studies for <italic>Scenario 1</italic>. We kept the original sample size of 100, number of causal genes at 8, effect size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e271" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, but this time added 1685 more randomly generated non-causal genes, corresponding to 81 more artificial pathways. Hence, the total number of genes in each data set is 2000, belonging to 90 pathways, and the R matrix (i.e., with elements valued at 1 or 0 to indicate pairwise gene-gene connectivity) is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e272" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Scenario 4</title>
<p>To study the case of large grouped causal genes as seen in <italic>Scenario 2</italic>, we artificially set 50 causal genes from 5 pathways (i.e., genes numbered 40–49, 305–314, 950–959, 1320–1329, 1710–1719) with causal-effect set as 1.0 for the 1st 10 causal genes, 2.5 for the 2nd 10 causal genes, and similarly 1.5, 3.5, and 1.2 for other three groups. For the 1st and 2nd gene sets, the pathways they belong to were drawn from the KEGG database with many gene-gene connections; but for the 3rd, 4th, and 5th sets of causal genes, the pathways they belong to were purposedly constructed with no gene connected to other genes.</p>
<sec id="s3e1">
<title>Parameter specification and MCMC sampler</title>
<p>For each scenario with each choice of effect size, we repeated the above procedure to create 100 data sets, each consisting of 100 samples. Each data set was fed to the iBVS algorithm for the selection of important genes, where we set hyper parameters as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e273" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Using Gelman and Rubin diagnostics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Gelman1">[72]</xref>, the burn-in length was set at 10000 iterations after which 50000 additional iterations were run for making posterior inference on each data set. The posterior gene/pathway selection probabilities were then averaged across 100 data sets to assess the performance of BVS and the averaged selection probabilities are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067672-g002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067672-g003">3</xref>. For each MCMC run on one set of data, it took about 10 minutes using a fairly fast desktop computer (Windows 7, with 4 core 2.3 GHz CPUs and 4 Gb memory). For the same task with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e274" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, it took 54 minutes, which is still an acceptable speed.</p>
<fig id="pone-0067672-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Gene and Pathway selection results in <italic>Scenario</italic> 1.</title>
<p>The top figure corresponds to the posterior distribution of gene with effect size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and second figure <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The two smaller figures on the bottom demonstrate the posterior pathway selection probabilities, with the left one corresponding to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and right one <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The labeled red lines indicate causal genes or causal pathways (those containing causal genes). These distributions were obtained by averaging over the 100 simulated sets of data.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0067672-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Gene and Pathway selection results in <italic>Scenario</italic> 2.</title>
<p>The top figure corresponds to the posterior probabilities of gene selection with effect size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and second figure <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The two smaller figures on the bottom demonstrate the posterior probabilities of pathway selection, with the left one corresponds to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and right one <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The red lines indicate causal genes or causal pathways (those containing causal genes). These distributions were obtained by averaging over the 100 simulated sets of data.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3f">
<title>Simulation Results</title>
<sec id="s3f1">
<title>Posterior selection probabilities for p = 315</title>
<p>In <italic>Scenario 1</italic>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067672-g002">Figure 2</xref> depicts the posterior gene/pathway selection probabilities, averaged over the 100 simulated sets of data, for the two levels of effect sizes. The labeled red lines indicate causal genes in the left plots and the ‘causal pathways’ (those containing causal genes) in the right plots. When the gene effect size was set as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e275" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the ‘signal-to-noise ratio (SNR)’ is as high as 54.5 and it is a relatively easier task of gene selection. One observes that our iBVS with PLS g-prior did a great job; all the eight genes with the highest posterior probabilities are exactly the same preset causal genes, and the five top pathways are exactly the same causal pathways.</p>
<p>In comparison, when the effect size was set as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e276" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the SNR becomes 3.4, which makes it a much harder job for gene selection. Even for this challenging task, our iBVS works fairly well. Although some non-causal genes' averaged selection probabilities stand out, even higher than those of several causal genes, these non-causal genes are meaningful markers in the sense that they belong to causal pathways and are highly correlated with the causal genes. For example, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e277" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> has a higher selection probability than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e278" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, but it belongs to a causal pathway (the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e279" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway) and has a correlation coefficient of 0.86 with the causal gene <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e280" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For two highly-correlated genes within one pathway, it does not make much difference which one is selected to act as the ‘marker’ in the conduct of personalized medicine.</p>
<p>As for influence of correlation structures, first in the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e281" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway, genes are weakly correlated, hence the causal genes are clearly selected out. In the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e282" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway, genes are highly correlated, we see that non-causal genes also have relatively high posterior selection probabilities and the cut between causal and non-causal is not that clear. This is especially seen in the case with smaller effect size. As one expects, the contribution of a pathway in predicting the outcome <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e283" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> should be determined not only by the effect sizes of causal genes in it, but also by the number of causal genes in it. This is exactly the result observed from the iBVS strategy. For example, gene <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e284" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is a causal gene, belonging to both the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e285" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e286" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathways. Hence we see that both pathways stand out from non-causal pathways, but at the same time their averaged posterior selection probabilities are lower than that of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e287" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway because the latter has two cause genes (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e288" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e289" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), each having equal effect size with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e290" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>In <italic>Scenario 2</italic> all genes in pathways <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e291" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e292" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are causal genes. Plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067672-g003">Figure 3</xref> clearly show that the two groups of genes tend to have higher posterior probabilities whether the effects of causal genes are high or low. It is even clear that the top two causal pathways stand much higher above the rest in terms of posterior selection probabilities. Comparing the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e293" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e294" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathways, it is seen that the former has a relatively lower pathway selection probability, although it has larger number of genes and each of the gens has stronger caul effect (i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e295" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). An interpretation is that the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e296" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway contains genes that are highly correlated; hence the effective degrees of freedom is smaller than that of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e297" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pathway. Once again, this proves that not only the number of causal genes, but the correlation structure between genes would affect the selection of pathway in predicting disease or phenotype.</p>
<p>It is also noted that pathways <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e298" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e299" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and their member genes tend to have higher selection probabilities as seen from the plots. This is because some of the genes in these two pathways are highly correlated with some of the causal genes in the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e300" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e301" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> genes. The higher absolute level a non-causal gene is correlated with some causal genes, the higher the posterior selection probability would be observed for it. This is also the reason that in practical settings, marker genes instead of causal genes are often identified. We also found that the direction of the correlation coefficient would not affect the selection probability of a marker gene; that is, the correlation coefficient of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e302" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e303" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> between non-causal gene A and the causal gene B would lead to the same increase of A's selection probability.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3f2">
<title>Posterior selection results for P = 2000</title>
<p>For <italic>Scenario 3</italic>, the posterior gene selection probabilities, averaged over 100 sets of simulated data are shown in the top part of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067672-g004">Figure 4</xref>. All the casual genes (marked by red color) still show significantly higher posterior selection probabilities than other genes. This further verified that our iBVS method works well for the case with p = 2000 genes, a number that we believe is commonly encountered in practical applications, as the majority of genes are unchanged between conditions or expressed at baseline levels. Compared to the simulation result with p = 315 genes, we found that the posterior gene selection probabilities are much lower in the case of p = 2000. For example, the selection probability for the causal gene 95, reduced from 93.6% (when p = 315) to 72.4% (when p = 2000).</p>
<fig id="pone-0067672-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Posterior Gene Selection Probabilities when P = 2000.</title>
<p>The top figure shows the result for <italic>Scenario</italic> 3, and the bottom one <italic>Scenario</italic> 4.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>In <italic>Scenario 4</italic>, the bottom figure in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067672-g004">Figure 4</xref> shows that all the casual genes (marked by red color) still show notably higher posterior selection probabilities than other non-causal genes. But this time, the cutoff between causal and non-causal gene selection is not as clear as in <italic>Scenario 3</italic>. It is interesting to see that the posterior selection probabilities are not that high for the 3rd, 4th, and 5th causal gene groups. This is because the groups associate with genes that are not connected to each other (in other words, they independently influence the phenotype or disease status). When groups of highly correlated causal genes are working in concert, they jointly show higher impact to the phenotype or disease status.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3f3">
<title>Determine significant causal or marker genes</title>
<p>When we determine which or how many genes are significant causal or marker genes based on the posterior probabilities distribution of all genes, we use cross-validation methods. In this procedure, a logistic regression model was used to examine the relationship between genes and the binary outcome variable. We started from simplest logistic regression model only including the gene with the highest posterior probability. Then we add the gene with next highest posterior probability to the model one at a time, until reaching a total number of 30 genes included in model. Two datasets were chosen randomly from 100 datasets, with one being used for estimating the regression coefficients of the model, and the other estimating the prediction error. We repeated this 200 times to find the average predicting error. The results of average prediction error are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067672-g005">Figure 5</xref> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e304" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e305" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. It was clear in the first plot that the model including the best eight genes had the lowest prediction error, where the eight genes were exactly the same simulated causal genes. In the second plot when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e306" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was smaller, we saw that the model with 17 genes performed the best. Note that among the 17 genes 13 are causal genes and 4 are non-causal genes.</p>
<fig id="pone-0067672-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Mean Square Error for Gene Selections.</title>
<p>Averaged over 100 simulated data in <italic>Scenario</italic> 1 for two set of gene effect sizes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The top one is for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and bottom one <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3f4">
<title>Compare iBVS with standard BVS</title>
<p>We further verified the advantage of our iBVS method with informative priors constructed from known gene-gene networks or pathways. To do this, we compared our method with other standard BVS schemes without informative priors. The method of Yang &amp; Song <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Yang1">[70]</xref> represents such a standard BVS method, (will be referred as YS-BVS later on), which is also the most comparable method to ours. In YS-BVS procedure, pathway selection is not considered and the existence of network relationships between the genes was completely ignored.</p>
<p>We ran YS-BVS to the same sets of simulated data. The following ROC curves for gene selection in two scenarios provide a direct comparison of this method with ours on gene selection accuracy in terms of sensitivity and specificity. From the plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067672-g006">Figure 6</xref>, it is obvious that both in the case of small number causal genes (<italic>Scenario 1</italic>) and in the case of large number small-effect genes (<italic>Scenario 2</italic>), our method has notably larger AUC (area under curve). For example, the AUC is 0.992 for iBVS compared to 0.981 for YS-BVS in Scenario 1. This is especially true for <italic>Scenario 2</italic> (AUC = 0.913 for iBVS and 0.750 for YS-BVS), which suggests that in dealing with diseases of complete genomic mechanisms involving many tiny-effect causal/marker genes, to consider gene selection within the given network/pathway background would definitely be a better approach for the task of biomarker identification. And when applying both methods to simulated data with higher noise levels (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067672-g006">Figure 6</xref>), our iBVS has a greater and significant advantage over YS-BVS.</p>
<fig id="pone-0067672-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>ROC Curves for iBVS and YS-BVS (Yang &amp; Song's BVS).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3g">
<title>Application</title>
<p>A blood-based biomarker of acute ischemic stroke is of significant value in clinical practice. Deidentified data was used from consented subjects recruited as part of the CLEAR Trial from the University of Cincinnati (Pancioli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Pancioli1">[85]</xref>). Ischemic stroke was scored by clinical evaluation and evident by neuroimaging. Demographic information for stroke subjects and healthy volunteers was recorded. Blood samples were drawn into PAXgene tubes (PreAnalytiX, Hilden, Germany) within three hours of stroke onset and prior to administration of any medication. RNA was isolated, prepared and hybridized to Affymetrix Human U133 Plus 2.0 microarrays as previously described (Stamova et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Stamova1">[86]</xref>) This study aimed to (1) identify genes in differentiating stroke patients (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e307" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-hr after stroke) from healthy controls; and (2) identify pathways as groups of genes in differentiating stroke patients from controls.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3h">
<title>Analysis Procedure</title>
<p>A 2-step STS strategy for biomarker identification was adopted in this application. Firstly, a robust gene screening and pathway analysis was conducted; then followed by the conduct of simultaneously selection of genes and pathways using the proposed iBVS method.</p>
<p>We first selected 815 probe sets by using univariate t-test (genefilter R package; rowttest) at significance level <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e308" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. These probe sets correspond to 605 unique genes. By mapping these genes to the KEGG database, we found 163 pathways, each containing at least one of the 605 genes. These 163 pathways contained 5467 genes in total. This group of genes was referred as <italic>grand signature gene set</italic> and it contained too many candidate genes for our iBVS discovery procedure.</p>
<p>To further reduce the number of candidate genes, we considered two schemes. The first one was by conducting gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) based on the hypergeometric distribution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Subramanian1">[40]</xref>. In this GSEA, each of the 163 pathways was viewed as a gene set and the network topology was totally ignored. By setting the p-value cut-off of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e309" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we kept 24 pathways for the following iBVS analysis; all with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e310" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. These 24 pathways contained a total of 1216 genes. For reference, these genes together is termed <italic>Signature Gene Set</italic>. An alternative approach is to subjectively select a small number of pathways according to their known biological functions that are related to stroke or cardiovascular problems. This method was not applied because, unlike protein-protein interaction networks, KEGG pathways offer less clinical interpretation.</p>
<p>Since we only have microarray data defined on probe set level, a procedure of mapping the probe sets to genes was also needed. We followed the lead of Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Li2">[87]</xref> to choose only one probe set to represent the expression level of a gene. If multiple probe sets were mapped to one gene, we kept the one with smallest <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e311" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> value in the above multiple t-test procedure.</p>
<p>Finally we conducted the iBVS analysis with PLS g-prior by considering only the Signature Gene Set and the associated 24 KEGG pathways. Then we followed the iBVS method for binomial regression with Probit distribution to carry out the variable selection. Similar hyper-parameters were set as in the simulation studies and we used Gelman and Rubin diagnostics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Gelman1">[72]</xref> to determine the burn-in length as 10000 iterations and 50000 additional iterations were run to make posterior inferences. It took 5 hours and 40 minutes using a desktop computer with single core 4.5GHz CPU and 4GB memory.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3i">
<title>Application Results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067672-g007">Figure 7</xref> shows the posterior probabilities of genes selected via our iBVS strategy with integrated biological priors. The top 30 genes (probe sets) are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0067672-t001">Table 1</xref>. In order to select only the most efficient predictive genes, cross-validation for our iBVS model was used. The top genes were added into the logistic model, one by one, to estimate the prediction error. The error analysis of the model with inclusion of different numbers of predictive genes shows that the smallest classification error appears when only the top 3 or 4 genes are selected as predictors. The error increases with the number of predictors of more than 4, but the errors greatly decrease again when the 13th or 16th genes are included in the model. The top 5 pathways are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0067672-t002">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0067672-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Gene and Pathway Selection Results for Stroke Data.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0067672-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Top 30 genes selected using BVS on Stroke Data.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0067672-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BVS.ID</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post.Prob.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probe.Set.ID</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene.Symbol</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene.Title</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.951</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206177_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARG1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">arginase, liver</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202635_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POLR2K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">polymerase (RNA) II (DNA directed) polypeptide K, 7.0kDa</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">356</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205067_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL1B</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interleukin 1, beta</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">486</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1552912_a_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL23R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interleukin 23 receptor</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">634</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235086_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">THBS1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">thrombospondin 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">514</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207445_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCR9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemokine (C-C motif) receptor 9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">576</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207113_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tumor necrosis factor</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203939_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT5E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5'-nucleotidase, ecto (CD73)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">541</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206126_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CXCR5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemokine (C-X-C motif) receptor 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219308_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AK5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adenylate kinase 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">559</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214146_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPBP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pro-platelet basic protein (chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">524</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210549_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCL23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">339</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205291_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL2RB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interleukin 2 receptor, beta</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">530</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216598_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCL2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">472</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205445_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">prolactin</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">343</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207072_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL18RAP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interleukin 18 receptor accessory protein</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223359_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDE7A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phosphodiesterase 7A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">397</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211333_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FASLG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fas ligand (TNF superfamily, member 6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1098</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52255_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COL5A3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">collagen, type V, alpha 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">394</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241819_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNFSF8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tumor necrosis factor (ligand) superfamily, member 8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212739_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NME4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-metastatic cells 4, protein expressed in</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203302_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DCK</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">deoxycytidine kinase</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">334</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205327_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACVR2A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">activin A receptor, type IIA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">448</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210755_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HGF</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hepatocyte growth factor (hepapoietin A; scatter factor)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205757_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENTPD5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ectonucleoside triphosphate diphosphohydrolase 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205403_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL1R2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interleukin 1 receptor, type II</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">344</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206618_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL18R1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interleukin 18 receptor 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1107</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204614_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SERPINB2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">serpin peptidase inhibitor, clade B (ovalbumin), member 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">560</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215101_s_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CXCL5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1553587_a_at</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POLE4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">polymerase (DNA-directed), epsilon 4 (p12 subunit)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>We list the detailed information on the top 30 genes. BVS.ID refers to the variables in the model: e.g. 196 refers to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e138" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in our model. Post.Prob. is the posterior probability of the particular variable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0067672-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Top Pathways Selected via BVS.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0067672-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KEGG.ID</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Top.genes.extracted</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total # of genes</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hsa05214</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glioma - Homo sapiens (human)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BVS.ID356 (IL1B), BVS.ID486 (IL23R)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hsa04060</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytokine-cytokine receptor interaction- Homo sapiens (human)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BVS.ID61 (POLR2K)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hsa05222</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small cell lung cancer - Homo sapiens (human)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BVS.ID196 (ARG1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hsa04623</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytosolic DNA-sensing pathway- Homo sapiens (human)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BVS.ID196 (ARG1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hsa04640</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hematopoietic cell lineage - Homo sapiens (human)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>We list the 5 pathways that have the highest posterior probabilities. Top.genes.extracts refers to the gene with highest posterior probability within a pathway. and Total # of genes refers to the total number of genes within a pathway.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>From a biological standpoint, the genes and pathways that represent the best gene predictors and key pathways are directly relevant. ARG1, the gene with the greatest predictive value, is a marker of M2 macrophage activation (Morris et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Morris1">[88]</xref>), which is associated with the inflammatory and immune response to stoke. Abrupt changes in gene transcription triggered as a response to stroke for initiation of cellular survival mechanisms would be mediated through POLR2K as a pivotal player in RNA transcription. IL1B and IL23R are also amongst the other top genes with the greatest predictive value. These and many others identified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0067672-t001">Table 1</xref> are key modulators in effecting the inflammatory response of cells responding to the injury of stroke (Wong et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Wong1">[89]</xref>).</p>
<p>Given the abundance of chemokine and immune modulating genes in our list, it was not surprising to see that the KEGG pathway for cytokine-cytokine interaction is represented, as is the highly immune pathway for cytosolic DNA-sensing. While gliomas are brain-related like stroke, the presence of this pathway may represent its more general cytokine or calcium-related signaling features. Smaller overlapping sub-networks of characterized pathways may account for the presence of seemingly unrelated, yet identified pathways such as that for small cell lung cancer, as it contains key components of cell proliferation and cell death, which are also prominent in brain injury.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this paper, we used a generalized Bayesian framework for biomarker identification. For problems with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e312" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, it would be appealing to remove noisy measures or those with lower quality beforehand and defining the proper level of model space to be further explored using stochastic search. We then followed the integrative biomarker discovery scheme to incorporate the gene network, i.e. pathway information, and adopted a novel PLS g-prior for the purpose of variable selection. Cross-validation methods were conceived for determining the Bayesian significance level in cutting off the posterior probabilities for selecting causal/marker genes in classifying patients or predicting risk of diseases.</p>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Subjective versus Objective Priors</title>
<p>In this paper, we mainly adopt the perspective of subjective Bayesian due to the fact that we want to incorporate informative priors from available scientific sources. Although we used MRF in this article to illustrate how gene-gene networking structure would cast upon gene selection, there are many different ways to use the abundant informative priors (Hill et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Hill1">[75]</xref>). As seen in the Method section, even for MRF, we have different ways to incorporate this information. Choosing an objective prior that satisfies some fundamental principles as summarized in Bayarri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Bayarri1">[52]</xref> would be theoretically appealing. For example, when specifying the prior distribution of the gene/pathway selection probability, we may choose a Bernoulli distribution with unknown hyper-parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e313" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with Beta prior distribution, instead of setting it at a fixed level. This would lead to the posterior selection of models that are not biased toward a mode dimension of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.e314" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Comparison to Other Marker Discovery Methods</title>
<p>As mentioned above briefly, regularization methods provide an alternative solution for feature selection and classification problems. For GWAS data, Guan and Stephens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Guan1">[4]</xref> have indicated that BVS provides better power and predictive performance than standard lasso techniques. Our experience with standard BVS for simulated microarray data with continuous outcomes also suggest that it outperforms lasso, elastic net <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Zou1">[90]</xref>, and stepwise variable selection with higher sensitivity and specificity. Nonetheless, there lacks of evidence in comparing BVS with grouped lasso <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0067672-Yuan1">[91]</xref>, which considers the grouping of genes into gene sets. As proved in the simulation studies, our iBVS performs better than, or at least equally as well as standard BVS for gene selection. It also has the advantage to tell you which networks, in addition to which genes, could predict disease and pathology. Compared to network-based marker discovery, our iBVS not only suggests which genes are important, but also could handle those ‘orphan’ genes that have not been classified into any pathway at the time of study.</p>
<p>In the conduct of standard GSEA or network marker discovery, one may calibrate the significance of a pathway in predicting disease or treatment effectiveness by using all its predefined member genes, but these include a large number of noisy genes (i.e., those non-contributive and non-causal genes). Alternatively, one may choose to use only a subset of contributing genes, but which subset to use is a big challenge. In our iBVS, the two components are merged together into one procedure, which allows the two parts learn from each other and reflects the uncertainty of gene/pathway selection using stochastic simulation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Future Directions</title>
<p>Although iBVS has been proven as an appealing alternative solution to traditional gene-wise biomarker identification, its computational challenges hinder its widespread adoption. With a large number of parameters in the model, the inference is mainly based on Monte Carlo simulation, which is time-consuming. Running over single computers, it would take hours even days to complete a round of simulation procedure. Nowadays, with the advent of high-speed cluster computers and the existence of cloud computing technologies, it is becoming very feasible to apply full iBVS methods for biomarker identification. Our research team is developing parallel MCMC algorithm over the Amazon Cloud platform using the idea of MapReduce.</p>
<p>Currently, the pathway information we have is limited to a small portion of genes that have been well-characterized. A relatively large amount of genes are not well-studied, nor their functions have been identified. In our application, we found that some genes had not been mapped to any KEGG pathways yet. Two potential solutions are conceived: (1) develop a stochastic inference of the gene-gene networks from the data and merge it into the current BVS MCMC algorithm; (2) query the Internet to find as more information, literature, and databases to help elicit richer priors. This topic is part of our ongoing research.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0067672.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0067672.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Text S1</label><caption>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors would like to thank the two anonymous reviewers and the academic editor for their valuable comments and suggestions, which helped improving the quality of this publication.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Jain1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Jain K (2009) Textbook of Personalized Medicine. Springer.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Paik1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A multigene assay to predict recurrence of tamoxifen-treated, node-negative breast cancer</article-title>. <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source> <volume>351</volume>: <fpage>2817</fpage>–<lpage>2826</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Mallick1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mallick B, Gold D, Baladandayuthapani V (2009) Bayesian Analysis of Gene Expression Data, volume 130. John Wiley &amp; Sons Inc.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Guan1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Bayesian variable selection regression for genome-wide association studies and other large-scale problems</article-title>. <source>The Annals of Applied Statistics</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1780</fpage>–<lpage>1815</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Golub1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Golub</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slonim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaasenbeek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Molecular classification of cancer: class discovery and class prediction by gene expression monitoring</article-title>. <source>science</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Nguyen1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Tumor classification by partial least squares using microarray gene expression data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Dettling1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dettling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Bagboosting for tumor classification with gene expression data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>3583</fpage>–<lpage>3593</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Smyth1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Linear models and empirical bayes methods for assessing differential expression in microarray experiments</article-title>. <source>Statistical applications in genetics and molecular biology</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Casella1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>An introduction to empirical bayes data analysis</article-title>. <source>The American Statistician</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Beaumont1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rannala</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The bayesian revolution in genetics</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Miller1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Miller A (2002) Subset selection in regression. Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-George1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Variable selection via gibbs sampling</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>881</fpage>–<lpage>889</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-George2"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Approaches for bayesian variable selection</article-title>. <source>Statistica Sinica</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Kuo1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kuo L, Mallick B (1998) Variable selection for regression models. Sankhyā: The Indian Journal of Statistics, Series B: 65–81.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Dellaportas1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Dellaportas P, Forster J, Ntzoufras I (1997) On bayesian model and variable selection using mcmc. In: paper based upon a talk presented at the HSSS Workshop on Variable Dimension MCMC, New Forest.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Geweke1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geweke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Variable selection and model comparison in regression</article-title>. <source>Bayesian statistics</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>609</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Green1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Reversible jump markov chain monte carlo computation and bayesian model determination</article-title>. <source>Biometrika</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>711</fpage>–<lpage>732</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Nott1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nott</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leonte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Sampling schemes for bayesian variable selection in generalized linear models</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>362</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Chen1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bayesian variable selection and computation for generalized linear models with conjugate priors</article-title>. <source>Bayesian analysis (Online)</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Brown1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Brown C (1998) Applied multivariate statistics in geohydrology and related sciences. Springer.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Meuwissen1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meuwissen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mapping multiple qtl using linkage disequilibrium and linkage analysis information and multitrait data</article-title>. <source>Genet Sel Evol</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Cai1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cai B, Dunson D (2008) Bayesian variable selection in generalized linear mixed models. Random Effect and Latent Variable Model Selection: 63–91.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-OHara1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Hara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sillanpää</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A review of bayesian variable selection methods: what, how and which</article-title>. <source>Bayesian Analysis</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Sillanp1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sillanpää</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corander</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Model choice in gene mapping: what and why</article-title>. <source>Trends in Genetics</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Hoti1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sillanpää</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Bayesian mapping of genotype× expression interactions in quantitative and qualitative traits</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Yi1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Stochastic search variable selection for identifying multiple quantitative trait loci</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>164</volume>: <fpage>1129</fpage>–<lpage>1138</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Kilpikari1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilpikari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sillanpää</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Bayesian analysis of multilocus association in quantitative and qualitative traits</article-title>. <source>Genetic epidemiology</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Yi2"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bayesian lasso for quantitative trait loci mapping</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>179</volume>: <fpage>1045</fpage>–<lpage>1055</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Baldi1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A bayesian framework for the analysis of microarray expression data: regularized t-test and statistical inferences of gene changes</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>519</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Hoggart1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoggart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Iorio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balding</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Simultaneous analysis of all snps in genomewide and re-sequencing association studies</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genetics</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000130</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Wakefield1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bayes factors for genome-wide association studies: comparison with p-values</article-title>. <source>Genetic epidemiology</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Ibrahim1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Bayesian models for gene expression with dna microarray data</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Ishwaran1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishwaran</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Detecting differentially expressed genes in microarrays using Bayesian model selection</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>438</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Lee1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vannucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mallick</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Gene selection: a bayesian variable selection approach</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-McLachlan1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLachlan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A simple implementation of a normal mixture approach to differential gene expression in multiclass microarrays</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1608</fpage>–<lpage>1615</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Gupta1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Variable selection in regression mixture modeling for the discovery of gene regulatory networks</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>867</fpage>–<lpage>880</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Shahbaba1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahbaba</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shachaf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plevritis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Bayesian gene set analysis for identifying significant biological pathways</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C (Applied Statistics)</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>557</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Stingo1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stingo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vannucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Incorporating biological information into linear models: a bayesian approach to the selection of pathways and genes</article-title>. <source>The Annals of Applied Statistics</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1978</fpage>–<lpage>2002</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Mootha1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mootha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bunkenborg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hjerrild</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wisniewski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Integrated analysis of protein composition, tissue diversity, and gene regulation in mouse mitochondria</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>640</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Subramanian1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mootha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>15545</fpage>–<lpage>15550</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Zahn1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sonu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazan-Mamczarz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional profiling of aging in human muscle reveals a common aging signature</article-title>. <source>PLoS genetics</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e115</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Mller1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kostka</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ulitsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Regulatory networks define phenotypic classes of human stem cell lines</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>455</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Li1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Bayesian variable selection in structured high-dimensional covariate spaces with applications in genomics</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>1202</fpage>–<lpage>1214</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Wei1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Network-based genomic discovery: application and comparison of markov random-field models</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C (Applied Statistics)</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-McCullagh1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCullagh P, Nelder J (1989) Generalized linear models, volume 37. Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Hoeting1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hoeting J, Madigan D, Raftery A, Volinsky C (1999) Bayesian model averaging: a tutorial. Statistical science: 382–401.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Zellner1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zellner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>On assessing prior distributions and bayesian regression analysis with g-prior distributions</article-title>. <source>Bayesian inference and decision techniques: Essays in Honor of Bruno De Finetti</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Jeffreys1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Jeffreys H (1961) Theory of probability. Clarendon Press Oxford.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Zellner2"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zellner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Posterior odds ratios for selected regression hypotheses</article-title>. <source>Trabajos de estadística y de investigación operativa</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>603</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Berger1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Berger J, Pericchi L, Ghosh J, Samanta T, De Santis F, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2001) Objective bayesian methods for model selection: introduction and comparison. Lecture Notes-Monograph Series: 135–207.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Liang1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paulo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clyde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mixtures of g priors for bayesian variable selection</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>410</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Bayarri1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayarri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>García-Donato</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Criteria for bayesian model choice with application to variable selection</article-title>. <source>The Annals of Statistics</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1550</fpage>–<lpage>1577</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Berger2"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pericchi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The intrinsic bayes factor for model selection and prediction</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Moreno1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertolino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Racugno</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>An intrinsic limiting procedure for model selection and hypotheses testing</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1451</fpage>–<lpage>1460</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-OHagan1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Hagan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Properties of intrinsic and fractional bayes factors</article-title>. <source>Test</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Prez1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Expected-posterior prior distributions for model selection</article-title>. <source>Biometrika</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>512</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Cano1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salmerón</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Integral equation solutions as prior distributions for Bayesian model selection</article-title>. <source>Test</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Scott1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>An exploration of aspects of bayesian multiple testing</article-title>. <source>Journal of Statistical Planning and Inference</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>2144</fpage>–<lpage>2162</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Do1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Do</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A bayesian mixture model for differential gene expression</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C (Applied Statistics)</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>627</fpage>–<lpage>644</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Newton1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Newton M, Kendziorski C (2003) Parametric empirical bayes methods for microarrays. The Analysis of Gene Expression Data: 254–271.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Newton2"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kendziorski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blattner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>On differential variability of expression ratios: improving statistical inference about gene expression changes from microarray data</article-title>. <source>Journal of computational biology</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Romero1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krummenacker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Computational prediction of human metabolic pathways from the complete human genome</article-title>. <source>Genome Biology</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>R2</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Phizicky1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phizicky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Protein-protein interactions: Methods for detection and analysis</article-title>. <source>Microbiological Reviews</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Zhang1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A general framework for weighted gene co-expression network analysis</article-title>. <source>Statistical applications in genetics and molecular biology</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1128</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Hastie1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alizadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Gene shaving'as a method for identifying distinct sets of genes with similar expression patterns</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>0003</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Godsill1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Godsill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>On the relationship between markov chain monte carlo methods for model uncertainty</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>230</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Yi3"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A unified markov chain monte carlo framework for mapping multiple quantitative trait loci</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>167</volume>: <fpage>967</fpage>–<lpage>975</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Furnival1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Furnival</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Regressions by leaps and bounds</article-title>. <source>Technometrics</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>499</fpage>–<lpage>511</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Annest1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Annest</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bumgarner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raftery</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Iterative bayesian model averaging: A method for the application of survival analysis to high-dimensional microarray data</article-title>. <source>BMC bioinformatics</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>72</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Yang1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Bayesian variable selection for disease classification using gene expression data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Wu1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beissinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Parallel markov chain monte carlobridging the gap to high-performance bayesian computation in animal breeding and genetics</article-title>. <source>Genetics Selection Evolution</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Gelman1"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Inference from iterative simulation using multiple sequences</article-title>. <source>Statistical science</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>472</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Mallat1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Matching pursuits with time-frequency dictionaries</article-title>. <source>Signal Processing, IEEE Transactions on</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>3397</fpage>–<lpage>3415</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Chen2"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Stochastic matching pursuit for bayesian variable selection</article-title>. <source>Statistics and Computing</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Hill1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neve</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bayani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ziyad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Integrating biological knowledge into variable selection: an empirical bayes approach with an application in cancer biology</article-title>. <source>BMC bioinformatics</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>94</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Kitchen1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitchen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wrin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Hiv-1 viral fitness estimation using exchangeable on subsets priors and prior model selection</article-title>. <source>Statistics in medicine</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>975</fpage>–<lpage>990</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Chuang1"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ideker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Network-based classification of breast cancer metastasis</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>140</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Lee2"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ideker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Inferring pathway activity toward precise disease classification</article-title>. <source>PLoS computational biology</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000217</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Ravasi1"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravasi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cannistraci</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bajic</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>An atlas of combinatorial transcriptional regulation in mouse and man</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>744</fpage>–<lpage>752</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Srivastava1"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A novel method incorporating gene ontology information for unsupervised clustering and feature selection</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e3860</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Robert1"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Robert C, Casella G (2004) Monte carlo statistical methods.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Madigan1"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madigan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raftery</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Model selection and accounting for model uncertainty in graphical models using occam's window</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>1535</fpage>–<lpage>1546</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Albert1"><label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chib</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Bayesian analysis of binary and polychotomous response data</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American statistical Association</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>679</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Wei2"><label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A markov random field model for network-based analysis of genomic data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1537</fpage>–<lpage>1544</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Pancioli1"><label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pancioli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broderick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brott</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomsick</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khoury</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The combined approach to lysis utilizing eptifibatide and rt-pa in acute ischemic stroke the clear stroke trial</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>3268</fpage>–<lpage>3276</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Stamova1"><label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stamova</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jickling</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bushnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Gene expression profiling of blood for the prediction of ischemic stroke</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>2171</fpage>–<lpage>2177</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Li2"><label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birkbak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gyorffy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szallasi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eklund</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Jetset: selecting the optimal microarray probe set to represent a gene</article-title>. <source>BMC bioinformatics</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>474</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Morris1"><label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kepka-Lenhart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Differential regulation of arginases and inducible nitric oxide synthase in murine macrophage cells</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Physiology-Endocrinology And Metabolism</source> <volume>275</volume>: <fpage>E740</fpage>–<lpage>E747</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Wong1"><label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bongiorno</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rettori</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Licinio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Interleukin (il) 1<italic>β</italic>, il-1 receptor antagonist, il-10, and il-13 gene expression in the central nervous system and anterior pituitary during systemic inammation: pathophysiological implications</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Zou1"><label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Regularization and variable selection via the elastic net</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Statistical Methodology)</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0067672-Yuan1"><label>91</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Model selection and estimation in regression with grouped variables</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Statistical Methodology)</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>