<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0152892</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-41747</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Political science</subject><subj-group><subject>Labor studies</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject><subj-group><subject>Gratitude</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject><subj-group><subject>Gratitude</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychometrics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychometrics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental health and psychiatry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematical and statistical techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Factor analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics (mathematics)</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Factor analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject><subj-group><subject>Happiness</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject><subj-group><subject>Happiness</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Public and occupational health</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavioral and social aspects of health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Labor economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Employment</subject><subj-group><subject>Jobs</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Measuring Psychological Capital: Construction and Validation of the Compound PsyCap Scale (CPC-12)</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Measuring Psychological Capital</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lorenz</surname>
<given-names>Timo</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Beer</surname>
<given-names>Clemens</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Pütz</surname>
<given-names>Jan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Heinitz</surname>
<given-names>Kathrin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><addr-line>Department of Work and Organizational Psychology, Freie Universität Berlin, Berlin, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Cipresso</surname>
<given-names>Pietro</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>IRCCS Istituto Auxologico Italiano, ITALY</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: TL CB JP. Performed the experiments: TL CB JP. Analyzed the data: TL CB JP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: TL CB JP KH. Wrote the paper: TL CB JP KH.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">timo.lorenz@fu-berlin.de</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>1</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<elocation-id>e0152892</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>21</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>21</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Lorenz et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0152892"/>
<abstract>
<p>With the Psychological Capital Questionnaire (PCQ) being the standard measure to assess psychological capital (PsyCap) in the context of organizations, this paper aims to broaden this domain-specific approach by introducing a measure with universal claim. Two studies were conducted to create and validate a German self-report scale (CPC-12) measuring PsyCap. We performed confirmatory factor analyses and correlations with other positive psychological constructs on the data of two German samples (N<sub>1</sub> = 321; N<sub>2</sub> = 202). The twelve-item CPC-12 exhibits the anticipated factorial structure with a very good model fit and associations to other constructs concur with previous findings with other measures of PsyCap.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The authors have no support or funding to report.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="1"/>
<table-count count="3"/>
<page-count count="17"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Psychological capital (PsyCap) draws from the significant body of research that Seligman and Csikszentmihalyi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref001">1</xref>] have initiated in the wake of the positive psychology movement. In shifting the focus of psychological research from human deficits like mental illnesses to human assets, strengths were scientifically studied and have been found to allow individuals, groups or even organizations to thrive and prosper [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref001">1</xref>]. Extending these findings to the work place, Luthans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref002">2</xref>] identified psychological constructs (i.e. self-efficacy, hope, optimism, happiness, and resilience), which met the criteria of being positive, based on theory and research, and state-like open to development, change and management for performance improvement. These five constructs were labeled positive organizational behavior (POB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref002">2</xref>]. Luthans and Youssef [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref003">3</xref>] bundled four of these states (hope, optimism, resilience, and self-efficacy) into the higher-order construct “positive psychological capital (PsyCap)”. This construct was developed to provide practitioners with a new framework to ensure a sustainable competitive advantage via human resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref003">3</xref>].</p>
<p>PsyCap as a whole is defined as “a core psychological factor of positivity in general, and [positive organizational behavior] criteria meeting states in particular, that go beyond human and social capital to gain a competitive advantage through investment/development of ‘who you are’”[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref004">4</xref>], its parts as follows: (a) Hope refers to an individual’s motivation to succeed at a specific task in a set context and the way or means by which that task may be accomplished [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref005">5</xref>]. (b) Optimism refers to an individual’s expectancy of positive outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref006">6</xref>]. (c) Resilience refers to the ability of an individual to bounce back from adversity, uncertainty, risk or failure, and adapt to changing and stressful life demands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref007">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref008">8</xref>]. (d) Self-efficacy refers to an individual’s confidence in their ability to mobilize their motivation, cognitive resources and courses of action to achieve high levels of performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref009">9</xref>].</p>
<p>PsyCap can be distinguished from other forms of people-related capital, specifically human (an individual’s stock of knowledge, skills and abilities that can be increased by experience and/or investment in education and training) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref010">10</xref>] and social capital (the aggregate of the actual or potential resources that are connected to the possession of a durable network of relationships) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref003">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref011">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref012">12</xref>]. It influences a variety of outcomes at the individual level of particular importance for organizations and even beyond the work place [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref013">13</xref>]. Previous research however focused heavily on a domain-specific measure settled in the context of work. PsyCap is shown to be associated with desirable employee attitudes, such as staying intentions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref013">13</xref>], job satisfaction and commitment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref014">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref015">15</xref>]. Employees high in PsyCap are found to be more empowered, which subsequently leads to less turnover intentions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref016">16</xref>], and the reduction of absenteeism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref017">17</xref>]. Furthermore, individuals high in PsyCap perform better than those low in PsyCap since they can draw upon more resources to pursue goals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref018">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref019">19</xref>]. Most importantly, PsyCap is shown to be developable through training interventions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref015">15</xref>], which makes it a useful and tangible construct actually able to influence individuals and even whole organizations in a positive way.</p>
<p>Besides these work place-specific benefits, studies found evidence linking PsyCap to an improved psychological and physical well-being by the reduction of stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref020">20</xref>]. Because of the reciprocal relationship between job satisfaction and life satisfaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref021">21</xref>], PsyCap enhances the latter. Due to the fact that PsyCap consists of more general constructs (hope, optimism, self-efficacy and resilience) the question at hand is—Is PsyCap merely a domain-specific construct with effects solely in work-related areas or is it a much broader construct influencing many possible areas of life?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Measuring Psychological Capital</title>
<p>The Psychological Capital Questionnaire (PCQ) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref003">3</xref>] is widely recognized as the standard scale measuring PsyCap [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref022">22</xref>]. It was developed as a compound measure consisting of (modified) items from published scales for hope [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref023">23</xref>], optimism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref024">24</xref>], resilience [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref025">25</xref>], and self-efficacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref026">26</xref>]. Predominantly, the PCQ was used in employee, manager and student samples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref022">22</xref>], and its items are closely tied to the work place (i.e. “I feel confident contributing to discussions about the company's strategy.”). One can thus state that the PCQ is a domain-specific measure.</p>
<p>Since PsyCap is shown to be linked to outcomes of general importance for individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref020">20</xref>], this study aims to design and validate a universal measure for the construct. Such a non-domain-specific measure could expedite research on PsyCap for constructs in other domains, i.e. sports and education. Therefore, we conducted two different studies. Study 1 drew from the item pool of published and proven measures for the four different PsyCap components to create a compound measure, which is deployable in a wide range of applications (including the work place). For testing convergent and discriminant validity, we additionally surveyed the existing PCQ and a measure for occupational self-efficacy. We hypothesized a strong positive association between the PCQ and our newly created measure (Compound Psychological Capital Scale– 12; CPC-12), a higher positive correlation between general self-efficacy and the CPC-12 compared to the PCQ and a lower positive one between occupational self-efficacy and the CPC-12 compared to the PCQ due to the domain specific traits of the PCQ. In study 2, we re-tested the factorial structure of the CPC-12. Furthermore, to test the external validity of the CPC-12, we also selected several important positive psychological constructs—affect, job satisfaction, satisfaction with life, subjective well-being, perceived social support, meaning of work, engagement, gratitude and personality. The specific hypotheses regarding the associations between the CPC-12 and these constructs are discussed below.</p>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Positive affect (PA) and negative affect (NA)</title>
<p>The relationship between PA and PsyCap becomes obvious upon reviewing the literature relating PA to three major components of PsyCap: resiliency, self-efficacy and optimism. These studies found that people high in PA show more effective problem resolving skills, more mature coping efforts, experience less conflict at the office [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref027">27</xref>] and furthermore that positive emotions enhance resilience in the face of adversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref028">28</xref>]. People who show more PA are also more optimistic and more likely to maintain a positive outlook during times of adversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref027">27</xref>]. Additionally, they are found to be high in personal competence and self-esteem and report higher self-efficacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref027">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref029">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref030">30</xref>]. Little, Gooty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref031">31</xref>] also reported significant positive correlations between all four components of PsyCap and PA (<italic>r</italic> = .28−.68).</p>
<p>There is evidently a remarkable overlap between PA and PsyCap. One study even found that the predictive power of PsyCap on work performance, motivation and job satisfaction becomes insignificant once one accounts for PA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref031">31</xref>]. Nonetheless the same study also pointed out that none of the PA-items loaded with the PsyCap constructs, meaning that besides the overlap, they are still clearly distinct constructs. For these reasons we expect a strong correlation between CPC-12 and PA. Lyubomirsky, King [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref027">27</xref>] state that NA and PA “regularly show moderate inverse relations across individuals, justifying the use of such negative states as the inverse of PA” (p. 822), thus we expect a moderate or high negative correlation between NA and PsyCap. This makes sense if you bear in mind the negative effects that PsyCap has on states like stress and anxiety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref020">20</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Job satisfaction</title>
<p>There is a clear relationship between job satisfaction and PsyCap. Studies indicate that people high in PsyCap also report higher job satisfaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref012">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref013">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref019">19</xref>]. Luthans, Avolio [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref019">19</xref>] report a positive correlation of <italic>r</italic> = .39, whereas the meta-analysis of Avey, Reichard [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref013">13</xref>] reports an even higher correlation of <italic>r =</italic> .50−.57. One explanation for this relationship is given by Avey, Reichard [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref013">13</xref>] who state: “Given the general expectancy of success derived from optimism and the belief in personal abilities derived from efficacy, those high in PsyCap report being more satisfied with their job.” (p. 132). In addition Luthans, Avolio [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref019">19</xref>] declare that employees who are hopeful and efficacious are more satisfied with their jobs due to better performance. They are confident to persist, accept challenges and put effort into achieving their goals (efficacy). Furthermore they identify subgoals and pathways to achieve them and are able to foresee and overcome obstacles by pursuing a variety of pathways (hope). We therefore expect the CPC-12 to positively correlate with job satisfaction in about the same range as stated above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Satisfaction with life</title>
<p>Previous studies on PsyCap concentrated on work-related outcomes, i.e. job satisfaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref012">12</xref>]. Nonetheless work and non-work life influence each other [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref032">32</xref>] and there is a positive correlation between job satisfaction and life satisfaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref033">33</xref>]. Ford, Heinen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref032">32</xref>] name time-based pressure as one major reason for this mutual interaction. If you have to work extra hours in the office you will have less time to enjoy time with family or friends, which can leave you unsatisfied and vice versa. Newman, Ucbasaran [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref012">12</xref>] also stated in their meta-analysis that besides predicting higher levels of work-family conflict, low PsyCap predicts less meaning of life, things that should result in a decrease in life satisfaction. Lastly it has been reported that life satisfaction is positively related to optimism and self-esteem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref034">34</xref>], posing another connection to PsyCap. For these reasons, we expect a moderate to high positive correlation between the CPC-12 and life satisfaction.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Subjective well-being</title>
<p>Since well-being is measured in many studies as a compound construct consisting of positive and negative affect, life satisfaction and job satisfaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref035">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref036">36</xref>], PsyCap, as expected, positively relates to well-being [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref022">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref037">37</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref039">39</xref>]. Avey, Luthans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref038">38</xref>] furthermore show that PsyCap can lead to psychological well-being over time. We therefore expect a high positive correlation between subjective well-being and the CPC-12.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Perceived Social Support</title>
<p>In their study “Very Happy People” Diener and Seligman stated that satisfying social relationships are central to human happiness, so much so that happiness cannot occur without them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref040">40</xref>]. Findings from Karademas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref041">41</xref>] support those claims as he reports a direct positive relationship between social support and life satisfaction as well as an indirect one through optimism. Optimistic people seem to positively appraise future events. To maintain such beliefs optimists rely on a “positive evaluation of the social context and its ‘ability’ to provide the necessary support” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref041">41</xref>]. Social support has furthermore not only been found to increase optimism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref041">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref042">42</xref>] but also to be associated with self-esteem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref042">42</xref>]. Positive correlations between social support and optimism have been found to be moderate (<italic>r</italic> = .29−.41), similar to the moderate positive ones with self-esteem (<italic>r</italic> = .44) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref041">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref042">42</xref>]. High levels of social support have also been found to reduce mortality and to result in positive health outcomes, due to social support functioning as an “exceptionally important stress resilience factor” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref043">43</xref>]. We expect a small to moderate positive correlation between perceived social support and the CPC-12 situated at the lower edge of the range stated above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Meaning of Work</title>
<p>When looking at meaning, its importance not only in the field of work, but for life in general [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref044">44</xref>], becomes clear. It is not just a positive influence on organizational performance or employee engagement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref045">45</xref>]. Having meaning in life is also of great importance for living a “full life” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref044">44</xref>], which is very desirable for many. Again there is a positive relationship with PsyCap as Coutu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref046">46</xref>] reported a strong relationship between meaning-making and resilience. She stated that one of the things distinguishing resilient people from less resilient people is their ability to create significance and meaning in their hardships and their lives in general. In addition, she reported the effective use of constructing meaning in resilience trainings for business people. Resilient people are more likely to see themselves not as victims in adversity, but rather to recognize the lesson and learning opportunity in their hardship. They are therefore able to create meaning in difficult situations in life and at work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref046">46</xref>]. The fact that a sense of self-worth and efficacy are found to be two important pillars in the search for meaning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref047">47</xref>], and the finding that lower levels of PsyCap seem to result in lower levels of meaning of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref012">12</xref>] underline the positive relationship between meaning of work and PsyCap. We expect a moderate positive correlation between the CPC-12 and meaning of work.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Engagement</title>
<p>Engagement is characterized by vigor, dedication and absorption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref048">48</xref>]. Vigor is a very similar construct to resilience as Bakker, Schaufeli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref048">48</xref>] describe vigorous people as mentally resilient, willing to put great effort into their work and to show persistence in the face of adversity. Resilience is not the only personal resource that has been found to reciprocally influence work engagement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref048">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref049">49</xref>]. Self-efficacy as well as optimism have been found to be equally connected to engagement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref050">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref051">51</xref>]. These personal resources show moderate positive correlations with work engagement (<italic>r</italic> = .29−.54) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref050">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref051">51</xref>]. Xanthopoulou, Bakker [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref051">51</xref>] explain the relationship by suggesting that people high in self-efficacy, optimism and resilience are “confident about their capabilities and optimistic about their future, and thus may identify or even create more aspects of their environment that facilitate goal attainment. This capability leads to goal confrontation and consequently to work engagement” (p. 137). It also has been explicitly stated that people high in PsyCap are more committed to their jobs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref013">13</xref>] as the organizations they work for fulfill their needs for accomplishment and efficacy, thus leading to them being more “likely to embed themselves and be enthusiastic about their work (engagement)” (p. 132). We therefore expect a solid moderate positive correlation between engagement and the CPC-12 in about a similar range as stated above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Gratitude</title>
<p>The close relationship of gratitude and PsyCap was demonstrated in a study by Luthans, Youssef [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref052">52</xref>], in which they discussed a range of possible constructs to be included into PsyCap. They regard gratitude as a promising aspirant for inclusion describing it as “the extra mile willingly traveled by those with high PsyCap” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref052">52</xref>]. They find that gratitude prevents people from having negative labels and thoughts about their fellow men, thus decreasing the positivity in those relationships, which would in turn lead to a lower level of PsyCap. They state that being grateful helps us to maintain a positive outlook on life and positively reinforce each other. Maintaining a positive view on life resembles parts of optimism and hope.This is also reflected in other studies, which found positive relationships between gratitude and optimism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref053">53</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref055">55</xref>], hope [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref054">54</xref>] and life satisfaction and happiness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref055">55</xref>]. McCullough, Emmons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref054">54</xref>] report moderate positive correlations between gratitude and optimism (<italic>r</italic> = .28−.58) as well as for gratitude and the two factors of hope (<italic>r</italic> = .18−.67). Considering the connection of gratitude to some of the PsyCap components and its actual consideration as a component itself, we expect a moderate positive correlation of gratitude with the CPC-12.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Personality</title>
<p>A proactive personality is desirable at an individual level as it predicts life satisfaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref056">56</xref>], but also from an organization’s perspective as it is for example positively related to job performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref057">57</xref>]. It means for a person to have an enhanced ability and desire to control the surrounding environment in an active, self-determined way. These control tendencies facilitate effective coping with occupational stressors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref056">56</xref>], thus showing similarities to resilience. Optimism also seems closely related to a proactive attitude. Schmitz and Schwarzer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref058">58</xref>] identify optimistic expectancy as the quintessence of the construct and describe proactive people as considering life to be full of opportunities. They furthermore associate proactive attitude with Bandura’s self-efficacy, deeming the two to be very similar constructs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref058">58</xref>]. We therefore expect a moderate to high positive correlation between proactive attitude and the CPC-12.</p>
<p>The “Big Five” personality traits extraversion (<italic>r</italic> = .36) and conscientiousness (<italic>r</italic> = .39) reportedly show the strongest relationship with PsyCap. The correlation of agreeableness with PsyCap (<italic>r</italic> = .06) is unremarkable, whereas openness (<italic>r</italic> = -.1) and neuroticism (<italic>r</italic> = -.12) show marginal negative correlations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref019">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref022">22</xref>]. The positive correlation with extraversion seems logical as it has also been found to be positively related to positive affect, life satisfaction and happiness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref027">27</xref>].</p>
<p>Looking at some of the PsyCap components respectively, one study testing the relationship of resilience with personality traits found a strong positive correlation with extraversion (<italic>r</italic> = .61) and conscientiousness (<italic>r</italic> = .45) as well as a strong negative correlation with neuroticism (<italic>r</italic> = -.65). The correlation with agreeableness was unremarkable, but there was a small positive correlation with openness (<italic>r</italic> = .20) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref059">59</xref>]. The strong negative relationship with neuroticism measures up to one’s expectations. Neurotic people are vulnerable to emotional distress and susceptible to negative emotions and poor coping [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref060">60</xref>]. Campbell-Sills, Cohan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref059">59</xref>] explain the strong positive relationships to extraversion as likely reflecting “the benefits of positive affective style, capacity for interpersonal closeness, and high levels of social interaction and activity” (p. 594). They furthermore explicate that the positive relationship with resilience can be fully explained by the tendency of conscientious people to use task-oriented coping. Taking all these findings together we expect a similar pattern of correlations between the “Big Five” and the CPC-12, moderate positive correlations with extraversion and conscientiousness, a moderate negative correlation with neuroticism, a small correlation with openness and no correlation with agreeableness.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Study 1—Methods</title>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Participants and Procedure</title>
<p>Study 1 consisted of a total of 334 participants. Thirteen people were excluded from the analysis (six due to implausible or missing job description e.g. “xxx”, seven due to implausible tenure). The remaining 321 participants averaged 34.89 years (SD = 12.78), 60% were women and 76.6% were employees, 8.4% were self-employed and 13.7% temporary workers. Participants worked on average 33.79 hours a week (SD = 13.39) and had been employed for half a month to 43 years (M<sub>employment</sub> = 7.91 years, SD = 9.72). 48% of the participants were in possession of a university degree and another 25% graduated with the general qualification for university entrance. Participants were recruited by publishing the link to the survey in several online social media groups. The survey was conducted in German. All participants were volunteers, no compensation was supplied.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Materials</title>
<p>All scales were surveyed using a 6-point response format ranging from 1 = “<italic>strongly disagree</italic>” to 6 = “<italic>strongly agree”</italic> in order to minimize potential effects of different response formats on the new scale.</p>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Hope</title>
<p>Hope was evaluated using the six item short version of the State Hope Scale (SHS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref023">23</xref>]. The German version of this scale was derived by translating the original version of the State Hope Scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref023">23</xref>] into German (including a retranslation for verification purposes) according to the guidelines for cross-cultural adaptation proposed by Guillemin, Bombardier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref061">61</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Optimism</title>
<p>Optimism was evaluated using two different scales. (a) The affective valence of the orientation towards the future-questionnaire (Affektive Valenz der Zukunftsorientierung, AFF) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref062">62</xref>] with five items including one inverted item. Cronbach’s α of the AFF was .82. (b) The revised German version of the Life Orientation Test (LOT-R) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref063">63</xref>] with ten items (four filler items and three items respectively tapping the subscales optimism and pessimism; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref064">64</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Resilience</title>
<p>Resilience was assessed using the German thirteen item short version of the Resilience Scale (RS-13) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref065">65</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Self-efficacy</title>
<p>Self-efficacy was evaluated using two different measures. (a) The German General Self Efficacy Scale (GSE) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref066">66</xref>] with ten items. (b) The German ten item short version of the Occupational Self-Efficacy Scale (OSE) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref067">67</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019">
<title>Psychological capital</title>
<p>PsyCap was surveyed using the German version of the Psychological Capital Questionnaire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref019">19</xref>] with 24 items. Six items each measured the four subscales hope, optimism, resilience and self-efficacy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020">
<title>Construction of Compound-Psychological-Capital-Scale</title>
<p>The five selected scales (SHS, AFF, LOT-R, RS-13, and GSE) constitute the pool of items from which the Compound-Psychological-Capital questionnaire (CPC-12) was developed. All four constructs (i.e., hope, resilience, optimism, and self-efficacy) should have equal weight; hence, the best three items of each construct in terms of content and face validity were taken into account. Furthermore, following the concept of rational construction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref068">68</xref>], only those items were included which met our claim of universality and are therefore not solely relevant to the workplace. All scales for the item pool were included in this study in their full length to be able to control their correlations comparing PCQ and CPC-12.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec021">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>The fit of all tested structural equation models was examined using the criteria proposed by Hu and Bentler [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref069">69</xref>]. Beyond χ² significance testing these criteria comprise a standardized root-mean-square residual (SRMR) ≤ 0.08 in combination with at least one of the following fit indices: a root-mean-square error of approximation (RMSEA) ≤ 0.06, a lower bound of the 90% confidence interval of the RMSEA ≤ 0.06, a comparative fit index (CFI) ≥ 0.95, or a Tucker-Lewis-index (TLI) ≥ 0.95. The Satorra-Bentler adjusted χ² was calculated to adjust for non-normal distributions of the variables [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref070">70</xref>]. The confirmatory factor analyses were conducted using the “lavaan” package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref071">71</xref>] of R statistical software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref072">72</xref>]. Due to forced choice in the standardized questionnaires, there was no missing data.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec022">
<title>Study 1—Results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0152892.t001">Table 1</xref> presents descriptive statistics, Cronbach’s α and the correlation matrix for the study variables. The strong positive relationship (<italic>r</italic> = .70, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) between the PCQ and the newly created CPC-12 alludes to the measurement of a similar but not identical construct. As hypothesized the correlation between CPC-12 and general self-efficacy is higher compared to the PCQ, while the correlation between CPC-12 and occupational self-efficacy is lower compared to the PCQ.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0152892.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0152892.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Descriptive statistics and inter-correlations for study 1.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0152892.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0152892.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center"/>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center">Hope</th>
<th align="center">Optimism (AFF)</th>
<th align="center">Optimism (LOT-R)</th>
<th align="center">Resilience</th>
<th align="center">General Self-Efficacy</th>
<th align="center">Occupational Self-Efficacy</th>
<th align="center">PsyCap (PCQ)</th>
<th align="center">PsyCap (CPC-12)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Hope</td>
<td align="char" char=".">4.25</td>
<td align="char" char=".">1.04</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>84</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Optimism (AFF)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">4.83</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.99</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>82</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Optimism (LOT-R)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">4.41</td>
<td align="char" char=".">1.04</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.44<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.58<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>74</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Resilience</td>
<td align="char" char=".">4.64</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.91</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.56<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.41<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>79</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">General Self-Efficacy</td>
<td align="char" char=".">4.22</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.86</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.70<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>88</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Occupational Self-Efficacy</td>
<td align="char" char=".">4.29</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.93</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.56<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.56<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.67<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>85</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">PsyCap (PCQ)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">4.51</td>
<td align="char" char=".">1.03</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.61<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.56<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.59<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.77<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>92</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">PsyCap (CPC-12)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">4.44</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.99</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.79<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.65<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.53<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.80<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.82<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.70<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>82</italic></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>Notes: Cronbach’s α is displayed diagonal; AFF = Affektive Valenz der Zukunftsorientierung (Affective valence of the future orientation), LOT-R = Life Orientation Test—Revised, PsyCap = Psychological Capital, PCQ = Psychological Capital Questionnaire, CPC-12 = Compound Psychological Capital Scale.; p-scores:</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p>* &lt;.05,</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn003"><p>** &lt;.01,</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn004"><p>*** &lt;.001.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0152892.t002">Table 2</xref> exhibits measurement models for all selected scales, including the PCQ measure for PsyCap. To examine the expected factorial structure of the PCQ, we conducted a confirmatory factor analysis (CFA). We began by fitting this model with the six items for each facet (i.e., hope, resilience, optimism, and self-efficacy) and then fit each of the four dimensions to the higher-order PsyCap. The estimates of model fit (SRMR = .062, RMSEA = .061, CFI = .841) are not acceptable according to Hu and Bentler [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref069">69</xref>].</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0152892.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0152892.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Measurement models for study 1 using MLM estimator.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0152892.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0152892.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="center">N factors</th>
<th align="center">X²</th>
<th align="center">df</th>
<th align="center">p</th>
<th align="center">SRMR</th>
<th align="center">TLI</th>
<th align="center">CFI</th>
<th align="center">RMSEA</th>
<th align="center">RMSEA 90%-CI</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">PsyCap (PCQ)</td>
<td align="center">4+g</td>
<td align="center">549.04</td>
<td align="center">248</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt;.001</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.062</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.823</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.841</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.061</td>
<td align="center">.055−.068</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">PsyCap (CPC-12)</td>
<td align="center">4+g</td>
<td align="center">77.727</td>
<td align="center">50</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.007</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.046</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.950</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.962</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.042</td>
<td align="center">.024−.058</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>Notes: PsyCap = Psychological Capital, PCQ = Psychological Capital Questionnaire, CPC-12 = Compound Psychological Capital Scale.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>To confirm the expected higher-order factor of PsyCap in the CPC-12, we conducted a CFA on the data analogous to the one above. We began by fitting this model with three items for each facet (i.e., hope, resilience, optimism, and self-efficacy) and then fit each of the four dimensions to the higher-order PsyCap. Results indicated the following estimates of model fit: SRMR = .046, RMSEA = .042, CFI = .962. The model seems to be a very good fit with all three indices meeting the cutoff criteria by Hu and Bentler [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref069">69</xref>].</p>
<p>Furthermore, each of the factor loadings was significant on their respective latent factor at <italic>p &lt;</italic> .01 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0152892.g001">Fig 1</xref>). The confirmatory factor analysis in Study 1 supports the proposed higher-order factor structure for the newly created PsyCap measure CPC-12.</p>
<fig id="pone.0152892.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0152892.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Four (plus g-) factor measurement model for Psychological Capital.</title>
<p>Abbreviated items refer to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0152892.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0152892.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec023">
<title>Study 2—Methods</title>
<sec id="sec024">
<title>Participants and Procedure</title>
<p>Sample 2 consisted of a total of 202 participants (82.7% employees, 9.4% self-employed, and 7.9% temporary workers) between 18–72 years (M<sub>age</sub> = 37.79, SD = 13.10). 72.3% were female. Participants worked on average 35.74 hours a week (SD = 11.18) and had been employed for one month to 45 years (M<sub>employment</sub> = 9.37 years, SD = 9.74). 35.1% were in possession of a university degree and another 25.2% graduated with the general qualification for university entrance. Participants were recruited by publishing the link to the survey in several social media groups. The survey was conducted in German. All participants were volunteers, no compensation was supplied.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec025">
<title>Materials</title>
<sec id="sec026">
<title>Psychological capital</title>
<p>PsyCap was measured with the CPC-12 (Study 1), using a 6-point response format ranging from 1 = “<italic>strongly disagree</italic>” to 6 = “<italic>strongly agree”</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec027">
<title>Positive and negative affect</title>
<p>PA and NA were evaluated using the Positive and Negative Affect Schedule [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref073">73</xref>]. Participants responded with 20 items to the question asking how they felt “during the past two weeks” (1 = <italic>“very slightly or not at all”</italic> to 5 = <italic>“very much”)</italic>. Ten items measured positive affect (e.g. excited, attentive) and ten items measured negative affect (e.g. guilty, afraid). The items were arranged randomly.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec028">
<title>Job satisfaction</title>
<p>Job satisfaction was measured using three items [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref035">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref074">74</xref>]. The first item measured general job satisfaction (“All things considered are you satisfied with your job?”), which participants were able to answer with “yes” or “no”. The second item (“How satisfied are you with your job in general?”) was rated using a 5-point scale from 1 = <italic>“very dissatisfied”</italic> to 5 = <italic>“very satisfied”</italic>. The third item asked participants to rate the percentage of time they feel satisfied, unsatisfied or neutral with their job in general (e.g. “The percent of time I feel satisfied with my present job.”). The analysis was conducted using the mean-score of the z-standardized items.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec029">
<title>Satisfaction with life</title>
<p>Life satisfaction was measured using the Satisfaction with Life Scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref075">75</xref>], using a 5-point response format ranging from 1 = <italic>“strongly agree”</italic> to 5 = <italic>“strongly disagree”</italic>. Participants rated five given statements (e.g. “I am satisfied with my life.”).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec030">
<title>Subjective well-being</title>
<p>The standardized z-scores of the four previously described scales were averaged to create subjective well-being. PA, NA and satisfaction with life were included because Arthaud-Day, Rode [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref076">76</xref>] found the three-factor model of subjective well-being consisting of PA, NA and life satisfaction to be superior to any other two- or one-factor model and the best fit to their data. Job satisfaction was then included to add a domain-specific focal point on work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref035">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref036">36</xref>] for the comparability to previous studies on well-being and PsyCap.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec031">
<title>Perceived social support</title>
<p>A short version of the Perceived Support Questionnaire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref077">77</xref>] was used to measure perceived social support. Using a 5-point response format ranging from 1 = <italic>“strongly disagree”</italic> to 5 = <italic>“strongly agree”</italic> participants had the possibility to rate to what extent the six given statements (e.g. “There is someone very close to me whose help I can always count on.”) fit their own lives.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec032">
<title>Meaning of work</title>
<p>The Work and Meaning Inventory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref078">78</xref>] was used to measure meaning of work. Using a 5-point response format ranging from 1 = <italic>“absolutely untrue”</italic> to 5 = <italic>“absolutely true”</italic> participants rated to what extent the ten given statements (e.g. “My work helps me make sense of the world around me.”) applied to them.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec033">
<title>Engagement</title>
<p>To measure engagement the Utrecht Work Engagement Scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref079">79</xref>] was used. Given a 7-point Likert scale ranging from 1 = <italic>“never”</italic> to 7 = <italic>“always”</italic> participants were asked to rate nine presented statements (e.g. “I am immersed in my job.”).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec034">
<title>Gratitude</title>
<p>Gratitude was evaluated using the Gratitude-Questionnaire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref054">54</xref>]. Given a 7-point Likert scale ranging from 1 = <italic>“strongly disagree”</italic> to 7 = <italic>“strongly agree”</italic> participants were asked to rate to what extent the six presented statements (e.g. “I have so much in life to be thankful for.”) applied to them.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec035">
<title>Proactive attitude</title>
<p>The Proactive Attitude Scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref058">58</xref>] was used to measure proactive attitude. Using a 4-point response format ranging from 1 = <italic>“not at all true”</italic> to 4 = <italic>“exactly true”</italic> participants rated to what extent the eight given statements (e.g. “I can choose my own actions.”) applied to them.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec036">
<title>“Big Five”</title>
<p>The five personality traits extraversion, neuroticism, conscientiousness, agreeableness and openness were assessed using the Big Five Inventory (BFI-S) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref080">80</xref>]. Participants rated 15 statements (e.g. “I see myself as someone who is outgoing, sociable.”) on a 7-point Likert scale from 1 = <italic>“does not apply to me at all”</italic> to 7 <italic>= “applies to me perfectly”</italic>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec037">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>The fit of all tested structural equation models was examined using the same criteria as presented in study 1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref069">69</xref>]. According to these indices the model for subjective well-being, which consisted of four independent constructs, showed an acceptable fit when tested for the unidimensional character of the compound variable using CFA (Satorra-Bentler-χ ² (2, 202) = 4.172, <italic>p</italic> &lt;.125, CFI = .957, SRMR = .035, RMSEA = .073, CI<sub>RMSEA</sub> = .00−.15).</p>
<p>The data analysis was run using the statistical software R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref072">72</xref>]. The confirmatory factor analyses were conducted using the “lavaan” package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref071">71</xref>], other used packages were “Hmisc” and “pastecs” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref081">81</xref>].</p>
<p>We used multiple imputation methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref082">82</xref>] to impute the three missing item responses prior to the statistical analysis. This maximizes power [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref083">83</xref>] and produces accurate parameter estimates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref084">84</xref>].</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec038">
<title>Study 2—Results</title>
<p>Results of the CFA for the CPC-12 indicated the following estimates of model fit: Satorra-Bentler-χ ² (50, 202) = 72.32, <italic>p</italic> &lt;.021, CFI = .955, SRMR = .052, RMSEA = .047, CI<sub>RMSEA</sub> = .022−.068. All the indices can be deemed to be a good model fit according to Hu and Bentler [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref069">69</xref>].</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0152892.t003">Table 3</xref> presents descriptive statistics, Cronbach’s α and bivariate correlations for the variables of study 2. All correlations are according to our hypotheses. Subjective well-being (<italic>r</italic> = .58), proactive attitude (<italic>r</italic> = .57) and positive affect (<italic>r</italic> = .54) showed the highest positive correlations, agreeableness showed no substantive correlation with the CPC-12, neuroticism and negative affect showed negative correlations.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0152892.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0152892.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Descriptive statistics and inter-correlations for study 2.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0152892.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0152892.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center"/>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center">PsyCap</th>
<th align="center">SWB<sup>a</sup></th>
<th align="center">PA</th>
<th align="center">NA<sup>b</sup></th>
<th align="center">JS<sup>a</sup></th>
<th align="center">LS</th>
<th align="center">PSS</th>
<th align="center">MoW</th>
<th align="center">Eng</th>
<th align="center">Grat</th>
<th align="center">ProA</th>
<th align="center">Con</th>
<th align="center">Extr</th>
<th align="center">Neur</th>
<th align="center">Open</th>
<th align="center">Agree</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center">PsyCap</td>
<td align="center">4.54</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.50</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>81</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">SWB<sup>a</sup></td>
<td align="center">0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn005"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.68<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn005"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.58<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="center"><italic>-</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">PA</td>
<td align="center">3.40</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.60</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.54<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.64<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>86</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">NA</td>
<td align="center">4.22</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.62</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.68<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>64</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">JS<sup>a</sup></td>
<td align="center">0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn005"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.81<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn005"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.70<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>72</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">LS</td>
<td align="center">3.74</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.63</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>74</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">PSS</td>
<td align="center">4.42</td>
<td align="char" char=".">1.3</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.41<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.14</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>87</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">MoW</td>
<td align="center">3.64</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.76</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>91</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Eng</td>
<td align="center">4.77</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.65</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.60<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.51<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.70<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>95</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Grat</td>
<td align="center">5.88</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.8</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>68</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">ProA</td>
<td align="center">3.07</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.39</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.57<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.54<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.41<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>48</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>67</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Con</td>
<td align="center">5.48</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.89</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>16</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>35</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>55</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Extr</td>
<td align="center">5.12</td>
<td align="char" char=".">1.11</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.05</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>25</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>34</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>18</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>70</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Neur</td>
<td align="center">3.96</td>
<td align="char" char=".">1.21</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="."><italic>-</italic>.<italic>16</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="."><italic>-</italic>.<italic>37</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="."><italic>-</italic>.<italic>12</italic></td>
<td align="char" char="."><italic>-</italic>.<italic>19</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>70</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Open</td>
<td align="center">5.19</td>
<td align="char" char=".">1.04</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.13</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.10</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.10</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.32<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>25</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>30</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>19</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>37</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>-08</italic></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>59</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Agree</td>
<td align="center">5.34</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.88</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.04</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.02</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.13</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.07</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>24</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>19</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>18</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>02</italic></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>06</italic></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>11</italic></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.<italic>37</italic></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p>Notes: Cronbach’s αs are displayed diagonal; CPC-12 = Compound Psychological Capital Scale, SWB<sup>a</sup> = aubjective well-being, PA = positive affect, NA = negative affect, JS<sup>a</sup> = job satisfaction, LS = satisfaction with life, PSS = perceived social support, MoW = meaning of work, Eng = engagement, Grat = gratitude, ProA = proactive attitude, Con = conscientiousness, Extr = extraversion, Neur = meuroticism, Open = openness, Agree = agreeableness; p-scores:</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p>* &lt;.05,</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn003"><p>** &lt;.01,</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn004"><p>*** &lt;.001.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn005"><p><sup>a</sup> standardized z-scores</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec039" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Since its emergence in 2004, the construct of PsyCap is assessed using the PCQ as the standard measure in more than 14 countries and languages, along with slight alterations of the scale to match the target group’s needs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref085">85</xref>]. The domain-specific measure itself is tied to the working world, although studies indicate associations with psychological constructs important for students, the unemployed, and retirees alike [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref020">20</xref>]. Therefore, the aim of this study was to develop and validate a German compound measure for PsyCap, with the general claim of being applicable to all domains of life.</p>
<p>According to our results, the CPC-12 fits the proposed model of PsyCap very well. The four subscales hope, optimism, resilience, and self-efficacy are identifiable as subcomponents of the overall measure while the higher-order factor can incrementally explain additional variance in the data. The moderate to high correlations to other work-related (MOW, job satisfaction and engagement; r = .28−.40) and more general constructs of positive psychology (i.e. subjective well-being, proactive attitude, and gratitude; r = .22.—.58) are comparable to previous research on PsyCap and speak for the external validity of the CPC-12. The results indicate that PsyCap could in fact be a general construct and applicable to more areas than POB. By abstaining from items with work related connotations, the CPC-12 can be applied to many fields of interest, i.e. sports and education. The CPC-12 is also an alternative in work-related research for areas where the item wordings of the PCQ might not be suitable, i.e. volunteering or small organizations, since its correlations with work-related constructs are similar to the PCQ. It is important to notice that while the CPC-12 is a short and economic way to measure PsyCap, we recommend using the original scales we used for the item pool if a specific sub-facet is the key area of interest.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec040">
<title>Future Directions</title>
<p>To achieve these desirable outcomes, future research should address the implementation of interventions that increase PsyCap. Although PsyCap is open to development and has already been proven to be alterable through interventions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref005">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref086">86</xref>], organizations to date still fail to increase their efforts to enhance this underemphasized positive core construct. We go one step further and propose to not only implement PsyCap interventions at the work place, but at schools, universities, or even in families. These interventions can be carried out on a group-level or as tailored training interventions based on individual scores. With the CPC-12 we provide a reliable tool to measure those individual PsyCap scores in many domains of life. In order to facilitate a reasonable interpretation of the scores, the quality criterion of standardization of the CPC-12 will have to be addressed to create up-to-date norms and to define the population to which they apply. The generalizability of the CPC-12 should be re-evaluated using different samples in other life-domains.</p>
<p>All in all, PsyCap seems to be multifarious and connected to a wide variety of other positive psychological constructs. High correlations with well-being, life satisfaction or job satisfaction make a case for PsyCap to become a focus of prospective research in positive psychology. We believe that people high in PsyCap are more likely to lead flourishing lives and probably even more likely to build a flourishing society.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec041">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>The following limitations should be kept in mind when interpreting the results. The high correlations between the CPC-12 and the scales used to create the CPC-12 in study 1 are in part due to common items in these scales and should not be interpreted without this context.</p>
<p>All participants were recruited online, which entails that findings may not generalize to people not using the internet or social networks. Although Gosling, Vazire, Srivastava and John [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0152892.ref087">87</xref>] agree that data from the internet is not free from methodological constraints, they do emphasize that samples using online recruitment are as diverse, adjusted, at least as good in quality as most traditional methods and “not as flawed as is commonly believed” (p. 102). The use of a nonprobability sample in this study raises further concerns about generalizability.</p>
<p>In addition, the scales for gratitude (α = .68) and proactive attitude (α = .67) lack reliability (smaller than .70). Results should therefore be considered with caution. The same caution should apply to the five personality traits as they also lack reliability. We found low merits for conscientiousness (α = .55), openness (α = .59) and agreeableness (α = .37), the latter being extremely low.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec042">
<title>Ethics Statement</title>
<p>This study is in accordance with the APA ethical principles regarding research with human participants. This study does not involve any conflict of ethics, since no clinical intervention was performed. Neither were blood or tissue samples taken for study purposes.</p>
<p>Participants were informed before participating that their responses would be treated confidentially and anonymously and that all data would be analyzed in a generalized manner so that no conclusions could be drawn about individual persons. The participants were informed that they would give their consent by proceeding past the welcome page of the online survey. This procedure is in accordance with the Freie Universität Berlin ethics committee’s guidelines. There was no contact between researchers and participants. Participation in this study was voluntary. This study was approved by the ethics committee of Freie Universität Berlin ID 102/2015.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec043">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0152892.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0152892.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Appendix</label>
<caption>
<title>Interview questionnaire on barriers to employment and their overcoming.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0152892.s002" mimetype="text/csv" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0152892.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Dataset</label>
<caption>
<title>Dataset study 1.</title>
<p>(CSV)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0152892.s003" mimetype="text/csv" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0152892.s003" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Dataset</label>
<caption>
<title>Dataset study 2.</title>
<p>(CSV)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seligman</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Csikszentmihalyi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Positive psychology: An introduction</article-title>. <source>Am Psychol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11392865</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Positive organizational behavior: Developing and managing psychological strengths</article-title>. <source>Acad Manage Exec</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Youssef</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Human, Social, and now Positive Psychological Capital Management: Investing in people for competitive advantage</article-title>. <source>Organ Dyn</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avolio</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walumbwa</surname> <given-names>FO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>The psychological capital of Chinese workers: Exploring the relationship with performance</article-title>. <source>Manage Organ Rev</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avolio</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avey</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The mediating role of psychological capital in the supportive organizational climate—employee performance relationship</article-title>. <source>J Organ Behav</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheier</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carver</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bridges</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Optimism, pessimism, and psychological well-being</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Optimism &amp; pessimism: Implications for theory, research, and practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC, US</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>; <year>2001</year>. p. <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masten</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Resilience in development</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>López</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Handbook of positive psychology</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>. p. <fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tugade</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fredrickson</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Resilient individuals use positive emotions to bounce back from negative emotional experiences</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>86</volume>: <fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>333</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14769087</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stajkovic</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Self-efficacy and work-related performance: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychol Bull</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>124</volume>: <fpage>240</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <source>Human Capital: A theoretical and empirical approach with special references to education</source>. <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>; <year>1993</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourdieu</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The forms of capital (1986)</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Szeman</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaposy</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Cultural theory: An anthology</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>. p. <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ucbasaran</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirst</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Psychological capital: A review and synthesis</article-title>. <source>J Organ Behav</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>120</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Avey</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reichard</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mhatre</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Meta‐analysis of the impact of positive psychological capital on employee attitudes, behaviors, and performance</article-title>. <source>Human resource development quarterly</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Potential added value of psychological capital in predicting work attitudes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Leadership &amp; Organizational Studies</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avey</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patera</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Experimental analysis of a web-based training intervention to develop positive psychological capital</article-title>. <source>Acad Manag Learn &amp; Edu</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Avey</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>KW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Using positivity, transformational leadership and empowerment to combat employee negativity</article-title>. <source>Leadership &amp; Organization Development Journal</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Avey</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patera</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The implications of positive psychological capital on employee absenteeism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Leadership &amp; Organizational Studies</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hobfoll</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Social and psychological resources and adaptation</article-title>. <source>Rev Gen Psychol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>324</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avolio</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avey</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Positive psychological capital: Measurement and relationship with performance and satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Pers Psychol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>60</volume>: <fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baron</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franklin</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hmieleski</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Why entrepreneurs often experience low, not high, levels of stress: The joint effects of selection and Psychological Capital</article-title>. <source>J Manage</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>742</fpage>–<lpage>768</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0149206313495411" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/0149206313495411</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Judge</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Another look at the job satisfaction-life satisfaction relationship</article-title>. <source>J appl psychol</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>78</volume>: <fpage>939</fpage>–<lpage>948</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawkins</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanderson</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Building on the positives: A psychometric review and critical analysis of the construct of psychological capital</article-title>. <source>J Occup Organ Psych</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>86</volume>: <fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sympson</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ybasco</surname> <given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borders</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babyak</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Development and validation of the State Hope Scale</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>70</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8636885</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheier</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carver</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Optimism, coping, and health: Assessment and implications of generalized outcome expectancies</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">4029106</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagnild</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Development and psychometric evaluation of the resilience scale</article-title>. <source>J Nurs Meas</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7850498</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Enhancing role breadth self-efficacy: The roles of job enrichment and other organizational interventions</article-title>. <source>J Appl Psychol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>835</fpage>–<lpage>852</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9885197</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyubomirsky</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diener</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>The benefits of frequent positive affect: does happiness lead to success?</article-title> <source>Psychol bull</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>131</volume>: <fpage>803</fpage>–<lpage>855</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16351326</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tugade</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fredrickson</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman Barrett</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Psychological resilience and positive emotional granularity: Examining the benefits of positive emotions on coping and health</article-title>. <source>J Pers</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>1161</fpage>–<lpage>1190</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15509280</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Jundt D, Hinsz VB, editors. Are happier workers more productive workers? The impact of mood on self-set goals, self-efficacy, and task performance. Paper presented at the annual meeting of the Midwestern Psychological Association, Chicago; 2001.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyubomirsky</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tkach</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiMatteo</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>. <article-title>What are the differences between happiness and self-esteem</article-title>. <source>Soc Indic Res</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>78</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gooty</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Positive psychological capital: Has positivity clouded measurement rigor</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Positive organizational behavior: Accentuating the positives at work</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE Publicatios Ltd</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>. p.<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinen</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langkamer</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Work and family satisfaction and conflict: a meta-analysis of cross-domain relations</article-title>. <source>J App Psychol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rojas M. The complexity of well-being: A life-satisfaction conception and a domains-of-life approach. Researching well-being in developing countries: From theory to research. Paper presented at the international workshop on researching well-being in developing countries, Delmenhorst; 2004.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diener</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suh</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Discriminant validity of well-being measures</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>71</volume>: <fpage>616</fpage>–<lpage>628</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8831165</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Judge</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klinger</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Job satisfaction</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Eid</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, editors. <source>The Science of Subjective Well-Being</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Guilford Press</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>. p. <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavot</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The assessment of subjective well-being</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Eid</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, editors. <source>The Science of Subjective Well-Being</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Guilford Press</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>. p. <fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Culbertson</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fullagar</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Feeling good and doing great: The relationship between psychological capital and well-being</article-title>. <source>J occup health psych</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Avey</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impact of positive psychological capital on employee well-being over time</article-title>. <source>J occup health psych</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Avey</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Psychological capital: A positive resource for combating employee stress and turnover</article-title>. <source>Hum Resour Manage</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>48</volume>: <fpage>677</fpage>–<lpage>693</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diener</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seligman</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>. <article-title>Very happy people</article-title>. <source>Psychol Sci</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11894851</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karademas</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Self-efficacy, social support and well-being: The mediating role of optimism</article-title>. <source>Pers Indiv Differ</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1281</fpage>–<lpage>1290</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Symister</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friend</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>The influence of social support and problematic support on optimism and depression in chronic illness: A prospective study evaluating self-esteem as a mediator</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12683732</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozbay</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fitterling</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charney</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Southwick</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Social support and resilience to stress across the life span: A neurobiologic framework</article-title>. <source>Curr Psychiatry Rep</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>304</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18627668</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seligman</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parks</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steen</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>A balanced psychology and a full life</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans-R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>. <year>2004</year>: <fpage>1379</fpage>–<lpage>1382</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15347529</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cartwright</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>The meaning of work: The challenge of regaining employee engagement and reducing cynicism</article-title>. <source>Hum Resour Manage R</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coutu</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>. <article-title>How resilience works</article-title>. <source>Harvard Bus Rev</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>80</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumeister</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name>. <source>Meanings of life</source>. <edition>1st ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>; <year>1991</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakker</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaufeli</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leiter</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taris</surname> <given-names>TW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Work engagement: An emerging concept in occupational health psychology</article-title>. <source>Work Stress</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakker</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gierveld</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Rijswijk</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <source>Succesfactoren bij vrouwelijke schoolleiders in het primair onderwijs: Een onderzoek naar burnout, bevlogenheid en prestaties [Success factors among female school principals in primary teaching: A study on burnout, work engagement, and performance]</source>. <publisher-loc>Diemen, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Right Management Consultants</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xanthopoulou</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bakker</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Demerouti</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaufeli</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reciprocal relationships between job resources, personal resources, and work engagement</article-title>. <source>J Vocat behav</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xanthopoulou</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bakker</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Demerouti</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaufeli</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of personal resources in the job demands-resources model</article-title>. <source>Int J Stress Manage</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Youssef</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avolio</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>. <source>Psychological capital: Developing the human competitive edge</source>. <edition>1st ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emmons</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCullough</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>. <article-title>Counting blessings versus burdens: An experimental investigation of gratitude and subjective well-being in daily life</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12585811</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCullough</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Emmons</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsang</surname> <given-names>J-A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The grateful disposition: a conceptual and empirical topography</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc psychol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>82</volume>: <fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11811629</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rash</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuba</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prkachin</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gratitude and well‐being: Who benefits the most from a gratitude intervention?</article-title> <source>Appl Psychol: Health Well‐Being</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De La Rosa</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name>. <article-title>The interactive effects of proactive personality and work-family interference on well-being</article-title>. <source>J Occup Health Psych</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crant</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Proactive Personality Scale and objective job performance among real estate agents</article-title>. <source>J Appl Psychol</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>80</volume>: <fpage>532</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname> <given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarzer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Proaktive Einstellung von Lehrern: Konstruktbeschreibung und psychometrische Analysen</article-title>. <source>Zeitschrift für Empirische Pädagogik</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell-Sills</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohan</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Relationship of resilience to personality, coping, and psychiatric symptoms in young adults</article-title>. <source>Behav res ther</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15998508</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCrae</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name>. <source>Revised NEO Personality Inventory and NEO Five-Factor Inventory: Professional manual</source>. <edition>1st ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Odessa, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Assessment Resources. Inc</publisher-name>; <year>1992</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillemin</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bombardier</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beaton</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cross-cultural adaptation of health-related quality of life measures: Literature review and proposed guidelines</article-title>. <source>J Clinical Epidemiol</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1417</fpage>–<lpage>1432</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandtstädter</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wentura</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Veränderungen der Zeit-und Zukunftsperspektive im Übergang zum höheren Erwachsenenalter: entwicklungspsychologische und differentielle Aspekte</article-title>. <source>Z Entwickl und Padagogis</source>; <year>1994</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glaesmer</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyer</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klotsche</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herzberg</surname> <given-names>PY</given-names></name>. <article-title>Die deutsche version des Life-Orientation-Tests (LOT-R) zum dispositionellen Optimismus und Pessimismus</article-title>. <source>Z Gesundh</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herzberg</surname> <given-names>PY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glaesmer</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyer</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Separating optimism and pessimism: A robust psychometric analysis of the revised Life Orientation Test (LOT-R)</article-title>. <source>Psychol Assessment</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>438</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leppert</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brähler</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strauß</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Die Resilienzskala (RS)–Überprüfung der Langform RS-25 und einer Kurzform RS-13</article-title>. <source>Klinische Diagnostik und Evaluation</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>226</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jerusalem</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarzer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Allgemeine Selbstwirksamkeit</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarzer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jerusalem</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Skalen zur Erfassung von Lehrer-und Schülermerkmalen</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Freie Universität Berlin</publisher-name>; <year>1999</year>. p. <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schyns</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Collani</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>A new occupational self-efficacy scale and its relation to personality constructs and organizational variables</article-title>. <source>Eur J Work Organ Psy</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moosbrugger</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelava</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <source>Testtheorie und Fragebogenkonstruktion</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>Lt</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bentler</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: Conventional criteria versus new alternatives</article-title>. <source>Struct Equ Modeling</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiStefano</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Non-normal and categorical data in structural equation modeling</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Hancock</surname> <given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname> <given-names>RO</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Structural equation modeling: A second course</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Charlotte, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Information Age Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>. p. <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosseel</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>lavaan: An R package for structural equation modeling</article-title>. <source>J Stat Softw</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>R Core Team</collab>. <source>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</source>. <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>; <year>2014</year>. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tellegen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Development and validation of brief measures of positive and negative affect: the PANAS scales</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>1063</fpage>–<lpage>1070</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3397865</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Judge</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boudreau</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bretz</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Job and life attitudes of male executives</article-title>. <source>J Appl Psychol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>79</volume>: <fpage>767</fpage>–<lpage>782</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7989277</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schumacher</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>SWLS–Satisfaction with life scale</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Schumacher</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klaiberg</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Braehler</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Diagnostische Verfahren zu Lebensqualität und Wohlbefinden</source>. <publisher-loc>Göttingen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hogrefe</publisher-name>; <year>2003</year>. p. <fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arthaud-Day</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rode</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mooney</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Near</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>The subjective well-being construct: A test of its convergent, discriminant, and factorial validity</article-title>. <source>Soc Indic Res</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kliem</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mößle</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rehbein</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellmann</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zenger</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brähler</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>A brief form of the Perceived Social Support Questionnaire (F-SozU) was developed, validated and standardized</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>562</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jclinepi.2014.11.003" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2014.11.003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25499982</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steger</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dik</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Measuring meaningful work: The work and meaning inventory (WAMI)</article-title>. <source>J Career Assessment</source>. <year>2012</year> <month>Feb</month> <day>19</day>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/1069072711436160" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/1069072711436160</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balducci</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fraccaroli</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaufeli</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Psychometric properties of the Italian version of the Utrecht Work Engagement Scale (UWES-9)</article-title>. <source>Eur J Psychol Assess</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gerlitz J-Y, Schupp J. Zur Erhebung der Big-Five-basierten persoenlichkeitsmerkmale im SOEP. DIW Research Notes 4; 2005.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Grosjean P, Ibanez F. Pastecs: Package for analysis of space-time ecological series. R package version 1.3–18; 2014.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Enders</surname> <given-names>CK</given-names></name>. <source>Applied missing data analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Publications</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gottschall</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enders</surname> <given-names>CK</given-names></name>. <article-title>A comparison of item-level and scale-level multiple imputation for questionnaire batteries</article-title>. <source>Multivar Behav Res</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Enders</surname> <given-names>CK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dealing with missing data in developmental research</article-title>. <source>Child Dev Perspect</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Youssef-Morgan</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avolio</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>. <source>Psychological Capital and beyond</source>. <edition>1st ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref086"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avey</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avolio</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Combs</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Psychological capital development: Toward a micro‐intervention</article-title>. <source>J Organ Behav</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0152892.ref087"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gosling</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vazire</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname> <given-names>OP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Should we trust web-based studies? A comparative analysis of six preconceptions about internet questionnaires</article-title>. <source>Am Psychol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14992636</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>