<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-15934</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104978</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Human genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Ecology and environmental sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Environmental impacts</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cardiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cardiovascular diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Cardiovascular disease risk</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cardiovascular disease epidemiology</subject><subject>Clinical epidemiology</subject><subject>Environmental epidemiology</subject><subject>Genetic epidemiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Modifying Effect of a Common Polymorphism in the Interleukin-6 Promoter on the Relationship between Long-Term Exposure to Traffic-Related Particulate Matter and Heart Rate Variability</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Does the IL6-174G/C SNP Alter the Heart Response to Air Pollution?</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imboden</surname><given-names>Medea</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boes</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>Emmanuel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Künzli</surname><given-names>Nino</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phuleria</surname><given-names>Harish Chandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kronenberg</surname><given-names>Florian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaspoz</surname><given-names>Jean-Michel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carballo</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Probst-Hensch</surname><given-names>Nicole</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Swiss Tropical and Public Health Institute, Basel, Switzerland</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Division of Genetic Epidemiology, Department of Medical Genetics, Molecular and Clinical Pharmacology, Innsbruck Medical University, Innsbruck, Austria</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Community Medicine, Primary Care and Emergency medicine, University Hospitals, Geneva, Switzerland</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Cardiology, Department of Internal Medicine Specialties, University Hospitals, Geneva, Switzerland</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coulombe</surname><given-names>Roger A.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Utah State University, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">martin.adam@unibas.ch</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: NPH. Performed the experiments: NPH MA MI EB FK MI DC JMG HCP NK ES. Analyzed the data: MA MI EB NPH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: NPH. Wrote the paper: NPH MA MI EB FK MI DC JMG HCP NK ES. Directly participated in the planning, execution, or analysis of the study and read, revised and approved the manuscript: NPH MA MI EB FK MI DC JMG HCP NK ES.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e104978</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Adam et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract><sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>Exposure to particulate matter (PM) has been associated with an increase in many inflammatory markers, including interleukin 6 (<italic>IL6</italic>). Air pollution exposure has also been suggested to induce an imbalance in the autonomic nervous system (ANS), such as a decrease in heart rate variability (HRV). In this study we aimed to investigate the modifying effect of polymorphisms in a major proinflammatory marker gene, interleukin 6 (<italic>IL6</italic>), on the relationship between long-term exposure to traffic-related PM<sub>10</sub> (TPM<sub>10</sub>) and HRV.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>For this cross-sectional study we analysed 1552 participants of the SAPALDIA cohort aged 50 years and older. Included were persons with valid genotype data, who underwent ambulatory 24-hr electrocardiogram monitoring, and reported on medical history and lifestyle. Main effects of annual average TPM<sub>10</sub> and <italic>IL6</italic> gene variants (rs1800795; rs2069827; rs2069840; rs10242595) on HRV indices and their interaction with average annual exposure to TPM<sub>10</sub> were tested, applying a multivariable mixed linear model.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>No overall association of TPM<sub>10</sub> on HRV was found. Carriers of two proinflammatory G-alleles of the functional <italic>IL6</italic> -174 G/C (rs1800795) polymorphism exhibited lower HRV. An inverse association between a 1 µg/m<sup>3</sup> increment in yearly averaged TPM<sub>10</sub> and HRV was restricted to GG genotypes at this locus with a standard deviation of normal-to-normal intervals (SDNN) (GG-carriers: −1.8%; 95% confidence interval −3.5 to 0.01; p<sub>interaction(additive)</sub> = 0.028); and low frequency power (LF) (GG-carriers: −5.7%; 95%CI: −10.4 to −0.8; p<sub>interaction(dominant)</sub> = 0.049).</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Our results are consistent with the hypothesis that traffic-related air pollution decreases heart rate variability through inflammatory mechanisms.</p>
</sec></abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation (grant numbers 33CSCO-108796, 3247BO-104283, 3247BO-104288, 3247BO-104284, 3247-065896, 3100-059302, 3200-052720, 3200-042532, 4026-028099), the Federal Office for Forest, Environment and Landscape, the Federal Office of Public Health, the Federal Office of Roads and Transport, the canton's government of Aargau, Basel-Stadt, Basel-Land, Geneva, Luzern, Ticino, Valais and Zurich, the Swiss Lung League and the canton's Lung League of Basel Stadt/ Basel Landschaft, Geneva, Ticino, Valais and Zurich. No form of payment was given to any of the authors to produce the manuscript. The study received funding through peer-reviewed grants and donations from non-profit organizations as listed above. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Exposure to air pollution as well as decreased heart rate variability (HRV) as measured by specific indices (SDNN, TP, LF, HF) have been associated with increased cardiovascular morbidity and mortality in longitudinal studies, both in patients with myocardial infarction and in healthy persons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Bigger1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Kleiger1">[3]</xref>. Heart rate variability (HRV) refers to the beat-to-beat variation in heart rate and is a non-invasive measure of the autonomic regulation of cardiac rhythm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Dekker1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Nolan1">[5]</xref>. A reduction in different HRV indices can reflect both an increase in sympathetic or a decrease in parasympathetic tone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Brook1">[2]</xref>. Several studies have introduced HRV as an intermediate factor between acute exposure to air pollution and cardiovascular morbidity, showing that PM exposure is associated with increased heart rate and reductions in most indices of HRV <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Link1">[6]</xref>, . A recent meta-analysis including 29 studies supported an inverse relationship between HRV and short-term particulate air pollution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Pieters1">[8]</xref>. Most studies, including a recent double-blind randomized cross-over study, often focused on acute exposure effects and persons with pre-existing cardiovascular diseases, diabetes mellitus or the elderly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Brook1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Mills1">[9]</xref>. Studies on the chronic impact of air pollution on HRV are scarce <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Adam1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-FelberDietrich1">[11]</xref>. The American Heart Association (AHA) recently stated that studies on long-term effects of air pollution on HRV and cardiovascular health are a major unresolved issue. In a previous study analysing the same study population for the association between long-term TPM<sub>10</sub> and HRV, we found an impact of air pollution on participants treated for hypertension and heart disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Brook1">[2]</xref>.</p>
<p>Air pollution exposure is associated in the short-term with elevated levels of inflammatory markers such as high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (hs-CRP), interleukin 6 (IL-6), fibrinogen and platelet activation, especially in elderly and diabetic subjects, but also in healthy populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Delfino1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Ruckerl1">[15]</xref>. Long-term circulating interleukin 6 levels in prospectively collected blood are predictive of subsequent risk of coronary heart disease, making <italic>IL6</italic> a strong candidate gene for modifying air pollution effects on coronary heart disease related phenotypes including mortality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Danesh1">[16]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Lee1">[18]</xref>.</p>
<p>To date, no study has investigated the main association of <italic>IL6</italic> polymorphisms on HRV and their modifying effect on the air pollution-HRV association in the general population. Investigating the modifying effect of genetic variants in interleukin 6 (<italic>IL6</italic>) encoding, a key marker of inflammatory response, on the association between traffic-related air pollution and heart rate variability, can improve the understanding of the mediating role of inflammatory processes. Using data from the “Swiss cohort study on air pollution and lung and heart disease in Adults” (SAPALDIA) we found novel evidence that genetic variation in the pleiotropic <italic>IL6</italic> gene alters heart rate variability and its association with long-term exposure to traffic-related particulate air pollution (TPM<sub>10</sub>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Ethics statement</title>
<p>The study complies with the declaration of Helsinki and ethical approval for the SAPALDIA study was given by the Swiss Academy of Medical Sciences, the national ethics committee for clinical research (UREK, Project Approval Number 123/00) and the Cantonal Ethics Committees for each of the eight examination areas (Ethics commissions of the cantons Aargau, Basel, Geneva, Grisons, Ticino, Valais, Vaud and Zurich). Participants were required to give written consent before any part of the health examination was conducted either globally (for all health examinations) or separately for each investigation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Study population</title>
<p>This study is part of the SAPALDIA cohort which was designed to investigate the long-term health effects of air pollution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-AckermannLiebrich1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Martin1">[20]</xref>. In 1991 a random population sample of white adults aged 18–60 years was recruited from eight areas in Switzerland featuring distinct geographic and environmental conditions. While the baseline examination of 9651 persons focused on respiratory health, at follow-up in 2002 (SAPALDIA2) a random sample of in total 1846 persons aged ≥50 years was invited to undergo a 24-hr electrocardiogram (ECG) recording to assess HRV. Exclusion criteria were general or spinal anaesthesia within 8 days (<italic>n</italic> = 5), myocardial infarction within 3 months before the examination (<italic>n</italic> = 2), taking digitalis (<italic>n</italic> = 6), an artificial internal pacemaker (n = 0), and ECG recordings showing atrial fibrillation (<italic>n</italic> = 12), less than 18 hours of recording (<italic>n</italic> = 73) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Electrophysiology1">[21]</xref> or of insufficient quality (<italic>n</italic> = 6) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-FelberDietrich2">[22]</xref>. From the 1742 participants with 24-hr ECG recordings, we finally included 1552 participants with valid data on cardiovascular risk factors, and TPM<sub>10</sub> long-term exposure.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>HRV measurements and definition</title>
<p>Measurement of HRV and assessment of cardiovascular risk factors in SAPALDIA have been previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-FelberDietrich2">[22]</xref> (Methods S1 in File S1). In brief, participants were asked to follow their regular daily routine during the recording period. Digital devices with a frequency response of 0.05–40 Hz and a resolution of 128 samples/s, recording on three leads (V<sub>1</sub>, altered V<sub>3</sub> with the electrode on the left mid clavicular line on the lowest rib, and altered V<sub>5</sub> with the electrode on the left anterior axillary line on the lowest rib) were used. The mean duration of the 24-hr ECG recordings was 22.1 (SD 2.3) hours. The standard deviation of all normal RR (NN) intervals (SDNN) and the following frequency domain variables were calculated: total power (TP) (≤0.40 Hz), ultra-low frequency (ULF) power (≤0.0033 Hz), very low frequency (VLF) power (0.0033–0.04 Hz), low frequency (LF) power (0.04–0.15 Hz), high frequency (HF) power (0.15–0.40 Hz), and the ratio between LF and HF (LF/HF).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Air pollutant exposure estimation</title>
<p>To assess the effect of long-term exposure to traffic-related pollution on HRV, exposure was defined as the average concentration of traffic-related PM<sub>10</sub> (TPM<sub>10</sub>) over 10 years. Given that total PM<sub>10</sub> is not specific to near-road traffic-related pollutants, we focused instead on TPM<sub>10</sub> to capture the high spatial variability of those source specific pollutants (Methods S1 in File S1). The dispersion modeling approach is described elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Liu1">[23]</xref>. In brief, these Gaussian plume models used the traffic-specific PM<sub>10</sub> on-road emissions from light- and heavy- duty vehicles, buses, and motorcycles, taking into account diurnal variability, weekday-weekend differences as well as seasonal patterns. Co-variables used in the dispersion models were wind speed and direction, temperature, mixing height, and atmospheric stability classes. By linking participants residential addresses to annual mean TPM<sub>10</sub> exposure concentrations derived for 200×200 meter grid cells from dispersion models and historical trend data of central site measurements, exposure was individually assigned to all residences of the participants reported for the period between 1990 and 2000 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Kunzli1">[24]</xref>. The PM<sub>10</sub> exposure modeling and details of the individual exposure assignment have been described before <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Liu1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Kunzli1">[24]</xref>. Since information on short-term TPM<sub>10</sub> was not available, short-term PM<sub>10</sub> exposure was used to assess short-term effects on HRV in a sensitivity analysis approach. Short-term PM<sub>10</sub> was assessed using averaged fixed monitoring station pollution measurements of the same day or up to one week preceding the Holter recording. Data was included from measurement stations nearest to the subjects' home addresses. Subjects living farther than 5 km from a station or having moved within the previous year were excluded for this sensitivity analysis.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Selection of IL6 genetic variants and genotyping</title>
<p>The single functional nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) in the <italic>IL6</italic> gene locus (rs1800795; <italic>IL6</italic> –174 G/C) was selected as the main candidate to capture the common genetic variation in this chromosomal region. This SNP has shown to be associated with circulating IL-6 blood concentrations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Brull1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Kelberman1">[26]</xref>. The G allele was identified as the proinflammatory allele in previous epidemiological and experimental studies. In an explorative supplementary analysis benefitting from available GWAS data, three additional <italic>IL6</italic>-SNPs (rs2069827, rs2069840, rs10242595) were included as their genotyping call rates were ≥97.5% and they were haplotype tagging SNPs or associated with cardiovascular phenotypes or in high linkage disequilibrium (LD) with such SNPs (Tables S1–S2 in File S1).</p>
<p>Genomic DNA was isolated from EDTA-buffered whole blood using PUREGENETM DNA Purification Kit (GENTRA Systems, Minneapolis, USA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-AckermannLiebrich1">[19]</xref>. Genotypes of three SNPs (rs2069827, rs2069840, rs10242595) were assessed using the Sequenom's MassARRAY system (Sequenom, San Diego, USA) by performing iPLEX single base primer extension and matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry as described elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Kormann1">[27]</xref>. Genotypes of one SNP (rs1800795) were assessed using 5'-nuclease fluorescent realtime PCR (TaqMan) genotyping assay (Applera Europe, Rotkreuz, Switzerland). End-point detection was done using a 7000 ABI System detection device (ABI, Rotkreuz, Switzerland) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Imboden1">[28]</xref>. For genotyping quality-control, a random selection of &gt;5% of the samples were genotyped twice.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) was assessed, irrespective of HRV measurement, for the total genotyped SAPALDIA population of 6055 subjects by using the STATA (Table S1 in File S1) genhwi command for global κ-statistic testing. Haploview 4.2 was used for analysis of Lewtonin's linkage disequilibrium (LD) calculating the metrics D-prime and R-squared (Table S2 in File S1).</p>
<p>The SAPALDIA subpopulation for this study is consistent with our previous analyses on the association between TPM<sub>10</sub> and the log-transformed outcome variable (HRV) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Adam1">[10]</xref>. An effect estimate represents percent change in geometric mean. Covariates included in the analysis were chosen in accordance with previous analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Adam1">[10]</xref> and supplemented by alcohol consumption, passive smoking, diabetes and noise exposure. Covariates included in the regression model were: sex (male as reference), age (years), age<sup>2</sup>, body mass index (bmi, kg/m<sup>2</sup>), bmi<sup>2</sup>, smoking status (never as reference, ever), daily exposure to environmental tobacco smoke (ETS, none as reference, &lt;3 hours, &gt;3 hours), daily alcohol consumption (&lt;1 drink as reference, ≥1 drink), weekly physical activity (to the point of getting out of breath or sweating) (none as reference, between ½ and 2 hours, &gt;2 hours), uric acid concentration (micromol/L), hypertension (no as reference, yes), heart disease (no as reference, yes), diabetes (no as reference, yes), street and railway noise exposure (mean dB(A) per night), seasonal effects (sine and cosine functions of the day of examination with a period of 1 year). High sensitive C-reactive protein (mg/l) was additionally included in the model to guard against potential confounding by unmeasured proinflammatory short-term effects, such as acute air pollution effects. A random intercept in a mixed regression model was included to adjust for potential residual clustering of data within the eight areas of Switzerland.</p>
<p>The underlying genetic model of the SNP effect was defined, using additive and dominance contrasts in the regression models and applying the Cochran-Armitage test to assess potential deviation from the additive model (Methods S1 in File S1). In such a model a significant dominance contrast measure represents deviation from the additive allele effect. To further differentiate in between a dominant and a recessive effect, we considered the direction of the association of the dominance parameter. In the paper we only show p-values of the most likely inheritance mode (additive, dominant or recessive) of the tested main effects of the <italic>IL6</italic> polymorphisms, as well as the interactions of the <italic>IL6</italic> polymorphisms with TPM<sub>10</sub>.</p>
<p>Main effects of <italic>IL6</italic> gene variants were derived from the mixed model described above and adjusted for long-term TPM<sub>10</sub>. <italic>IL6</italic> variants and interaction terms between TPM<sub>10</sub> and the <italic>IL6</italic> variants were entered into the regression model separately for each genotype. Genotype-specific effect estimates for TPM<sub>10</sub> were obtained by including the stratum-specific product terms of the genotype with TPM<sub>10</sub> exposure in covariate-adjusted mixed linear models.</p>
<p>In sensitivity analysis, to control the possible acute effects of ambient air pollution on HRV, we also adjusted the core mixed model for the community average ambient PM<sub>10</sub>-level of the 3 days prior to the Holter recording. Furthermore, we replaced TPM<sub>10</sub> exposure with the annual NO<sub>2</sub> exposure averaged over the previous 10 years. In a previous publication we had not found a main effect of NO<sub>2</sub> on HRV <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-FelberDietrich1">[11]</xref>.</p>
<p>As this is an exploratory study investigating potential inflammatory mechanisms through a genetic key marker of inflammatory response and a functional SNP in this gene, selected a priori, we did not adjust for multiple testing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Bender1">[29]</xref>.</p>
<p>All tests were two-sided with a significance level of 0.05. Statistical analyses were performed using STATA, version 12 (StataCorp. 2011. Stata Statistical Software: Release 12. College Station, TX: StataCorp LP) and SAS V 9.2 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, 2008).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>As described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104978-t001">Table 1</xref>, the mean age of the study population was 60.3 (SD 6.2) years with a mean BMI of 26.7 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. Among the subjects, 50.4% were females, 57% ever smokers, 21.5% were exposed to second hand smoke, 46.3% consumed alcohol regularly, 41.2% were physically inactive, 47.7% reported hypertension, 9.5% diabetes and 24.7% a heart disease.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0104978-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104978.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Characteristics of the study population (N = 1552).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104978-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104978.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">All (n = 1552)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gender</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">770</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">782</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±6.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Lifestyle factors</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> Smoking status</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never Smokers</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">668</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ever Smokers</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">884</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ETS exposure</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1218</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;3 h/ day</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥3 h/ day</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alcohol</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;1glass / day</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">834</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥1glass / day</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">718</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Physical acitivity</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">640</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.5–1.5 h/ week</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">508</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥2 h/ week</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">404</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cardiovascular health</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systolic blood pressure (mmHG)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±19.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diastolic blood pressure (mmHG)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±10.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±4.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Diabetes</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1404</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypertension</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">811</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">741</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Heart disease</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1168</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">384</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Noise Exposure</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Street noise (dB(A))</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±7.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Railway noise (dB(A))</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±10.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Air pollution</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average annual traffic related PM10 (µg/m3)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-days lag PM10 (µg/m3)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±14.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>IL6</italic></bold><bold> polymorphisms</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> candidate SNP: rs1800795 (−174G/C)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1549</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">584</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">704</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SNPs included in exploratory analyses: rs2069827</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1524</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1264</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">246</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> rs2069840</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1526</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">638</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">706</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> rs10242595</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1529</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">664</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">686</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>ETS indicates environmental tobacco smoke exposure; SBP, systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; BMI, body mass index;</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>a</label><p>Annual average over 10 years previous to the study.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>b</label><p>average over 3 days previous to the HRV measurement.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>The overall analysis including the whole study population (n = 1552) showed no general association of any HRV parameter with TPM<sub>10</sub> except for the LF/HF ratio which was 3.6% lowered (95% confidence interval (95%CI), −6.9 to −0.2) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Adam1">[10]</xref>. The functional <italic>IL6</italic>-174 G/C (rs1800795; n = 1549) polymorphism, which was previously associated with circulating IL-6 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Chan1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Ljungman1">[31]</xref>, was associated with some of the HRV metrics in either an additive or a dominant manner (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104978-t002">Table 2</xref>). Compared with −174 GG genotypes, participants having only one or no G-risk allele exhibited higher SDNN (GC: 3.8%; 0.8 to 6.8; CC: 4.0%; 95%CI, 0.1 to 8.0; p<sub>additive</sub> = 0.015) and TP (GC: 7.5%; 95%CI, 0.7 to 14.9; CC: 7.6%; 95%CI, −1.4 to 17.5; p<sub>additive</sub> = 0.041), while the LF/HF ratio decreased (GC: −8.8%; 95%CI, −14.7 to −2.5; CC: −1.3%; 95%CI, −9.6 to 8.0; p<sub>dominant</sub> = 0.021). No significant overall association was observed for HF and LF power. None of the other <italic>IL6</italic> SNPs included in the supplementary explorative analysis were statistically significantly associated with HRV (Tables S3–S7 in File S1).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0104978-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104978.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Unadjusted and adjusted<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref> geometric means of the HRV indices and percent differences in HRV indices by traffic-related PM<sub>10</sub> (TPM<sub>10</sub>) and by <italic>IL6</italic>-174G/C genotypes (N = 1549).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104978-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104978.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HRV parameters</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Exposures</italic></td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Crude Mean, 95%CI</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Adjusted Mean, 95%CI<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% change</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lower CI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">upper CI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">c</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDNN</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPM<sub>10</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>131.6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>131.6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.08</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.905</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>127.9</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>128.6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.015 (1)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>133.7</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>133.3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.76</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>134.5</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>133.6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.98</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Power (TP)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPM<sub>10</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3678.4</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3566.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3793.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3678.4</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3570.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3789.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.05</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.76</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.972</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3481.7</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3311.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3660.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3510.9</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3343.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3686.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.041 (1)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3791.2</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3621.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3968.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3778.6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3615.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3949.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.54</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3825.8</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3549.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4123.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3788.8</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3521.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4076.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.62</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.48</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low Frequency Power (LF)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPM<sub>10</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>220.2</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>220.2</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.07</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.279</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>212.9</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>214.9</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.296 (1)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>220.4</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>221.4</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.68</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.96</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.93</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.503</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>236.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>228.3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.64</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.297</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High Frequency Power (HF)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPM<sub>10</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>68.6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>68.6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.07</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.64</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.663</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>63.6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>64.3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.116 (1)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>72.4</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>72.3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12.70</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>70.2</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>68.6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.13</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.309</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LF/ HF Ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPM<sub>10</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.2</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.2</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−3.60</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.021 (2)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−8.80</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14.68</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.4</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−1.27</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.66</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.778</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>HRV indicates heart rate variability: SDNN indicates standard deviation of all NN intervals (units ms); TP, total power (ms<sup>2</sup>); HF, high frequency power (ms<sup>2</sup>); LF, low frequency power (ms<sup>2</sup>).</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>a</label><p>adjusted for gender, age, age squared, BMI, BMI squared, smoking status, environmental tobacco smoke exposure, alcohol consumption, physical activity, high-sensitivity C-reactive protein, uric acid levels, hypertension, heart disease, diabetes, street and railway noise, seasonal effects and area.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>b</label><p>p-values of genotype-specific main effects of the <italic>IL6</italic>-174G/C polymorphism and TPM<sub>10</sub> on HRV (codominant genetic model).</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label>c</label><p>p-values of main effects of the <italic>IL6</italic> -174G/C polymorphism on HRV indices were tested for additive, dominant and recessive genetic models; p-values of the most significant mode of inheritance are presented (<sup>1</sup>additive or <sup>2</sup>dominant).</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label>d</label><p>per 1 µg/m<sup>3</sup> TPM<sub>10</sub> increase.</p></fn><fn id="nt109"><label>e</label><p>compared to reference genotype G/G.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104978-t003">Table 3</xref> presents the results for the interaction between TPM<sub>10</sub> exposure and the <italic>IL6</italic>-174 G/C on change in HRV. The <italic>IL6</italic>-174 G/C polymorphism showed interactions with traffic-related PM<sub>10</sub> and the following HRV metrics: SDNN (p<sub>interaction(additive)</sub> = 0.028) and LF (p<sub>interaction(dominant)</sub> = 0.049) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104978-t002">Table 2</xref>). A 1 µg/m<sup>3</sup> increment in yearly averaged TPM<sub>10</sub> level was associated with a decrease in SDNN of 1.8% (95% confidence interval (95%CI), −3.5 to 0.01) and in LF power of 5.7% (95%CI, −10.4 to −0.8) in participants with the −174 GG genotype. No significant interaction with TPM<sub>10</sub> exposure and the other HRV metrics (TP, HF power and LF/HF ratio) was observed but for all parameters except HF, TPM<sub>10</sub> decreased heart rate variability strongest among GG genotype carriers. All other <italic>IL6</italic> SNPs included in the supplementary analysis showed a weaker or no effect modification of TPM<sub>10</sub> on HRV, respectively, and did not add additional information (Tables S8–S12 in File S1).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0104978-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104978.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Adjusted<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt111">a</xref> estimates of the mean percent difference of HRV associated with a 1 µg/m<sup>3</sup> increase in average exposure to traffic-related PM10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt112">b</xref> by <italic>IL6</italic>-174 G/C genotypes (N = 1549).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104978-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104978.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HRV parameters</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>IL6</italic>-174 G/C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt111">a</xref></td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">95% CI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<sub>TPM10</sub> (by genotype)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt113">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<sub>interaction</sub> (genetic model)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt114">d</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDNN</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−1.77</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.028 (1)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.06</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.47</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.177</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.73</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.62</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Power (TP)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−3.34</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.177 (1)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.54</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−1.00</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.717</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low Frequency Power (LF)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−5.70</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.36</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.049 (2)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.51</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.09</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−4.98</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High Frequency Power (HF)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.16</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.36</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.45</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.961</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.671 (1)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.70</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.84</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.346</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−3.83</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LF/ HF Ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−5.82</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.070 (2)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−1.51</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.441</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−1.54</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.592</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt110"><label/><p>HRV indicates heart rate variability: SDNN indicates standard deviation of all NN intervals (units ms); TP, total power (ms<sup>2</sup>); HF, high frequency power (ms<sup>2</sup>); LF, low frequency power (ms<sup>2</sup>).</p></fn><fn id="nt111"><label>a</label><p>adjusted for gender, age, age squared, BMI, BMI squared, smoking status, environmental tobacco smoke exposure, alcohol consumption, physical activity, high-sensitivity C-reactive protein, uric acid levels, hypertension, heart disease, diabetes, street and railway noise, seasonal effects and area.</p></fn><fn id="nt112"><label>b</label><p>Annual average over 10 years previous to the study.</p></fn><fn id="nt113"><label>c</label><p>p-values for the genotype- specific TPM<sub>10</sub> effect estimate.</p></fn><fn id="nt114"><label>d</label><p>p-values of interaction effects of the <italic>IL6</italic>-174 G/C polymorphism with TPM<sub>10</sub> on HRV were tested for additive, dominant and recessive genetic models; p-values of the most significant mode of inheritance are presented (additive<sup>1</sup> or dominant<sup>2</sup>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>In order to guard against confounding by short-term exposure of PM<sub>10</sub>, which was not considered in the main and interaction effect model, we included a mean daily PM<sub>10</sub> exposure measurement over the three days previous to the ECG assessment. Associations reported for long-term exposure to TPM<sub>10</sub> with <italic>IL6</italic> polymorphisms and their interactions differed only slightly when adjusting additionally for short-term PM<sub>10</sub> exposure (data not shown). When we replaced TPM<sub>10</sub> with NO<sub>2</sub> we observed interactions with <italic>IL6</italic>-174 G/C that were highly comparable to those observed for TPM<sub>10</sub> (data not shown).</p>
</sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>To our knowledge, this is the first report on both, the main effect of genetic variation in <italic>IL6</italic> on HRV and the interaction of <italic>IL6</italic> polymorphisms with air pollution on HRV. In this candidate-approach association study in the general population, we observed the previously described functional <italic>IL6</italic>-174G/C promoter polymorphism to be associated with HRV (SDNN; TP; LF; HF). The association of TPM<sub>10</sub> with decreased HRV parameters was restricted to carriers of the <italic>IL6</italic>-174 GG genotype. The results lend support to the notion that inflammatory mechanisms mediate part of the air pollution related effects on heart rate variability.</p>
<p>The pleiotropic cytokine IL-6 is central in acute and chronic inflammation by inducing hepatic synthesis of acute phase proteins and by modulating the inflammatory response. In other studies, circulating IL-6 as well as hs-CRP were inversely associated with parasympathetic nervous system tone measured as LF of HRV both, in healthy individuals and patients with CVD or diabetes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Haensel1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Lieb1">[33]</xref>. Separate lines of evidence provide support to the role of genetic variation in <italic>IL6</italic> in low grade systemic inflammation and, albeit less consistently, cardiovascular disease risk. First, several studies investigated the association of <italic>IL6</italic> gene variants with circulating IL-6 concentrations and with gene activity, most of them focusing on the SNP <italic>IL6</italic>-174 G/C (rs1800795) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Chan1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Ljungman1">[31]</xref>. The <italic>IL</italic> –174 G-allele, which was associated with lower HRV in this current study was previously associated with higher IL-6 blood concentrations, higher <italic>IL6</italic> gene transcriptional activity, and higher inducible IL-6 responses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Fishman1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Hulkkonen1">[35]</xref>. The restriction of the TPM<sub>10</sub> effect on lowering HRV is therefore consistent with an effect in a subgroup predisposed to a proinflammatory state. Second, increased serum levels of repeatedly measured IL-6 were observed among survivors of myocardial infarction who carried the G-allele of this SNP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Ljungman1">[31]</xref>. Third, <italic>IL6</italic> polymorphisms and in particular the −174 G/C variant were previously associated with various cardiovascular disease outcomes and risk factors, including ischemic cerebrovascular events <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Lalouschek1">[36]</xref>, coronary heart disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Humphries1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Sie1">[38]</xref>, high blood pressure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Humphries1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Hulkkonen2">[39]</xref>, total cholesterol, LDL, fasting glucose, BMI <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Riikola1">[40]</xref>, carotid artery compliance and carotid intima media thickness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Hulkkonen2">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Mayosi1">[41]</xref> as well as arterial stiffness and pulse pressure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Sie2">[42]</xref>. Yet, in a meta-analysis from 2006 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Sie1">[38]</xref> the authors concluded that most of the studies looking at the 174 G/C promoter polymorphism and its association with risk of coronary heart disease (CHD) were case-control studies showing heterogeneous associations between the genotypes and risk of cardiovascular heart disease. In contrast, we excluded all severely ill patients to specifically assess potential effects on HRV in the general population.</p>
<p>Evidence to support the role of systemic low grade inflammation in mediating susceptibility of the autonomic nervous system to air pollution is sparse. A small panel study reported short-term effects of particulate air pollution on decreased HRV to be stronger among elderly persons with high levels of CRP and fibrinogen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-LuttmannGibson1">[43]</xref>. While studies on the interaction between air pollution and inflammatory gene variants may be better suited for assessing susceptibility to long-term exposures, data on gene-air pollution interactions in cardiovascular health area generally very sparse as recently reviewed by Zanobetti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Zanobetti1">[44]</xref>. In fact, all results published on gene-air pollution interactions in relation to HRV were derived from a single study, the Normative Ageing Study of men, and focused on acute effects of air pollution. Results from this study generally support the role of pulmonary or systemic oxidative stress in linking air pollution and HRV <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Park1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Ren1">[46]</xref>. The SAPADIA cohort team previously reported on the modifying effect of antioxidative <italic>GST</italic> gene polymorphisms (<italic>GSTM1</italic> and <italic>GSTT1</italic> gene deletions and the <italic>GSTP1</italic> SNP Ile105Val) in the association of HRV with the inflammatory risk factors second-hand smoke and obesity in the general population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-ProbstHensch1">[47]</xref>. These <italic>GST</italic> polymorphisms did not modify the association between TPM<sub>10</sub> and HRV in this study.</p>
<p>A major strength of our study is the population-based design and the detailed information available on participants. The exposure assessment of TPM<sub>10</sub> with individual exposure estimates taking residential history into consideration has advantages to assess long-term exposure to traffic-related air pollution, providing good differentiation. Due to the detailed information on numerous cardiovascular risk factors, we were able to control for major confounding factors. Furthermore, we were able to guard our analysis of long-term TM<sub>10</sub> effects against confounding by short-term PM<sub>10</sub> exposure. The likely absence of confounding by short-term air pollution is further supported by the fact that non-inclusion of high sensitive C-reactive protein as model covariate did not materially alter the results (Tables S13-S14 in File S1).</p>
<p>This study has also a number of limitations. First, the results presented refer to statistical associations and interactions. The low prevalence of some genotypes limited statistical power of the explanatory analyses. Calculations indicate we had sufficient power to observe a main effect and a TPM<sub>10</sub> interaction effect for the candidate SNP <italic>IL6</italic>-174 G/C on SDNN of the order of magnitude reported or larger. These power calculations assumed different HRV parameters to not be independent. Second, we did not have information about IL-6 serum levels and cannot draw conclusions on how the polymorphisms studied influenced the circulating IL-6 levels and finally the cardiovascular health of the SAPALDIA participants. But the <italic>IL6</italic>-174 G/C SNP was associated with higher high sensitive C-reactive protein (mg/l) concentrations in the blood (GG: 2.8; GC: 2.5; CC: 2.4). Third, data on short-term TPM<sub>10</sub> was not available, and hence short-term exposure was assessed using averaged normal PM<sub>10</sub> from fixed monitoring station measurements. We had obtained 24-hr ECG recordings only once for each participant and were therefore not able to look at longitudinal changes in HRV and its association with the incidence of cardiovascular diseases. Fourth, we had previously reported that the association between TPM<sub>10</sub> and HRV is restricted to persons reporting intake of angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEI) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104978-Adam1">[10]</xref>. The now reported interaction between the <italic>IL6</italic>-174G/C polymorphism and TPM<sub>10</sub> remained unchanged after exclusion of participants on ACEI, but we lacked the statistical power for formal assessment of 3-way interactions between TPM<sub>10</sub>, <italic>IL6</italic> variants and ACEI. Finally, we were unable to adjust our analysis for some short-term factors influencing HRV, such as physical exercise. However, physical exercise at the time of heart rate variability measurement is unlikely to be associated with chronic exposure to TPM<sub>10</sub> and thus unlikely to confound the associations reported.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In summary, this cross-sectional study from the general population provides supportive evidence that genetic variation in one of the major proinflammatoy cytokines, <italic>IL6</italic>, alters HRV and its association with long-term exposure to traffic-related particulate air pollution. Our findings contribute to the research effort to pinpoint biologic mechanisms mediating air pollution related broad health effects. While the results guide future research efforts to use <italic>IL6</italic> as an important candidate gene in studies of HRV and air pollution, they essentially need replication in different study populations, in longitudinal studies, for different air pollution exposure metrics, and with genetic variant information derived from deep sequencing of the <italic>IL6</italic> gene region.</p>
</sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The SAPALDIA group involves more than 50 people that have supplied data and given minor contributions to the interpretation of the results. We would like to thank the whole SAPALDIA team (Acknowledgements S1 in File S1) for their contribution to the study. Additionally, the study could not have been done without the help of the study participants, technical and administrative support and the medical teams and field workers at the local study sites.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Bigger1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bigger</surname><given-names>JT</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fleiss</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rolnitzky</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinman</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Frequency domain measures of heart period variability to assess risk late after myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>729</fpage>–<lpage>736</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Brook1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rajagopalan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>CA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatnagar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Particulate matter air pollution and cardiovascular disease: An update to the scientific statement from the American Heart Association</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>2331</fpage>–<lpage>2378</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Kleiger1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleiger</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bigger</surname><given-names>JT</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Decreased heart rate variability and its association with increased mortality after acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Dekker1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crow</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Folsom</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hannan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Low heart rate variability in a 2-minute rhythm strip predicts risk of coronary heart disease and mortality from several causes: the ARIC Study. Atherosclerosis Risk In Communities</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>1239</fpage>–<lpage>1244</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Nolan1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Batin</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brooksby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Prospective study of heart rate variability and mortality in chronic heart failure: results of the United Kingdom heart failure evaluation and assessment of risk trial (UK-heart)</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>1510</fpage>–<lpage>1516</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Link1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Link</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dockery</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Air pollution and the triggering of cardiac arrhythmias</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cardiol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Pope1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>CA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eatough</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Ambient particulate air pollution, heart rate variability, and blood markers of inflammation in a panel of elderly subjects</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source> <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Pieters1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pieters</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plusquin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kicinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vangronsveld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>An epidemiological appraisal of the association between heart rate variability and particulate air pollution: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Heart</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>1127</fpage>–<lpage>1135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Mills1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tornqvist</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Diesel exhaust inhalation does not affect heart rhythm or heart rate variability</article-title>. <source>Heart</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>544</fpage>–<lpage>550</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Adam1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Felber Dietrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carballo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barthelemy</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Long-term exposure to traffic-related PM(10) and decreased heart rate variability: is the association restricted to subjects taking ACE inhibitors</article-title>? <source>Environ Int</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-FelberDietrich1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Felber Dietrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gemperli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaspoz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Differences in heart rate variability associated with longterm exposure to NO2</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>1357</fpage>–<lpage>1361</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Delfino1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delfino</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staimer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tjoa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arhami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polidori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Associations of primary and secondary organic aerosols with airway and systemic inflammation in an elderly panel cohort</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>892</fpage>–<lpage>902</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Delfino2"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delfino</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staimer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tjoa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gillen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polidori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Air pollution exposures and circulating biomarkers of effect in a susceptible population: clues to potential causal component mixtures and mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>1232</fpage>–<lpage>1238</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Lampert1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lampert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Decreased heart rate variability is associated with higher levels of inflammation in middle-aged men</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source> <volume>156</volume>: <fpage>759 e751</fpage>–<lpage>757</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Ruckerl1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruckerl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greven</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ljungman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aalto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antoniades</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Air pollution and inflammation (interleukin-6, C-reactive protein, fibrinogen) in myocardial infarction survivors</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source> <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>1072</fpage>–<lpage>1080</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Danesh1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Danesh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaptoge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarwar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Long-term interleukin-6 levels and subsequent risk of coronary heart disease: two new prospective studies and a systematic review</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e78</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Kaptoge1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaptoge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seshasai</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freitag</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butterworth</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Inflammatory cytokines and risk of coronary heart disease: new prospective study and updated meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>578</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Lee1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bettencourt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett-Connor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Association between serum interleukin-6 concentrations and mortality in older adults: the Rancho Bernardo study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e34218</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-AckermannLiebrich1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ackermann-Liebrich</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuna-Dibbert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Probst-Hensch</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Felber Dietrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Follow-up of the Swiss Cohort Study on Air Pollution and Lung Diseases in Adults (SAPALDIA 2) 1991-2003: Methods and characterization of participants</article-title>. <source>Soz Praventivmed</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Martin1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ackermann-Liebrich</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leuenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stutz</surname><given-names>EZ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>SAPALDIA: methods and participation in the cross-sectional part of the Swiss Study on Air Pollution and Lung Diseases in Adults</article-title>. <source>Soz Praventivmed</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Electrophysiology1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Electrophysiology</surname><given-names>NASoPa</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Heart rate variability: standards of measurement, physiological interpretation and clinical use. Task Force of the European Society of Cardiology and the North American Society of Pacing and Electrophysiology</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1043</fpage>–<lpage>1065</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-FelberDietrich2"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Felber Dietrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barthelemy</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tschopp</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Heart rate variability in an ageing population and its association with lifestyle and cardiovascular risk factors: results of the SAPALDIA study</article-title>. <source>Europace</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>529</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Liu1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Curjuric</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keidel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heldstab</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Characterization of source-specific air pollution exposure for a large population-based Swiss cohort (SAPALDIA)</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source> <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>1638</fpage>–<lpage>1645</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Kunzli1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bridevaux</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Esteban</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Traffic-related air pollution correlates with adult-onset asthma among never-smokers</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>664</fpage>–<lpage>670</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Brull1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brull</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dhamrait</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Interleukin-6 gene −174g&gt;c and -572g&gt;c promoter polymorphisms are strong predictors of plasma interleukin-6 levels after coronary artery bypass surgery</article-title>. <source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1458</fpage>–<lpage>1463</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Kelberman1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelberman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fife</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rockman</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brull</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Analysis of common IL-6 promoter SNP variants and the AnTn tract in humans and primates and effects on plasma IL-6 levels following coronary artery bypass graft surgery</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1688</volume>: <fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Kormann1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kormann</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klopp</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Illig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leupold</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>G-Protein-coupled receptor polymorphisms are associated with asthma in a large German population</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source> <volume>171</volume>: <fpage>1358</fpage>–<lpage>1362</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Imboden1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imboden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieters</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bircher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brutsche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Cytokine gene polymorphisms and atopic disease in two European cohorts. (ECRHS-Basel and SAPALDIA)</article-title>. <source>Clin Mol Allergy</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Bender1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Adjusting for multiple testing–when and how</article-title>? <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Chan1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Common variations in the genes encoding C-reactive protein, tumor necrosis factor-alpha, and interleukin-6, and the risk of clinical diabetes in the Women's Health Initiative Observational Study</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Ljungman1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ljungman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bellander</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lampa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacquemin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>DNA variants, plasma levels and variability of interleukin-6 in myocardial infarction survivors: results from the AIRGENE study</article-title>. <source>Thromb Res</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Haensel1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haensel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelesen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dimsdale</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The relationship between heart rate variability and inflammatory markers in cardiovascular diseases</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>1305</fpage>–<lpage>1312</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Lieb1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieb</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parson</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mamikunian</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vinik</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Cardiac autonomic imbalance in newly diagnosed and established diabetes is associated with markers of adipose tissue inflammation</article-title>. <source>Exp Diabetes Res</source> <volume>2012</volume>: <fpage>878760</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Fishman1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faulds</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed-Ali</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yudkin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The effect of novel polymorphisms in the interleukin-6 (IL-6) gene on IL-6 transcription and plasma IL-6 levels, and an association with systemic-onset juvenile chronic arthritis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>1369</fpage>–<lpage>1376</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Hulkkonen1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulkkonen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pertovaara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antonen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pasternack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hurme</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Elevated interleukin-6 plasma levels are regulated by the promoter region polymorphism of the IL6 gene in primary Sjogren's syndrome and correlate with the clinical manifestations of the disease</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology (Oxford)</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>656</fpage>–<lpage>661</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Lalouschek1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalouschek</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schillinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greisenegger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Polymorphisms of the inflammatory system and risk of ischemic cerebrovascular events</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem Lab Med</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>918</fpage>–<lpage>923</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Humphries1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luong</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogg</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The interleukin-6 -174 G/C promoter polymorphism is associated with risk of coronary heart disease and systolic blood pressure in healthy men</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2243</fpage>–<lpage>2252</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Sie1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sie</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sayed-Tabatabaei</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oei</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uitterlinden</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pols</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Interleukin 6 −174 g/c promoter polymorphism and risk of coronary heart disease: results from the rotterdam study and a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Hulkkonen2"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulkkonen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehtimaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mononen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Juonala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutri-Kahonen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Polymorphism in the IL6 promoter region is associated with the risk factors and markers of subclinical atherosclerosis in men: The Cardiovascular Risk in Young Finns Study</article-title>. <source>Atherosclerosis</source> <volume>203</volume>: <fpage>454</fpage>–<lpage>458</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Riikola1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riikola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sipila</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kahonen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jula</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieminen</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Interleukin-6 promoter polymorphism and cardiovascular risk factors: the Health 2000 Survey</article-title>. <source>Atherosclerosis</source> <volume>207</volume>: <fpage>466</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Mayosi1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayosi</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaukrodger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imrie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genotype at the -174G/C polymorphism of the interleukin-6 gene is associated with common carotid artery intimal-medial thickness: family study and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>2215</fpage>–<lpage>2219</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Sie2"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sie</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mattace-Raso</surname><given-names>FU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uitterlinden</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arp</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hofman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The interleukin-6-174 G/C promoter polymorphism and arterial stiffness; the Rotterdam Study</article-title>. <source>Vasc Health Risk Manag</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>863</fpage>–<lpage>869</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-LuttmannGibson1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luttmann-Gibson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coull</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dockery</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarnat</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Systemic inflammation, heart rate variability and air pollution in a cohort of senior adults</article-title>. <source>Occupational and Environmental Medicine</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>630</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Zanobetti1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanobetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baccarelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Gene-air pollution interaction and cardiovascular disease: a review</article-title>. <source>Prog Cardiovasc Dis</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Park1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vokonas</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>HFE genotype, particulate air pollution, and heart rate variability: a gene-environment interaction</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>2798</fpage>–<lpage>2805</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-Ren1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vokonas</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Air pollution and homocysteine: more evidence that oxidative stress-related genes modify effects of particulate air pollution</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104978-ProbstHensch1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Probst-Hensch</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imboden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Felber Dietrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barthelemy</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ackermann-Liebrich</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Glutathione S-transferase polymorphisms, passive smoking, obesity, and heart rate variability in nonsmokers</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>1494</fpage>–<lpage>1499</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>