<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-17993</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045664</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Evolutionary systematics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Taxonomy</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Microbial taxonomy</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Molecular systematics</subject>
                <subject>Phylogenetics</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Marine biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Marine monitoring</subject>
              <subject>Phycology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Microbiology</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Plant science</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plants</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Algae</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Plant Biology</subject>
          <subject>Marine and Aquatic Sciences</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Distance and Character-Based Evaluation of the V4 Region of the 18S rRNA Gene for the Identification of Diatoms (Bacillariophyceae)</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">V4-Based DNA Barcode in Diatoms</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Luddington</surname>
            <given-names>Ian A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kaczmarska</surname>
            <given-names>Irena</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Lovejoy</surname>
            <given-names>Connie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Biology, Mount Allison University, Sackville, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Québec-Océan, Département de Biologie and Institut de Biologie Intégrative et des Systèmes, Université Laval, Québec, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Paranhos</surname>
            <given-names>Rodolfo</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Instituto de Biologia, Brazil</addr-line>
      </aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">ialuddington@mta.ca</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: IAL IK. Performed the experiments: IAL. Analyzed the data: IAL IK CL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: IK. Wrote the paper: IAL IK CL.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e45664</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><permissions>
        
        <copyright-holder>Luddington et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions><abstract>
        <p>DNA barcoding is a molecular tool that exploits a unique DNA sequence of a standardized gene or non-coding region for the species identification of unknown individuals. The investigation into a suitable barcode for diatoms is ongoing and there are several promising candidates including mitochondrial, plastidial and nuclear markers. We analyzed 272 sequences from 76 diatoms species in the orders Thalassiosirales, Lithodesmiales and Cymatosirales, using distance and character based approaches, to assess the applicability of a DNA barcode based on the hypervariable V4 region of the nuclear 18S rRNA gene. We show that the proposed V4 barcode separated ca. 97% of all centric diatom taxa tested using a threshold <italic>p-</italic>distance of 0.02 and that many problem pairs were further separated using a character based approach. The reliability of amplification, extensive reference library and variability seen in the V4 region make it the most promising candidate to date for a barcode marker for diatoms particularly when combined with DNA character analysis<bold>.</bold></p>
      </abstract><funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by NSERC discovery grant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca/professors-professeurs/grants-subs/dgigp-psigp_eng.aspand" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca/professors-professeurs/grants-subs/dgigp-psigp_eng.aspand</ext-link>) and Canadian Healthy Oceans Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://chone.marinebiodiversity.ca/" xlink:type="simple">http://chone.marinebiodiversity.ca/</ext-link>), awarded to Irena Kaczmarska and Connie Lovejoy. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Diatoms are ubiquitous and morphological species are widely used to identify environmental changes in both freshwater and marine ecosystems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Smol1">[1]</xref>. Diatoms, especially the thalassiosiroids are also responsible for much of the primary production throughout the world oceans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Armbrust1">[2]</xref>. A rapid means of correct species identification is essential to fully exploit high throughput environmental sequence surveys, archived material, including ancient DNA, and data from clone libraries of uncultivated eukaryotes. Accurate identification of diatoms will also facilitate expanded monitoring efforts in the face of natural versus anthropogenic changes in marine and freshwater ecosystems. The high number of described morpho-species and an ever increasing number of newly discovered semi-cryptic and cryptic species adds to the challenges of expediency in the routine identification of diatoms. Additionally, in the last decade or so, nearly every study applying a combination of molecular and classical methods to taxonomically re-apprise “difficult” species resulted in discovery of species complexes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Lundholm1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Sarno1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-MacGillivary1">[5]</xref>, highlighting the need to revise interpretations of previous findings in microbial population and community ecology and geography.</p>
      <p>In light of this challenge, molecular methods can add to the taxonomic tool-kit by finding a genetic distance between organisms and resolving species boundaries. DNA barcoding takes this idea in molecular taxonomy even further by proposing a standardized, short DNA fragment that can consistently recognize species over a wide range of organisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hebert1">[6]</xref>, thereby providing a common metric for populations of conspecifics worldwide and aiding in the identification of ambiguous species.</p>
      <p>For animals, a fragment of the 5′ end of the mitochondrial gene encoding for the cytochrome c oxidase subunit 1 (<italic>cox</italic>1), is sufficient for the identification of approximately 96% of species in seven phyla <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hebert1">[6]</xref>. Other groups, for example, cnidarians <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hebert2">[7]</xref>, land plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hollingsworth1">[8]</xref> and fungi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Chase1">[9]</xref> do not segregate well using this gene. The utility of <italic>cox</italic>1 to identify protists, which are phylogenetically diverse and have uncertain evolutionary relationships, is mixed. The <italic>cox</italic>1 marker and other barcodes tested in green algae are ineffective <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hall1">[10]</xref> due to inconsistent amplification. Among the major macroalgae <italic>cox</italic>1 is a useful marker for rhodophytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Saunders1">[11]</xref>, while in some phaeophytes (specifically the genus <italic>Alaria</italic>) the gene fragment cannot discriminate well defined species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Lane1">[12]</xref>. The <italic>cox</italic>1 marker is even less promising for dinoflagellates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Lin1">[13]</xref>, and other short DNA sequences such as the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region of the gene coding for rRNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Litaker1">[14]</xref> or the mitochondrial cytochrome <italic>b</italic> gene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Lin2">[15]</xref> seem to be more promising.</p>
      <p>Up until now, four markers have been evaluated systematically for diatoms; <italic>cox</italic>1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Evans1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Kaczmarska1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Moniz1">[18]</xref>, the plastidial <italic>rbc</italic>L gene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hamsher1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-MacGillivary2">[20]</xref>, nuclear rDNA ITS region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Evans1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Moniz1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Moniz2">[21]</xref> and the nuclear small subunit rRNA gene (18S) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref>. Detailed discussions of the advantages and disadvantages of the first three markers are treated in the publications cited above and are therefore not repeated here. The 18S rRNA gene is a frequently used marker for deep phylogenetic research, but is relatively long and the utility of short variable regions within the 18S rRNA gene is more promising <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Because of its high and unrivaled amplification success and reasonable resolving power the potential utility of the 18S rRNA gene as a species specific barcode has been highlighted at least within one large dataset tested <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref>. Although Moniz and Kaczmarska <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Moniz1">[18]</xref> found that a 1600 bp long fragment of the ca. 1800 bp 18S rRNA gene did not contain sufficient variability to delineate species, another approach <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref> demonstrated that a shorter region of the gene could be used instead. Zimmermann <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref> systematically tested the entire 18S gene sequence and identified promising regions based on their variability. Following sequencing of 123 freshwater test-taxa, they found that the ca. 30 bp V4 region was the most variable and this and flanking regions (420 bp) discriminated all but eight species from 123 and they posited that it could serve as a barcode for diatoms. The eight morpho-species that were unresolved all belonged to the thalassiosiroid genus <italic>Stephanodiscus</italic> and included<italic>: S. agassizensis, S. binderanus, S. hantzsxhii, S. minutulus, S. neoastraea, S. niagarae, S. reimeri,</italic> and <italic>S. yellowstonensis.</italic> All eight showed very low divergence levels overall including in the V4 region. Therefore, the authors suggested that the resolving power of V4 may be limited to well diverged species, while in the closely related species complexes or groups including cryptic and recently evolved species it may be best combined with more sensitive markers, such as 5.8-ITS-2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref>. Other recent research indicates that the V4 region more closely approximates the variability of the entire 18S gene compared to the V9 hyper-variable <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Dunthorn1">[23]</xref>, another candidate barcode region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-AmaralZettler1">[24]</xref> albeit not in diatoms. Since Zimmerman <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref> focused on mostly freshwater genera and the thalassiosiroids were among the least successfully resolved taxa and contained many similar morpho-species, the aim of the present study was to further investigate the utility of the V4 region of the 18S gene for species identification, particularly in this group. We focused on mostly marine, closely allied Thalassiosirales and select other diatoms that were not included in the earlier study. The development of a standardized DNA marker with a large reference database in this group would significantly aid our understanding of the ecology of the diatoms with special emphasis on the thalassiosiroids. Members of this order form the most important constituent of summer blooms in the North Atlantic. A timely and reliable method of species identification would enable refined analyses of bloom dynamics, taxonomic composition and the characterization of long-range transport and species invasions, all increasingly important in a rapidly changing environment. Not only common species and main bloom constituents but also members of the “rare biosphere” could be readily elucidated through the use of a V4 based barcode in next generation high throughput sequencing including 454 pyrosequencing technology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Medlin1">[25]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Our approach was to amplify and sequence the V4 region from three marine, species rich orders: Thalassiosirales, Lithodesmiales and the little studied Cymatosirales. We combined the new sequences with sequences of the V4 region that were available from GenBank, which we curated with the objective to further test the resolving power of the 18S V4 region as a possible barcode for diatoms. We expanded the specific and geographic coverage used by Zimmermann <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref> for the V4 test-set and included biologically defined species and a greater number of closely related morpho-species. Additionally, we evaluated the recently advocated character based approach <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-DeSalle1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Taylor1">[27]</xref> to identify diatom sequences from the V4 region when unresolved by distance methods alone.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>Overall we obtained 272 sequences (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0045664.s001">Table S1</xref></bold>) from 272 strains, clones or isolates. DNA template for this study was extracted from 42 monoclonal cultures previously established in our Mount Allison lab, and 32 additional strains from the National Center for Marine Algae and Microbiota (NCMA). Monoclonal cultures from 10 sex compatible clones of <italic>Tabularia fasiculata</italic> (order Fragilariales) and 3 <italic>Campylosira cymbelliformis</italic> (Cymatosirales) were sequenced as part of the test set to represent biologically defined species. DNA was also extracted from 8 single chains, of known species, isolated from environmental samples. At Mount Allison, diatom cultures were grown and their DNA extracted as described by Moniz &amp; Kaczmarska <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Moniz2">[21]</xref> and MacGillivary &amp; Kaczmarska <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-MacGillivary2">[20]</xref> for a total of 82 new sequences. Voucher SEM images of the clones and strains can be retrieved via the BOLD accession numbers listed in <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0045664.s001">Table S1</xref></bold>.</p>
      <p>The remaining 190 sequences were retrieved from Genbank and in total 76 species were analyzed, 30 from this study and 46 from GenBank. These retrieved sequences included much of, or the entire 18S gene and were trimmed to cover only the V4 region and flanking regions. Sequences from GenBank were selected based on the availability of corroborative evidence of species identity from published sources or communication with the depositors.</p>
      <p>The V4 region along with conserved flanking regions (approximately 420 bp) was amplified using primers D512: <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-ATT CCA GCT CCA ATA GCG-3′</named-content> and D978: 5′-GAC TAC GAT GGT ATC TAA TC-3′ following Zimmermann <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Reactions of 25 µL for all cultured strains contained 12.5 µL of GoTaq Mastermix (Promega), 0.75 µL each of forward and reverse primers (final concentration of 0.3 µM), 9 µL of DEPC treated water and 2 µL of DNA template. Cycling conditions following an initial denaturation step of 30s at 95°C were 35 cycles of 30s at 94°C, 30s at 50°C and 30s at 72°C. Strains which exhibited low PCR yield were subjected to a second round reamplification under the same conditions.</p>
      <p>Single chains isolated directly from seawater or ethanol preserved samples were subjected to a two round, nested-PCR protocol following Lang &amp; Kaczmarska <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Lang1">[28]</xref> with the following modifications: First round primers were 18F <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Iwatani1">[29]</xref> and ITS4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-White1">[30]</xref> and the cycling conditions were an initial 3 min at 94°C followed by 14 cycles of 94°C for 30s, 48°C for 30s and 72°C for 1 min and then 19 cycles of 94°C for 30s, 48°C for 30s and finished with 72°C for 2 min 30s (increased by 10s each round). The second, nested round used 1 µL of first round PCR product as template, and otherwise followed the same cycling conditions and reaction volumes as for cultures. PCR products were then visualized on a 1.2% agarose gel precast with SYBR safe gel stain (Invitrogen). Post-PCR SEM was performed on two isolates of <italic>Thalassiosira anguste-lineata</italic> following Lang &amp; Kaczmarska <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Lang1">[28]</xref>.</p>
      <p>PCR products were purified and sequenced at McGill University and Génome Quebec by Sanger sequencing (3730xl DNA analyzer, Applied Biosystems). Sanger sequencing was preferred because we were using direct PCR on morphologically identified cells and the relatively few samples were not compatible with high throughput sequencing. Additionally, the accuracy and ability to cross-check base-calling allowed us to produce robust non ambiguous reference sequences, which are required for environmental gene surveys. Resultant chromatograms and sequences were inspected, edited and checked against similar GenBank sequences using the NCBI Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST), further checked for correct base-calling using FinchTV <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Geospiza1">[31]</xref> and the alignment was manually refined with BioEdit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hall2">[32]</xref>. Our final sequences were 333 bp long after primer sequences and the redundant, super-conserved downstream region (totaling to 420 bp in Zimmermann <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref>) was removed. Sequence analysis including the calculation of <italic>p</italic>-distances was conducted using MEGA5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Tamura1">[33]</xref>. Uncorrected <italic>p-</italic>distances were chosen as other models tested did not give significantly different distances (i.e. K2P distances). The maximum-likelihood phylogenetic tree was constructed in MEGA5 using the Tamura-3-paramter model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Tamura2">[34]</xref> based on the best fit subsitution model and which produced trees closest to previously resolved phylogenies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Kaczmarska2">[35]</xref>. Identical sequences were removed to improve terminal branch clarity.</p>
      <p>Character-based analysis was performed manually by analyzing sequence motifs within the Sequence Data Explorer in MEGA5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Tamura1">[33]</xref> because the chosen groups contained a small number of variable sites and sequences and therefore software was not required. Pure diagnostic (i.e. a transition or transversion unique to one group of sequences or species) and compound private diagnostics (i.e. a combination of two substitutions which alone are not unique to a group of sequences or species yet together are) were discerned from sequence alignments following Sarkar <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Sarkar1">[36]</xref> and used to classify sequences based on a neighbor-joining (NJ) guide tree. Unlike Sarkar <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Sarkar1">[36]</xref> however, a doubly compound private character (i.e. three private characters at different variable sites) was used as a pure diagnostic for the classification of one sequence group (<italic>S. costatum</italic> Subgroup B and <italic>S. grethae</italic>). This analysis method was used for all <italic>Skeletonema</italic> species as well as all Cymatosirales species because these genera contained several poorly resolved morpho-species and were represented by multiple sequences per species.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Amplification and Sequencing</title>
        <p>We successfully amplified and sequenced 30 species from 17 genera. Amplification success for all clones was 100% for all cultured strains and 47% for single chains. All successful amplifications were sequenced. Some strains, including all of the Cymatosirales but also <italic>Skeletonema marinoi</italic>, and <italic>S. menzelli</italic> needed to be amplified a second time from the first PCR product to ensure sufficient DNA for sequencing. The alignment of sequences was not collinear with insertions and deletions (indels), especially within the V4 region. However, conserved flanking regions and species-specific sequence motifs allowed for unambiguous manual alignment. Two sequences, from <italic>Extubocellulus cribriger</italic> and <italic>E</italic>. <italic>spinifer</italic> (CCMP391 and 393) had an approximately 150 bp insertion downstream of the V4 region, however, since these indels were outside the region of interest they had no effect on alignment. Although these two species amplified and sequenced well for the V4 region, there were two bands visualized in the gels used to verify the amplification steps with one of the bands 450 bp, which was the target length and the second band approximately 600 bp. PCR products were sequenced directly without excision and the longer of these products sequenced preferentially. Likewise, similar double bands were seen for <italic>Minutocellus polymorphus</italic> (CCMP499<italic>)</italic> though in this case the smaller band was stronger and sequenced preferentially. After trimming, final aligned sequences containing the ca. 30 bp highly variable V4 region were 333 bp in length.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Distance Analysis</title>
        <p>Intraspecific uncorrected <italic>p-</italic>distances for all species tested ranged from 0 to 0.007 with an average of 0.0014. The highest value of 0.012 was found between the strains of <italic>Cyclotella meneghiniana</italic>. Forty five species which had multiple strains were included in this analysis for a total of 232 sequences. Interspecific uncorrected <italic>p-</italic>distances for all 76 species ranged from 0 to 0.248 with an average <italic>p-</italic>distance of 0.076. Very low (p&lt;0.004) interspecific distances were observed between each of the following pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g001"><bold>Fig. 1</bold></xref><bold>)</bold>: between <italic>Cyclostephanos dubius</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>invisitatus; Skeletonema grethae</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>costatum, S. pseudocostatum</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>tropicum; S</italic>. <italic>ardens</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>pseudocostatum; S</italic>. <italic>ardens</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>tropicum; S</italic>. <italic>costatum</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>tropicum, Minidiscus variabilis</italic> and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>trioculatus; T</italic>. <italic>gravida</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>rotula; T. tenera</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>pacifica; T. oestrupii</italic> v. <italic>venrickae</italic> and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>trioculatus</italic> and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>variabilis;</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g002"><bold>Fig. 2</bold></xref>) <italic>Arcocellulus mammifer</italic> and <italic>Minutocellus polymorphus</italic> and <italic>Plagiogrammopsis vanheurckii</italic> and <italic>Brockmanniella brockmannii</italic>. This distance represents 0–2 nucleotide differences over the 333 bp of the fragment tested.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0045664-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Maximum-likelihood tree for the order Thalassiosirales.</title>
            <p>The phylogenetic tree was constructed using the Tamura-3-parameter model with all unique V4-region sequences. Boot strap values (1000 replicates) above 80% are shown at branch nodes. Identical sequences were removed from analysis and the representative sequence referenced in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0045664.s001">Table S1</xref>. The number of identical sequences per species is listed in brackets and problem pairs discussed in the text are indicated by an *.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0045664-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Maximum-likelihood trees for the orders Cymatosirales and Lithodesmiales.</title>
            <p>The phylogenetic tree was constructed using identical parameters to the Thalassiosirales tree. Bootstrap values (1000 replicates) above 80% are shown at branch nodes. Identical sequences were removed from analysis and the representative sequence referenced in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0045664.s001">Table S1</xref>. The number of identical sequences per species is listed in brackets and problem pairs discussed in the text are indicated by an *.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>For comparison, the V4 region from sexually compatible clones established from geographically distant locations was sequenced for 10 clones of <italic>Tabularia fasiculata</italic> (Fragilariales) from the West and East Coasts of Canada and from Ukraine, and for 3 clones of <italic>Campylosira cymbelliformis</italic> (Cymatosirales) from the West Coast of the USA, the East Coast of Canada and England, which were also compared with a Gulf of Mexico sequence deposited in Genbank. The average <italic>p-</italic>distance was 0.001 (average of 0.33 nucleotides in the entire V4 region) for <italic>Tabularia fasiculata</italic> (two Pacific clones separate from all others). All <italic>Campylosira cymbelliformis</italic> clone sequences showed 100% identity.</p>
        <p>In some species pairs little to no variability was seen in the V4 region but much higher variability was found when much longer (ca. 1680 bp) 18S gene sequences were compared for the same pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g003"><bold>Fig. 3</bold></xref>). For instance, <italic>M</italic>. <italic>trioculatus</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>oestrupii</italic> v. <italic>venrickae</italic> showed a <italic>p-</italic>distance of only 0.003 or 2 nucleotides in the V4 region whereas the full 18S sequences showed a <italic>p-</italic>distance of 0.023 or 39 nucleotides, 6 of which were in the V9 region. Other comparisons that showed this trend, though not as pronounced, were <italic>Planktoniella sol</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>tenera</italic> which differed from 0.009 in the V4 region to 0.0132 in the full-length 18S sequence, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>angulata</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>tenera</italic> which differed from 0.006 (V4) to 0.0133 (full 18S) and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>tenera</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>pacifica</italic> which differed 0.003 (V4) to 0.0087 (full 18s) though in these cases the V9 region did not show higher variability than the V4 as with <italic>M. trioculatus</italic> and <italic>T. oestrupii</italic> v. <italic>venrickae</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0045664-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison of the variability of the V4 region barcode used in this study (333 bp) with a 1682 bp fragment representing most of the full 18S gene.</title>
            <p>All comparisons represented are between one sequence each of the same strain/clone. Differences are represented by the proportion of differences between the sequence pair (<italic>p-</italic>value).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Intergeneric distances were analyzed among the 26 genera based on 264 sequences. The average intergeneric <italic>p-</italic>distance was 0.0873 and ranged from 0.001 to 0.235. The lowest distance (<italic>p = </italic>0.001) was between the two cymatosiroid genera <italic>Arcocellulus</italic> and <italic>Minutocellus</italic>.</p>
        <p>The maximum-likelihood trees (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g001"><bold>Fig. 1</bold></xref><bold> &amp; </bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g002"><bold>2</bold></xref>) constructed from unique sequences of all three orders: Thalassiosirales, Lithodesmiales and Cymatosirales recovered topology generally similar to those proposed earlier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Kaczmarska2">[35]</xref> and showed resolution of most species. The species not resolved were those whose <italic>p-</italic>values were low as reported above.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Reassessment of Sequence Identities for Distance Analysis</title>
        <p>An instructive preliminary inspection of the Thalassiosirales tree <bold>(</bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g001"><bold>Fig. 1</bold></xref>) revealed that several sequences with the same name retrieved from GenBank were clearly separated from others, while in other cases 100% identical (in V-4 region) sequences carried different names. Prior to distance analysis we attempted to resolve some of these anomalies by re-examination of either sequences or images associated with the sequences. The conclusions of this examination are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0045664-t001"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0045664-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Summary of the reassessment of sequence identities.</title>
          </caption><alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0045664-t001-1" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accession Number</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Strain Code</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Published or GenBank Name</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Morphological Species</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JX437374</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCMP982</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira antarctica</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira antarctica</italic>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EF140621</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira antarctica</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Thalassiosira</italic> sp.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DQ093366</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCMP991</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira minima</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Bacterosira</italic> sp.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DQ514876</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCMP990</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira minima</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira minima</italic>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DQ514867</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BEN02-35</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira angulata</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira allenii</italic>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AJ810854</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MHta1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira anguste-lineata</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira angulata</italic>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JX437386</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IIIB3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira angulata</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira angulata</italic>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HM991688</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DDZ-2010a</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira allenii</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Thalassiosira allenii</italic>
                  </td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <p>The names used here correspond to the morphological identity from new or published SEM images (see text for details).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>Firstly, two sequences identified as <italic>Thalassiosira antarctica</italic> (CCMP982:JX437374 and T1:EF140621) grouped into separate clades and were distinct in terms of genetic distance with <italic>p = </italic>0.012 diff/site, thus far exceeding most of the intraspecific distances in our data set. One sequence (CCMP982) clustered with <italic>T. minima</italic> whereas the other (currently named <italic>Thalassiosira</italic> sp 1, T1) grouped with <italic>Thalassiosira minuscula</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g001"><bold>Fig. 1</bold></xref>). CCMP982 had been cultured in our Mount Allison laboratory some years ago and SEM images (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g004"><bold>Fig. 4A</bold></xref><bold>)</bold> available showed that this clone morphologically conformed to T. <italic>antarctica</italic> (metric data: mean±SEM of the following characters: diameter, d = 14.33±0.16, valve face areolae in 10 µm a = 23.81±0.57 and fultoportulae in 10 µm f = 7.38±0.32, metrics will follow this order below) as per Hasle and Heimdal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hasle1">[37]</xref> albeit cells in our culture were at or below the species range for valve diameter and with no evidence of spores. Therefore, we conclude that CCMP982 is likely <italic>T. antarctica</italic> while the strain T1 represents a species for which an identified reference sequence is not yet available.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0045664-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>SEM images of <italic>Thalassiosira</italic> species used in this study for the reassessment of sequence identity for ambiguous sequences.</title>
            <p>Scale bars = 3 µm (A), 1 µm (B), 2 µm (C,D) and 5 µm (E,F). (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>Thalassiosira antarctica</italic> strain CCMP 982 (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>Thalassiosira minima</italic> strain CCMP 985 (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>Thalassiosira “minima”</italic> strain CCMP 991 (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>Thalassiosira angulata</italic> clone PCB2 (E-F) <italic>Thalassiosira anguste-lineata</italic> isolate Art-22/127 from post-PCR SEM, not acid cleaned.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Secondly, two sequences attributed to <italic>T. minima</italic> (DQ093366.1, CCMP991 and DQ514876, CCMP990) differed phylogenetically as well. The former was closest to <italic>Bacterosira bathyomphala</italic> while the latter was closest to CCMP985 (JX437382), <italic>Thalassiosira floridana</italic> (currently synonymized to <italic>T. minima</italic> in Hasle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hasle2">[38]</xref>. Again, two of these strains had been grown earlier in our Mount Allison lab and we have SEM images for CCMP985 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g004"><bold>Fig. 4B</bold></xref><bold>)</bold> and CCMP991 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g004"><bold>Fig. 4C</bold></xref><bold>)</bold>. They both fit the morphological descriptions of <italic>T. minima</italic> by Hasle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hasle2">[38]</xref> with two central strutted processes and in terms of measurements for diameter (5.97±0.12 µm for CCMP985 and 10.2±0.6 µm for CCMP991), areolae in 10 µm (37.29±1.23 for CCMP985 and 42.1±8.4 for CCMP991) and number of fultoportulae in 10 µm (4.48±0.07 for CCMP985 and 4.5±0.8 for CCMP991) though cultured CCMP991 shows no distinct areolae throughout the valve face except at the margin. Because of the sequence differences and the lack of areolation on the valve face in CCMP991 we concur that this strain may represent a novel species related to the genus <italic>Bacterosira</italic> as suggested by Alverson <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Alverson1">[39]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Even more convoluted seems the case involving four other sequences (DQ514867, AJ810854, JX437386 and HM991688) summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0045664-t001"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>. These are identified as “<italic>Thalassiosira angulata”</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Alverson1">[39]</xref>, “<italic>T. anguste-lineata”</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hoppenrath1">[40]</xref>, T. <italic>angulata</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Moniz2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Mills1">[41]</xref> and <italic>T. allenii</italic> (GenBank direct submission). The first of these sequences, “<italic>T. angulata”</italic> (DQ514867) is identical to the fourth, <italic>T. allenii</italic> (HM991688), and is different from our clones of <italic>T. angulata</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g004"><bold>Fig. 4D</bold></xref>) which have metrics (as ordered above) of d = 12.13±0.26 µm, a = 18.43±0.43/10 µm and f = 2.79±0.03/10 µm consistent with the type <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hasle3">[42]</xref>. SEM images of this clone BEN02-35 (DQ514867) retrieved from ProtistCentral also differ from the specimens of <italic>T. angulata</italic> by the areolae on the valve mantle being smaller then on the valve face, a character attributed to <italic>T. allenii</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hasle3">[42]</xref>. Consequently, we assigned this clone to <italic>T. allenii</italic> for this study.</p>
        <p>The second sequence (AJ810854) deposited as “<italic>T. anguste-lineata”</italic> is, however, identical to our clones of <italic>T. angulata</italic> from the Canadian Maritimes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Moniz2">[21]</xref> represented by sequence 3 (JX437386). This is an intriguing case because we have 5 clones of <italic>T. angulata</italic> sequenced and morphologically they all meet the specific diagnostic morpho-criteria of Hasle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hasle3">[42]</xref> attributed to this species. However, the SEM images presented in Hoppenrath <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hoppenrath1">[40]</xref> seem to represent <italic>T. anguste-lineata</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Fryxell1">[43]</xref> though with clusters of only one to two central fultoportulae. Furthermore, the sequence and images retrieved from our own isolate chains of <italic>T. anguste-lineata</italic> Art-22 and Art-137 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g004"><bold>Fig. 4E–F</bold></xref><bold>)</bold> also conform well to the type description <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Fryxell1">[43]</xref> (as per measurements of d = 28.16±0.41 µm, a = 14.17±1.17/10 µm and f = 3.22±0.11/10 µm) and morphological and sequence data from Alverson <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Alverson1">[39]</xref> and differ considerably from AJ810854. We therefore conclude that this sequence represents <italic>T. angulata,</italic> a conclusion shared by the authors (Hoppenrath M &amp; Beszteri B, pers. comm.). These conclusions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0045664.s001">Table S1</xref>) were applied to distance metrics and are incorporated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g001"><bold>Fig. 1</bold></xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Character Analysis</title>
        <p>A character based analysis was performed on the 11 species from the genus <italic>Skeletonema</italic> as well as from the order Cymatosirales (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g005"><bold>Fig. 5</bold></xref>). These groups were chosen because of their very low intraspecific genetic distances. For members of the genus <italic>Skeletonema</italic> all species but 2 were separated by this approach. Three species (<italic>S. menzelli, S. grevillei,</italic> and <italic>S. marinoi</italic>) were readily separated using single, pure diagnostic characters (transition or transversion unique to a species). <italic>Skeletonema pseudocostatum</italic> and <italic>S. tropicum,</italic> two species which showed no genetic distance between them were separated as a pair from all others by a single diagnostic character as well. In addition, four other species were separated by compound pure diagnostic characters, <italic>S</italic>. <italic>japonicum, S. subsalsum, S. ardens</italic>, and <italic>S. dohrnii</italic>. Further, <italic>S. costatum</italic> and <italic>S. grethae</italic> were separated as a pair from all others by a double compound pure diagnostic character. Finally, <italic>S</italic>. <italic>costatum</italic> sequences were separated into two subgroups: those identical to <italic>S. grethae</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g001"><bold>Fig. 1</bold></xref><bold> Subgroup B</bold>) and those separated by a compound diagnostic character from <italic>S. grethae</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0045664-g001"><bold>Fig. 1</bold></xref><bold> Subgroup A</bold>). In total nine of the <italic>Skeletonema</italic> species were separated using a character based approach while two species, <italic>S. grethae</italic> and <italic>S. tropicum</italic> remained inseparable. Many private characters (unique to one or more sequences but not the entire group/species) were also found in different GenBank sequences of various <italic>Skeletonema</italic> species exhibiting no particular pattern with respect to type of change (i.e. transition or transversion) or geography.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0045664-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Variable sites used as diagnostic characters in the V4 region of select sequences.</title>
            <p>(<bold>A</bold>) sequences from the genus Skeletonema and (<bold>B</bold>) sequences from the order Cymatosirales. Numbers above sequences represent variable sites and points represent sequence identity with the top sequence. Conserved regions between variable sites were collapsed for brevity.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>This approach was equally successful for the members of the order Cymatosirales showing extremely low divergence in the V4 region. Four species were separated by single, pure diagnostic characters (<italic>Cymatosira belgica, Extubocellulus cribriger, E. spinifer</italic> and <italic>Minutocellulus polymorphus</italic>) and four more species were separated by compound pure diagnostic characters, (<italic>Plagiogrammopsis vanheurckii</italic>, <italic>Brockmanniella brockmannii</italic>, <italic>Campylosira cymbelliformis</italic> and <italic>Papiliocellulus elegans</italic>). In this case the only species out of nine included in our dataset that did not have a pure diagnostic character in the tested fragment was <italic>Arcocellulus mammifer</italic> which was identical to <italic>M. polymorphus</italic> in the V4 region.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Barcode Threshold</title>
        <p>All sequences in this study were examined for how well they separated species according to a threshold value. A threshold of p = 0.02 successfully separated 96.9% of species tested. The efficacy of the marker increased when the threshold level was reduced to p = 0.01 (3 nucleotides) with 99.6% of all species separated. However, this lower threshold resulted in the overlap of six intraspecific values (of 45 species groups) and thus indicates that a threshold lower than p = 0.02 would be too low to retain necessary taxonomic information at the species level.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Amplification and Sequencing</title>
        <p>A useful DNA barcode should amplify reliably, be universal for all taxa at the taxonomic level chosen and be variable enough to separate species. The V4 region of the 18S gene amplified and sequenced successfully for all cultured strains and for nearly half of single chains. This ease of amplification and sequencing across the taxa was also reported by Zimmermann <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref> and indicates that the V4 region primers are sufficiently universal and the V4 locus is readily accessible. Thus, this DNA fragment met the first two criteria of an effective barcode. The poorer success rate for our single chains was most likely a consequence of the small amount of genetic material available from the few cells in the chain seen also for other multiplexed targets <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Lang1">[28]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Importantly for the application of a candidate barcode, Zimmermann <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref> noted that the 18S gene already has a strong representation in GenBank. This history of record provides the needed reference sequence base with which to compare unknown, newly retrieved sequences that otherwise could not be identified. Unlike the entire 18S sequence or other barcodes, however the V4 region is short and thus can be easily retrieved from small or precious samples as well as from fixed or heavily degraded DNA similar to cox1 “minibarcodes” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Hajibabaei1">[44]</xref>. Recent high throughput amplicon sequencing efforts have also focused on the V4 region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Comeau1">[45]</xref> and increased taxonomic resolution of these sequences would be a significant benefit.</p>
        <p>The V4 region amplified included flanking homologous base pairs that were readily aligned. This contrasts the 5.8S, ITS2 barcode region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Moniz2">[21]</xref> where specific parameters and conserved anchor points are needed to produce a confident alignment. This ease of alignment means that little editing is required to accurately represent sequence homology. Here, even the three sequences with large inserts (<italic>Extubocellulus cribriger</italic>, <italic>E. spinifer</italic> and <italic>Cymatosira belgica</italic>) were readily aligned with all other sequences as the inserts occurred downstream of the V4 region and flanking conserved regions and were removed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Distance Analysis</title>
        <p>Intraspecific uncorrected <italic>p-</italic>distances expressed as the proportion of differing sites between two sequences were on average much lower than interspecific distances which represent a characteristic of a good DNA barcode. Some species pairs showed very low interspecific <italic>p</italic>-distances (problem pairs listed above) and some of them were also morphologically semi-cryptic. Zimmermann <italic>et</italic> <italic>al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref> already found that some members of the genus <italic>Stephanodiscus</italic> showed little divergence and the same pattern was seen for sister clades in our study. For example, <italic>Cyclostephanos dubius</italic> and <italic>C. invisiatus</italic> showed no difference in the V4 region. Among our new sequences, those from the genus <italic>Skeletonema</italic> were particularly troublesome in terms of species separation by the V4 region. Among these the <italic>p-</italic>distances with very little resolution were the following species pairs: <italic>Skeletonema grethae</italic> and <italic>S. costatum</italic> (0.003), <italic>S. pseudocostatum</italic> and <italic>S. tropicum</italic> (0.001), <italic>S. ardens</italic> and <italic>S. pseudocostatum</italic> (0.007) and <italic>S. ardens,</italic> and <italic>S. tropicum</italic> (0.006).</p>
        <p>Until recently, however, the genus <italic>Skeletonema</italic> included only a few species: <italic>S. costatum, S. tropicum</italic>, <italic>S. subsalsum</italic>, <italic>S. potamos</italic>, <italic>S. cylindraceum</italic> and <italic>S. menzelii,</italic> though in most cases field samples containing <italic>Skeletonema</italic> are identified as “<italic>S. costatum”</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Sarno1">[4]</xref>. This attests to the semi-cryptic nature of these species’ morphology. Sarno <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Sarno1">[4]</xref> applied extensive morphological analysis in conjunction with a molecular assessment of the 18S and 28S rDNA genes and found evidence supporting the segregation of the <italic>Skeletonema costatum</italic>-complex into four new species (<italic>S. dohrnii</italic>, <italic>S. grethae</italic>, <italic>S. japonicum</italic> and <italic>S. marinoi</italic>). Sarno <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Sarno2">[46]</xref> though, also found that the entire 18S gene poorly resolved the relationships between some of the <italic>Skeletonema</italic> species and thus the V4 region alone may also be insufficient in resolving all morpho-species in this complex without a companion marker.</p>
        <p><italic>Mindiscus variabilis</italic> and <italic>M. trioculatus</italic> were also identical over the V4 region, however, some genetic distances between these two morpho-species were previously reported using the whole 18S gene as well as the ITS region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Kaczmarska3">[47]</xref>, the two species were also relatively easy to separate morphologically and the separation of the two species was justified on that basis.</p>
        <p>Among the 32 <italic>Thalassiosira</italic> species there were three problem pairs: <italic>Thalassiosira gravida</italic> and <italic>T.</italic> <italic>rotula</italic>; <italic>T.</italic> <italic>tenera</italic> and <italic>T.</italic> <italic>pacifica</italic>; <italic>T.</italic> <italic>oestrupii v.</italic> <italic>venrickae</italic> and <italic>M.</italic> <italic>trioculatus</italic> as well as <italic>M.</italic> <italic>variabilis</italic>. The difference between <italic>T.</italic> <italic>gravida</italic> and <italic>T.</italic> <italic>rotula</italic> was very small (p = 0.00362). This may reflect the long standing debate as to whether the two are distinct species or the same species with varying morphologies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Syvertsen1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Sar1">[49]</xref>, and may support the latter. The other species pairs representing a more interesting case and will be discussed further below.</p>
        <p>Within the order Cymatosirales <italic>Arcocellulus mammifer</italic> and <italic>Minutocellus polymorphus</italic> were identical and <italic>Plagiogrammopsis vanheurckii</italic> and <italic>Brockmanniella brockmannii</italic> differed by only p = 0.003 over the region tested, suggesting the V4 region could be a poor barcode for genera in this order based on distance methods alone though in this order the dataset was limited.</p>
        <p>Biologically defined species used in this study, those with separate mating types from the genera <italic>Tabularia</italic> and <italic>Campylosira</italic> were represented by clones isolated from sites across continents and oceans and showed very low genetic distances. These very low genetic distances may be expected among representatives of panmictic (random mating) populations. One sequence of <italic>C. cymbelliformis</italic> from GenBank showed 100% sequence similarity to the other clones suggesting perhaps genetic conservatism in this locus independent of geography or that there is ongoing genetic exchange via long range transport between North Pacific, North Atlantic and the Caribbean.</p>
        <p>Some species pairs in our test-set exhibited very low variability in the V4 region but much higher variability over the entire 18S sequence (e.g. <italic>Minidiscus trioculatus</italic> and <italic>T. oestrupii</italic> v. <italic>venrickae</italic>, <italic>Planktoniella sol</italic> and <italic>T. tenera, T. angulata</italic> and <italic>T. tenera</italic> and <italic>T. tenera</italic> and <italic>T. pacifica</italic>). While our study only examined diatoms, a recent study by Dunthorn <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Dunthorn1">[23]</xref> compared the V4 region with the alternate hyper-variable region V9 in ciliates and came to the conclusion that the V4 region also more closely approximates the variability of the entire gene in agreement with Zimmermann <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref>. While this suggests the phenomenon is not widespread, our observation nonetheless illustrates a possible shortcoming for a V4 based barcode and emphasizes the need for further taxon sampling among diatoms to establish whether the phenomenon is common.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Character Analysis</title>
        <p>Applying a character based approach to DNA barcoding at the level of genus resolved some of the ambiguities in the distance method. In the case of <italic>Skeletonema</italic> all species with the exception of S. <italic>tropicum</italic> and S. <italic>grethae</italic> were separated. The private characteristics observed in various GenBank <italic>Skeletonema</italic> sequences that did not correspond to species or subgroups were consistent with sequence base-calling error. Additionally, the application of character analysis may have clarified sequence relationships between subgroups of <italic>S</italic>. <italic>costatum.</italic> Two groups of S. <italic>costatum</italic> sequences, subgroup A and B were recoverd. Subgroup A was distinguised from subgroup B containing <italic>S. grethae</italic> and several GenBank sequences attributed to <italic>S</italic>. <italic>costatum</italic> (CCMP1077/4 A-D, 2A–2D) by a pure diagnostic character. This suggests that <italic>S</italic>. <italic>costatum</italic> subgroup B and S. <italic>grethae</italic> may be conspecific. This is consistent with the fact that one S. <italic>grethae</italic> sequence (X85395) in this subgroup belongs to a specimen which was first attributed to <italic>S</italic>. <italic>costatum</italic> based on morphology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Medlin2">[50]</xref> but then subsequently transferred to <italic>S</italic>. <italic>grethae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Sarno1">[4]</xref>. Similarly, it may be that the other sequences attributed to S. <italic>costatum</italic> in Alverson &amp; Kolnick <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Alverson2">[51]</xref> of subgroup B are in fact <italic>S</italic>. <italic>grethae</italic>. If so, the two species can be separated by character analysis.</p>
        <p>As with the genus <italic>Skeletonema,</italic> character analysis in Cymatosirales resolved several of the ambiguities resulting from genetic distance analysis alone. All species in the order showed pure diagnostic characters (single and compound) that distinguished them, including <italic>Plagiogrammopsis</italic> and <italic>Brockmanniella brockmannii</italic> whose separation was justified by a CC-CT difference in the 14<sup>th</sup> and 15<sup>th</sup> variable sites. The only exception was <italic>Arcocellulus mammifer</italic> whose separation from <italic>Minutocellus polymorphus</italic> could not be justified based on our marker.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Barcode Threshold</title>
        <p>A key test for a DNA barcode is its efficacy in separating species according to a threshold value. In this study, a threshold of p = 0.02 was found to separate 96.9% of all species. Zimmermann <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref> found that all but the members of <italic>Stephanodiscus</italic> were successfully separated using V4 as a barcode. Though Zimmermann <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref> did not define a species threshold value intrageneric distances of greater than 0.029 suggest that a threshold of 0.02 sufficiently separated the majority of species except for the genera <italic>Mayamaea</italic> (0.01) and <italic>Stephanodiscus</italic> (0.001). In comparison to other proposed barcode markers, the V4 region fares well. The rbcL barcode tested resolved only 90% of species tested at a threshold of <italic>p</italic> = 0.02 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-MacGillivary2">[20]</xref> and the 5.8S-ITS2 barcode marker proposed separated 95% of all species tested using a much higher threshold of <italic>p</italic> = 0.11 and with a much larger dataset <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Moniz2">[21]</xref>. Therefore, the V4 region performed better than rbcL and similarly to 5.8S-ITS2. The much higher threshold value seen in the 5.8S-ITS2 barcode <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-MacGillivary2">[20]</xref> suggests that it could be used as a conxurrently amplified companion marker for situations where V4 alone does not resolve species.</p>
        <p>Aside from the few problem pairs discussed above the majority of thalassiosiroid morpho-species were successfully separated by a V4 barcode through distance methods alone. Additionally, through the application of a character based analysis a better separation (97.5% vs. 96.9%) of species was achieved and a better still separation would likely result from the application of this method to the order Thalassiosirales which would likely require more sequences per species and an additional step utilizing existing software <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Sarkar2">[52]</xref> to handle the high number of similar sequences.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p>Our findings support those of Zimmermann <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">[22]</xref> that the V4 region could serve as an effective barcode for diatoms as it separated 96.9% of all tested species. Some species for which there was little separation in the V4 region were then separated by additional character analysis. We suggest that due to the ease of amplification, the extensive database of 18S sequences and resolving power, the V4 region of the 18S gene would be a suitable barcode marker for diatoms. Furthermore, we advocate a combined approach using distance methods, tree building and character based analysis for species identification of diatoms using DNA barcodes especially for cases of closely related or otherwise difficult to segregate species.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0045664.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0045664.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Strains and clones used in this study, their representative geography accession numbers and BOLD accession numbers for sequences generated in this study when available.</bold> Strains in bold are those included in the phylogenetic trees representing multiple identical sequences; accession numbers in bold indicate sequences generated in this study and strains whose taxonomic affinity is discussed in the text are indicated by †.</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We would like to thank like M Moniz and M MacGillivary for providing access to culture material and DNA, K Pauley of the Bedford Institute of Oceanography (BIO) for weekly samples, J Ehrman of Mount Allison University’s Digital Microscope Lab for SEM work and support and R Andersen and all NCMA staff for freely sharing their cultures. We are also indebted to colleagues at Mount Allison University and Laval University for support and two anonymous reviewers for positive suggestions which improved the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Smol1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smol</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birks</surname><given-names>HJB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>MSV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Climate-driven regime shifts in the biological communities of Arctic lakes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>4397</fpage>–<lpage>4402</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Armbrust1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Armbrust</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berges</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The genome of the diatom Thalassiosira pseudonana: Ecology, evolution, and metabolism</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>306</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Lundholm1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lundholm</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moestrup</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Inter- and intraspecific variation of the Pseudo-nitzschia delicatissima complex (Bacillariophyceae) illustrated by rRNA probes, morphological data and phylogenetic analyses</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>464</fpage>–<lpage>481</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Sarno1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarno</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kooistra</surname><given-names>WHCF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medlin</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Percopo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zingone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Diversity in the genus skeletonema (Bacillariophyceae) II. An assessment of the taxonomy of S. costatum-like species with the description of four new species</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-MacGillivary1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacGillivary</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczmarska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genetic differentiation within the Paralia longispina (Bacillariophyta) species complex</article-title>. <source>Botany</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Hebert1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cywinska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>deWaard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Biological identifications through DNA barcodes</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B</source> <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Hebert2">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnasingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>deWaard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Barcoding animal life: cytochrome c oxidase subunit 1 divergences among closely related species</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B</source> <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>596</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Hollingsworth1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hollingsworth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Choosing and Using a Plant DNA Barcode</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e19254</fpage> doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0019254.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Chase1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Barcoding of Plants and Fungi</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>325</volume>: <fpage>682</fpage>–<lpage>683</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Hall1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fucikova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karol</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>An assessment of proposed DNA barcodes in freshwater green algae</article-title>. <source>Algologie</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>555</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Saunders1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Applying DNA barcoding to red macroalgae: a preliminary appraisal holds promise for future applications</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc B</source> <volume>360</volume>: <fpage>1879</fpage>–<lpage>1888</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Lane1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A molecular assessment of northeast Pacific Alaria species (Laminariales, Phaeophyceae) with reference to the utility of DNA barcoding</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>634</fpage>–<lpage>648</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Lin1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>High-level diversity of dinoflagellates in the natural environment revealed by assessment of mitochondrial cox1 and cob genes for dinoflagellate DNA barcoding</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>1279</fpage>–<lpage>1290</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Litaker1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Litaker</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vandersea</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kibler</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Recognizing dinoflagellate species using ITS rDNA sequences</article-title>. <source>J of Phycol</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Lin2">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Potential utility of mitochondrial cytochrome b and its mRNA editing in resolving closely related dinoflagellates: a case study of prorocentrum (dinophyceae)</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>646</fpage>–<lpage>654</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Evans1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wortley</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>An assessment of potential diatom “barcode” genes (cox1, rbcL, 18S and ITS rDNA) and their effectiveness in determining relationships in sellaphora (Bacillariophyta)</article-title>. <source>Protist</source> <volume>158</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Kaczmarska1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kaczmarska I, Reid C, Moniz M (2007) Diatom taxonomy: morphology, molecules and barcodes, presented at Proceedings of the 1st Central-European Diatom Meeting 2007, Botanic Garden and Botanical Museum Berlin-Dahlem, FU-Berlin. 69–72.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Moniz1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moniz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczmarska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Barcoding diatoms: Is there a good marker?</article-title> <source>Mol Ecol Res</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Hamsher1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamsher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poulickova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Barcoding Diatoms: Exploring Alternatives to CO1–5P</article-title>. <source>Protist</source> <volume>162</volume>: <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>422</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-MacGillivary2">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacGillivary</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczmarska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Survey of the efficacy of a short fragment of the rbcL gene as a supplemental DNA barcode for diatoms</article-title>. <source>Journal of Euk Microbiol</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>536</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Moniz2">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moniz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczmarska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Barcoding of Diatoms: Nuclear Encoded ITS Revisited</article-title>. <source>Protist</source> <volume>161</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Zimmermann1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jahn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gemeinholzer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Barcoding diatoms: evaluation of the V4 subregion on the 18S rRNA gene including new primers and protocols</article-title>. <source>Org Divers Evol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Dunthorn1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunthorn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bunge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stoeck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Comparing the Hyper-Variable V4 and V9 Regions of the Small Subunit rDNA forAssessment of Ciliate Environmental Diversity</article-title>. <source>J Euk Microbiol</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-AmaralZettler1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Amaral-Zettler L, McCliment E, Ducklow H, Huse S (2009) A method for studying protistan diversity using massively parallel sequencing of V9 hypervariable regions of small-subunit ribosomal RNA genes. PLoS ONE 4: doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0006372.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Medlin1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Medlin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kooistra</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Methods to estimate the diversity in the marine photosynthetic protist community with illustrations from case studies: a review</article-title>. <source>Diversity</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>973</fpage>–<lpage>1014</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-DeSalle1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeSalle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siddall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The unholy trinity: taxonomy, species delimitation and DNA barcoding</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans R Soc B</source> <volume>360</volume>: <fpage>1905</fpage>–<lpage>1916</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Taylor1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Taylor H, Harris W (2012) An emergent science on the brink of irrelevance: a review of the past 8 years of DNA barcoding. Mol Ecol Res 12: doi: 10.1111/j.1755–0998.2012.03119.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Lang1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczmarska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A protocol for a single-cell pcr of diatoms from fixed samples: method validation using Ditylum brightwellii (T. West) Grunow</article-title>. <source>Diatom Res</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Iwatani1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwatani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A sequencing protocol of some DNA regions in nuclear, chloroplasticand mitochondrial genomes with an individual colony of Thalassiosira nordenskioeldii Cleve (Bacillariophyceae)</article-title>. <source>Polar Biosci</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-White1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">White TJ, Taylor J (1990) in PCR Protocols: A Guide to Methods and Applications. London: Academic Press. 315–322.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Geospiza1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Geospiza website. FinchTV 1.4.0. Geospiza, Inc.; Seattle, WA, USA. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geospiza.com/products/finchtv.shtml" xlink:type="simple">http://www.geospiza.com/products/finchtv.shtml</ext-link>. Accessed 2010 Oct. 26.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Hall2">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Symp Ser</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Tamura1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tamura K, Peterson D, Peterson N, Stecher G, Nei M, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2011) MEGA5: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods. Mol Biol Evol 28: doi: 10.1093/molbev/msr121.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Tamura2">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Estimation of the number of nucleotide substitutions when there are strong transition-transversion and G+C content biases</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>678</fpage>–<lpage>687</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Kaczmarska2">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczmarska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beaton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benoit</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogeny of selected members of the order Thalassiosirales (Bacillariophyta) and evolution of the fultoportula</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Sarkar1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Planet</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Figurski</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schierwater</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>An automated phylogenetic key for classifying homeoboxes</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogen Evol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>388</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Hasle1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heimdal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1968</year>) <article-title>Morphology and distribution of the marine centric diatom Thalassiosira antarctica Comber</article-title>. <source>J Roy Micr Soc</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Hasle2">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Examination of Thalassiosira type material: T. minima and T. delicatula (Bacillariophyceae)</article-title>. <source>Norwegian J Bot</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Alverson1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alverson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Theriot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Bridging the Rubicon: Phylogenetic analysis reveals repeated colonizations of marine and fresh waters by thalassiosiroid diatoms</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Hoppenrath1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoppenrath</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beszteri</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drebes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halliger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Beusekom</surname><given-names>JEE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Thalassiosira species (Bacillariophyceae, Thalassiosirales) in the North Sea at Helgoland (German Bight) and Sylt (North Frisian Wadden Sea) – a first approach to assessing diversity</article-title>. <source>Eur J Phycol</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Mills1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczmarska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Autogamic reproductive behavior and sex cell structure in Thalassiosira angulata (Bacillariophyta)</article-title>. <source>Bot Mar</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>430</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Hasle3">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>Some Thalassiosira species with one central process (Bacillariophyceae)</article-title>. <source>Norwegian J Bot</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Fryxell1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fryxell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hasle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>The genus Thalassiosira: some species with a modified ring of central strutted processes</article-title>. <source>Beih Nova Hedwigia</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Hajibabaei1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A minimalist barcode can identify a specimen whose DNA is degraded</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Notes</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>959</fpage>–<lpage>964</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Comeau1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Comeau A, Li W, Tremblay J-E, Carmack E, Lovejoy C (2011) Arctic Ocean microbial community structure before and after the 2007 record sea ice minimum. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic> 6: doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0027492.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Sarno2">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarno</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kooistra</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balzano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hargraves</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zingone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Diversity in the genus Skeletonema (Bacillariophyceae): III. Phylogenetic position and morphological variability of Skeletonema costatum and Skeletonema grevillei, with the description of Skeletonema ardens sp. nov</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Kaczmarska3">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczmarska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovejoy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Potvin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macgillivary</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Morphological and molecular characteristics of selected species of Minidiscus (Bacillariophyta, Thalassiosiraceae)</article-title>. <source>Eur J Phycol</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>–<lpage>475</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Syvertsen1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Syvertsen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Thalassiosira rotula and T. gravida : ecology and morphology</article-title>. <source>Nova Hedwigia</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Sar1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sunesan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lavigne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lofeudo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Thalassiosira rotula, a heterotypic synonym of Thalassiosira gravida: morphological evidence</article-title>. <source>Diatom Res</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Medlin2">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Medlin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elwood</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stickel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sogin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Morphology and genetic variation within the diatom Skeletonema costatum (Bacillariophyta): evidence for a new speices, Skeletonema pseudocostatum</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>514</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Alverson2">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alverson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolnick</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Intragenomic nucleotide polymorphism among small subunit (18s) rDNA paralogs in the diatom genus Skeletonema (Bacillariophyta)</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1248</fpage>–<lpage>1257</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0045664-Sarkar2">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Planet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desalle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>caos software for use in character-based DNA barcoding</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1256</fpage>–<lpage>1259</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>