<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-11061</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Agriculture</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Pest control</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Evolutionary systematics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Taxonomy</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Animal taxonomy</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Phylogenetics</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genetic polymorphism</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Evolutionary genetics</subject>
              <subject>Genomic evolution</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Plant science</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant pathology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Plant pests</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Population biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genetic polymorphism</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Zoology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Entomology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Plant Biology</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Taxonomic Identity of the Invasive Fruit Fly Pest, <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic>: Concordance in Morphometry and DNA Barcoding</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> Morphometry and DNA Barcoding</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Khamis</surname>
            <given-names>Fathiya M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Masiga</surname>
            <given-names>Daniel K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mohamed</surname>
            <given-names>Samira A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Salifu</surname>
            <given-names>Daisy</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>de Meyer</surname>
            <given-names>Marc</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ekesi</surname>
            <given-names>Sunday</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>African Fruit Fly Programme, International Centre of Insect Physiology and Ecology (icipe), Nairobi, Kenya</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Biochemistry and Biotechnology, Kenyatta University, Nairobi, Kenya</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Molecular Biology and Biotechnology Department, International Centre of Insect Physiology and Ecology (icipe), Nairobi, Kenya</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Royal Museum for Central Africa, Tervuren, Belgium</addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Filatov</surname>
            <given-names>Dmitry A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of Oxford, United Kingdom</addr-line>
      </aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">fkhamis@icipe.org</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: FMK SE DM MDM SAM. Performed the experiments: FMK. Analyzed the data: FMK DS SAM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SE FMK SAM DS DM MDM. Wrote the paper: FMK DM SAM DS MDM SE.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e44862</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><permissions>
        
        <copyright-holder>Khamis et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions><abstract>
        <p>In 2003, a new fruit fly pest species was recorded for the first time in Kenya and has subsequently been found in 28 countries across tropical Africa. The insect was described as <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic>, due to its rapid invasion of the African continent. In this study, the morphometry and DNA Barcoding of different populations of <italic>B. invadens</italic> distributed across the species range of tropical Africa and a sample from the pest's putative aboriginal home of Sri Lanka was investigated. Morphometry using wing veins and tibia length was used to separate <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations from other closely related <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species. The Principal component analysis yielded 15 components which correspond to the 15 morphometric measurements. The first two principal axes contributed to 90.7% of the total variance and showed partial separation of these populations. Canonical discriminant analysis indicated that only the first five canonical variates were statistically significant. The first two canonical variates contributed a total of 80.9% of the total variance clustering <italic>B. invadens</italic> with other members of the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex while distinctly separating <italic>B. correcta</italic>, <italic>B. cucurbitae</italic>, <italic>B. oleae</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic>. The largest Mahalanobis squared distance (D<sup>2</sup> = 122.9) was found to be between <italic>B. cucurbitae</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic>, while the lowest was observed between <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations against <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> (8.1) and against <italic>B. dorsalis s.s</italic> (11.4). Evolutionary history inferred by the Neighbor-Joining method clustered the <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species populations into four clusters. First cluster consisted of the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex (<italic>B. invadens</italic>, <italic>B. kandiensis and B. dorsalis s. s.</italic>), branching from the same node while the second group was paraphyletic clades of <italic>B. correcta</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic>. The last two are monophyletic clades, consisting of <italic>B. cucurbitae</italic> and <italic>B. oleae</italic>, respectively. Principal component analysis using the genetic distances confirmed the clustering inferred by the NJ tree.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group>
        <funding-statement>The authors are grateful to the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) Vienna, Austria (Contract number 16072), and the German Ministry of Economic Cooperation and Development (BMZ) through Deutsche Gesellschaft für Internationale Zusammenarbeit (GIZ) (Contract number 81132021) for grant support for this investigation. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="9"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Globally, Dacine fruit flies of the genus <italic>Bactrocera</italic> Macquart (Diptera: Tephrtitidae) are among the most important pests of fruits and vegetables <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Clarke1">[1]</xref>. In addition to the polyphagous nature of some species, several are considered highly invasive; aided by globalization of trade and poor quarantine infrastructure in the developing countries. Adults often exhibit a strong tendency for dispersal and the immature stages are readily transported to new areas via fruits movement <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-McPheron1">[2]</xref>. In Africa, a member of the genus <italic>Bactrocera</italic> was detected in 2003 at the Kenyan coast <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Lux1">[3]</xref> and later described as <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> Drew, Tsuruta &amp; White <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew1">[4]</xref>. The pest is believed to be native to Sri Lanka <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew2">[5]</xref> and has rapidly expanded its geographical range, now reported from 28 African countries including the Indian Ocean archipelago of the Comoros <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-French1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Vayssires1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Ekesi1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Mwatawala1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Ekesi2">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Abanda1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Rwomushana1">[12]</xref>. <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> is an emerging polyphagous fruit fly pest and in Africa it has been reported to attack over 43 fruit species from 23 families with mango being one of the most preferred cultivated host <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Ekesi2">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Rwomushana1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Mwatawala2">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Goergen1">[14]</xref>. Direct damage to mango due to <italic>B. invadens</italic> has been reported to range from 30–80% depending on the cultivar, locality and season <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Ekesi1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Rwomushana1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Vayssires2">[15]</xref>. In addition to the direct losses, indirect losses attributed to quarantine restrictions have been enormous. The direct and indirect damage continue to have wide reaching socio-economic implications for millions of rural and urban populations involved in the mango value chain across Africa. The pest has been described as “a devastating quarantine pest” by the Inter-African Phytosanitary Council <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-French1">[6]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Many economically important fruit fly pest species from the family Tephritidae belong to complexes of sibling species, presenting difficulties in identification, even to the experts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-VanHoudt1">[16]</xref>. <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> is believed to belong to the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> (Hendel) complex of tropical fruit flies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew1">[4]</xref>. This complex comprises of more than 75 species largely endemic to South-East Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew3">[17]</xref> with undescribed species remaining in collections <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Lawson1">[18]</xref>. Indeed, the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex of fruit fly species appear to be evolving rapidly demanding the need for closer assessment of their taxonomic identity through morphometric and genetic analysis. For example, Drew <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew1">[4]</xref> depicted different thoracic colourations of <italic>B. invadens</italic> that are morphotypes of the same pest but that has complicated the taxonomic identity of this pest.</p>
      <p>Detail review of the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex by Drew &amp; Hancock <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew3">[17]</xref> has led to considerable debate over species, and a number of published works has aimed at defining the limits of some species populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Armstrong1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Muraji1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Nakahara1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Clarke1">[1]</xref>. A study by Tan <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Tan1">[22]</xref> compared the profiles of phenylpropanoid metabolites of four <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species from the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex, that includes <italic>B. dorsalis s.s.</italic>, <italic>B. invadens</italic>, <italic>B. correcta</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic> and revealed that different profiles of phenylpropanoid ingredients in the rectal glands can be used for identification of these four species. Other studies on identification of the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex by Schutze <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Schutze1">[23]</xref> used geometric morphometric analysis of wing size and shape to discriminate species within this complex. However, recent observations by Drew <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew2">[5]</xref> emphasized the need to continue research on this complex to provide validity or otherwise, for all species in the complex, for both economic reasons and for refining the systematics of the Subfamily Dacinae. Due to the complexity of this group of fruit flies and the arrival of <italic>B. invadens</italic> into Africa, the need to undertake the inventory of the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex in Asia and make comparison with what is in Africa becomes important in order to redefine this complex.</p>
      <p>Morphometric analyses have been a useful technique in detecting morphological differences among organisms to distinguish closely related species including fruit flies, justify synonymies, demonstrate morphological variation along altitudinal or geographical gradients and propose new species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Reyment1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Perero1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Willig1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-McNamee1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Selivon1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Adsavakulchai1">[29]</xref>. Indeed, in some frugivorous tephritid fruit fly species, diagnostic morphological characters for the identification of adult flies are now available <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Adsavakulchai1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-DeMeyer1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew4">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew2">[5]</xref>. However, morphological tools present some limitations, mainly due to high homoplasy in most morphological characters and the existence of cryptic species groups across the family. Thus, the classification of Tephritids to the species level based on adult morphology alone is sometimes unreliable <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Armstrong2">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-DeMeyer2">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-McPheron2">[34]</xref>. These limitations have led several taxonomists and quarantine officials alike to seek viable alternative ways of fruit fly identification including the use of molecular markers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Sonvinco1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Armstrong2">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Morrow1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Barr1">[37]</xref>. Recently, the current molecular tool of choice is DNA Barcoding, which is a system that employs sequence diversity in short, standardized gene regions aiding in identification of species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Ratnasingham1">[38]</xref>. This standardized method for identifications of species focuses sequencing efforts on one target gene, cytochrome c oxidase subunit I (COI) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hebert1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hebert2">[40]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The main objective of our study was to establish whether <italic>B. invadens</italic> individuals collected from Africa could be distinguished from other Asian <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species using both multivariate morphometric analysis and molecular methods. Because <italic>B. invadens</italic> belongs to a complex, we believe that information generated from this investigation should help clarify its identity, resolve its placement in the right phylogeny, ease quarantine restrictions and potentially contribute to better management of the pest if sterile insect technique or eradication from particular locality or region becomes an option.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The PCA yielded 15 components which correspond to the 15 morphometric measurements. Bartlett χ tests indicated that only the first 13 components were statistically significant. Projection of the morphometric data of the <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species on the first two principal axes showed a partial separation of these populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g001">Figure 1</xref>). The first two principal components contributed to 90.7% of the total variance (PC1 = 86.3% and PC2 = 4.4%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0044862-t001">Table 1</xref>). The third, fourth and fifth components contributed 2.3%, 2.0% and 1.7%, respectively, but did not improve separation of the populations. <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> populations and the other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species belonging to the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex could not be separated by PCA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g001">Figure 1</xref>). However, the first two principal components separated <italic>B. cucurbitae</italic>, <italic>B. oleae</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic> into distinct groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Contributions or loadings of the individual measurements indicate that PC1 represented the overall size, thus all loadings on PC1 are negative and within a small range (−0.34 to −0.15). PC2 is a contrast between vein 3, 4, 5, 6, 14 and tibia length with negative coefficients and the rest of the variables with positive coefficients hence PC2 is associated with wing shape (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0044862-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0044862-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Projection of the wing and tibia data of <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> compared with the other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species on the first two principal components.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0044862-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
          <title>Eigen values and coefficients (loadings) of the first two principal components (PC1 and PC2) for the log-transformed wing measurements data of the fruit fly populations.</title>
        </caption><alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0044862-t001-1" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PC1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PC2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Proportion of variance</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86.30%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.40%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Eigen value</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.046 0.002</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Loadings</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein1(a_m)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.24</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein2 (a_b)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.21</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein3 (b_c)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.25</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.05</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein4 (d_e)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.34</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.73</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein5 (e_f)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.28</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.21</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein6 (f_g)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.31</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.09</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein7 (g_h)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.23</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein8 (h_i)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.29</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein9 (i_e)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.24</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein10 (c_j)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.29</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.27</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein11 (d_k)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.23</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein12 (i_l)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.15</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein13 (j_k)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.24</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein14 (n_o)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.26</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.01</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tibia length</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.26</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.04</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives></table-wrap>
      <p>Tests for dimensionality for the canonical discriminant analysis revealed that only the first five canonical variates were statistically significant. Projection of the data on the first two canonical variate axes showed a better pattern of separation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g002">Figure 2</xref>) compared with PCA. The first two canonical variates contributed a total of 80.9% (CV1 = 52.5% and CV2 = 28.4%) of the total variance. The third, fourth and fifth canonical variates contributed 9.3%, 5.7% and 2.9% of the total variance, respectively. The standardized canonical coefficients (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0044862-t002">Table 2</xref>) showed that CV1 is strongly dominated by positive correlation with vein4 and tibia length while strongly negatively correlated with vein1. CV2 is dominated by positive correlation with vein 14 and negative correlation with vein 3 and vein 10. <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> populations and the other <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> species complex clustered together while <italic>B. correcta</italic>, <italic>B. cucurbitae</italic>, <italic>B. oleae</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic> distinctly separated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0044862-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Projection of the wing and tibia data of <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> compared with other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species on the first two canonical variates.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0044862-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
          <title>Raw and standardized canonical coefficients for the canonical discriminant analysis on log-transformed wing measurements data for the fruit fly populations.</title>
        </caption><alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0044862-t002-2" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Raw coefficients</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Standardised coefficients</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CV1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CV2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CV1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CV2</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein1(a_m)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−46.32</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.75</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.71</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein2 (a_b)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−16.96</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−18.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.63</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.67</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein3 (b_c)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.87</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−38.17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.26</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein4 (d_e)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.84</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.95</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.89</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein5 (e_f)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.00</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.93</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein6 (f_g)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.56</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−19.66</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.39</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.90</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein7 (g_h)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.82</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.65</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein8 (h_i)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−12.93</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−16.33</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.59</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.74</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein9 (i_e)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.50</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.49</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein10 (c_j)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.01</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−22.88</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.10</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.13</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein11 (d_k)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−12.44</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−22.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.46</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.82</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein12 (i_l)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−22.96</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.55</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.72</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein13 (j_k)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.47</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.96</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.32</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein14 (n_o)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.42</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tibia length</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.65</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.56</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives></table-wrap>
      <p>Mahalanobis distances used to compare morphometric divergence among populations group centroids showed a large degree of segregation in populations outside the <italic>B. dosrsalis</italic> complex and little interpopulation variability within the complex. For example, the largest Mahalanobis squared distance (D<sup>2</sup> = 122.9) was found to be between <italic>B. cucurbitae</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic>, followed by <italic>B. oleae</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic> (111.8), <italic>B. correcta</italic> and <italic>B. curcubitae</italic> (88.4), and <italic>B. cucurbiate</italic> and <italic>B. oleae</italic> (68) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0044862-t003">Table 3</xref>). Comparison of <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations against <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> sample gave a square distance of 11.4. The smallest distance was between the <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations and <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> (8.1).</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0044862-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
          <title>Mahalanobis Squared Distances (D<sup>2</sup>) between clusters representing the species/populations of <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> and other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species.</title>
        </caption><alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0044862-t003-3" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Species</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcor</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcu</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bdo</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Binvadens</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bka</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bole</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bzo</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcor</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcu</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bdo</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Binvadens</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bka</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bole</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bzo</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label/>
            <p>Bcor – <italic>B. correcta</italic>, Bcu – <italic>B. cucurbitae</italic>, Bdo – <italic>B. dorsalis</italic>, Binvadens – <italic>B. invadens</italic>, Bka – <italic>B. kandiensis</italic>, Bole – <italic>B. oleae</italic> and Bzo – <italic>B. zonata</italic>.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <p>The first phylogenetic tree was derived considering only the species belonging to the <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis</italic> complex, the <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations from Kenya, Uganda, Zaria and Sri Lanka, <italic>B. dorsalis s.s.</italic> and <italic>B. kandiensis</italic>. The optimal tree with the sum of branch length = 0.14854468 is as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g003">Figure 3</xref>. The percentage of replicate trees in which the associated taxa clustered together in the bootstrap test (1000 replicates) are shown next to the branches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Felsenstein1">[41]</xref>. The tree is drawn to scale, with branch lengths in the same units as those of the evolutionary distances used to infer the phylogenetic tree. The evolutionary distances were computed using the Kimura 2-parameter method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Kimura1">[42]</xref> and are in the units of the number of base substitutions per site. The analysis involved 62 nucleotide sequences. Codon positions included were 1st+2nd+3rd+Noncoding. All positions containing gaps and missing data were eliminated from the dataset (Complete deletion option). There were a total of 658 positions in the final dataset. The tree separated the <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations into two clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g003">Figure 3</xref>). One cluster consisted of <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations from Kenya, Uganda, Zaria and Sri Lanka with a separate branch consisting of <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> population. The second cluster was dominated by <italic>B. invadens</italic> individuals from Sri Lanka that were grouped with <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0044862-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g003</object-id>
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Evolutionary relationships between <italic>Bactocera invadens</italic> populations, <italic>B. dorsalis s.s</italic> and <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> as inferred using Neighbour-Joining method by Mega 5 program (Tamura <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011).</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The second tree was constructed for all the <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species for which DNA barcodes have been generated in this study. The optimal tree with the sum of branch length = 0.49981941 is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g004">Figure 4</xref>. The percentage of replicate trees in which the associated taxa clustered together in the bootstrap test (1000 replicates) are shown next to the branches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Felsenstein1">[41]</xref>. The tree is drawn to scale, with branch lengths in the same units as those of the evolutionary distances used to infer the phylogenetic tree. The evolutionary distances were computed using the Kimura 2-parameter method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Kimura1">[42]</xref> and are in the units of the number of base substitutions per site. The analysis involved 74 nucleotide sequences. Codon positions included were 1st+2nd+3rd+Noncoding. All positions containing gaps and missing data were eliminated. There were a total of 658 positions in the final dataset. This analysis clustered the <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species populations into four groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g004">Figure 4</xref>). The first group had the clustering of the <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis</italic> species complex (<italic>B. invadens</italic>, <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> and <italic>B. dorsalis sensu stricto</italic>), branching from the same node. The second group consisted of <italic>B. correcta</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic> branching from the same node. While the last two groups are clades, consisting of <italic>B. cucurbitae</italic> and <italic>B. oleae</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0044862-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g004</object-id>
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Evolutionary relationships between <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations and other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species included in the study as inferred using Neighbour-Joining method by Mega 5 program (Tamura <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011).</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The table of genetic distances (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0044862-t004">Table 4</xref>) was constructed by Mega 5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Tamura1">[43]</xref> using the Kimura 2-parameter model. The output was used to generate principal component plots, using GenAlEx 6.41 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Peakall1">[44]</xref>. In this analysis of the <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species using principal coordinate analysis (PCA), the first two axes explained 59.38% of the variation (the first axis 34.93%, and the second axis 24.46%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g005">Figure 5</xref>). The PCA separated the seven species into four distinct clusters. A cluster was occupied by the species belonging to the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex, a cluster consisting of <italic>B. correcta</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic>, <italic>B. cucurbiate</italic> on its own cluster and likewise, <italic>B. oleae</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g005">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0044862-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g005</object-id>
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Plots of the principal coordinate analysis (PCA) from the covariance matrix with data standardization calculated using GenAlEx for the <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0044862-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
          <title>Estimates of Evolutionary Divergence over Sequence Pairs between Groups generated by Mega 5 program (Tamura <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011).</title>
        </caption><alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0044862-t004-4" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Species</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcu</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcor</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bzo</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Binvadens</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bka</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bdo</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bole</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcu</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcor</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.181</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bzo</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.183</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.076</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Binvadens</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.176</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.098</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.105</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bka</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.187</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.099</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.101</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.057</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bdo</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.167</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.091</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.100</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.025</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bole</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.194</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.175</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.185</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.177</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.175</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt102">
            <label/>
            <p>Bcor – <italic>B. correcta</italic>, Bcu – <italic>B. cucurbitae</italic>, Bdo – <italic>B. dorsalis</italic>, Binvadens – <italic>B. invadens</italic>, Bka – <italic>B. kandiensis</italic>, Bole – <italic>B. oleae</italic> and Bzo – <italic>B. zonata</italic>.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Among tephritid fruit flies, morphometric analysis has been tested and successfully used for determining differences among species of the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex and to analyse variability among populations of <italic>Anastrepha fraterculus</italic> (Wiedemann) (Diptera: Tephritidae) collected from different host plants using aculeus, wing and head (frontal plate) characters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Perero1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Selivon1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Adsavakulchai1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hernandezortiz1">[45]</xref>. Our results showed that <italic>B. invadens</italic> can be morphometrically separated from other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species (<italic>B. correcta, B. cucurbitae, B. oleae</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic>) used in this study with respect to wing morphology and the tibia length. However, the degree of morphological variation with respect to <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations and <italic>B. dorsalis s. s.</italic> used in this study was extremely low (Mahalanobis distance = 11.4). This is in line with the observations of Drew <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew1">[4]</xref> who classified <italic>B. invadens</italic> as a member of the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex in possessing a very narrow coastal band and anal streak in addition to other abdominal and thoracic features. In a later study, Drew <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew2">[5]</xref> using aedeagus length was able to further discriminate between populations of <italic>B. invadens</italic> from those of <italic>B. carambolae</italic>, <italic>B. dorsalis</italic>, <italic>B. papayae</italic> and <italic>B. philippinensis</italic>. In our study, though the Sri Lankan populations of <italic>B. invadens</italic> were associated with different ecological and biogeographical conditions (i.e. different climate, altitude, vegetational community, etc.) (S.A. Mohamed et al., unpublished data), they showed similar morphology to the African samples, distinct from the other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species but clustering with the <italic>B. dorsalis s.s.</italic> and supports the fact that the two species are closely related. In another study, Tan <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Tan1">[22]</xref> using chemoecological analysis of phenylpropanoid volatiles in male rectal pheromone gland, showed that males of laboratory-raised <italic>B. invadens</italic> accumulated two metabolites, 2-allyl-4,5-dimethoxyphenol (DMP) and (<italic>E</italic>)-coniferyl alcohol (E-CF) similar to <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> in almost equal quantities, in the rectal sac. On the basis of this finding, the authors concluded that the two pest species are biologically identical. Ongoing mating compatibility studies between <italic>B. invadens</italic> and <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> should further shed more light as to whether the two species belong to the same clade.</p>
      <p>In our studies, we also observed that the Mahalanobis distance between <italic>B. invadens</italic> and <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> was short (8.1) indicating that the two species are closely related. Drew <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew1">[4]</xref> in the description of <italic>B. invadens</italic> stated that this exotic species in Africa was morphologically similar to <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> based on wing and abdominal characters. The only differentiating characters reported by Drew <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew1">[4]</xref> was femora that was entirely fulvous in <italic>B. invadens</italic> and the variation in microtrichia pattern in the basal area of cell br, above cell bm. In a more recent study Drew <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew2">[5]</xref> did not find any difference in the thorax length between <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> (3.10 mm) and <italic>B. invadens</italic> (3.10 mm); wing length, <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> (6.18 mm) and <italic>B. invadens</italic> (6.21 mm); wing vein, <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> (2.25 mm) and <italic>B. invadens</italic> (2.25 mm); and hind tibia length, <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> (1.86 mm) and <italic>B. invadens</italic> (1.85 mm). The results of our findings therefore, concur with those of Drew <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Drew2">[5]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Although morphological characters are primarily used to define species, the genetic and behavioural boundaries of species need to be understood and elucidated. This is particularly true for groups of economically important species such as those in the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex. In this regard, DNA barcoding that involves retrieval of a standard region of mitochondrial gene, Cytochrome c oxidase 1 (CO1) at its 5′ end containing ≈650 base pairs gene (acting as barcode) for identification and delineation of all animal life <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hebert1">[39]</xref> has shown to be potentially a useful tool to separate members of Tephritid groups of fruit flies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-VanHoudt1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Armstrong3">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Virgilio1">[47]</xref>. The use of COI sequences together with quantitative support in terms of bootstraps and divergence values provides a better resolution for fruit flies identification than was possible with other methods like the PCR-RFLP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Armstrong3">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Barr2">[48]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The use of DNA barcodes utilizing the CO1 gene has enabled the interpretation of the relationship between <italic>B. invadens</italic> and the other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species. In this study, the smallest genetic distance (0.025) was detected between populations of <italic>B. invadens</italic> and <italic>B. dorsalis</italic>, <italic>B. invadens</italic> and <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> (0.057) and <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> and <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> (0.06). This is a typical scenario of divergences between congeneric species which are normally higher than within species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hebert1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hebert2">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Virgilio1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Barr3">[49]</xref>. Similar studies by Tan <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Tan1">[22]</xref> using COI gene clustered <italic>B. invadens</italic> and <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> in the same branch. The molecular findings in the current study further substantiate our morphometric data obtained above, in which the Canonical variate plots separated <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations from all the other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species but matched <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations with <italic>B. dorsalis s.s.</italic> and <italic>B. kandiensis</italic>. This is also evident in the PCA plots using the genetic distances, where <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations clustered with the <italic>B. dorsalis s.s.</italic> and <italic>B. kandiensis</italic>.</p>
      <p>Although we recorded some levels of concordance between the molecular and the morphometric results, large divergence at micro-geographic scale was observed among populations of <italic>B. invadens</italic>. For instance, some individuals belonging to <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations of Sri Lanka clustered together with <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> in the NJ trees generated in the study. Therefore, the NJ tree did not fully discriminate the populations belonging to the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex. This is also true in the study by Armstrong and Ball <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Armstrong3">[46]</xref> where the COI gene could not confidently separate some of the species within the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex, and hence, have suggested the use of additional gene regions to overcome this limitation.</p>
      <p>Some representatives of the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex are extremely polyphagous and highly invasive pests, thus it is one of the most important pest species complexes in world agriculture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Clarke1">[1]</xref>. Because of their economic and quarantine importance, species-level taxonomic work and diagnostics in the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex is relatively advanced <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Muraji2">[50]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Muraji1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Nakahara1">[21]</xref>, but much effort in this regard is still required. Since the primary goal of DNA barcoding is to develop an accurate, rapid, cost-effective, and universally accessible DNA-based system for species identifications <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hebert1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hebert2">[40]</xref>, this method could be adopted as a standard method of identification of invasive alien species that pose a high risk on the global economy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Armstrong3">[46]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The use of DNA barcoding in conjunction with other molecular diagnostic tools, for biosecurity will bridge the limitations of previous molecular tools such as inconsistency in technology use, and finite taxas in some of the invasive species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Armstrong3">[46]</xref>. Several studies have demonstrated the effectiveness of DNA barcoding in different insect groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hebert1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hebert2">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hebert3">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Smith1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Armstrong3">[46]</xref>. These projects have shown that &gt;95% of species possess unique COI barcode sequences; thus species-level identifications are regularly attained <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Hajibabaei1">[53]</xref>. Although DNA barcoding is a current molecular tool of choice and to a certain extent can provide answers to molecular identification (e.g. DNA from incomplete libraries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Virgilio1">[47]</xref>), conclusive phylogeny should include an array of molecular diagnostic tools. Our study has contributed to unraveling the identity of <italic>B. invadens</italic>, a finding which could facilitate its placement in the right phylogeny, potentially easing quarantine restrictions and improvement in the management of this invasive pest. Nevertheless, divergent views still exist. Hence additional studies on the pest chemoecology, behaviour, morphometry and genetics are warranted.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Ethics Statement</title>
        <p>No specific permits were required for the described field studies.</p>
        <p>No specific permissions were required for these locations/activities.</p>
        <p>The locations are not privately-owned or protected in any way.</p>
        <p>The field studies did not involve endangered or protected species.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Sample collection</title>
        <p>Male samples of <italic>B. invadens</italic> were collected (using Methyl eugenol baited traps) from different countries in Africa and South East Asia. The collected insects were preserved in ethanol (70% for morphometric analysis and 95% for DNA analysis). In Africa, the sampling area included regions from the East to West Africa (Data not included). Some representative samples included in the study are from East Africa: from Kenya (Nguruman) and Uganda (Kawanda) and a sample from West Africa, Zaria, Nigeria (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0044862-t005">Table 5</xref>). The South East Asian sample is represented by Sri Lanka (the presumed aboriginal home of <italic>B. invadens</italic>). Also included in this study, were other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species belonging to the <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> species complex namely <italic>B. dorsalis sensu stricto</italic> (Hendel) (Hawaii) and <italic>B. kandiensis</italic> (Drew &amp; Hancock) (Sri Lanka). Other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species considered in the study that do not belong to <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex were: <italic>B. correcta</italic> (Bezzi) (India), <italic>B. cucurbitae</italic> (Coquillett) (Kenya), <italic>B. oleae</italic> Gmelin (Kenya) and <italic>B. zonata</italic> (Saunders) (Mauritius). The specimens were identified by M.K. Billah (Department of Zoology, University of Ghana, Legon).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0044862-t005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption>
            <title>Key of the veins used in morphometrics analysis.</title>
          </caption><alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0044862-t005-5" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Representation</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">a_m</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wing length</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">a_b</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Humeral break – Subcostal break</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">b_c</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Subcostal break – vein R1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">d_e</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">r – m</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">e_f</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Upper length of dm-cell</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">f_g</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Basal height of dm-cell</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 7</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">g_h</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lower length of dm-cell</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 8</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">h_i</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Apical height of dm-cell</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">i_e</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Upper length of dm-cell</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 10</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">c_j</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vein R1 – Vein R2+3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 11</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">d_k</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R<sub>4+5</sub></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 12</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">i_l</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 13</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">J_k</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vein 14</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n_o</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wing width</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Morphometry</title>
        <p>Specimens of the different <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species were prepared following the general procedure for slide preparation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Billah1">[54]</xref> with modifications according to the needs or state of the specimen. Images of the right wing and right hind tibia from the slide mounted specimens were captured using video microscopy – Leica MZ 125 Microscope, fitted with Toshiba 3CCD camera using the Auto Montage software (Syncroscopy, Synoptics group, 2004) at magnification ×25 for total length and width of the wing, ×50 for the wing veins and ×63 for the tibia. Measurements were taken by the program Image-Pro® Plus version 4.1 for Windows™ (Media Cybernetics, 1999) and the data exported directly to an Excel data sheet. For all parts, measurements were taken in triplicate (to an accuracy of 0.001 mm). Fourteen wing distances between 15 selected landmarks on the wing were computed to characterize the shape and size of the wings for differentiation. These distances are: the Humeral break – Subcostal break, Subcostal break – vein R1, r – m, Upper length of dm-cell, Basal height of dm-cell, Lower length of dm-cell, Apical height of dm-cell, Vein R1 – Vein R2+3, R<sub>4+5</sub>, M, C, the wing length and width, and tibia length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g006">Figure 6</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0044862-g007">7</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0044862-t005">Table 5</xref>). Voucher specimens of all insects and slides are deposited at the Biosystematics Unit of the International Centre of Insect physiology and Ecology (<italic>icipe</italic>), Nairobi, Kenya.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0044862-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Wing showing points of reading taken for morphometric analysis.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0044862-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Tibia points of measurement (measurement taken from point A to point B).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>DNA extraction and PCR</title>
        <p>The insects used for DNA barcoding were photographed laterally, dorsally and ventrally and appropriately labeled prior to DNA extraction. DNA from whole insects was extracted using the Qiagen DNeasy® Blood and Tissue Kit (Qiagen, GmbH-Hilden, Germany) as per manufacturer's instructions. The extracted DNA was stored at −20°C until required for amplification. PCR was carried out using universal primers, Forward primer (LCO1490) <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GGTCAACAAATCATAAAGATATTGG-3′</named-content> and reverse primer (HCO2198) <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-TAAACTTCAGGGTGACCAAAAAATCA-3′</named-content> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Folmer1">[55]</xref> to amplify a 658 bp fragment of the COI gene. The PCR amplification was carried out in a 20 µl volume containing 1× reaction Buffer, 200 µm of dNTP mix, 0.4 pmol/µl of each primer, 2.5 mM, MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 unit <italic>Taq</italic> DNA polymerase (Genescript) and 1 ng DNA template. Standard cycling conditions of 5 min at 94°C, then 35 cycles of 30 s at 94°C, 1 min at annealing temperature of 45°C and 1 min at 72°C, followed by a final elongation step of 5 min at 72°C were used. The products were purified using QIAquick PCR purification kit (Qiagen, GmbH-Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer's instructions and subsequently sequenced in both directions using ABI 3700 genetic analyzers. The COI sequences were submitted to the Barcode of Life database (BOLD) and deposited in GenBank (Accession numbers are found in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0044862-t006">Table 6</xref>). The DNA voucher specimens are kept in <italic>icipe</italic> Molecular biology and biotechnology department.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0044862-t006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption>
            <title>Collection data of <italic>B. invadens</italic> populations and other <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species used in this study.</title>
          </caption><alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0044862-t006-6" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0044862.t006" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Region/Country</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample name</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample site</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Collection</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coordinates</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GenBank Accession numbers</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Africa</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kenya</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ke</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nguruman</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ME</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">01°48′32S, 036°03′35E</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JQ692820, JQ692701, JQ692801, JQ692845, JQ692688, JQ692664, JQ692811, JQ692781, JQ692805, JQ692780</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Uganda</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ug</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kawanda</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ME</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">00°49′52S, 031°55′05″E</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JQ692633,JQ692709, JQ692824, JQ692854, JQ692650, JQ692794, JQ692844, JQ692752, JQ692681, JQ692841</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nigeria</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nig</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zaria</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ME</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11°06′N, 07°42′E</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JQ692727, JQ692723, JQ692698, JQ692742, JQ692867, JQ692816, JQ692825, JQ692719, JQ692731, JQ692636, JQ692684, JQ692812</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asia</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sri Lanka</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SL</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ranbukpitiya</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tropical almond</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JQ692669, JQ692818, JQ692757, JQ692661, JQ692741, JQ692737, JQ692708, JQ692838, JQ692722, JQ692639, JQ692764, JQ692835</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Bactocera correcta</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcor</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sri Lanka-Anuradhapura</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ME</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">08°21′0″N, 080°23′1″E</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JQ692856,JQ692753, JQ692641, JQ692784, JQ692787</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Bactrocera cucurbitae</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcu</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kenya-Nairobi</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LT &amp; Cu Lure</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">01°13′952S, 036°51′314E</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JQ692734, JQ692803, JQ692772, JQ692685, JQ692740</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis s.s</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bdo</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hawaii</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Laboratory reared</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JQ692775, JQ692829, JQ692694, JQ692790, JQ692747, JQ692706, JQ692864, JQ692758, JQ692678</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Bactrocera kandiensis</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bka</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sri Lanka-Kandy</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ME</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">07°16′753N, 80°35′731E</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JQ692767, JQ692836, JQ692837, JQ692692, JQ692806, JQ692673, JQ692813, JQ692674, JQ692686</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bole</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kenya-Burguret forest</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ex-fruits (olives)</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">00°06′720S, 37°02′342E</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JQ692833, JQ692687, JQ692778, JQ692762, JQ692808</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Bactrocera zonata</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bzo</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mauritius</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Laboratory reared</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JQ692749, JQ692662, JQ692819, JQ692799, JQ692705</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Data analysis</title>
        <sec id="s4e1">
          <title>Morphometry</title>
          <p>Principal component analysis (PCA), a multivariate statistical procedure commonly used to reveal patterns in measured correlated variables, was used to determine if there was any clustering in the fruit fly species populations based on the wing veins measurements. The data were transformed (log<sub>10</sub>) prior to PCA to stabilize the variance of the measured variables and thus give the variables approximately equal weights in the PCA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Baxter1">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Sokal1">[57]</xref>. Since PCA is inherently a single-group procedure and is not guaranteed to find group differences even if they exist, the log-transformed morphometric data were also subjected to canonical discriminant analysis, a method for analyzing group structure in multivariate data. Bartlett's χ<sup>2</sup> was used to test for significance of principal components and canonical variates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Bartlett1">[58]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Bartlett2">[59]</xref>. Mahalanobis squared distances between fruit fly species were obtained as a measure of distance between species based on means, variances and covariances <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Zar1">[60]</xref>. The analyses were performed using R 2.13.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-R1">[61]</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4e2">
          <title>COI sequence data analysis</title>
          <p>Sequences were assembled and edited using Chromas version 2.13 (Technelysium Pty ltd, Queensland, Australia), and aligned using ClustalX version 1.81 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Thompson1">[62]</xref>. Phylogenetic and molecular evolutionary analyses were conducted using MEGA version 5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Tamura1">[43]</xref> and a Neighbour-joining tree constructed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Saitou1">[63]</xref> with bootstrapping and using the Kimura 2 distance matrix <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Kimura1">[42]</xref>. A table of between species distances was also constructed using MEGA version 5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Tamura1">[43]</xref>. This table of distances was used to generate the principal component plots using GenAlEx 6.41 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0044862-Peakall1">[44]</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank J. Gitau for slides preparation. We would also like to acknowledge Nathalie Erbout for her assistance in the morphometric work. We are also grateful to numerous partners of the African Fruit Fly Program for providing insects from Africa and other parts of the world.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Clarke1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Invasive phytophagous pests arising through a recent evolutionary radiation: the <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis</italic> complex of fruit flies</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Entomology</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-McPheron1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McPheron BA, Steck GJ (1996) Fruit Fly Pests: A world assessment of their biology and management. St Lucie Press, Delray Beach, FL.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Lux1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lux</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manrakhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Billah</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A New Invasive Fruit Fly Species from the <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis</italic> (Hendel) Group Detected in East Africa</article-title>. <source>Insect Science and Its Application</source> <volume>23</volume><supplement>(4)</supplement>:<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Drew1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>RAI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuruta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A new species of pest fruit fly (Diptera: Tephritidae: Dacinae) from Sri Lanka and Africa</article-title>. <source>African Entomology</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Drew2">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>RAI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halcoop</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bridging the morphological and biological species concepts: studies on the <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis</italic> (Hendel) complex (Diptera: Tephritidae: Dacinae) in South-east Asia</article-title>. <source>Biological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-French1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">French C (2005) The new invasive <italic>Bactrocera species</italic>. pp. 19–20 <italic>in Insect Pest Control Newsletter</italic>, <italic>No. 65</italic>. International Atomic Energy Agency, Vienna, Austria.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Vayssires1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vayssières</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goergen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lokossou</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dossa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akponon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A new <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species in Benin among mango fruit fly (Diptera: Tephritidae) species</article-title>. <source>Fruits</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>377</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Ekesi1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekesi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nderitu</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rwomushana</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Field infestation, life history and demographic parameters of the fruit fly <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae) in Africa</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>386</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Mwatawala1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mwatawala</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Makundi</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maerere</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name> (<year>2006a</year>) <article-title>Biodiversity of fruit flies (Diptera, Tephritidae) at orchards in different agro-ecological zones of the Morogoro region, Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Fruits</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Ekesi2">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ekesi S, Billah MK (2007) A field guide to the management of economically important tephritid fruit flies in Africa. ICIPE Science Press, Nairobi, Kenya.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Abanda1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abanda</surname><given-names>F-XN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quilici</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vayssiéres</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kouodiekong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Inventory of fruit flies species on guava in the area of Yaounde, Cameroon</article-title>. <source>Fruits</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Rwomushana1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rwomushana</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ekesi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogol</surname><given-names>CKPO</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Host plant and host plant preference studies for <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae) in Kenya, a new invasive fruit fly species in Africa</article-title>. <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Mwatawala2">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mwatawala</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Makundi</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maerere</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Host range and distribution of fruit-infesting pestiferous fruit flies (Diptera, Tephritidae) in selected areas of Central Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research</source> <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Goergen1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goergen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vayssières</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gnanvossou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tindo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title><italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae), a new invasive fruit fly pest for the Afrotropical region: Host plant range and distribution in west and central Africa</article-title>. <source>Entomological Society of America</source> <volume>40</volume><supplement>(4)</supplement>:<fpage>844</fpage>–<lpage>854</lpage> 2011. DOI: 10.1603/EN11017.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Vayssires2">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vayssières</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Korie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayegnon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Correlation of fruit fly (Diptera Tephritidae) infestation of major mango cultivars in Borgou (Benin) with abiotic and biotic factors and assessment of damage</article-title>. <source>Crop protection</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-VanHoudt1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Houdt</surname><given-names>JKJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breman</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Virgilio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Recovering full DNA barcodes from natural history collections of Tephritid fruitflies (Tephritidae, Diptera) using mini barcodes</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Drew3">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>RAI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis</italic> complex of fruit flies (Diptera: Tephritidae: Dacinae) in Asia</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research, Supplement Series</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Lawson1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Lawson AE, McGuire DJ, Yeates DK, Drew RAI, Clarke AR (2003) <italic>Dorsalis</italic>: an interactive identification tool to fruit flies of the <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis</italic> complex. CD-ROM Publication, Griffith University, Brisbane, Australia.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Armstrong1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Armstrong KF, Cameron CM (2000) Species identification of tephritids across a broad taxonomic range. In: Tan KH, ed. Area-wide control of fruit flies and other insect pests. London: CABI, 703–710.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Muraji1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muraji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakahara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Discrimination among pest species of <italic>Bactrocera</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae) based on PCR-RFLP of the mitochrondrial DNA</article-title>. <source>Applied Entomology and Zoology</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>446</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Nakahara1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakahara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaneda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muraji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Identification of <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis</italic> complex species (Diptara: Tephritidae) by PCR-RFLP analysis. II.Astudy of genetic variation in <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> complex (Philippines population) and <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> (Taiwan population)</article-title>. <source>Res Bull Plant Prot Serv Jpn</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Tan1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tan KH, Tokushima I, Ono H, Nishida R (2010) Comparison of phenylpropanoid volatiles in male rectal pheromone gland after methyl eugenol consumption, and molecular phylogenetic relationship of four global pest fruit fly species: <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic>, <italic>B. dorsalis</italic>, <italic>B. correcta</italic> and <italic>B. zonata</italic>. Chemoecology, Springer. DOI 10.1007/s00049-010-0063-1.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Schutze1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schutze</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jessup</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Wing shape as a potential discriminator of morphologically similar pest taxa within the <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis</italic> species complex (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research</source> <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage> Doi:10.1017/S0007485311000423.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Reyment1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Reyment RA, Blackith RE, Campbell NA (1984) Multivariate morphometrics (second edition). Academic Press, London.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Perero1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Perero JG, Nasca AJ, Stilinovic D (1984) Introducción a un estudio morfológico-taxonómico de especímenes de <italic>Anastrepha fraterculus</italic> Wiedemann colectados sobre distintos hospederos en la Provincia de Tucumán. pp. 421–455 in Anales II Congreso Internacional de Biomatemáticas, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Buenos Aires, Argentina.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Willig1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willig</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colbert</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Assessment of morphometric variation in natural populations: the inadequacy of the univariate approach</article-title>. <source>Systematic Zoology</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-McNamee1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McNamee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dytham</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Morphometric discrimination of the species <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (Meigen) and <italic>D. simulans</italic> (Sturtevant) (Diptera: Drosophilidae)</article-title>. <source>Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Selivon1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Selivon D (1996) <italic>Estudo sobre a diferenciaçâo populacional em</italic> Anastrepha fraterculus <italic>(Wiedemann) (Diptera: Tephritidae)</italic>. 137 pp. PhD thesis (unpublished), Instituto de Biociencias, Universidade de Sâo Paulo, Brazil.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Adsavakulchai1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adsavakulchai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baimai</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prachyabrued</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grote</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lertlum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Morphometric study for identification of the <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis</italic> complex (Diptera: Tephritidae) using wing image analysis</article-title>. <source>Biotropica</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-DeMeyer1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships within the fruit fly genus <italic>Ceratitis</italic> MacLeay (Diptera: Tephritidae), derived from morphological and host plant evidence</article-title>. <source>Insect Systematics and Evolution</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Drew4">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>RAI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dorji</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romig</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loday</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Attractiveness of various combinations of colors and shapes to females and males of <italic>Bactrocera minax</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae) in a commercial mandarin grove in Bhutan</article-title>. <source>Journal of Economic Entomology</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>1651</fpage>–<lpage>1656</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Armstrong2">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frampton</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Fruit fly (Diptera: Tephritidae) species identification: a rapid molecular diagnostic technique for quarantine application</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-DeMeyer2">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Systematic revision of the subgenus <italic>Ceratitis</italic> MacLeay <italic>s. s</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>. <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>467</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-McPheron2">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McPheron BA (2000) Population genetics and cryptic species. In Tan, K.-H., (Ed). Area wide control of fruit flies and other insect pests. Pernerbit Universiti sains Malaysia, Peneng, p. 483–490, 782p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Sonvinco1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonvinco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manso</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quesada-Allue</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Discrimination between the immature stages of <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> and <italic>Anastrepha fraterculus</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae) populations by random amplified polymorphic DNA polymerase chain reactiopn</article-title>. <source>Journal of Economic Entomology</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>1208</fpage>–<lpage>1212</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Morrow1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Congdon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeates</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frommer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Close genetic similarity between two sympatric species of tephritid fruit fly reproductively isolated by mating time</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>899</fpage>–<lpage>910</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Barr1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masiga</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kibogo</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Molecular diagnostics of economically important <italic>Ceratitis</italic> fruit fly species (Diptera: Tephritidae) in Africa using PCR and RFLP analyses</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>521</lpage> DOI: 10.1079/BER2006452.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Ratnasingham1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnasingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>BOLD: The Barcode of Life Data System (www.barcodinglife.org)</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Notes</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Hebert1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cywinska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Waard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2003a</year>) <article-title>Biological identifications through DNA barcodes</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B</source> <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Hebert2">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnasingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Waard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2003b</year>) <article-title>Barcoding animal life: cytochrome c oxidase subunit 1 divergences among closely related species</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>270</volume><supplement>(Suppl.)</supplement>:<fpage>S96</fpage>–<lpage>S99</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Felsenstein1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Confidence limits on phylogenies: An approach using the bootstrap</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>783</fpage>–<lpage>791</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Kimura1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>A simple method for estimating evolutionary rate of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences</article-title>. <source>Journal of Molecular Evolution</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Tamura1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MEGA 5: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis using Maximum Likelihood, Evolutionary Distance, and Maximum Parsimony Methods</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source> (In Press).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Peakall1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peakall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smouse</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>GENALEX 6: genetic analysis in Excel. Population genetic software for teaching and research</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Notes</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Hernandezortiz1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez-ortiz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartolucci</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morales-Valles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frias</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selivon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Cryptic species of the Anastrepha fraterculus complex (Diptera: Tephritidae): A multivariate approach for the recognition of the South American morphotypes</article-title>. <source>Entomological society of America</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Armstrong3">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>DNA barcodes for biosecurity: invasive species identification</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans R Soc B</source> <volume>2005 360</volume>: <fpage>1813</fpage>–<lpage>1823</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Virgilio1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Virgilio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jordaens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breman</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Backeljau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Identifying Insects with Incomplete DNA Barcode Libraries, African Fruit Flies (Diptera: Tephritidae) as a Test Case</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>7</volume><supplement>(2)</supplement>:<fpage>e31581</fpage> doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0031581.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Barr2">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Pathway analysis of <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae) using mitochondrial DNA</article-title>. <source>Journal of Economical Entomolology</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Barr3">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McPheron</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Molecular identification of <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae) using DNA sequences of the COI barcode region</article-title>. <source>Annals of the Entomological Socociety of America</source> <volume>105</volume><supplement>(2)</supplement>:<fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage> DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1603/AN11100" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1603/AN11100</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Muraji2">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muraji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakahara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships among fruit flies, <italic>Bactrocera</italic> (Diptera, Tephritidae), based on the mitochondrial rDNA sequences</article-title>. <source>Insect Mol Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Hebert3">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penton</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2004a</year>) <article-title>Ten species in one: DNA barcoding reveals cryptic species in the neotropical skipper butterfly Astraptes fulgerator</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>14 812</fpage>–<lpage>14 817</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Smith1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woodley</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>DNA barcodes reveal cryptic host-specificity within the presumed polyphagous members of a genus of parasitoid flies (Diptera: Tachinidae)</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>3657</fpage>–<lpage>3662</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Hajibabaei1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>DAC</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>DNA barcoding: how it complements taxonomy, molecular Phylogenetics and population genetics</article-title>. <source>Science direct</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Billah1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Billah</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimani-Njogu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Overholt</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The effect of host larvae on three <italic>Psyttalia</italic> species (Hymenoptera: Braconidae), parasitoids of fruit nesting flies (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>. <source>Int J Trop Insect Sci</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Folmer1">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Folmer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeh</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>DNA primers for amplification of mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit I from diverse metazoan invertebrates</article-title>. <source>Molecular Marine Biological Biotechnology</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>294</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Baxter1">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Standardization and Transformation in Principal Component Analysis, with Applications to Archaeometry</article-title>. <source>Applied Statististics V</source> <volume>44</volume><supplement>(4)</supplement>:<fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>527</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Sokal1">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sokal RR, Rohlf FJ (1995) Biometry: The principles and Practice of Statistics in Biological Research. 3<sup>rd</sup> Edition. W. H. Freeman &amp; Company, USA. 887 pp.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Bartlett1">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name> (<year>1950</year>) <article-title>Tests of significance in factor analysis</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychology</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Bartlett2">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name> (<year>1951</year>) <article-title>A further note on tests of significance</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychology</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Zar1">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zar JH (1999) Biostatistical analysis. 4th edition. Prentice Hall, Upper Saddle River, NJ.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-R1">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">R Development Core Team (2011) R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria. ISBN 3-900051-07-0, URL <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Thompson1">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plewniak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeanmougin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The ClustalX windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>4876</fpage>–<lpage>4882</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0044862-Saitou1">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>The neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>