<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">09-PONE-RA-12466R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009883</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Population Genetics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Delimiting Species without Nuclear Monophyly in Madagascar's Mouse Lemurs</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Species Delimitation in Lemurs</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weisrock</surname><given-names>David W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¤</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasoloarison</surname><given-names>Rodin M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorentino</surname><given-names>Isabella</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ralison</surname><given-names>José M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>Steven M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kappeler</surname><given-names>Peter M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>Anne D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Biology, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Behavioural Ecology and Sociobiology, German Primate Centre, Göttingen, Germany</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Département de Biologie Animale, Université d'Antananarivo, Antananarivo, Madagascar</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, Illinois, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Vahatra, Antananarivo, Madagascar</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>Duke Lemur Center, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kayser</surname><given-names>Manfred</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Erasmus University Medical Center, Netherlands</aff><author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">dweis2@uky.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: DWW PK ADY. Performed the experiments: DWW IF. Analyzed the data: DWW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RMR JMR SMG PK ADY. Wrote the paper: DWW SMG PK ADY.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="current-aff" id="fn1"><label>¤</label><p>Current address: Department of Biology, University of Kentucky, Lexington, Kentucky, United States of America</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e9883</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2010</year></date>
</history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Weisrock et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>Speciation begins when populations become genetically separated through a substantial reduction in gene flow, and it is at this point that a genetically cohesive set of populations attain the sole property of species: the independent evolution of a population-level lineage. The comprehensive delimitation of species within biodiversity hotspots, regardless of their level of divergence, is important for understanding the factors that drive the diversification of biota and for identifying them as targets for conservation. However, delimiting recently diverged species is challenging due to insufficient time for the differential evolution of characters—including morphological differences, reproductive isolation, and gene tree monophyly—that are typically used as evidence for separately evolving lineages.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methodology</title>
<p>In this study, we assembled multiple lines of evidence from the analysis of mtDNA and nDNA sequence data for the delimitation of a high diversity of cryptically diverged population-level mouse lemur lineages across the island of Madagascar. Our study uses a multi-faceted approach that applies phylogenetic, population genetic, and genealogical analysis for recognizing lineage diversity and presents the most thoroughly sampled species delimitation of mouse lemur ever performed.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The resolution of a large number of geographically defined clades in the mtDNA gene tree provides strong initial evidence for recognizing a high diversity of population-level lineages in mouse lemurs. We find additional support for lineage recognition in the striking concordance between mtDNA clades and patterns of nuclear population structure. Lineages identified using these two sources of evidence also exhibit patterns of population divergence according to genealogical exclusivity estimates. Mouse lemur lineage diversity is reflected in both a geographically fine-scaled pattern of population divergence within established and geographically widespread taxa, as well as newly resolved patterns of micro-endemism revealed through expanded field sampling into previously poorly and well-sampled regions.</p>
</sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This project was supported by grant DEB 0516276 from the National Science Foundation, and by funding from the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation, the German Primate Center (DPZ), the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (grant Ka 1082-8), and the Volkswagen Foundation. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Through decades of diverging opinions, at least one component of the species problem – the disagreement over what exactly species are – has found resolution in the consensus view that species are solely defined as separately evolving metapopulation lineages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Mayden1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz2">[3]</xref>. As such, species exist from the very beginning of their separation and divergence from other lineages and the many available criteria for delimiting these lineages thus mark different points in this process <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Mayden2">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz3">[5]</xref>. Despite this reconciliation, evolutionary biologists still have great difficulty in recognizing species in the early stages of divergence due to the limited time for differences to evolve that satisfy most delimitation criteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz3">[5]</xref>. Identifying lineages in the early stages of species divergence is, nonetheless, extremely important because the study of these lineages is expected to be the most informative about the speciation process <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wiens1">[6]</xref>.</p>
<p>Until recently, species delimitation methods that provide valid biological evidence for the early stages of lineage divergence have been difficult to properly enumerate. Recent developments in the population genetics of speciation may offer new power to resolve recently diverged lineages, however <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wiens2">[7]</xref>. Genetic patterns generated by population-level processes operating within diverging lineages are expected to contain the signal of speciation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Rosenberg1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Degnan1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Pons1">[10]</xref> even though divergence is not long enough to generate overt phylogenetic patterns of independent evolution, such as exclusive monophyly at multiple loci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Baum1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Avise1">[12]</xref>. This is, in part, the basis for favoring the use of monophyly in mitochondrial DNA gene trees as evidence for speciation due to a reduced effective population size relative to nuclear loci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Hebert1">[13]</xref>. This preference relies on the expectation that an increased rate of lineage sorting leads to mtDNA monophyly prior to nuclear monophyly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Moore1">[14]</xref>. Even so, accuracy in species delimitation requires the use of more than a single locus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Hudson1">[15]</xref> and information from multiple loci, ideally in combination with other types of data, are expected to provide a more robust estimate of independently evolving lineages. Methods that summarize population genetic and genealogical patterns across multiple loci are essential for diagnosing these young evolutionary lineages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Knowles1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Cummings1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Shaffer1">[18]</xref>.</p>
<p>Lemurs (Lemuriformes: Primates) are a flagship group in the study of the evolutionary and biogeographic mechanisms that have lead to Madagascar's megadiverse biota <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Martin1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Thalmann1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wilm1">[21]</xref>, but face enormous pressure from human-related activity associated with the destruction of their natural forest habitat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Harper1">[22]</xref>. A realistic understanding of the species diversity and boundaries of lemurs is therefore fundamental to understanding the evolution of Malagasy biodiversity and in conserving these threatened primates.</p>
<p>In the past decade, the species diversity of mouse lemurs (genus <italic>Microcebus</italic>) has increased more than seven-fold, largely through the analysis of mtDNA sequence data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Kappeler1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Andriantompohavana1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Olivieri1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Radespiel1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Rasoloarison1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis2">[29]</xref>. This rapid increase in species numbers has led to a questioning of the true level of lemur species diversity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Tattersall1">[30]</xref> and debate over whether or not this represents overdiagnosis or a true representation of species diversity. The sole utilization of mtDNA, typical of these recent studies, is problematic in that such data do not address the lack of independence of substitutions among nucleotide positions and ignores the potential discord between gene trees and species trees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Weisrock1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Funk1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Maddison1">[33]</xref>. For example, the exhibition of female philopatry in mouse lemurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Fredsted1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wimmer1">[35]</xref> suggests that the maternally inherited mtDNA locus may be strongly biased in such cases.</p>
<p>In this paper, we present the most thoroughly sampled species delimitation study of Malagasy mouse lemurs to date. We present our analyses as a working example of species delimitation where many lineages are morphologically cryptic and recently diverged. These small nocturnal primates also typify the complexities that evolutionary biologists face in assessing diversity in an organismal group that is difficult to study. In the case of mouse lemurs, which are phenotypically very similar, morphological data in most cases cannot be used to separate putative cryptic species, available sample sizes are typically small, both within and among populations, and ecological and behavioral data are often lacking. Instead of viewing these groups as systematically intractable, we argue that the accumulation of substantial genetic data allows us to progress towards a general assessment of species delimitation. Given that lemurs are for the most part forest-dependent, the stakes are often very high, with habitat destruction perhaps erasing species as fast as we can identify and study them <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Allnutt1">[36]</xref>.</p>
<p>In the case of the present study, we geographically sampled mouse lemurs from the remaining forested areas across Madagascar, covering virtually all of the island's unique biomes and micro-endemic regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wilm1">[21]</xref>. While the number of individuals from any given locality is sometimes reduced, the total sample of 216 individuals (286, with the inclusion of GenBank mtDNA data) represents the effort of numerous field biologists from a time span of more than a decade. As such, it is the most complete synthesis to date, though future sampling efforts will continue to augment our understanding of mouse lemur evolutionary diversity. Although previous studies of mouse lemur evolutionary diversity have included morphological data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Rasoloarison1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Yoder1">[37]</xref>, here we focus primarily on genetic data sampled from mtDNA and four independent nuclear loci. We assess patterns of monophyly across independently reconstructed gene trees to identify lineages that exhibit genealogical exclusivity, an expected pattern for lineages with long durations of divergence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Baum1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Avise1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Hudson1">[15]</xref>. However, the larger focus of this study is on the delimitation of population-level lineages that have a relatively recent history of divergence. We use a combined data approach to identify distinct nuclear genetic clusters using analyses of population structure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Shaffer1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Duminil1">[38]</xref>. We test hypotheses of diverging lineages identified through the mtDNA gene tree and nuclear clustering with recently developed statistics that quantify the degree of exclusive ancestry in an assemblage of gene trees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Cummings1">[17]</xref>. As such, this study offers an opportunity to fully explore the strengths, as well as the limitations, of genetic data for the interpretation of species boundaries. In conclusion, we aim to show that a well-developed multi-locus genetic data set that is analyzed appropriately can yield penetrating insights into the history and reproductive boundaries both within and among the evolutionary lineages that we infer to be species.</p>
<fig id="pone-0009883-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>The geographic positions for sampled <italic>Microcebus</italic> localities presented in this study.</title>
<p>Numbers in parentheses refer to a detailed listing of localities found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s001">Table S1</xref>. Localities marked with an open circle are new to this study and are represented with mtDNA and nDNA data. Localities marked with a filled circle are from Yoder et al. (2000) and Heckman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Heckman1">[39]</xref> and are represented by mtDNA and nDNA sequence data. Localities marked with filled diamonds and open squares are from Louis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis1">[25]</xref> and Olivieri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Olivieri1">[26]</xref>, respectively, and are represented only by mtDNA data. The island is broken up into regions of micro-endemism (colored sections) and retreat-dispersion (outlined white sections) as defined by Wilmé et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wilm1">[21]</xref>. Shaded polygons overlay the known distribution of lineages resolved in this study. Localities not encompassed by a shaded polygon are represented by a mtDNA clade that cannot be linked to a nuclear genotypic cluster, limiting a full species delimitation assessment. Due to the extensive overlap of <italic>M. murinus</italic> with other lineages across the western portion of the island, its full range is not depicted.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Organismal sampling</title>
<p>MtDNA sequence data were analyzed from 286 individual mouse lemurs distributed across Madagascar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). 102 of these represent new material from 23 previously unsampled localities distributed throughout Madagascar. MtDNA sequence data from the remaining individuals comes from previous work <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Olivieri1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Yoder1">[37]</xref>. Nuclear sequence data were analyzed from a total of 216 mouse lemurs. As with the mtDNA data, 102 of these are new material from the 23 previously unsampled localities. Nuclear sequence data from the remaining samples are those of Heckman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Heckman1">[39]</xref>, which are from the same localities presented in the mtDNA work of Yoder et al. (2000). Full details regarding the number of individuals per locality, locality names, and geographic coordinate data can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s001">Table S1</xref>. The nuclear sequence data of Heckman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Heckman1">[39]</xref> required editing for the identification of previously unidentified heterozygous nucleotide positions, and for the refinement of allele phases, and are deposited in GenBank with new accession numbers. Outgroup sequences for phylogenetic analysis were obtained from GenBank for single individuals of each of the following species: <italic>Cheirogaleus crossleyi</italic>, <italic>C. major</italic>, <italic>C. medius</italic>, and <italic>Mirza coquereli</italic>. GenBank accession numbers for all outgroup individuals and for the mtDNA data of Louis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis1">[25]</xref> and Olivieri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Olivieri1">[26]</xref> can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s002">Table S2</xref>. All new sequence data and sequence data from the studies of Yoder et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Yoder1">[37]</xref> and Heckman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Heckman1">[39]</xref> are available in GenBank with the following accession numbers: mtDNA <italic>cox2</italic> (GU326974-GU327160), mtDNA <italic>cob</italic> (GU327161-GU327362), <italic>adora3</italic> (GU230899-GU231330), <italic>eno</italic> (GU231331-GU231716), <italic>fga</italic> (GU231717-GU232130), and <italic>vwf</italic> (GU232131-GU232490).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Genetic Sampling and Data Collection</title>
<p>MtDNA sequence data from two separate regions, <italic>cox2</italic> and <italic>cob</italic>, were generated using PCR and direct sequencing with the PCR primers L7553/H8320 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Adkins1">[40]</xref> and L14724/H15915 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Irwin1">[41]</xref>, respectively. Nuclear DNA sequence data were generated from four independent loci (<italic>adora3</italic>, <italic>fga</italic>, <italic>eno</italic>, and <italic>vwf</italic>). These are the same loci used in Heckman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Heckman1">[39]</xref> and PCR primer information are found within that reference except for those used in the amplification of <italic>adora3</italic>, which are from Horvath et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Horvath1">[42]</xref>. PCR was performed in volumes of 20 µl using 2 µl template DNA (approximately 50-150 ng DNA), 25 µM each dNTP, 1 µM each primer, and 0.625U Taq polymerase in a standard 1x reaction buffer. Typical mtDNA amplification conditions were carried out with an initial 94°C denaturation for 2 min, followed by 35 cycles of 30 s at 94°C, 30 s at 50°C and 45 s at 68°C. A final 7 minutes extension was performed at 72°C. See Horvath et al. (2008) for specific annealing conditions for each nuclear locus. PCR products were directly sequenced using both forward and reverse PCR primers and BigDye® Terminator v3.1 (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). Prior to sequencing, 9 µl PCR product was treated with 1.5U exonuclease I and 0.3U shrimp alkaline phosphatase. Cycle sequencing was performed in a total volume of 5 µL including 1 µl Exo/SAP treated product, 2 µM primer, 0.5 µl BDv3.1 and water to 5 µl. Cycle sequencing conditions were carried out for 25 cycles: 95°C for 10 sec, 55°C for 5 sec, 60°C for 2 min and a final hold at 10°C. Fluorescent traces were analyzed using an ABI 3730xl DNA Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). Most nuclear PCR products that generated sequence exhibiting polymorphic sites or length heterogeneity were cloned using a Topo® TA cloning kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), and for each cloned PCR, eight colonies were sequenced to identify alleles. Haplotypes for some heterozygous sequences were phased using an algorithmic approach implemented in PHASE v2.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Stephens1">[43]</xref>. Within each nuclear locus we estimated the minimum number of recombination events <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Hudson2">[44]</xref> using DnaSP v4.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Rozas1">[45]</xref>. We tested for departure from neutral evolution within individual loci using Fu and Li's F* statistics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Fu1">[46]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Phylogenetic Reconstruction</title>
<p>Bayesian phylogenetic analysis was performed on single-gene haplotype data sets and on single-gene full nuclear data sets including all individuals and their respective gene copies using MrBayes v3.1.2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Ronquist1">[47]</xref>. Evolutionary models for each locus were assessed for the haplotype data sets using Akaike Information Criteria in MrModeltest v2.3 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Nylander1">[48]</xref>. MtDNA data for individual mouse lemurs were concatenated and analyzed in a two-partition framework with model parameters estimated separately for the <italic>cox2</italic> and <italic>cytb</italic> genes. Nuclear gene data sets were analyzed as a single partition. Four Markov chains were used with the default temperature parameter of 0.2. Default priors were used in all analyses and random trees were used to start each Markov chain. Chains were run for 10 million generations with topology and model parameter estimates sampled every 1000 generations. The first five million generations were discarded as burn-in yielding a posterior distribution of 5000 sampled trees. Mean log likelihood (lnL), branch lengths and topologies were compared across four replicate analyses to insure that a stable posterior distribution was reached. Sampled trees from the posterior distributions of replicate analyses were pooled and parsed with MrBayes to construct a majority rule consensus tree and to calculate posterior probabilities (PPs) of all resulting branches. We assessed nuclear monophyly of terminal clades resolved in the mtDNA haplotype tree and for previously described taxa by filtering the nuclear Bayesian posterior distributions for trees that meet that constraint of monophyly for specified groups. Tree filtering was performed in PAUP* version 4.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Swofford1">[49]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Bayesian Structure Analysis</title>
<p>Analysis of population structure was assessed using a genotype matrix of the nuclear loci in STRUCTURE v2.2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Pritchard1">[50]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Falush1">[51]</xref>. We ran a series of analyses under models assuming a specific number of populations (<italic>K</italic>), with a range of <italic>K</italic> from 2 to 26. In each iteration, individuals were assigned probabilistically to a cluster based on their multilocus genotype. All analyses used one million MCMC generations to estimate the posterior distribution following a burnin period of one million generations. Our model incorporated the possibility that some individuals may have mixed population ancestry and the possibility that allele frequencies are correlated among populations due to migration or shared ancestry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Falush1">[51]</xref>. For each <italic>K</italic>, the log (ln) probability of the data (X) was estimated [ln Pr(X|<italic>K</italic>)] and used to calculate the posterior probability (PP) of <italic>K</italic> under the assumption of a uniform prior. We also calculated Δ<italic>K</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Evanno1">[52]</xref>, which is based on the rate of change in ln Pr(X|<italic>K</italic>) between successive <italic>K</italic> values. These two measures often identify different optimal measures of <italic>K</italic>, and Δ<italic>K</italic> may favor smaller values of <italic>K</italic> that represent basal levels of hierarchical structure in systems that substantially deviate from an island model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Evanno1">[52]</xref>. We visualized the optimal <italic>K</italic> STRUCTURE plot using Microsoft Excel. Membership coefficients for individuals with posterior probabilities less than 0.05 were disregarded and proportionally assigned to the other cluster assignment coefficients.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Genealogical Tests of Population Divergence</title>
<p>We assessed the level of genealogical divergence in our nuclear gene trees for hypothesized lineages identified in the mtDNA gene tree and nuclear STRUCTURE analysis using the genealogical sorting index (<italic>gsi</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Cummings1">[17]</xref>. For pre-defined groups in a gene tree, the <italic>gsi</italic> is a standardized measure of the degree to which they exhibit exclusive ancestry. The <italic>gsi</italic> statistic ranges from 1 (monophyly) to 0 (a complete lack of genealogical divergence with other groups). A major benefit of the <italic>gsi</italic> statistic for species delimitation is the ability to assess its statistical significance through the randomization of group labels across the tips in a gene tree. Consequently, hypothesized lineages can be tested against a null hypothesis of no divergence, as measured by coalescent patterns in their gene trees. For each individual nuclear locus, we calculated the <italic>gsi</italic> for 100 trees randomly sampled from the combined Bayesian posterior distribution of trees. These 100 individual <italic>gsi</italic> measurements were then used together with equal weight to calculate an ensemble <italic>gsi</italic> statistic (<italic>gsi<sub>T</sub></italic>) for each locus. Thus, g<italic>si<sub>T</sub></italic> measurements serve as a summary of the genealogical exclusivity across the Bayesian posterior distribution of trees for a given locus. In addition to the single-locus assessments of genealogical exclusivity, we also calculated <italic>gsi<sub>T</sub></italic> for the set of majority-rule consensus trees of all four nuclear loci. The significance of all <italic>gsi</italic> and <italic>gsi<sub>T</sub></italic> statistics was assessed using 1000 randomization permutations. All analyses were performed using the Genealogical Sorting Index web server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genealogicalsorting.org" xlink:type="simple">www.genealogicalsorting.org</ext-link>).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Information regarding size, level of variability, molecular evolutionary models, and likelihood values from phylogenetic analyses for all mtDNA and nDNA genes can be found in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t001">Table 1</xref>. No evidence was found for recombination within any of the four nuclear loci. Furthermore, no locus yielded a significant signature of a departure from neutrality.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0009883-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Information for loci used in this study.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0009883-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Locus</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Size (bp)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable Sites</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of Haplotypes</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Favored Model<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean Bayesian lnL (haplotype data)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean Bayesian lnL (full data)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ML lnL (full data)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mtDNA (<italic>cox2</italic>)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">684</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">176</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">169<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HKY+I+G</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−13360.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref> (−13400.0, −13320.0)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mtDNA (<italic>cytb</italic>)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1184</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">396</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">169<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HKY+I+G</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>adora3</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">384</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HKY+G</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1104.6 (−1118.3, −1093.08</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1223.7 (−1244.3, −1204.9)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−852.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>eno</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">913</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">156</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HKY+I+G</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4557.6 (−4582.1, −4531.5)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4717.33 (−4754.1, −4684.4)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3915.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>fga</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">632</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HKY+I+G</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2232.9 (−2251.07, −2215.7)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2433.1 (−2460.1, −2406.9)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1953.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>vwf</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">824</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">117</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HKY+I+G</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3980.1 (−4007.5, −3953.3)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4164.8 (−4230.8, −4099.0)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3379.7</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p>Model selected according to the Akaike Information Criterion in the program MrModelTest.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>b</label><p>Haplotype number includes sequence data from GenBank and is calculated for the concatenated set of mtDNA data.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>c</label><p>Scores are calculated for the concatenated mtDNA data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="s3a">
<title>MtDNA Gene Tree</title>
<p>The mtDNA haplotype tree resolved the majority of previously described species as clades (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>; full mtDNA gene tree details are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s003">Figure S1</xref>) with just two exceptions: <italic>M</italic>. <italic>rufus</italic> mtDNA haplotypes are paraphyletic and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>jollyae</italic> and <italic>Microcebus</italic> sp. nova 3 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis1">[25]</xref> share a mtDNA haplotype. MtDNA variation is highly structured across the island with numerous sampling localities within currently recognized species exhibiting monophyly (dashed-line clades in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). In addition, some sets of localities within described species are reconstructed as geographically paraphyletic groups (e.g. within <italic>M. griseorufus</italic> and <italic>M. myoxinus</italic>). Three novel mtDNA clades are resolved based on new field sampling: (1) haplotypes sampled from Marolambo (locality 64), (2) haplotypes sampled from the localities of Ivorona and Manantantely (localities 66 and 67), and (3) haplotypes sampled from Ambanja and Montagne d'Ambre (Localities 56 and 79). This latter clade may represent <italic>M. arnholdi</italic>, a recently described species from Montagne d'Ambre that was diagnosed using patterns of mtDNA divergence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis2">[29]</xref>. However, that study used different mtDNA gene regions than those used here, preventing a direct link with the lineage resolved in our mtDNA gene tree. Therefore, we treat the Ambanja+Montagne d'Ambre lineage resolved here as an unnamed lineage with the understanding that it may represent <italic>M. arnholdi</italic>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0009883-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Correspondence between clades in the mtDNA gene tree and nuclear Structure clusters.</title>
<p>The mtDNA gene tree results from Bayesian analysis of concatenated <italic>cox2</italic> and <italic>cytb</italic> sequence. It is presented as a maximum credibility topology with branch lengths averaged across the posterior distribution. Numbers on branches represent posterior probabilities. Relationships within terminal clades are collapsed for ease of presentation and clades are labeled according to present species designations. Locality numbers are given in parentheses and correspond to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g001">Fig. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s001">Table S1</xref>. Clades are mapped to corresponding clusters in the nuclear STRUCTURE plot. Each cluster is designated by a different color with horizontal bars representing individuals and the proportion of a bar assigned to a single color representing the posterior probability that an individual is assigned to that cluster. This can also be interpreted as the percentage of an individuals genome that is derived from that particular genetic cluster. Localities from which individuals are sampled from are given along the right side of the plot. MtDNA clades not mapped to the assignment plot represent individuals for which corresponding nDNA data is not available. The colors in the Bayesian assignment plot do not correspond to colored areas of micro-endemism in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g001">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0009883-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Probability of monophyly in the single-gene Bayesian posterior distributions and nuclear cluster assignments for <italic>Microcebus</italic> species and populations.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0009883-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lineage</td>
<td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Posterior probability for monophyly</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bayesian assignment cluster(s) w/average individual membership coefficients</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MtDNA group + genotypic cluster</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mtDNA</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>adora3</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>eno</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>fga</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>vwf</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. griseorufus</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0004</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.28), 2 (0.71), <bold>1+2 (1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. murinus</italic> – sensu lato</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.17), 4 (0.29), 5 (0.28), 6 (0.25), <bold>3+4+5+6 (0.99)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">– Bemanasy</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3 (0.99)</bold>, 4 (0.01)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">– And/Kir/Manam/Vohi</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.05), 4 (0.47), 5 (0.45), <bold>4+5 (0.92)</bold>, 6 (0.03)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">– Mandena</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>6 (1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. danfossi</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. bongolavensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.99</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. ravelobensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9781</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9914</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>7 (1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Microcebus</italic> sp. – Marolambo</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.576</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.205</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>8 (1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Microcebus</italic> sp. – Ivorona/Manantantely</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9754</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.01), 8 (0.01), <bold>9 (0.93)</bold>, 14 (0.04), 15 (0.01)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. jollyae</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Data</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. simmonsi</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9957</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9914</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>10 (1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. tavaratra</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9318</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>11 (0.99)</bold>, 19 (0.01)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. mamiratra</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (1.0)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Microcebus</italic> sp. Ambanja/Montagne d'Ambre</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.301</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>13 (1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. sambiranensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.149</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>12 (.98)</bold>, 15 (0.02)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M. mittermeieri</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>14 (0.97)</bold>, 15 (0.03)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. lehilahytsara</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (0.04), <bold>15 (0.95)</bold>, 18 (0.01)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. berthae</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>16 (0.91),</bold> 17 (0.04), 18 (0.02), 19 (0.03)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">c</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. rufus</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (0.01), 16 (0.12), 17 (0.78), 18 (0.02), 19 (0.07)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">c</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. myoxinus</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.77</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (0.01), 14 (∼0), 15 (∼0), 17 (0.01), 18 (0.36), 19 (0.62), <bold>18+19 (0.98)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">c</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Total number of diagnosed lineages = </td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>16</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>For definitions of the locality acronyms within <italic>M. murinus</italic> see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s001">Table S1</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>a</label><p>The populations of Andranomena+Kirindy(CFPF)+ Mamamby and the population of Vohimena each form separate mtDNA clades.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>b</label><p><italic>Microcebus rufus</italic> is paraphyletic with respect to <italic>M. myoxinus</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label>c</label><p><italic>Microcebus berthae</italic> and <italic>M. myoxinus</italic> both are placed into distinct nuclear clusters that are also present in greater than 5% of the average cluster assignments of <italic>M. rufus</italic>. We diagnose these as three distinct clusters based on their geographic distributions (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">discussion</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Nuclear Gene Trees</title>
<p>Bayesian phylogenetic analysis of haplotype data for the individual nuclear genes results in majority rule consensus trees that resolve only a subset of the clades resolved in the mtDNA gene tree (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s004">Figures S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s005">S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s006">S4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s007">S5</xref>). Filtering of trees from the full-data Bayesian posterior distributions reveals that few of the mtDNA-based clades exhibit monophyly with posterior probabilities greater than 0.05 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>). The exceptions to this are <italic>M. griseorufus</italic>, <italic>M. sambiranensis</italic>, <italic>Microcebus</italic> sp. (Ambanja+Montagne d'Ambre), and <italic>Microcebus</italic> sp. (Ivorona-+Manantantely), all of which are monophyletic in one nuclear gene tree, <italic>M. mamiratra</italic>, which is monophyletic in two nuclear gene trees, <italic>M. tavaratra</italic> and <italic>Microcebus</italic> sp. (Marolambo), both of which are monophyletic in three nuclear gene trees, and <italic>M. ravelobensis</italic> and <italic>M. simmonsi</italic>, which exhibit monophyly in all four nuclear gene trees (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>). Finally, construction of a strict consensus tree from the ML nuclear gene trees does not yield reciprocal monophyly for additional groups that are not present in the mtDNA gene tree (results not shown), but instead yields reciprocal monophyly for just two species, <italic>M. ravelobensis</italic> and <italic>M. simmonsi</italic>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Nuclear Population Structure</title>
<p>Plots of the estimated log probability of the data [log Pr(X|<italic>K</italic>)] for replicated STRUCTURE analyses reveal a general pattern of a plateau or decrease in values above a <italic>K</italic> = 19 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s008">Figure S6</xref>). Four replicate analyses yield a posterior probability of 1.0 for a <italic>K</italic> = 19 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s008">Figure S6</xref>). The remaining replicate analyses had posterior probabilities of 1.0 for <italic>K</italic>s of 20, 23, 24, and 26. In contrast, calculations of Δ<italic>K</italic> produce a peak at <italic>K</italic> = 2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s008">Figure S6</xref>). This result likely stems from the identification of a basal level of hierarchical structure in the data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Evanno1">[52]</xref>. The plateau in patterns of the log Pr(X|<italic>K</italic>) around a <italic>K</italic> = 19, and the high posterior probabilities for <italic>K</italic>≥19, suggest an overall higher population cluster number. A plot of individual membership coefficients for <italic>K</italic> = 19 reveals a high number of population clusters with average individual membership coefficients (i.e. posterior probabilities) greater than 0.9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>). STRUCTURE plots for <italic>K</italic>&gt;19 do not yield additional clusters with high membership coefficients for more exclusive sets of populations or individuals, but instead further divide already admixed sets of individuals (e.g. populations within <italic>M. murinus</italic>) into additional admixed cluster assignments. Therefore, we place our focus on <italic>K</italic> = 19 as an estimate of the upper level of population clustering.</p>
<p>There is strong concordance between identified nuclear clusters and terminal mtDNA clades (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). Of the 12 mtDNA clades representing described species, and for which we have corresponding nuclear data, 11 map to one or more nuclear genotypic clusters characteristic to that clade. Many populations within described species that exhibit mtDNA monophyly also map to distinct nuclear clusters with high individual membership coefficients (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>). For example, all individuals sampled from the <italic>M. murinus</italic> population of Mandena (locality 4) have a monophyletic assemblage of mtDNA haplotypes and an assignment to a single nuclear STRUCTURE cluster with average membership coefficients of 1.0. The three novel mtDNA clades from the populations of Marolambo, Ivorona+Manantantely, and Ambanja+Montagne d'Ambre also each map to their own respective nuclear clusters with average individual membership coefficients of 1.0, 0.93, and 1.0, respectively. In total, using corresponding patterns of nuclear STRUCTURE clustering and mtDNA monophyly, we diagnose a total of 16 hypothesized lineages of <italic>Microcebus</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>). These criteria focus on the assignment of mtDNA clade-specific localities or sets of localities to one or more characteristic nuclear clusters with limited signs of admixture (i.e. average cluster membership coefficients ≤5% for other localities).</p>
<p>In contrast to these patterns, individuals within the mtDNA haplotype clade that correspond to the recently described species, <italic>M. mamiratra</italic>, have nuclear STRUCTURE assignments identical to individuals of <italic>M. sambiranensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>). Similar patterns are also seen for some localities within described species that exhibit mtDNA monophyly, but do not have high membership coefficients to distinct nuclear clusters (e.g. the locality of Vohimena within <italic>M. murinus</italic> and the locality of Ambalimby within <italic>M. myoxinus</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Nuclear Genealogical Sorting</title>
<p>Overall, there is considerable variation in measures of genealogical divergence across hypothesized lineages, across gene trees within lineages, and across the Bayesian posterior distribution of individual gene trees (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t003">Table 3</xref>). Nonetheless, significant measures of exclusive ancestry are estimated at all of these levels of organization with just two exceptions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t003">Table 3</xref>): (1) the <italic>adora3</italic> Bayesian posterior distribution contains &gt;5 individual trees in which the <italic>gsi</italic> for <italic>M. lehilahytsara</italic> is not significant; however, the <italic>adora3 gsi<sub>T</sub></italic> for <italic>M. lehilahytsara</italic> significantly rejects the null hypothesis of no divergence, and (2) the <italic>adora3</italic> Bayesian posterior distribution contains &gt;5 individual trees in which the <italic>gsi</italic> for the undescribed lineage (<italic>Microcebus</italic> sp.) from Marolambo is not significant. However, in this latter case the overall <italic>adora3 gsi<sub>T</sub></italic> measurement is not significant. <italic>Gsi<sub>T</sub></italic> values for most lineages are lower for the <italic>adora3</italic> locus than the other three nuclear loci, a result consistent with the overall lower level of genetic variation in the <italic>adora3</italic> data set (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0009883-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Ensemble genealogical sorting indices (<italic>gsi<sub>T</sub></italic>) for the combined set of majority-rule consensus trees from all four nuclear loci and for the Bayesian posterior distributions of each individual nuclear locus.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0009883-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lineage</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All loci <italic>gsi<sub>T</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>adora3 gsi<sub>T</sub></italic> (min-max)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>eno gsi<sub>T</sub></italic> (min-max)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>fib gsi<sub>T</sub></italic> (min-max)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>vwf gsi<sub>T</sub></italic> (min-max)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. berthae</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.158</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.185 (0.141–0.269)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.573 (0.377–0.843)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.259 (0.207–0.343)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.303 (0.222–0.412)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. griseorufus</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.487</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.414 (0.257–0.519)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.729 (0.683–0.814)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.673 (0.664–0.717)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.48 (0.359–0.576)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. lehilahytsara</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.069</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.119</bold> (0.074–0.187)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.243 (0.155–0.529)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.407 (0.27–0.538)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.226 (0.149–0.344)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. mittermeieri</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.142</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.141 (0.103–0.211)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.384 (0.255–0.643)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.361 (0.179–0.639)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.512 (0.304–0.739)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. murinus</italic> (Bemanasy)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.157</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.224 (0.153–0.327)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.204 (0.168–0.247)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.2 (0.141–0.28)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.323 (0.246–0.487)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. murinus</italic> (Mandena)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.357</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.314 (0.255–0.377)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.768 (0.765–0.862)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.323 (0.246–0.45)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.474 (0.4–0.571)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. murinus</italic> (remaining pops)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.406</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.469 (0.395–0.571)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.892 (0.842–0.926)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.36 (0.279–0.506)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.45 (0.317–0.57)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. myoxinus</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.416</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.341 (0.311–0.392)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.522 (0.441–0.631)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.429 (0.368–0.489)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.736 (0.672–0.793)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. ravelobensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0 (0.956–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0 (1.0–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.995 (0.727–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0 (1.0–1.0)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. rufus</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.326</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.302 (0.25–0.357)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.533 (0.45–0.67)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.431 (0.369–0.5)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.7 (0.62–0.829)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. sambiranensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.491</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.913 (0.334–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.407 (0.293–0.605)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.344 (0.203–0.465)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.756 (0.559–0.935)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. simmonsi</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0 (0.981–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0 (1.0–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0 (1.0–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.999 (0.944–1.0)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. tavaratra</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.724</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.981 (0.495–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0 (1.0–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.359 (0.194–0.511)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.895 (0.761–1.0)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Microcebus</italic> sp. (Ambanja/Montagne d'Ambre)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.270</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.259 (0.126–0.538)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.892 (0.725–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.516 (0.296–0.78)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.383 (0.183–0.536)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Microcebus</italic> sp. (Ivorona/Manantantely)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.478</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.141 (0.125–0.23)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.669 (0.589–0.8)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0 (1.0–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.383 (0.187–0.566)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Microcebus</italic> sp. (Marolambo)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.713</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.097 (0.062–0.183)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.0 (1.0–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.966 (0.831–1.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.861 (0.71–1.0)</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt108"><label>a</label><p>&gt;5 of the 100 trees sampled from the Bayesian posterior distribution had <italic>gsi</italic> values with p&gt;0.05.</p></fn><fn id="nt109"><label>b</label><p><italic>Microcebus rufus</italic> is not diagnosed as a diverging lineage according to the criteria used in this study, but is included here based on patterns of population differentiation from <italic>M. berthae</italic> and <italic>M. myoxinus</italic> and due to its delimitation based on morphological and ecological traits <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Yoder1">[37]</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt110"><label/><p>The minimum and maximum <italic>gsi</italic> for individual trees within the Bayesian posterior distributions are given in parentheses.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Species delimitation in mouse lemurs</title>
<p>Speciation begins when populations become genetically separated through a substantial reduction in gene flow, either through vicariance, or through selection and adaptation, and it is at this point that a genetically cohesive set of populations attain the sole property of species: the independent evolution of a population-level lineage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz2">[3]</xref>. The delimitation of lineages in these early stages of speciation is important because their study is most likely to yield insights into the mechanisms that drove their formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wiens1">[6]</xref>. The comprehensive delimitation of all diverging lineages within hotspots of biodiversity, regardless of their level of divergence, is important for understanding the factors driving the diversification of biota <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wilm1">[e.g. 21]</xref> and guiding biologically realistic conservation action <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Andreone1">[53]</xref>. However, delimiting recently diverged lineages is challenging due to insufficient time for the differential evolution of characters – including morphological differences, reproductive isolation, and monophyly in gene trees – that are typically used as evidence for separately evolving lineages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz3">[5]</xref>. The most likely patterns to evolve over short time scales of divergence are the population genetic patterns of differentiation. The reduction of gene flow among populations allows genetic drift to operate independently within cohesive sets of populations yielding distinctive patterns in allele frequencies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Slatkin1">[54]</xref> and in gene trees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Degnan1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Pamilo1">[55]</xref>. The application of species delimitation criteria that identify lineages exhibiting the population genetic patterns of cohesion through gene flow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Shaffer1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Duminil1">[38]</xref> and genealogical patterns of divergence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Knowles1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Cummings1">[17]</xref> can thus have significant benefits over criteria that are more often limited to identifying lineages that are well into the process of divergence.</p>
<p>In this study, we assembled multiple lines of evidence from the analysis of mtDNA and nDNA sequence data for the delimitation of numerous cryptically diverged lineages of mouse lemurs across the island of Madagascar. This evidence included one of the more standard phylogeographic components of lineage diagnosis: the resolution of clades in a mtDNA gene tree. However, there is an overall lack of corresponding nuclear monophyly for most mtDNA clades. Only two population-level lineages, the previously described <italic>M. ravelobensis</italic> and <italic>M. simmonsi</italic>, are delimited via monophyly in all mtDNA and nDNA gene trees (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>), and just nine lineages are delimited when this criterion was relaxed to monophyly in mtDNA and at least one nuclear gene tree. Interestingly, these monophyly criteria fail to delimit many lineages previously described as species on the basis of clear and concordant patterns of mtDNA, morphological, and ecological differentiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Rasoloarison1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Yoder1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Yoder2">[56]</xref>. In contrast, STRUCTURE analysis of the nuclear data clustered individuals into groups that strongly align with mtDNA clades (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). Furthermore, despite a lack of nuclear monophyly for most of these population groupings, estimates of their <italic>gsi</italic> significantly favor independent histories of lineage divergence (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t003">Table 3</xref>). Within the framework of the general lineage concept of species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz2">[3]</xref>, which clarifies that new species arise at the very beginning of lineage divergence from an ancestor, corroborating lines of evidence that indicate the independent divergence of a lineage provide substantial support for its delimitation as a species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz3">[5]</xref>. We, therefore, present our study as a working example of a comprehensive approach for delimitating recently diverged species and elaborate on the individual components of this approach below.</p>
<p>The resolution of a large number of geographically defined clades in the mtDNA gene tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>) provided a strong suggestion for a high diversity of mouse lemur lineages. Many mtDNA clades correspond to groups resolved in previous mtDNA-based studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Andriantompohavana1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Olivieri1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Yoder1">[37]</xref>. This is in large part due to our inclusion of GenBank mtDNA data from these previous studies, which facilitated the placement of much of our nuclear results within the context of previous species delimitation work. Novel to this study, however, was the resolution of additional mtDNA clades resolved on the basis of two different sampling regimes. First, expanded field sampling led to the resolution of mtDNA clades within described species that are specific to one or a few sampling localities. For example, within the <italic>M. murinus</italic> mtDNA clade the localities of Bemanasy and Mandena were each resolved as monophyletic sets of haplotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). This fine scale pattern of mtDNA differentiation was also seen in paraphyletic groupings within described species. For example, both <italic>M. griseorufus</italic> and <italic>M. myoxinus</italic> contained paraphyletic groups with respect to other single-locality monophyletic groupings (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>). Both of these phylogenetic patterns represent a potentially fine-scale level of geographic genetic divergence not previously considered within mouse lemurs. Second, we also resolved three novel and relatively divergent mtDNA clades (each labeled <italic>Microcebus</italic> sp. in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>), each of which corresponds to new localities that had not previously been sampled. These patterns indicate that the upper limit of our understanding of mouse lemur lineage diversity may also be constrained by our ability to comprehensively sample across Madagascar.</p>
<p>Much of the recent flurry of mouse lemur species descriptions has been based primarily on patterns in mtDNA gene trees. While the sorting of mtDNA variation may, on average, track lineage divergence more rapidly than nDNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Moore1">[14]</xref>, there are important reasons for not relying on mtDNA as a sole source of evidence in species delimitation, including the potential to over diagnose mtDNA lineages influenced by selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Hudson1">[15]</xref> or sex-biased dispersal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Caparroz1">[57]</xref>. Accordingly, the strongest genetic evidence for speciation comes from evaluating patterns of variation across multiple loci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Hudson1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Hudson3">[58]</xref>. We find additional evidence for mouse lemur lineage divergence in the striking degree of concordance between mtDNA clades and patterns of nuclear population genetic structure. Localities or sets of localities that are resolved as a clade in the mtDNA gene tree are predominantly assigned to a characteristic nuclear genotypic cluster with high average assignment probabilities (0.9–1.0) in the STRUCTURE assignment plot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>). There are only limited signs of admixture between some population clusters, a pattern consistent with mtDNA evidence for a lack of gene flow between groups. In contrast to the evolution of nuclear monophyly, which can require long durations of time [(∼4-7N generations for just 50% of the nuclear genome's gene trees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Hudson1">[15]</xref>], the evolution of allele frequency differences and genome-wide patterns of Hardy-Weinberg and linkage equilibrium within lineages is expected to occur more rapidly. Population assignment analyses based on these parameters may serve as useful methods for delimiting the early stages of lineage divergence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Shaffer1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Duminil1">[38]</xref>.</p>
<p>One potential criticism of our interpretation of the STRUCTURE results is that these patterns simply represent the geographic structuring of intraspecific variation. For example, STRUCTURE analysis places human population genetic variation into geographically-defined clusters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Rosenberg2">[59]</xref>. A major benefit to the use of STRUCTURE analysis is its ability to identify individuals with admixed genomic profiles that arise through gene flow between previously isolated population clusters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Falush1">[51]</xref>. Human populations are undoubtedly cohesive through gene flow, as evidenced, in part, by signatures of admixture in their STRUCTURE profiles. However, this does not negate STRUCTURE's ability to identify cluster patterns that reflect <italic>histories</italic> of isolation and divergence. In fact, the models implemented in STRUCTURE specifically allow for the reconstruction of ancestral clusters even if most individuals are largely composed of admixed genotypes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Falush1">[51]</xref>. Consequently, we contend that, within natural systems, populations characterized by distinct genotypic clusters with limited signs of admixture exhibit at least one layer of evidence for lineage divergence.</p>
<p>To further test the hypothesis that these sets of mouse lemur populations have an underlying history of lineage divergence, we quantified the magnitude of their genealogical divergence and tested whether or not genealogical patterns within lineages were significantly different from those expected under a history of no divergence. Accompanying the speciation process is an expected transition, driven by genetic drift, in the gene genealogies of a diverging lineage from polyphyletic sets of ancestral gene copies to monophyletic sets of unique gene copies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Avise1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Maddison1">[33]</xref>. Consequently, characteristic topological patterns are expected to evolve in the gene trees of a diverging lineage long before the evolution of monophyly, and these patterns can be used to distinguish independent and recently diverged sets of populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Knowles1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Cummings1">[17]</xref>. All mouse lemur lineages delimited via mtDNA monophyly and nuclear clustering have significant patterns of genealogical exclusivity in their nuclear gene trees, as measured by <italic>gsi</italic> values for the Bayesian posterior distributions of individual gene trees, and by the ensemble <italic>gsi<sub>T</sub></italic>, which integrates patterns across loci (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t003">Table 3</xref>). These results clarify our interpretations of the nuclear STRUCTURE clusters by providing a genealogical perspective of their underlying history. Despite the fact that the majority of nuclear clusters do not represent monophyletic groups in their component nuclear gene trees, they nonetheless have genealogical patterns consistent with a history of lineage divergence. <italic>Gsi<sub>T</sub></italic> values across loci indicate a broad range in the degree of genealogical exclusivity across loci (0.069–1.0). However, because the progression to monophyly is governed by both time and effective population size <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Maddison1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Pamilo1">[55]</xref>, it is difficult to place lineages on a relative temporal scale of divergence based on their overall <italic>Gsi<sub>T</sub></italic>. Instead, the resolution of lineages with significant gene tree-wide <italic>Gsi<sub>T</sub></italic> values provides a simple, but quantitative indication of divergence for many lineages that have not been diverging long enough to have evolved concordant patterns of monophyly across the majority of their gene trees.</p>
<p>Based on this total set of evidence, we diagnose 16 population-level lineages of mouse lemurs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Tables 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t003">3</xref>). Within the framework of the metapopulation lineage concept of species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-deQueiroz2">[3]</xref>, all of these lineages are recognized as species, regardless of their relative level of divergence. In contrast, species criteria that place greater emphases on more explicit properties of species (e.g. reproductive isolation or gene tree monophyly) would yield a substantially lower number of delimited and recognized species. Without placing emphasis on the number of species formally recognized by our results, we highlight the strong evidence for considerable lineage formation within <italic>Microcebus</italic>, including lineages with genetic patterns indicative of long durations of independent divergence, as well as those with patterns suggestive of a shallower depth of divergence. In total, these results are counter to a recently proposed argument that the escalation in lemur species diversity is largely due to oversplitting of geographically localized variants that are merely components of larger cohesive lineages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Tattersall1">[30]</xref>. Instead, our estimates of a high lineage diversity of mouse lemurs is reflected in both a geographically fine-scale pattern of population divergence within established and geographically widespread species, as well as newly resolved patterns of micro-endemism revealed through expanded field sampling into previously poorly and well-sampled regions. Fine-scale patterns of lineage divergence are particularly pronounced within <italic>M</italic>. <italic>murinus</italic> in the southeastern populations of Bemanasy and Mandena, which are genetically diverged and distinct from each other and from western <italic>M</italic>. <italic>murinus</italic> populations. The geographic scale of divergence between these two southeastern lineages within <italic>M</italic>. <italic>murinus</italic> across a pronounced bioclimatic ecotone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Goodman1">[60]</xref> is striking, with a physical separation of just 27 km (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g003">Fig. 3</xref>), but genetic patterns that seem to exclude any sign of genetic exchange. Moreover, new regions of micro-endemic lineages are revealed. From the newly-sampled Marolambo population (locality 64) on the central eastern side of the island, a novel lineage was discovered that displays no evidence of gene flow with <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lehilahytsara</italic> or <italic>M</italic>. <italic>simmonsi</italic> to the north, or <italic>M</italic>. <italic>rufus</italic> to the south (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). In the well-sampled regions of Ivorona and Manantantely (localities 66 and 67) in the extreme southeast, we observe sympatric distributions of three distinct lineages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g003">Fig. 3</xref>) that show no evidence of gene flow, despite the fact that these populations are separated by no more than 10 km. Yet, another novel lineage is detected in the northern populations of Ambanja (locality 79) and Montagne d'Ambre (locality 56). This latter lineage may equate with a recently described species from Montagne d'Ambre, <italic>M. arnholdi</italic>, which was described on the basis of mtDNA divergence from other northern populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis2">[29]</xref>. However, the lack of overlapping mtDNA regions across studies limits a direct connection between the lineage diagnosed here and <italic>M. arnholdi</italic>. Overall, these patterns of lineage divergence suggest that mouse lemur speciation can occur at a broad range of geographic levels, and indeed, indicates the probability of even more as-yet-undescribed lineage diversity. A number of additional species have been described in recent years that we cannot address with the nuclear data in this study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Olivieri1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Radespiel1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis2">[29]</xref> and future work will be needed to assess the validity of these described taxa as independent lineages.</p>
<fig id="pone-0009883-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Phylogenetic descriptions of areas of sympatry and fine-scale allopatry among <italic>Microcebus</italic> lineages.</title>
<p>Colored sections in the maps of Madagascar signify areas of micro-endemism and white sections signify retreat dispersion regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wilm1">[21]</xref>. All known regions of sympatry in mouse lemurs involve populations of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>murinus</italic> sensu lato. The top two outlined boxes highlight regions of sympatry involving <italic>M</italic>. <italic>murinus</italic> and at least three other species (<italic>M</italic>. <italic>bongolavensis</italic> could not be assessed in this study), each of which shares a most recent common ancestor with <italic>M. murinus</italic> at the root of most gene trees. However, at least one case of sympatry is known that involves <italic>M. murinus</italic> and its sister lineage, <italic>M. griseorufus</italic>, in the Berenty Reserve in southern Madagascar [not sampled in this study and not depicted here <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Yoder3">[69]</xref>. As further support for the speciation model of Wilmé et al. (2006), areas of sympatry appear to be clustered in or near retreat dispersion regions, which are proposed to have influenced the expansion of species ranges during the Quaternary. In contrast, the bottom outlined box highlights lineage distributions within a single region of micro-endemism in the southeast.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.g003" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>In contrast, the analytical approach and criteria used here also identified patterns reflecting the signal of population divergence, but without straightforward evidence for independent evolution. This is best exemplified with a set of three previously described species: <italic>M</italic>. <italic>berthae</italic> and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>myoxinus</italic> in the western part of the island, and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>rufus</italic> in the east. Each is distinct in the mtDNA gene tree (<italic>M</italic>. <italic>rufus</italic> is paraphyletic), is largely comprised of a characteristic nuclear cluster in STRUCTURE analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>), and has significant <italic>gsi</italic> estimates. However, while individuals within <italic>M</italic>. <italic>berthae</italic> and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>myoxinus</italic> are predominantly assigned to distinct nuclear clusters, the <italic>M</italic>. <italic>rufus</italic> population of Ranomafana has an average of 12% of its overall membership coefficients attributed to the <italic>M</italic>. <italic>berthae</italic> cluster and 9% attributed to <italic>M. myoxinus</italic> clusters (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>). As a comparison, no other species diagnosed in this study had an average membership coefficient of &gt;5% from any other species' nuclear cluster. These patterns are suggestive of gene flow into the range of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>rufus</italic>. In such cases, determining the evolutionary independence of these potential lineages will require additional sources of information. In this particular case, geography is particularly informative: the western lineages (<italic>M. berthae</italic> and <italic>M. myoxinus</italic>) are highly genetically distinct from each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009883-t002">Table 2</xref>), but are extremely close geographically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g001">Figs. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g003">3</xref>). In contrast, both are separated from <italic>M. rufus</italic> by a high elevation north-south mountain system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). These geographic patterns indicate that if gene flow is the cause of the slightly mixed cluster assignment for <italic>M. rufus</italic>, then it is historical in nature, and currently all three lineages (<italic>M</italic>. <italic>berthae</italic>, <italic>M</italic>. <italic>myoxinus</italic>, and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>rufus</italic>) are genetically isolated. As such, these patterns suggest that all three are diverging population-level lineages.</p>
<p>Finally, we not only identify sets of independently evolving lineages with this approach, but also identify cohesive sets of populations, particularly in situations where mtDNA distinctiveness would suggest divergence. This is best exemplified with the recently described <italic>M</italic>. <italic>mamiratra</italic> from northwest Madagascar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Andriantompohavana1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Olivieri1">[26]</xref>. Our results find some individuals from Ambanja (locality 79) to contain mtDNA haplotypes placed within the <italic>M</italic>. <italic>mamiratra</italic> clade, which nonetheless have a nuclear structure profile indistinguishable from individuals of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>sambiranensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). We therefore propose that the diagnosis of <italic>M. mamiratra</italic> is based on insufficient structure in mtDNA variation and should not be recognized. Similar patterns exist within the currently recognized taxa <italic>M</italic>. <italic>murinus</italic>, <italic>M</italic>. <italic>myoxinus</italic>, and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>simmonsi</italic>. Within each of these taxa, subsets of populations exhibit monophyly in the mtDNA gene tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>), suggestive of lineage divergence; yet, these subpopulations also exhibit nuclear STRUCTURE profiles that indicate an admixed background of nuclear gene flow and cohesion with other populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). These contrasting patterns between the mtDNA and nuclear genetic data may be related to the propensity for female philopatry in lemurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Fredsted1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wimmer1">[35]</xref> and highlight the potential pitfalls of relying solely on mtDNA gene tree patterns in the delimitation of mouse lemur species.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Mouse lemur evolution</title>
<p>What do these results have to say about the mechanism of speciation in <italic>Microcebus</italic>, and about lemur diversification in general? The isolated geographic distributions of most mouse lemur species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g002">Fig. 2</xref>) indicate a strong role for allopatric speciation. Furthermore, while we are currently limited in our ability to infer a robust species tree and divergence time estimates for mouse lemur lineages, the predominant lack of reciprocal monophyly across nuclear gene trees (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s004">Figures S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s005">S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s006">S4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009883.s007">S5</xref>) suggests relatively recent divergence times for most. These two inferences align with a recent model for the origin of micro-endemic regions in Madagascar, which places emphasis on reduced precipitation during the Quaternary and formation of forest refugia in lower elevation river catchments around the periphery of the island <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wilm1">[21]</xref>. A number of mouse lemur lineages lie within, or mostly within, these areas of micro-endemism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009883-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), indicating that this model may account for diversification at some level. Additional diversification models developed for Madagascar, including the roles of climate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Pearson1">[61]</xref>, rivers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Martin1">[19]</xref>, and mountains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Wollenberg1">[62]</xref> also remain to be tested with a robust estimate of the mouse lemur species tree <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Vences1">[63]</xref>.</p>
<p>Also of interest is the paralleled high level of recently recognized species diversity in other nocturnal lemur genera (e.g. <italic>Avahi</italic>, <italic>Lepilemur</italic>), suggesting a link between nocturnal activity and unrealized population genetic structure. An important behavioral mechanism in nocturnal lemurs is acoustic signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Fichtel1">[64]</xref>, a necessary form of communication in the dark. Mouse lemur species in particular have evolved distinctly different male advertisement calls <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Braune1">[65]</xref>, providing a potential mechanism for premating isolation that can limit admixture among populations that have previously experienced allopatric divergence. Contrastingly, however, a study of the closely related and nocturnal dwarf lemurs (<italic>Cheirogaleus</italic>) using the same markers and some of the methods applied here finds a disproportionately low level of taxonomic diversity [3 diagnosable species as compared to 7 proposed in recent years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Groves1">[66]</xref>], despite having a similar island-wide distribution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Groeneveld1">[67]</xref>.</p>
<p>We provide here the most comprehensive species delimitation study of lemurs ever performed and are the first to integrate gene tree analysis, Bayesian STRUCTURE analysis, and quantifications of genealogical divergence in the identification of population-level lineages. While our results confirm the high lineage diversity results of previous mtDNA-based studies, this should not serve as justification for limiting future studies to a single marker in a DNA-barcoding protocol. Instead, our results regarding the lack of corresponding nuclear evidence of divergence for some resolved mtDNA lineages and the under appreciation of fine-scale geographic patterns of lineage divergence not previously highlighted in mtDNA studies emphasizes the need for a more thorough approach utilizing appropriate genetic data and analytical methods. The approach outlined here may also serve as a general model for lineage diagnosis of other groups with a predominant pattern of cryptic diversity. For example, recent surveys of Malagasy frogs found an additional 129 mtDNA lineages that either lack clear morphological or acoustic differences, or that have not yet been studied with independent data that can be used to test their distinctiveness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Vieites1">[68]</xref>. Testing these lineages with the population genetic and genealogical framework used here may provide an ideal alternative to further field and museum-based assessments of species delimitation.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0009883.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.s001" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p>Locality and sampling information for all <italic>Microcebus</italic> localities used in this study.</p>
<p>(0.19 MB DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0009883.s002" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.s002" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p>GenBank accession numbers for all outgroup sequence data and the <italic>Microcebus</italic> mtDNA sequence data of Louis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Andriantompohavana1">[24]</xref> and Olivieri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0009883-Louis1">[25]</xref>.</p>
<p>(0.12 MB DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0009883.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.s003" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p>MtDNA gene tree. The tree results from Bayesian phylogenetic analysis of the mtDNA haplotype data set and is presented as the maximum credible topology with branch lengths averaged across the posterior distribution (Mean -lnL = 1.33×10<sup>4</sup>, Std. Dev. = 7.76). Tip labels include a species name if the haplotype was sampled from an individual identified to a species in a previous study. Haplotypes recovered from newly sampled individuals are indicated with the locality name.</p>
<p>(1.84 MB TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0009883.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.s004" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><italic>adora3</italic> gene tree. The tree results from Bayesian phylogenetic analysis of the <italic>adora3</italic> haplotype data set and is presented as the maximum credible topology with branch lengths averaged across the posterior distribution (Mean -lnL = 1104.67, 95% HPD = 1118.35-1093.08). Tip labels include a species name if the haplotype was sampled from an individual identified to a species in a previous study. Haplotypes recovered from newly sampled individuals are indicated with the locality name.</p>
<p>(1.54 MB TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0009883.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.s005" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><italic>eno</italic> gene tree. The tree results from Bayesian phylogenetic analysis of the <italic>eno</italic> haplotype data set and is presented as the maximum credible topology with branch lengths averaged across the posterior distribution (Mean -lnL = 4557.6, 95%HPD = 4582.15-4531.58). Tip labels include a species name if the haplotype was sampled from an individual identified to a species in a previous study. Haplotypes recovered from newly sampled individuals are indicated with the locality name.</p>
<p>(1.74 MB TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0009883.s006" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.s006" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p><italic>fga</italic> gene tree. The tree results from Bayesian phylogenetic analysis of the <italic>fga</italic> haplotype data set and is presented as the maximum credible topology with branch lengths averaged across the posterior distribution (Mean -lnL = 2232.92, 95%HPD = 2251.07-2215.76). Tip labels include a species name if the haplotype was sampled from an individual identified to a species in a previous study. Haplotypes recovered from newly sampled individuals are indicated with the locality name.</p>
<p>(1.84 MB TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0009883.s007" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.s007" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S5</label><caption>
<p><italic>vwf</italic> gene tree. The tree results from Bayesian phylogenetic analysis of the <italic>vwf</italic> haplotype data set and is presented as the maximum credible topology with branch lengths averaged across the posterior distribution (Mean -lnL = 3980.14, 95%HPD = 4007.55-3953.37). Tip labels include a species name if the haplotype was sampled from an individual identified to a species in a previous study. Haplotypes recovered from newly sampled individuals are indicated with the locality name.</p>
<p>(1.81 MB TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0009883.s008" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009883.s008" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S6</label><caption>
<p>Plots of calculations for various K values in STRUCTURE analysis of the nuclear data. (a) The log probability of the data for K = 10 to 26. Colored lines represent replicate STRUCTURE analyses. (b) Posterior probabilities for K = 10 to 26 for replicate STRUCTURE analyses. Different dashed lines represent replicate analyses, many of which have the same posterior probability. (c) ΔK values for K = 2 to 25.</p>
<p>(1.55 MB TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We are grateful to the Direction des Eaux et Forêts and Association National pour la Gestion des Aires Protégées for issuing permits to capture specimens, and to Dr. D. Rakotondravony and the late Prof. O. Ramilijaona for help with numerous administrative details. We are also grateful to A. Bazinet for computing assistance in the calculation of <italic>gsi</italic> values, and to T. Ai for assistance in data collection. This work was enhanced by information exchanged in a workshop funded by the National Evolutionary Synthesis Center (NESCent).</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0009883-deQueiroz1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>de Queiroz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>The general lineage concept of species, species criteria, and the process of speciation: a conceptual unification and terminological recommendations.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Berlocher</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <source>Endless forms: species and speciation</source>             <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>57</fpage>             <lpage>75</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Mayden1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mayden</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>The denouement in the saga of the species problem.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Claridge</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dawah</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <source>Species: The units of biodiversity</source>             <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>             <fpage>381</fpage>             <lpage>424</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-deQueiroz2"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>de Queiroz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>The general lineage concept of species and the defining properties of the species category.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <source>Species: New Interdisciplinary Essays</source>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge, , MA</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>49</fpage>             <lpage>89</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Mayden2"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mayden</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Consilience and a hierarchy of species concepts: advances toward closure on the species puzzle.</article-title>             <source>J Nematol</source>             <volume>31</volume>             <fpage>95</fpage>             <lpage>116</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-deQueiroz3"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>de Queiroz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Species concepts and species delimitation.</article-title>             <source>Syst Biol</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>879</fpage>             <lpage>886</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Wiens1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wiens</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>What is speciation and how should we study it?</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>163</volume>             <fpage>914</fpage>             <lpage>923</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Wiens2"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wiens</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Species delimitation: new approaches for discovering diversity.</article-title>             <source>Syst Biol</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>875</fpage>             <lpage>878</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Rosenberg1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nordborg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Genealogical trees, coalescent theory and the analysis of genetic polymorphisms.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>380</fpage>             <lpage>390</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Degnan1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Degnan</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Salter</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Gene tree distributions under the coalescent process.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>59</volume>             <fpage>24</fpage>             <lpage>37</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Pons1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barraclough</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Zurita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Sequence-based species delimitation for the DNA taxonomy of undescribed insects.</article-title>             <source>Syst Biol</source>             <volume>55</volume>             <fpage>595</fpage>             <lpage>609</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Baum1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Genealogical perspectives on the species problem.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hoch</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <source>Experimental and Molecular Approaches to Plant Biosystematics</source>             <publisher-loc>St. Louis</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Missouri Botanical Garden</publisher-name>             <fpage>289</fpage>             <lpage>303</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Avise1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Avise</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Principles of genealogical concordance in species concepts and biological taxonomy.</article-title>             <source>Oxf Surv Evol Biol</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>45</fpage>             <lpage>67</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Hebert1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cywinska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>DeWaard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Biological identifications through DNA barcodes.</article-title>             <source>P Roy Soc Lond B Bio</source>             <volume>270</volume>             <fpage>313</fpage>             <lpage>321</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Moore1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Inferring phylogenies from mtDNA variation: mitochondrial gene trees versus nuclear gene trees.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>49</volume>             <fpage>718</fpage>             <lpage>726</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Hudson1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Mathematical consequences of the genealogical species concept.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>1557</fpage>             <lpage>1565</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Knowles1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carstens</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Delimiting species without monophyletic gene trees.</article-title>             <source>Syst Biol</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>887</fpage>             <lpage>895</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Cummings1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Neel</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>A genealogical approach to quantifying lineage divergence.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>62</volume>             <fpage>2411</fpage>             <lpage>2422</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Shaffer1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Delimiting species in recent radiations.</article-title>             <source>Syst Biol</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>896</fpage>             <lpage>906</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Martin1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1972</year>             <article-title>Adaptive radiation and behavior of Malagasy lemurs.</article-title>             <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond, B, Biol Sci</source>             <volume>264</volume>             <fpage>295</fpage>             <lpage>352</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Thalmann1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thalmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Biodiversity, phylogeography, biogeography and conservation: lemurs as an example.</article-title>             <source>Folia Primatol</source>             <volume>78</volume>             <fpage>420</fpage>             <lpage>443</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Wilm1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wilmé</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ganzhorn</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Biogeographic evolution of Madagascar's microendemic biota.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>312</volume>             <fpage>1063</fpage>             <lpage>1065</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Harper1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Steininger</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Juhn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Fifty years of deforestation and forest fragmentation in Madagascar.</article-title>             <source>Environ Conserv</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>325</fpage>             <lpage>333</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Kappeler1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kappeler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rasoloarison</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Razafimanantsoa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Morphology, behaviour and molecular evolution of giant mouse lemurs (<italic>Mirza</italic> spp.) Gray, 1870, with description of a new species.</article-title>             <source>Primate Rep</source>             <volume>71</volume>             <fpage>3</fpage>             <lpage>26</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Andriantompohavana1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andriantompohavana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zaonarivelo</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Engberg</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Randriamampionona</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Mouse lemurs of northwestern Madagascar with a description of a new species at Lokobe Special Reserve.</article-title>             <source>Occas Pap Tex Tech Univ Mus</source>             <volume>259</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>23</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Louis1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andriantompohavana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Engberg</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Revision of the mouse lemurs (<italic>Microcebus</italic>) of eastern Madagascar.</article-title>             <source>Int J Primatol</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <fpage>347</fpage>             <lpage>389</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Olivieri1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Randrianambinina</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rasoloharijaona</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rakotondravony</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>The ever-increasing diversity in mouse lemurs: three new species in north and northwestern Madagascar.</article-title>             <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>309</fpage>             <lpage>327</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Radespiel1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Radespiel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rasolofoson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rakotondratsimba</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rakotonirainy</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Exceptional diversity of mouse lemurs (<italic>Microcebus</italic> spp.) in the Makira region with the description of one new species.</article-title>             <source>Am J Primatol</source>             <volume>70</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>14</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Rasoloarison1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rasoloarison</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ganzhorn</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Taxonomic revision of mouse lemurs (<italic>Microcebus</italic>) in the western portions of Madagascar.</article-title>             <source>Int J Primatol</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>963</fpage>             <lpage>1019</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Louis2"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Engberg</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mcguire</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Randriamampionona</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Revision of the mouse lemurs, <italic>Microcebus</italic> (Primates, Lemuriformes), of northern and northwestern Madagascar with descriptions of two new species at Montagne d'Ambre National Park and Antafondro Classified Forest.</article-title>             <source>Primate Conservation</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>19</fpage>             <lpage>38</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Tattersall1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tattersall</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Madagascar's lemurs: cryptic diversity or taxonomic inflation?</article-title>             <source>Evol Anthropol</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>12</fpage>             <lpage>23</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Weisrock1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weisrock</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Multiple nuclear gene sequences identify phylogenetic species boundaries in the rapidly radiating clade of Mexican ambystomatid salamanders.</article-title>             <source>Mol Ecol</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>2489</fpage>             <lpage>2503</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Funk1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Omland</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Species-level paraphyly and polyphyly: frequency, causes, and consequences, with insights from animal mitochondrial DNA.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>397</fpage>             <lpage>423</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Maddison1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Gene trees in species trees.</article-title>             <source>Syst Biol</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>523</fpage>             <lpage>536</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Fredsted1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fredsted</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pertoldi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schierup</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kappeler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Microsatellite analyses reveal fine-scale genetic structure in grey mouse lemurs (<italic>Microcebus murinus</italic>).</article-title>             <source>Mol Ecol</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>2363</fpage>             <lpage>2372</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Wimmer1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wimmer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tautz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kappeler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>The genetic population structure of the gray mouse lemur (<italic>Microcebus murinus</italic>), a basal primate from Madagascar.</article-title>             <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source>             <volume>52</volume>             <fpage>166</fpage>             <lpage>175</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Allnutt1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Allnutt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Manion</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ricketts</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>A method for quantifying biodiversity loss and its application to a 50-year record of deforestation across Madagascar.</article-title>             <source>Conservation Letters</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>173</fpage>             <lpage>181</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Yoder1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rasoloarison</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Atsalis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Remarkable species diversity in Malagasy mouse lemurs (primates, <italic>Microcebus</italic>).</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>97</volume>             <fpage>11325</fpage>             <lpage>11330</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Duminil1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Duminil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Scotti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cazal</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Blind population genetics survey of tropical rainforest trees.</article-title>             <source>Mol Ecol</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>3505</fpage>             <lpage>3513</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Heckman1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Heckman</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rasoloarison</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Multiple nuclear loci reveal patterns of incomplete lineage sorting and complex species history within western mouse lemurs (<italic>Microcebus</italic>).</article-title>             <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>353</fpage>             <lpage>367</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Adkins1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Adkins</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Honeycutt</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>Evolution of the primate Cytochrome <italic>c</italic> Oxidase Subunit II gene.</article-title>             <source>J Mol Evol</source>             <volume>38</volume>             <fpage>215</fpage>             <lpage>231</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Irwin1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kocher</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Evolution of the Cytochrome <italic>b</italic> gene of mammals.</article-title>             <source>J Mol Evol</source>             <volume>32</volume>             <fpage>128</fpage>             <lpage>144</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Horvath1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weisrock</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Embry</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorentino</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Balhoff</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Development and application of a phylogenomic toolkit: resolving the evolutionary history of Madagascar's lemurs.</article-title>             <source>Genome Res</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>489</fpage>             <lpage>499</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Stephens1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>A new statistical method for haplotype reconstruction from population data.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>68</volume>             <fpage>978</fpage>             <lpage>989</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Hudson2"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1985</year>             <article-title>Statistical properties of the number of recombination events in the history of a sample of DNA sequences.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>111</volume>             <fpage>147</fpage>             <lpage>164</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Rozas1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-DelBarrio</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Messeguer</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>DnaSP, DNA polymorphism analyses by the coalescent and other methods.</article-title>             <source>Bioinformatics</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>2496</fpage>             <lpage>2497</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Fu1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Statistical tests of neutrality of mutations.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>133</volume>             <fpage>693</fpage>             <lpage>709</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Ronquist1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>MrBayes 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed models.</article-title>             <source>Bioinformatics</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>1572</fpage>             <lpage>1574</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Nylander1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nylander</surname><given-names>JAA</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>MrModeltest v2. Program distributed by the author.</article-title>             <source>Evolutionary Biology Centre, Uppsala University</source>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Swofford1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Swofford</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>PAUP*. Phylogenetic Analysis Using Parsimony (*and Other Methods). 4 ed.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Sunderland, Massachusettes</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Sinauer Associates</publisher-name>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Pritchard1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Inference of population structure using multilocus genotype data.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>155</volume>             <fpage>945</fpage>             <lpage>959</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Falush1"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Falush</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Inference of population structure using multilocus genotype data: linked loci and correlated allele frequencies.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>164</volume>             <fpage>1567</fpage>             <lpage>1587</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Evanno1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Evanno</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Regnaut</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: a simulation study.</article-title>             <source>Mol Ecol</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>2611</fpage>             <lpage>2620</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Andreone1"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andreone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>du Preez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>The challenge of conserving amphibian megadiversity in Madagascar.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>943</fpage>             <lpage>946</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Slatkin1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Slatkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>Gene flow and the geographic structure of natural populations.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>236</volume>             <fpage>787</fpage>             <lpage>792</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Pamilo1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pamilo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>Relationships between gene trees and species trees.</article-title>             <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>568</fpage>             <lpage>583</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Yoder2"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hanley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Heckman</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rasoloarison</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>A multidimensional approach for detecting species patterns in Malagasy vertebrates.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>102</volume>             <fpage>6587</fpage>             <lpage>6594</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Caparroz1"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Caparroz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Miyaki</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Contrasting phylogeographic patterns in mitochondrial DNA and microsatellites: evidence of female philopatry and male-biased gene flow among regional populations of the Blue-and-yellow Macaw (Psittaciformes: <italic>Ara ararauna</italic>) in Brazil.</article-title>             <source>Auk</source>             <volume>126</volume>             <fpage>359</fpage>             <lpage>370</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Hudson3"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Turelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Stochasticity overrules the “three-times rule”: genetic drift, genetic draft, and coalescence times for nuclear loci versus mitochondrial DNA.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>57</volume>             <fpage>182</fpage>             <lpage>190</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Rosenberg2"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cann</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Genetic structure of human populations.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>298</volume>             <fpage>2381</fpage>             <lpage>2385</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Goodman1"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pidgeon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>AFA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schulenberg</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>The birds of southeastern Madagascar.</article-title>             <source>Fieldiana</source>             <volume>87</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>132</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Pearson1"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Raxworthy</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>The evolution of local endemism in Madagascar: watershed versus climatic gradient hypotheses evaluated by null biogeographic models.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>63</volume>             <fpage>959</fpage>             <lpage>967</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Wollenberg1"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wollenberg</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vieites</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>van der Meijden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Glaw</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cannatella</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Patterns of endemism and species richness in Malagasy cophyline frogs support a key role of mountainous areas for speciation.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>62</volume>             <fpage>1890</fpage>             <lpage>1907</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Vences1"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vences</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wollenberg</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vieites</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Madagascar as a model region of species diversification.</article-title>             <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>456</fpage>             <lpage>465</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Fichtel1"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fichtel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Avoiding predators at night: antipredator strategies in red-tailed sportive lemurs (<italic>Lepilemur ruficaudatus</italic>).</article-title>             <source>Am J Primatol</source>             <volume>69</volume>             <fpage>611</fpage>             <lpage>624</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Braune1"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Braune</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Acoustic divergence in the communication of cryptic species of nocturnal primates (<italic>Microcebus</italic> ssp.).</article-title>             <source>BMC Biol</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>19</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Groves1"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Groves</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>The genus <italic>Cheirogaleus</italic>: unrecognized biodiversity in dwarf lemurs.</article-title>             <source>Int J Primatol</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>943</fpage>             <lpage>962</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Groeneveld1"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Groeneveld</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weisrock</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rasoloarison</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kappeler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Species delimitation in lemurs: multiple genetic loci reveal low levels of species diversity in the genus <italic>Cheirogaleus</italic>.</article-title>             <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>30</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Vieites1"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vieites</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wollenberg</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andreone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Glaw</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Vast underestimation of Madagascar's biodiversity evidenced by an integrative amphibian inventory.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>106</volume>             <fpage>8267</fpage>             <lpage>8272</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0009883-Yoder3"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Genin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Molecular evidence of reproductive isolation in sympatric sibling species of mouse lemurs.</article-title>             <source>Int J Primatol</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>1335</fpage>             <lpage>1343</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
</ref-list>

</back>
</article>