<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-45465</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Circuit models</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biophysic al simulations</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Circuit models</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Learning and memory</subject><subject>Neural networks</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Computer science</subject><subj-group><subject>Computer modeling</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Calcium-Dependent Calcium Decay Explains STDP in a Dynamic Model of Hippocampal Synapses</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Calcium-Dependent Calcium Decay Explains STDP</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Standage</surname><given-names>Dominic</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trappenberg</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blohm</surname><given-names>Gunnar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences and Center for Neuroscience Studies, Queen’s University, Kingston, Ontario, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Faculty of Computer Science, Dalhousie University, Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maravall</surname><given-names>Miguel</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Instituto de Neurociencias de Alicante UMH-CSIC, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">standage@queensu.ca</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: DS TT. Performed the experiments: DS. Analyzed the data: DS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: DS TT GB. Wrote the paper: DS TT GB.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<elocation-id>e86248</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Standage et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>It is widely accepted that the direction and magnitude of synaptic plasticity depends on post-synaptic calcium flux, where high levels of calcium lead to long-term potentiation and moderate levels lead to long-term depression. At synapses onto neurons in region CA1 of the hippocampus (and many other synapses), NMDA receptors provide the relevant source of calcium. In this regard, post-synaptic calcium captures the coincidence of pre- and post-synaptic activity, due to the blockage of these receptors at low voltage. Previous studies show that under spike timing dependent plasticity (STDP) protocols, potentiation at CA1 synapses requires post-synaptic bursting and an inter-pairing frequency in the range of the hippocampal theta rhythm. We hypothesize that these requirements reflect the saturation of the mechanisms of calcium extrusion from the post-synaptic spine. We test this hypothesis with a minimal model of NMDA receptor-dependent plasticity, simulating slow extrusion with a calcium-dependent calcium time constant. In simulations of STDP experiments, the model accounts for latency-dependent depression with either post-synaptic bursting or theta-frequency pairing (or neither) and accounts for latency-dependent potentiation when both of these requirements are met. The model makes testable predictions for STDP experiments and our simple implementation is tractable at the network level, demonstrating associative learning in a biophysical network model with realistic synaptic dynamics.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by The Canadian Institutes of Health Research and The Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Activity-dependent change in synaptic strength is widely believed to underlie learning and memory, as originally proposed by Hebb <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Hebb1">[1]</xref>. To have behavioural significance, synapses must be equipped to extract statistical regularities in the spiking behaviour of their pre- and post-synaptic neurons. Numerous algorithms have implemented this principle in artificial neural networks, where the strength of connections between processing units changes as a function of correlations in their output rates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Kohonen1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Lawrence1">[6]</xref>. These algorithms readily learn to associate patterns of network activity with one another, that is, they implement Hebbian associative learning (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Trappenberg1">[7]</xref>). Similarly, activity-dependent change in the strength of synapses, or synaptic plasticity, is well established in the forms of long term potentiation (LTP) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bliss1">[8]</xref> and long term depression (LTD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Dudek1">[9]</xref>. Notably, the direction of plasticity (LTP or LTD) has been shown to depend on pre- and post-synaptic activation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Artola1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Ngezahayo1">[11]</xref>, including pre- and post-synaptic spike timing correlations (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bi1">[12]</xref>).</p>
<p>Spike timing-dependent plasticity (STDP) refers to experimental data showing that the direction and magnitude of synaptic change can be controlled by the precise timing of repeated pre- and post-synaptic spike patterns <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Markram1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>. STDP has played an important role in revealing the mechanisms underlying plasticity (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Dan1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Lisman1">[21]</xref>), but ‘learning rules’ fit to these data do not easily generalize to deviations from the strict protocols under which the data were recorded (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval1">[22]</xref>). In contrast, by simulating the underlying neurophysiology, synaptic models have provided mechanistic explanations for data recorded under different STDP protocols and at different synapses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval2">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bush1">[30]</xref>. The fundamental premise of these models is that a biological variable captures the statistics of pre- and post-synaptic spiking and is used by intracellular signalling pathways to modify synaptic strength accordingly.</p>
<p>Here, we focus on the synapse that has been most intensively studied in plasticity experiments to date, that between pyramidal neurons in regions CA3 and CA1 of the hippocampus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval1">[22]</xref>. As with virtually all synapses, plasticity at CA3-CA1 synapses depends on post-synaptic calcium (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) in dendritic spines, where high levels of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> lead to LTP, and moderate, above-baseline levels lead to LTD (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Artola2">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Malenka1">[32]</xref>). We follow the approach of Shouval and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval2">[23]</xref> by further assuming that the relevant supply of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is mediated by NMDA receptors (NMDARs), known to be required for LTP and LTD at synapses onto CA1 neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Malenka1">[32]</xref>. In this regard, NMDARs provide a mechanism for pre- and post-synaptic coincidence detection: they bind glutamate, providing a marker for pre-synaptic spiking, but they are blocked by magnesium until sufficiently depolarized by back-propagating action potentials (BAPs), which provide markers for post-synaptic spiking. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> enters the post-synaptic spine when these two markers overlap.</p>
<p>Under STDP protocols, LTP at CA3-CA1 synapses not only depends on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> flux and NMDAR activation, but also requires post-synaptic bursting and an inter-pairing frequency in the range of the hippocampal theta rhythm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). We build on earlier modelling work <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval2">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bush1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Kumar1">[33]</xref> by proposing a novel mechanistic explanation for these two requirements for LTP. We hypothesize that these requirements reflect the saturation of the mechanisms underlying <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion from the post-synaptic spine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Sabatini1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Scheuss1">[35]</xref>, supporting the buildup of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> by preventing its decay with sufficiently-vigorous spiking activity. We test this hypothesis with a dynamic model of post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> flux, where the rate of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> decay is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent. We show that our model accounts for the post-synaptic burst-dependence and theta-frequency pairing-dependence of LTP under spike timing protocols at CA3-CA1 synapses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pike1">[36]</xref>; we demonstrate that under biophysically plausible parameter values, the model cannot reproduce these findings without the dynamic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant; and we make predictions for experimental verification. We further demonstrate that under the same parameters that reproduce these data, our model supports Hebbian associative learning in a biophysical network model of hippocampal circuitry with realistic synaptic dynamics.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Our model is based on the premise that high levels of post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> trigger kinase-activated intracellular pathways, leading to LTP, and moderate, above-baseline levels trigger phosphatase-activated pathways, leading to LTD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Artola2">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Lisman2">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pi1">[38]</xref>. Consistent with evidence that plasticity at CA1 synapses is NMDAR-dependent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Malenka1">[32]</xref>, we assume that NMDARs provide a coincidence detector of pre- and post-synaptic activity, permitting the influx of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> when their activation coincides with BAPs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval2">[23]</xref>. We take a simple approach in this regard, simulating the activation of NMDARs as the proportion of glutamate-bound channels at the synapse, simulating BAPs as the proportion of maximum dendritic depolarization, and simulating <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> flux as the decaying product of these two terms, scaled by a soft cap. Note that our model addresses homosynaptic plasticity, implicit in the assumption of coincidence detection by NMDARs. Like earlier authors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rackham1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bush1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Kumar1">[33]</xref>, we assume that the tail of the BAP has a residual buildup, so that the overlap between NMDARs and BAPs supports <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> flux when post-synaptic spikes precede pre-synaptic spikes during STDP protocols (see below).</p>
<p>To test the hypothesis that the post-synaptic burst-dependence and inter-pairing frequency dependence of LTP at CA3-CA1 synapses can be explained by the saturation of the mechanisms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion from the spine, we modelled the saturation of these mechanisms with a <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant. As such, the time constant of decay was modelled as the summation of a baseline time constant and a sigmoidal function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We directly simulated the STDP experiments of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> by generating pre- and post-synaptic impulses according to their experimental protocols, as well as experiments from two earlier, related studies of CA3-CA1 synapses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pike1">[36]</xref>.</p>
<p>To demonstrate that our <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-based plasticity model can support Hebbian associative learning under biologically plausible conditions, we embedded the model in a network of leaky integrate-and-fire neurons with realistic synaptic dynamics. Our chosen task was auto-associative recall, a classic task for models of hippocampal circuitry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Marr1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Alvarez1">[40]</xref>.</p>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>A <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-based Plasticity Model with a <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Time Constant</title>
<p>The activation of NMDARs is described by<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e025"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e025" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the time constant of decay, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> controls receptor saturation and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the opening of receptor channels. Channel opening is described by<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e029"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e029" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> determines rise time, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the Dirac delta function and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the time of pre-synaptic firing.</p>
<p>BAPs are composed of a peak and a tail <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rackham1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bush1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Kumar1">[33]</xref>. The peak is defined by<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e033"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e033" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the time constant of decay, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the time of post-synaptic firing, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is a scale factor determining the proportion of the BAP magnitude attributable to the peak.</p>
<p>The BAP tail is defined by<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e037"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e037" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>with half-life <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and scale factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The composite BAP is defined by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g001">Figure 1A</xref>. In simulations with more than one post-synaptic spike in each pairing, we allow the BAPs to summate, as seen during theta-burst stimulation of CA1 neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rosenkranz1">[41]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Minimal <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> plasticity model with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant.</title>
<p>(A) Simulated back-propagating action potentials (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, bottom) are composed of a peak (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, top) and a tail (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, middle). The two vertical dashes above the figure indicate the timing of post-synaptic spikes. (B) The <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-like variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the scaled product of NMDAR activation and the BAP (see Methods). Grey and black vertical dashes indicate the timing of pre- and post-synaptic spikes respectively. (C) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, capturing the saturation of the mechanisms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion at high <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> levels.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The level of post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is simulated by<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e042"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e042" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is a scale factor, Ca<sup><italic>max</italic></sup>=1 provides a cap on post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is a <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant, capturing the slow extrusion of high levels of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from the spine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Scheuss1">[35]</xref>. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g001">Figure 1B</xref>. We use a sigmoid function for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, defined by<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e052"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e052" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> serves as a baseline time constant for post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> decay, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> places an upper limit on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> decay time, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> determines the slope of the function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g001">Figure 1C</xref>).</p>
<p>Plasticity is determined by simultaneous LTP and LTD processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wang1">[18]</xref>. Our LTP rule is<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e058"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e058" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the potentiation learning rate, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> provides a maximum weight (conductance strength) for synaptic weight <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (given initial value 1), and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> threshold for potentiation.</p>
<p>Our LTD rule is<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e076"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e076" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the depression learning rate and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> threshold for depression.</p>
<sec id="s2a1">
<title>Parameter values</title>
<p>For NMDARs, our parameter values were <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Hestrin1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Brigman1">[43]</xref>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Compte1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wang2">[45]</xref>. For BAPs, we followed an earlier <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-based plasticity model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Kumar1">[33]</xref> by setting <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, justified by data from CA1 slices <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Magee1">[46]</xref>. For the potentiation and depression learning rates, we set <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, consistent with experimental data showing that LTD takes much longer to elicit than LTP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Dudek1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>. The chosen values were <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For the LTP threshold, we chose a high value to emphasize the robustness of the proposed mechanism, <italic>i.e.</italic> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was far from the threshold when the inter-pairing frequency and post-synaptic burst requirements of LTP were not satisfied (shown in the Results). For the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we chose a saturating function because our model captures a saturating process (extrusion of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from the spine). The baseline <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant was <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Sabatini1">[34]</xref> and the maximum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant was <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, previously reported as the time constant of recovery from saturated extrusion in the spine at CA1 synapses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Scheuss1">[35]</xref>. We set the slope parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to a moderate value (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). The only remaining parameters were the LTD threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the scale factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which we adjusted to produce a good approximation of the LTP data by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> for 5 Hz pairings of a single pre-synaptic spike with two post-synaptic spikes (shown in the Results). The chosen values were <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which we used in our simulations of all other protocols. Note that within a reasonable range (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), the LTD threshold controlled the width of the LTD window as a function of the latency between pre- and post-synaptic activity, but did not qualitatively effect our results.</p>
<p>It is worth noting that the baseline time constant of calcium decay (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) refers to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion from the spine, which dominates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> clearance at synapses onto pyramidal neurons (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Higley1">[47]</xref>). Measurement of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is achieved by visualizing calcium transients with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-sensitive fluorescent molecules (calcium indicators), <italic>i.e.</italic> the indicators bind calcium so the transients can be measured. However, the binding of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> by indicators lengthens the duration of decay by providing an ‘exogenous buffer’ for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which slows its clearance. As such, numerous studies have reported <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constants on the order of hundreds of milliseconds, but these measurements included the effects of indicators. The time constant of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> decay can be estimated by using multiple concentrations of indicator, measuring the time constant of decay for each concentration, and regressing to the case of 0-indicator. As such, the baseline time constant of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> decay in dendritic spines is estimated to be several tens of milliseconds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Sabatini1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Simons1">[48]</xref>. At high concentrations of spine <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the mechanisms of extrusion saturate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Scheuss1">[35]</xref>, providing the basis for our model. See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Higley1">[47]</xref> for a thorough review of these and related issues.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>The Network Model</title>
<p>The local circuit model is a fully recurrent network of leaky integrate-and-fire neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Tuckwell1">[49]</xref>, comprised of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> simulated pyramidal neurons and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> fast-spiking inhibitory interneurons. Excitatory currents from pyramidal neurons were mediated by AMPA receptor (AMPAR) and NMDAR conductances, and inhibitory currents from interneurons were mediated by GABA receptor (GABAR) conductances. Synaptic connections from pyramidal neurons to interneurons, from interneurons to pyramidal neurons, and from interneurons to interneurons were uniform. Synaptic connections from pyramidal neurons to pyramidal neurons were scaled by weight <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, set to 0.5 at the start of each trial.</p>
<p>Each model neuron is described by<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e120"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e120" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the membrane capacitance of the neuron, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the leakage conductance, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the membrane potential, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e124" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the equilibrium potential, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e125" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the total input current. When <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e126" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reaches a threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e127" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, it is reset to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, after which it is unresponsive to its input for an absolute refractory period of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e129" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For pyramidal neurons, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e130" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e131" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e132" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e133" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e134" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e135" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For interneurons, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e136" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e137" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e138" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e139" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e140" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e141" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Compte1">[44]</xref>.</p>
<p>The total input current to each neuron <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e142" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is given by<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e143"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e143" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e144" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e145" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e146" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are the summed AMPAR, NMDAR and GABAR currents from intrinsic (recurrent collateral) synapses, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e147" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is background activity and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e148" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is selective input. The intrinsic currents are defined by<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e149"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e149" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e150" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e151" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e152" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are the respective strengths of AMPAR, NMDAR and GABAR conductance, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e153" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the reversal potential for AMPARs and NMDARs, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e154" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the reversal potential for GABARs, and indeces <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e155" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e156" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> indicate the synaptic connection to pyramidal neuron <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e157" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from pyramidal neuron <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e158" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. AMPAR and GABAR activation (proportion of open channels) are described by<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e159"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e159" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e160" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the time of firing of a pre-synaptic neuron. NMDAR activation is described above in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0086248.e025">Equation 1</xref>. The voltage-dependence of NMDARs is captured by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e161" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e162" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> describes the extracellular magnesium concentration and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e163" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is measured in millivolts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Jahr1">[50]</xref>.</p>
<p>At intrinsic synapses onto pyramidal neurons, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e164" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e165" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e166" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. At synapses onto interneurons, these conductances were scaled by a factor of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e167" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, a common approach in this class of network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Compte1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wang2">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Brunel1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Albantakis1">[52]</xref>. At extrinsic (feedforward) synapses onto pyramidal neurons, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e168" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, supporting strong selective input to the network. Consistent with recordings in hippocampal slices, the synaptic time constants used were <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e169" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Colquhoun1">[53]</xref> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e170" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Collingridge1">[54]</xref> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e171" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is provided above).</p>
<sec id="s2b1">
<title>Background activity</title>
<p>Theta-rhythmic background activity was simulated by sinusoidal current injection. The current injected at each neuron was the product of a <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e172" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> sin wave and the point conductance model of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Destexhe1">[55]</xref>. For each neuron, current <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e173" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is defined by<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e174"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e174" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(13)</label></disp-formula>where reversal potentials <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e175" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e176" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are given above (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0086248.e149">Equation 11</xref>). The time-dependent excitatory and inhibitory conductances <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e177" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e178" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are updated at each timestep <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e179" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> according to</p>
<p><disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e180"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e180" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(14)</label></disp-formula>and<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e181"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e181" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(15)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e182" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e183" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are average conductances, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e184" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e185" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are time constants, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e186" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is normally distributed random noise with 0 mean and unit standard deviation. Amplitude coefficients <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e187" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e188" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are defined by</p>
<p><disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e189"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e189" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(16)</label></disp-formula>and<disp-formula id="pone.0086248.e190"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e190" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(17)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e191" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e192" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are noise ‘diffusion’ coefficients. See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Destexhe1">[55]</xref> for the derivation of these equations. We followed <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0086248-t001">Table 1</xref> of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Destexhe1">[55]</xref> for parameter values <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e193" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e194" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e195" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e196" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for pyramidal neurons and interneurons and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e197" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for pyramidal neurons. We gave nominal values to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e198" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for interneurons and to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e199" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for pyramidal neurons and interneurons, setting these conductances to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e200" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <italic>i.e.</italic> the network’s intrinsic connectivity was sufficient to mediate realistic levels of inhibitory background activity onto pyramidal neurons and excitatory and inhibitory background activity onto interneurons. All simulations were run with timestep <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e201" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the standard implementation of Euler’s forward method. Our results were verified with the standard fourth order Runge-Kutta method.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0086248-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>A comparison of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e202" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-based plasticity models.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0086248-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shouval et al. (2002)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">int</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sym</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karmarkar and Buonomano (2002)</td>
<td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">peak</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sym</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">peak</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">asym</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abarbanelet al. (2003)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">time</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sym</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rubin et al. (2005)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">time</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">both</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hartley et al. (2006)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">int</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">both</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rackham et al. (2010)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">peak</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sym</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kumar and Mehta (2011)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">int</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sym</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Graupner and Brunel (2012)</td>
<td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear model</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">int</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">both</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonlinearmodel</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">int</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">asym</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bush and Jin (2012)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">int</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sym</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Our model</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">int</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sym</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>A comparison of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e203" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-based plasticity models. In relation to our model, earlier models can be distinguished along dimensions including: whether NMDARs provide the only source of calcium for plasticity (NM: yes/no); whether plasticity outcomes are determined by integrated <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e204" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, peak <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e205" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or the timecourse of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e206" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transients (CT: int/peak/time); whether an intermediate process transforms calcium levels to plasticity outcomes (IP: yes/no); whether LTP and LTD depend on the same source of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e207" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (SS: yes/no); whether saturation of the mechanisms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e208" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion was simulated (CE: yes/no); whether the model accounts for symmetric and/or asymmetric STDP data (TD: sym/asym/both); and whether the model demonstrated learning and memory (LM: yes/no).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Before showing our results, it is useful to summarise the data being addressed. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> recorded at CA3-CA1 synapses in slice preparations, where repetitive pairings of a single pre-synaptic spike with a single post-synaptic spike (the doublet protocol) produced LTD, the magnitude of which was inversely related to the time between spikes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e209" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This was the case regardless of the order of pre- and post-synaptic spiking (the sign of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e210" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) or the inter-pairing frequency (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e211" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e212" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e213" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). LTP not only required repetitive low-latency pairings of a pre-synaptic spike with at least two post-synaptic spikes (the triplet protocol), but also required an inter-pairing frequency of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e214" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. As with the doublet protocol, negative latencies produced LTD under the triplet protocol, the magnitude of which was inversely related to latency. Notably, these conditions also produced an LTD window at intermediate positive latencies, that is, LTD occurred when a post-synaptic burst followed a pre-synaptic spike by several tens of milliseconds. These data suggest temporally <italic>symmetric</italic> learning during the hippocampal theta rhythm, where tight coincidence of burst firing yields LTP, loose coincidence yields LTD, and a lack of coincidence yields no synaptic change (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval1">[22]</xref>). Note that these constraints fit naturally with auto-associative models of hippocampal learning <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Marr1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Alvarez1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Jensen1">[56]</xref>, demonstrated in Results section <italic>Hebbian associative learning in the network model</italic>. We refer to this form of STDP as temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP. We refer to STDP data in which pre-before-post pairings lead only to LTP and post-before-pre pairings lead only to LTD as temporally <italic>asymmetric</italic>, bidirectional STDP. In summary, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> ran experiments with four combinations of spike pairings and inter-pairing frequencies: (1) the doublet protocol at 0.1 Hz and 0.5 Hz produced LTD; (2) the doublet protocol at 5 Hz produced LTD; (3) the triplet protocol at 0.5 Hz produced LTD; and (4) the triplet protocol at 5 Hz produced temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP. Thus, LTP required short-latency pairings in the range of theta and post-synaptic bursting. LTD was produced if either of these requirements was not met.</p>
<p>In addition to the data by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, we also addressed data from two earlier plasticity studies with inter-pairing frequencies in the theta range, one demonstrating the requirement of post-synaptic bursting for LTP at CA1 synapses under protocols different than those described above <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pike1">[36]</xref>, and one showing temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP at CA1 synapses without the requirement of post-synaptic bursting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1">[15]</xref>. In the latter case, we demonstrate that the physiological explanation provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> for the lack of burst-dependence found by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1">[15]</xref> accounts for these data in our model. All these results were produced under the same parameters.</p>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Temporally Symmetric STDP at CA3-CA1 Synapses</title>
<p>To determine whether our <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e215" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> plasticity model can account for the data, we followed three STDP protocols used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>. First, we conducted simulations of the doublet protocol at latencies <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e216" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, using inter-pairing frequencies of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e217" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e218" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We refer to these pairings as pre-post for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e219" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and post-pre for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e220" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Next, we simulated the triplet protocol (a single pre-synaptic spike and two post-synaptic spikes) over the same range of latencies <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e221" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, using an inter-pairing frequency of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e222" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In this case, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e223" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the time between the pre-synaptic spike and the second post-synaptic spike. The post-synaptic spikes were separated by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e224" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We refer to these pairings as pre-post-post for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e225" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, post-pre-post for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e226" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and post-post-pre for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e227" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Finally, we repeated the triplet protocol with an inter-pairing frequency of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e228" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For all three sets of simulations, we used 75 pairings, consistent with the corresponding experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> used <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e229" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pairings in different conditions). These protocols and corresponding terminology are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g002">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Spike timing dependent plasticity (STDP) protocols.</title>
<p>STDP protocols used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> and corresponding terminology used here. For the doublet protocol, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e230" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the time between the pre-synaptic spike and the post-synaptic spike at each pairing. Pairings are referred to as pre-post (left) and post-pre (right). For the triplet protocol, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e231" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the time between the pre-synaptic spike and the second post-synaptic spike. Pairings are referred to as pre-post-post (left), post-pre-post (middle) and post-post-pre (right). The time between post-synaptic spikes is referred as to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e232" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The inter-pairing frequency is the reciprocal of the time between pairings, the inter-pairing interval. Two spike trains are depicted for pre-post-post pairings, with low (upper) and high (lower) inter-pairing frequency respectively.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The doublet protocol at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e233" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e234" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> produced LTD-only curves, where the magnitude of LTD was greatest at low latency, decreasing with increasing latency in the causal (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e235" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and anti-causal (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e236" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) directions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). Very similar curves were produced for all frequencies less than or equal to 9 Hz. Quantitatively, these LTD-only curves are narrower than the Gaussian fit to the data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g003">Figure 3A</xref>, but their qualitative resemblance is clear. The triplet protocol at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e237" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> produced an LTP window for tight temporal coincidence (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e238" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), surrounded by LTD windows in which the magnitude of LTD decreased with increasing latency on either side of the LTP window (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g004">Figure 4B</xref>, solid black). The corresponding data are reproduced from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g004">Figure 4A</xref>. Note that a graded transition between maximal LTP and LTD can be produced by tuning the LTP threshold. The triplet protocol at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e239" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> produced an LTD-only curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g004">Figure 4B</xref>, dotted grey). The mean value of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e240" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e241" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e242" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g003">Figures 3C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g004">4C</xref> for each condition shown in panel B in each figure.</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>STDP at CA3-CA1 synapses with single pre- and post-synaptic spikes (the doublet protocol).</title>
<p>(A) Data reproduced from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, fit with a Gaussian function (least squares fit). The grey dots indicate an inter-pairing frequency of 0.1 Hz and 0.5 Hz. The black dots indicate an inter-pairing frequency of 5 Hz. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e243" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the time between the pre-synaptic spike and the post-synaptic spike. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e244" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the change in synaptic strength relative to initial strength. (B) The model produced latency-dependent LTD-only curves (0.5 Hz grey, 5 Hz black). The curves are nearly indistinguishable. (C) Mean value of the dynamic time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e245" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for each value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e246" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in panel B. The doublet protocol has little effect on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e247" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Curves correspond to those in panel B.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0086248-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>STDP at CA3-CA1 synapses with a single pre-synaptic spike and two post-synaptic spikes (the triplet protocol).</title>
<p>(A) Data reproduced from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, fit with a difference of Gaussians (least squares fit). <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e248" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to time between the pre-synaptic spike and the second post-synaptic spike. (B) An inter-pairing frequency of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e249" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> produced a ‘symmetric’ STDP curve, where a narrow LTP window is shifted in the causal (pre-before-post) direction, surrounded by two latency-dependent LTD windows (solid black). An inter-pairing frequency of 0.5 Hz produced a depression-only curve (dotted grey). The post-synaptic spikes were separated by 10 ms. (C) Mean value of the dynamic time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e250" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for each value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e251" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in panel B (corresponding curves).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Our simulations thus support the hypothesis that the post-synaptic burst-dependence and inter-pairing frequency dependence of LTP at CA3-CA1 synapses can explained by the saturation of the mechanisms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e252" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion from the post-synaptic density. The mechanistic basis of these results is clear in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g005">Figure 5</xref>, where the dynamic time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e253" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the corresponding values of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e254" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-like variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e255" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are shown for the above protocols. The dynamic time constant supports high levels of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e256" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the triplet protocol at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e257" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, but under the other protocols, it decays to baseline between pairings (see figure caption for details).</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>The <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e258" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e259" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e260" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and corresponding values of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e261" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-like variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e262" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> under the STDP protocols used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>.</title>
<p>(A) The solid black curve shows <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e263" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for pre-post-post spiking with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e264" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and an inter-pairing frequency of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e265" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e266" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the time between the pre-synaptic spike and the second post-synaptic spike. Post-synaptic spikes were separated by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e267" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The grey curve shows <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e268" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> under the same spiking protocol, but with an inter-pairing frequency of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e269" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The dotted black curve shows <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e270" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for pre-post spiking with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e271" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and an inter-pairing frequency of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e272" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e273" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the time between the pre-synaptic spike and the post-synaptic spike. (B) The <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e274" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-like variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e275" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> during the same simulations as panel A, with corresponding curves. The upper and lower horizontal lines show the LTP and LTD thresholds respectively.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Simulations without the Dynamic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e276" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Time Constant</title>
<p>To determine whether the dynamic time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e277" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is required for the model to reproduce the data, we repeated our simulations without it, <italic>i.e.</italic> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e278" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> set to the baseline <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e279" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e280" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Because the parameter values given above were chosen for the intact model, it was necessary to choose parameter values without the dynamic time constant before running these simulations. To this end, we searched the space of values for three parameters: the baseline <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e281" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e282" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the time constant of decay of the BAP tail <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e283" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and the LTP threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e284" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Both versions of the model (with and without the dynamic time constant) readily account for the LTD data under the doublet protocol, so we searched for parameter values that produce LTP under the triplet protocol at 5 Hz, but produce LTD under the triplet protocol at 0.5 Hz. We did not search the time constants of rise and decay of NMDAR activation because the LTP window shown by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> was approximately <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e285" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, whereas the decay constant of NMDARs is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e286" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <italic>i.e.</italic> reasonable values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e287" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> govern the width of causal (pre-before-post) LTD, but do not effect the occurrence of LTP. We did not search the scale factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e288" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0086248.e042">Equation 5</xref>) because without the non-linearity of the dynamic time constant, this factor changes the scale of the simulations, not the phenomenology, <italic>i.e.</italic> any changes to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e289" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can be overcome by changes to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e290" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We did not search the proportion of the BAP given to the peak and the tail because these parameters change the scale of calcium transients for a given value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e291" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, but not their decay time. As long as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e292" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> does not have the opportunity to buildup between pairings, LTP will not occur at 0.5 Hz. Note that the available data support our chosen values, justified in Methods section <italic>Parameter values</italic>. Finally, we ignored the learning rates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e293" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e294" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> because they govern the magnitude of LTP and LTD respectively, not their occurrence.</p>
<p>The results of our parameter search for the model without the dynamic time constant are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g006">Figure 6</xref>, where the LTP window (expressed as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e295" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) is shown over the LTP threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e296" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for different values of the baseline <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e297" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e298" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (panels A, B and C) and the BAP tail <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e299" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (panel D). The lower and upper curves show the lowest and highest values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e300" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> under the triplet protocol for a given set of parameters. The black and grey curves show results for 5 Hz and 0.5 Hz respectively, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e301" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was incremented by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e302" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the search. For a given set of parameters to be consistent with the data, there should be an LTP window between approximately 0 and 25 ms for 5 Hz, but not for 0.5 Hz, <italic>i.e.</italic> there should be black curves, but not grey curves in this region. For <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e303" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e304" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (justified in Methods section <italic>Parameter values</italic>), fine tuning of the LTP threshold permits a non-overlapping region for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e305" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). Doubling <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e306" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> has little effect (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e307" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g006">Figure 6B</xref>). The data can be approximately reproduced for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e308" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g006">Figure 6C</xref>), but this value is biologically implausible (see Methods section 0). Alternatively, with the plausible baseline <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e309" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e310" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the data can be approximated with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e311" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g006">Figure 6D</xref>), but we are unaware of any data to support a BAP tail longer than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e312" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Thus, fine-tuning the model’s parameters allows the reproduction of the data without the dynamic time constant, but not under realistic parameter values. Further to this, we considered the robustness of the model by including noise in simulations of the triplet protocol at 0.5 Hz. Without the dynamic time constant, the model was given <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e313" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the implausible baseline <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e314" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e315" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g006">Figure 6C</xref>). We added normally distributed noise with mean <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e316" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and standard deviation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e317" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to each parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e318" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in each version of the model (with and without the dynamic time constant), and we ran 100 trials for each value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e319" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (the time between the pre-synaptic spike and the second post-synaptic spike) for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e320" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (increments of 1 ms). This range of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e321" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> in their experiments with spike triplets at 0.5 Hz, producing LTD. The noise had little impact on the dynamic model, where only 6 out of 1100 trials produced LTP. Without the dynamic time constant, these simulations produced LTP on 256 trials out of 1100.</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>The LTP window <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e322" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of the LTP threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e323" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> under the triplet protocol without the dynamic time constant (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e324" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).</title>
<p>The time between the pre-synaptic spike and the second post-synaptic spike was <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e325" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Post-synaptic spikes were separated by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e326" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e327" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is defined by the onset (lower curves) and offset (upper curves) of LTP as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e328" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g004">Figure 4</xref>. Black and grey curves show results for inter-pairing frequencies of 5 Hz and 0.5 Hz respectively. To be consistent with the data by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, the black and grey curves should not overlap from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e329" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Without the dynamic time constant, the model requires biologically implausible parameter values to reproduce the data (panels C and D, see text). (A) The LTP window for parameter values justified in the Methods (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e330" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e331" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). (B) The LTP window for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e332" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e333" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. (C) An implausibly long baseline time constant of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e334" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> decay approximates the data (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e335" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e336" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). (D) An implausibly long time constant of decay of the BAP tail approximates the data, though <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e337" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> expands slightly in the anti-causal direction (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e338" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e339" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Simulations of Further Spike-timing Protocols at CA1 Synapses</title>
<p>The study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> is not the only one to demonstrate the requirement of post-synaptic bursting for LTP at CA1 synapses under spike-timing protocols with an inter-pairing frequency in the theta range. Earlier work by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pike1">[36]</xref> also showed this requirement, where four protocols were followed: one pre-synaptic spike followed by one post-synaptic spike (1-pre-1-post), three pre-synaptic spikes followed by one post-synaptic spike (3-pre-1-post), one pre-synaptic spike followed by three post-synaptic spikes (1-pre-3-post), and three pre-synaptic spikes followed by three post-synaptic spikes (3-pre-3-post). For the 3-pre-1-post and 3-pre-3-post protocols, the time between pre-synaptic spikes was <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e340" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For the 1-pre-3-post and 3-pre-3-post protocols, post-synaptic spikes were elicited by current pulses of 20 ms, during which time the post-synaptic neuron emitted three spikes. In all cases, pre-synaptic activity preceded post-synaptic activity by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e341" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Ten pairings were provided with an inter-pairing frequency of 5 Hz, repeated four times at 10 s intervals. We simulated all four protocols for each integer value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e342" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We set the time between post-synaptic spikes to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e343" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, running simulations for each integer value within this range. For all <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e344" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e345" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the model reproduced the finding by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pike1">[36]</xref> that post-synaptic bursting is required for LTP. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g007">Figure 7</xref> shows the corresponding values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e346" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> during ten pairings for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e347" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e348" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Note that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pike1">[36]</xref> did not show LTD under these protocols, <italic>i.e.</italic> they showed no synaptic change, whereas the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e349" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transients in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g007">Figure 7</xref> for the 1-pre-1-post and 3-pre-1-post simulations exceed the LTD threshold used in our simulations of the experiments by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>. Raising the LTD threshold from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e350" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to approximately <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e351" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> would reproduce this aspect of the data of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pike1">[36]</xref>. Such an approach seems reasonable when comparing data from different studies, especially given the much higher <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e352" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transients with post-synaptic bursting.</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>The <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e353" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-like variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e354" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in simulations of the experiments by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pike1">[36]</xref></title>
<p> Results are shown for simulations with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e355" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e356" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e357" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e358" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the time between the last pre-synaptic spike and the first post-synaptic spike, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e359" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the time between pre-synaptic spikes and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e360" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the time between post-synaptic spikes. The LTP threshold (horizontal line) is only exceeded under conditions with post-synaptic bursting (1-pre-3-post and 3-pre-3-post), while pre-synaptic bursting has little effect on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e361" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (3-pre-1-post). The inter-pairing frequency was 5 Hz.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Where the study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> found that LTP at CA3-CA1 synapses required post-synaptic bursting and an inter-pairing frequency of 5 Hz, earlier authors found LTP at these synapses by pairing a single pre-synaptic spike with a single post-synaptic spike <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1">[15]</xref>, <italic>i.e.</italic> the doublet protocol, also at 5 Hz. A possible explanation for this discrepancy was given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, who pointed to the use by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1">[15]</xref> of an intracellular solution containing cesium instead of the normally-occurring potassium. Cesium blocks potassium channels, which can broaden action potentials and enhance BAPs in the apical dendrite, where CA3 neurons synapse onto CA1 neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Hoffman1">[57]</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> therefore made further recordings under the doublet protocol (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e362" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) with a cesium-based intracellular solution, finding that action potentials were broadened by a factor of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e363" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This manipulation was sufficient to rescue LTP. We simulated the effect of their cesium solution by broadening the decay constant of the BAP peak by a factor of 5 (from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e364" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e365" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and re-running our simulations of the doublet protocol for the full range of latencies <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e366" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This small change to the model’s parameters was sufficient to qualitatively reproduce the data by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1">[15]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g008">Figure 8</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>Temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP under the double protocol at 5 Hz in a cesium-based intracellular solution (see text).</title>
<p>(A) Data reproduced from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1">[15]</xref>, fit with a difference of Gaussians (least squares fit). (B) The effect of the cesium-based solution was simulated in the model by increasing the time constant of decay of the BAP peak by a factor of 5 (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e371" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>)).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Predictions for Experimental Enquiry</title>
<p>Having shown that the model accounts for the inter-pairing frequency dependence and post-synaptic burst dependence of LTP at CA3-CA1 synapses under the STDP protocols of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, we ran further simulations to investigate more subtle variations of these two independent variables. First, we ran simulations of the doublet protocol at inter-pairing frequencies above <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e367" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For frequencies <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e368" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the model produced LTD-only curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g009">Figure 9A</xref>), similar to those shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g003">Figure 3B</xref>. A narrow, causal LTP window emerged at 10 Hz, expanding in both directions as frequency was increased up to 14 Hz, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g009">Figure 9B</xref>. Note that the decreasing range of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e369" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with increasing frequency in the figure reflects the shortening of the period. At 15 Hz, LTP was saturated for all <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e370" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g009">Figure 9B</xref>). The model thus predicts that temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP can be produced by the doublet protocol at higher frequencies within the theta band, including LTP under low-latency post-pre pairings, and that the spike timing-dependence of LTP is dominated by spike rate at frequencies higher than theta.</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption>
<title>Predictions for STDP curves at CA3-CA1 synapses under the doublet protocol for a gradient of inter-pairing frequencies in the theta band (and higher).</title>
<p>(A) 75 pairings at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e372" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> produced latency-dependent, LTD-only curves. (B) Temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP was supported by frequencies from 10 Hz to 14 Hz (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e373" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as defined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g003">Figure 3</xref>). At 15 Hz, LTP is saturated for all latencies (horizontal black). In each panel, darker shades correspond to higher frequencies (see panel legends).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Next, we ran simulations of the triplet protocol with a range of inter-pairing frequencies. For frequencies <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e374" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the model produced LTD-only curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g010">Figure 10A</xref>), identical to the dotted grey curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g004">Figure 4B</xref>. At 4 Hz, a narrow, causal LTP window emerged. Similar to the higher-frequency doublet simulations, this LTP window expanded in both directions as frequency was increased up to 10 Hz (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g010">Figure 10B</xref>). At 11 Hz, LTP was saturated for all <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e375" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g010">Figure 10B</xref>). The model thus predicts that under the triplet protocol, the LTP window of temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP expands in both directions at higher frequencies within the theta band, including LTP under post-post-pre pairings, and that the spike timing-dependence of LTP is dominated by spike rate at sufficiently high frequency.</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g010" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption>
<title>Predictions for STDP curves at CA3-CA1 synapses under the triplet protocol for a gradient of inter-pairing frequencies in the theta band (and lower).</title>
<p>(A) 75 pairings at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e376" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> produced latency-dependent LTD-only curves. (B) Temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP was supported by frequencies from 4 Hz to 10 Hz (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e377" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as defined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g004">Figure 4</xref>). At 11 Hz, LTP is saturated for all latencies (horizontal black). Darker curves correspond to higher frequencies (see panel legend).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Having made predictions for a gradient of frequencies under the doublet and triplet protocols, we investigated the post-synaptic burst-dependence of LTP under low-frequency protocols with more than 2 post-synaptic spikes. We ran simulations at 2 Hz and 3 Hz with a quadruplet protocol, where one pre-synaptic spike was paired with three post-synaptic spikes. As with the doublet and triplet protocols, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e378" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was defined as the temporal difference between the pre-synaptic spike and the last post-synaptic spike (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e379" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is also defined this way for quintuplet and sextuplet pairings below). Under the quadruplet protocol, an LTP window emerged at 3 Hz, shifted in the causal direction (LTP onset at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e380" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g011">Figure 11A</xref>). At 2 Hz, a graded, LTD-only curve was produced by this protocol. Similarly, we ran simulations with a quintuplet protocol, where one pre-synaptic spike was paired with four post-synaptic spikes at frequencies of 1 Hz and 2 Hz. Temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP was produced under these low inter-pairing frequencies (identical curves in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g011">Figure 11B</xref>). These predictions are important to the interpretation of the data by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g011">Figures 11C and D</xref>, there is a difference between the mechanism underlying LTP under the triplet protocol and under the quintuplet and sextuplet protocols (5 post-synaptic spikes). Under the triplet protocol, an inter-pairing frequency in the theta range prevents <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e381" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from decaying to baseline between pairings, so <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e382" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> builds up over several pairings and eventually exceeds the LTP threshold (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Under the quintuplet and sextuplet protocols, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e383" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> exceeds the LTP threshold during each post-synaptic burst, but decays to baseline between pairings. This mechanistic difference explains why the STDP curves under the quintuplet protocol were identical at 1 Hz and 2 Hz, <italic>i.e.</italic> the inter-pairing frequency made no difference (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g011">Figure 11B</xref>). The model thus predicts that with bursts of more than two or three post-synaptic spikes, LTP does not require theta-frequency pairings.</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g011" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g011</object-id><label>Figure 11</label><caption>
<title>Predictions for STDP curves at CA3-CA1 synapses when a single pre-synaptic spike is paired with more than two post-synaptic spikes at inter-pairing frequencies lower than the theta band.</title>
<p>(A) 75 pairings under the quadruplet protocol (3 post-synaptic spikes) at frequencies of 2 Hz (dotted grey) and 3 Hz (solid black). (B) 75 pairings under the quintuplet protocol (4 post-synaptic spikes) at 1 Hz and 2 Hz. The curves are indistinguishable. (C) The dynamic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e384" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e385" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> under the quintuplet and sextuplet (5 post-synaptic spikes) protocols at 1 Hz. Post-synaptic spiking followed the pre-synaptic spike by 5 ms. (D) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e386" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transients, where curves correspond to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e387" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in panel C. The horizontal line shows the LTP threshold. In panels A and B, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e388" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is defined as the time between the pre-synaptic spike and the last post-synaptic spike. In panels C and D, black and grey curves correspond to the quintuplet and sextuplet protocols respectively. Post-synaptic spikes were separated by 10 ms under all protocols.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g011" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Hebbian Associative Learning in the Network Model</title>
<p>Having shown that our plasticity model qualitatively reproduces STDP data from CA3-CA1 synapses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pike1">[36]</xref> and makes predictions for experimental enquiry, we embedded the model in a network of integrate-and-fire neurons with realistic synaptic dynamics to determine whether it supports Hebbian associative learning under biophysically plausible conditions. Our chosen task was auto-associative recall, a classic task for hippocampal models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Marr1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Alvarez1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Jensen1">[56]</xref>, in which a spatial pattern of neural activity is associated with itself by the modification of excitatory recurrent synapses (see Discussion section <italic>Synaptic plasticity, learning and memory</italic>). All neurons in the network received noisy, theta-rhythmic current injection (see Methods section <italic>Background activity</italic>), while the neurons in a selective population (neurons 50–100 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g012">Figure 12A</xref>) each received independent, homogeneous Poisson spike trains at 500 Hz, mediated by AMPAR conductance synapses. The input to the selective population was provided for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e389" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> while the plasticity model was implemented at all recurrent synapses. We then provided the 500 Hz spike trains to half the selective population (neurons 75–100 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g012">Figure 12A</xref>) for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e390" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> without the plasticity model. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g012">Figure 12</xref>, the model supported associative learning, <italic>i.e.</italic> the network recalled the full spatial activity pattern from partial input. The value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e391" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at a randomly-chosen synapse between two neurons in the selective population is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g012">Figure 12B</xref>. The final strength of all synapses in the network is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g012">Figure 12C</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g012" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g012</object-id><label>Figure 12</label><caption>
<title>The <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e392" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> plasticity model supports Hebbian associative learning in a biophysical network model with realistic synaptic dynamics.</title>
<p>(A) Raster plot showing network spiking during learning (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e393" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and auto-associative recall (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e394" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The vertical line distinguishes these stages of the trial. Pyramidal neurons and inhibitory interneurons are indexed from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e395" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e396" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> respectively. The upper horizontal line distinguishes these cell types. All neurons received noisy theta-band current injection (see text). Neurons <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e397" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> received Poisson spike trains at 500 Hz during the learning stage of the trial. Neurons <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e398" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> received this input during the recall stage. The population receiving the input spike trains is outlined with a thin black line. (B) The trajectory of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e399" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-like variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e400" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> over the full trial at a randomly chosen synapse between two neurons in the selective population. Upper and lower horizontal lines show the LTP and LTD thresholds. (C) Synaptic conductance strength in the fully-connected network after learning, where lighter shades correspond to stronger synaptic connectivity.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g012" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Under STDP protocols, LTP at CA3-CA1 synapses depends on post-synaptic bursting and an inter-pairing frequency in the range of the hippocampal theta rhythm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>. We hypothesize that these dependencies reflect the saturation of the mechanisms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e401" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion from the post-synaptic spine. We have tested this hypothesis with a minimal model of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e402" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent plasticity, where the saturation of the mechanisms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e403" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion is simulated by the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e404" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependence of the time constant of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e405" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> decay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Our model qualitatively reproduces the STDP data of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, where latency-dependent LTD is elicited by pre- and post-synaptic spike doublets at frequencies of 5 Hz or less (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g003">Figure 3</xref>), and by spike triplets (one pre-synaptic spike and two post-synaptic spikes) at frequencies of 0.5 Hz or less (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g004">Figure 4</xref>). At a frequency of 5 Hz, triplet pairings produce temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Without the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e406" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e407" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant, the minimal model cannot reproduce these data under biologically plausible parameter values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g006">Figure 6</xref>). The model further accounts for the dependence of LTP on post-synaptic bursting at CA1 synapses under other spike timing protocols, including those with multiple pre-synaptic spikes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pike1">[36]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g007">Figure 7</xref>); and accounts for temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP under spike doublets with intracellular solutions that broaden BAPs at CA3-CA1 synapses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g008">Figure 8</xref>).</p>
<p>The model makes testable predictions about the burst-dependence and frequency-dependence of STDP at CA3-CA1 synapses. For example, our simulations predict that temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP will emerge under the doublet protocol at higher frequencies within the theta band (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e408" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), with the LTP window expanding in the causal and anti-causal directions with increasing frequency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g009">Figure 9</xref>). The model predicts that this expansion will also occur under the triplet protocol at lower theta frequencies (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e409" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g010">Figure 10</xref>) and that pairing pre-synaptic spikes with more than two or three post-synaptic spikes will elicit LTP at any sub-theta frequency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g011">Figure 11</xref>). Our <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e410" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> plasticity model is simple enough to be implemented at the network level and we have demonstrated associative learning and recall under theta oscillations in a biophysical network model with realistic synaptic dynamics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g012">Figure 12</xref>).</p>
<p>Our model is based on the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e411" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> control hypothesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bush1">[30]</xref>, where high levels of post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e412" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> lead to LTP and moderate levels lead to LTD. Consistent with the NMDAR-dependence of plasticity at CA3-CA1 synapses, NMDARs provide the relevant source of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e413" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We refer to our model as ‘minimal’ because the only biophysical mechanisms included in the model are those required to reproduce the data being addressed: a marker for pre-synaptic spikes, a marker for post-synaptic spikes, and a variable to quantify the coincidence of these markers, the time constant of which is monotonically dependent on the magnitude of the variable. The respective biophysical correlates of these computational requirements are NMDARs, long-tailed BAPs, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e414" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e415" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e416" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e417" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This parsimonious approach not only limits the assumptions of the model, but affords a simple implementation at the network level. Indeed, the chosen network model is endowed with the minimum biophysical detail to account for a range of data from perceptual and cognitive tasks (<italic>e.g.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wang2">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Brunel1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Albantakis1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Buehlmann1">[58]</xref>). The only biophysical mechanism that we added to this generic network is the BAP, driving <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e418" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> dynamics in conjunction with NMDARs.</p>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>STDP and the Need for Physiologically-motivated Models</title>
<p>Since the discovery of graded, temporally asymmetric STDP in cultured hippocampal cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bi2">[14]</xref>, numerous computational models have sought to characterize synaptic plasticity according to these data. In much of this work, ‘STDP rules’ have been defined by curves fit to the data, which are assumed to capture the phenomenology of synaptic change with ongoing pre- and post-synaptic spikes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Kempter1">[59]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Standage1">[64]</xref>. This assumption is perfectly reasonable, indeed unavoidable, for the spike trains under which the data were recorded. Given the implicitly Hebbian form of temporally asymmetric STDP, this approach has an intuitive appeal, <italic>i.e.</italic> pre-post spike doublets imply that a pre-synaptic cell ‘repeatedly and persistently takes part in firing’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Hebb1">[1]</xref> a post-synaptic cell and should therefore lead to LTP, whereas post-pre doublets imply a lack of causality and therefore LTD. Further appeal stems from competitive interactions between the LTP and LTD portions of asymmetric STDP curves, known to support synaptic scaling with uncorrelated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Song1">[65]</xref> and correlated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Standage1">[64]</xref> pre- and post-synaptic spiking.</p>
<p>The application of asymmetric STDP rules to spike trains different from those that produced the underlying data has not been straightforward. In neural simulations, the sampling of STDP curves with each pre- and post-synaptic spike has not accurately predicted the outcome of various triplet, quadruplet, and quintuplet protocols (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval1">[22]</xref>). Augmenting STDP rules with so-called spike interaction rules has been productive in this regard, limiting the contribution of individual spikes to plasticity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Froemke1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Izhikevich1">[62]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Standage2">[66]</xref>. Biological correlates have been proposed for the time-dependent suppression of interactions between spikes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Froemke2">[67]</xref>, but ultimately, this approach requires the continual addition of rules to accommodate data recorded under different spiking conditions. See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval1">[22]</xref> for a thorough treatment of the limitations of this phenomenological approach. Note that temporally symmetric, bidirectional STDP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1">[15]</xref> was discovered near-concurrently to its asymmetric homologue, but its phenomenology has received little attention.</p>
<sec id="s4a1">
<title><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e419" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-based plasticity models</title>
<p>An alternative to the phenomenological approach is to model synaptic physiology, providing a mechanistic explanation for plasticity data recorded under any protocol. STDP data have motivated several such models, including ours. As described above, all such models are based on the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e420" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> control hypothesis, where high and moderate levels of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e421" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> lead to LTP and LTD via kinase- and phosphatase-activated pathways respectively. Our minimal model simulates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e422" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transients by the product of NMDAR activation and the BAP, where the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e423" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e424" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e425" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> captures the saturation of the mechanisms of post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e426" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion. Earlier <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e427" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> models differ along a number of dimensions, including their underlying assumptions, their levels of biophysical detail, and the data they address. All of these models assume that NMDARs provide <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e428" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for plasticity, but some assume that voltage-gated <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e429" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> channels (VGCCs) are also required (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Karmarkar1">[24]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rubin1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Graupner1">[29]</xref>), an assumption supported by experimental data under some conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bauer1">[68]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Golding1">[69]</xref>). Assumptions differ about the relevant aspect of supra-threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e430" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, such as integrated <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e431" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Hartley1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Graupner1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bush1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Kumar1">[33]</xref> and the peak <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Karmarkar1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rackham1">[28]</xref> and timecourse <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Abarbanel1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rubin1">[26]</xref> of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e432" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transients.</p>
<p><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e433" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-based models have been used to address temporally symmetric and asymmetric STDP data. Any model based only on post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e434" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> levels will demonstrate anti-causal LTD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rubin1">[26]</xref> and will therefore account for symmetric STDP. Additional mechanisms are required to explain asymmetric STDP, for example, the inclusion of separate sources of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e435" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for LTP and LTD processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Karmarkar1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Hartley1">[27]</xref> or competitive interactions between these processes and an LTD veto process for appropriate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e436" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rubin1">[26]</xref>. The former is supported by data from neocortical slices <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bender1">[70]</xref> and the latter is consistent with competition between kinases and phosphatases (<italic>e.g.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Lee1">[71]</xref>). Since BAPs are known to attenuate with dendtric distance from the soma, several studies have considered plasticity outcomes as a function of dendritic location <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Graupner1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bush1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Kumar1">[33]</xref>, accounting for experimental data showing a switch from LTP to LTD at longer distances <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Sjostrom2">[72]</xref>.</p>
<p>Like our model, some existing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e437" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-based models have simulated LTP and LTD directly from supra-threshold levels of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e438" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Karmarkar1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rackham1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Kumar1">[33]</xref>, but others have included an intermediate processes for each of LTP and LTD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rubin1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Hartley1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Graupner1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bush1">[30]</xref>. These processes correspond to intracellular signalling cascades that mediate plasticity outcomes from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e439" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> levels, which may be loosely equated with kinase- and phosphatase-activated pathways respectively. Two recent studies augmented this approach with a mechanism for synaptic bistability, addressing STDP data. In the model by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Graupner1">[29]</xref>, post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e440" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the sum of independent pre- and post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e441" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> components, assumed to be mediated by NMDARs and VGCCs respectively. Their <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e442" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> variable is thus incremented with every pre- or post-synaptic spike, increasing or decreasing the efficacy of bistable synapses when it exceeds the respective thresholds for LTP and LTD. While their <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e443" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> variable has a time constant of a few milliseconds (like <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e444" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> here), their synaptic changes occur on a timescale on the order of minutes, driving all-or-none transitions to a down-state or an up-state, to which the efficacy variable relaxes in the absence of synaptic activity. Their model reproduces a broad range of data by varying the magnitude of the independent pre- and post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e445" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> components, the LTP and LTD thresholds, and the learning rates for LTP and LTD. In the model by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bush1">[30]</xref>, supra-threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e446" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transients change the probability of switching from the down-state to the up-state or <italic>vice versa</italic>, where these changes tend to occur following spiking activity.</p>
<p>As a model of CA1 plasticity, our model addresses temporally symmetric STDP, where the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e447" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependence of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e448" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> decay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Scheuss1">[35]</xref> accounts for the frequency and burst-dependence of LTP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>. The coincidence of NMDAR activation and the BAP provides the only source <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e449" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in our model. Above the thresholds for LTD and LTP, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e450" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is integrated, decreasing and increasing simulated synaptic strength respectively. Note that we do not claim that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e451" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> dependent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e452" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> decay is the only mechanism that could possibly account for the frequency and burst dependencies of LTP, but we have shown that under our minimalist assumptions, the model requires implausible parameter values to account for these dependencies without the proposed mechanism. A concise comparison of the above models and ours is provided by <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0086248-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<p>It is worth noting that several authors have developed plasticity models that occupy the middle ground between phenomenological and physiological models. Under this approach, abstract variables are responsive to pre- and post-synaptic activity and their values serve as parameters to learning rules that determine changes to synaptic weights. These models have successfully generalized across timing- and rate-based plasticity protocols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pfister1">[73]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Mayr1">[74]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4a2">
<title>The timecourse of supra-threshold calcium transients for LTP and LTD</title>
<p>It has been suggested that high levels of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e453" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> leading to LTP can be brief, but that moderate levels leading to LTD must be prolonged (<italic>e.g.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rubin1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Mizuno1">[75]</xref>). The technical challenges of controlling and measuring <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e454" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> flux at individual synapses are considerable and direct evidence for or against this suggestion is consequently sparse. Perhaps most convincingly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Yang1">[76]</xref> used <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e455" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> ‘uncaging’ to control post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e456" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> elevation over tens of seconds, where high elevations over <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e457" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> produced LTP and moderate elevations over <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e458" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> produced LTD. These authors noted that the magnitude and duration of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e459" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> elevation comprise a two-dimensional space that is largely unexplored. For instance, it is unclear whether a high-magnitude elevation over a long timescale (<italic>e.g.</italic> 60 s) would lead to LTP. To the best of our knowledge, this possibility has not been addressed. The flip side of this issue is whether LTD requires <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e460" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to remain above the LTD threshold for an unbroken period of time, as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Rubin1">[26]</xref>, or simply requires more repetitions of a given protocol than LTP, <italic>i.e</italic> a higher number of discrete supra-threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e461" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transients. If the latter, then the slow onset of LTD under several protocols (<italic>e.g.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Dudek1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-OConnor1">[77]</xref>) can be explained by a low LTD learning rate (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e462" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in our model). Notably, at least two studies have shown <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e463" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transients that reach higher amplitudes and decay <italic>more slowly</italic> with LTP-inducing stimuli than with LTD-inducing stimuli <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Hansel1">[78]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Hansel2">[79]</xref>. Our model is very robust to parametric variation and our results can be obtained qualitatively for parameters under which <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e464" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> exceeds the LTP threshold either in discrete jumps or for an unbroken interval. For <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e465" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to remain above the LTD threshold for an unbroken interval, an additional mechanism is required, <italic>e.g.</italic> VGCCs. This characterization is apparent in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g005">Figure 5</xref>, where the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e466" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependence of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e467" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant prevents high levels of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e468" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from undergoing significant decay, but moderate levels of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e469" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> drop to baseline between pairings. <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Methods</xref> for controlling and measuring post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e470" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are continually improving (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Higley1">[47]</xref>), so we expect these considerations will be addressed in due course.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Addressing Data from Different Plasticity Protocols</title>
<p>We have stated that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e471" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-based models capture the underlying physiology of plasticity and are therefore able to address data recorded under different protocols. Several studies have taken this approach (<italic>e.g.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Abarbanel1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Graupner1">[29]</xref>), though it is unclear that a given model should account for data recorded from different tissue preparations and brain regions, <italic>i.e.</italic> ‘caution is warranted when generalizing from one synapse to another’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Malenka1">[32]</xref>. We have also stated that our model contains the minimal biophysical detail to explain the post-synaptic burst-dependence and inter-pairing frequency-dependence of LTP at CA3-CA1 synapses under STDP protocols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>. Notably, no additional mechanisms or parameter changes were required for the model to reproduce the major findings of studies in which axonal tracts onto CA1 neurons were subject to tetanic stimulation. These studies showed that a brief period of high-rate stimulation (<italic>e.g.</italic> 100 Hz stimulation for 1 s) produces LTP and a long period of low-rate stimulation (<italic>e.g.</italic> 1 Hz for 1000 s) produces LTD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Dudek1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>. It is not surprising that we were able to reproduce these findings with an integrate-and-fire neuron. If pre-synaptic stimulation is strong enough to drive the neuron, then low-rate stimulation will lead to LTD in our model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g003">Figures 3B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g009">9A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g010">10A</xref>). Under the same parameters, high-rate stimulation effectively produces multiple low-latency, pre- and post-synaptic spikes, leading to LTP (not shown).</p>
<p>An aspect of the data by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref> that we did not address above is the dependence of STDP on the number of triplet pairings. Specifically, these authors showed that with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e472" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> triplet pairings (instead of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e473" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), their data were fit with a latency-dependent LTP-only curve. These data can be explained by several mechanisms. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Graupner1">[29]</xref> allowed each of their independent pre- and post-synaptic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e474" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transients to exceed the LTP threshold. Another possibility is short term fatigue of the mechanisms initiating LTP, readily simulated in our model by increasing the LTP threshold with ongoing LTP. To demonstrate this mechanism, we ran 25 pairings under the triplet protocol with an LTP-dependent LTP threshold. The resulting LTP-only curve is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g013">Figure 13</xref> (see the caption for details).</p>
<fig id="pone-0086248-g013" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g013</object-id><label>Figure 13</label><caption>
<title>LTP-only curves for a small number of pairings under the triplet protocol at 5 Hz.</title>
<p>(A) Data reproduced from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, fit with a Gaussian function (lease squares fit). (B) LTP ‘fatigue’ produces an LTP-only curve for 25 pairings under the triplet protocol. Fatigue of the processes initiating LTP was simulated with an LTP-dependent LTP threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e475" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e476" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was given an initial value equal to the LTD threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e477" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, to which it decayed with a time constant of 1 s. For all positive values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e478" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e479" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was incremented by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e480" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. All other parameters are identical to the simulations above. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e481" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the change in synaptic strength relative to initial strength (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e482" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> defined as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086248-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.g013" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Synaptic Plasticity, Learning and Memory</title>
<p>The use of biophysical plasticity models in network simulations is an important direction in neuroscience, allowing the investigation of the network- and systems-level consequences of plasticity processes. Network- and systems-level modelling with synaptic resolution has a fruitful recent history. For example, our understanding of the respective roles of AMPARs and NMDARs in cortical processing has been greatly advanced by simulations of persistent mnemonic activity in working memory tasks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Compte1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Brunel1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wang3">[80]</xref>, the integration of evidence in decision tasks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wang2">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Standage3">[81]</xref>, and the role of oscillations in the transfer of information between cortical networks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Buehlmann1">[58]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Buehlmann2">[82]</xref>. Several recent papers have discussed the need for this level of biophysical resolution in network models with plastic synapses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Graupner1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Bush1">[30]</xref>. Our simulations of associative memory show that our plasticity model is tractable in this regard. We are aware of only one model to previously bridge this gap, doing so under different assumptions than ours and performing a different learning task <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Hartley1">[27]</xref>.</p>
<p>Our <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e483" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> plasticity model is based on data from CA3-CA1 synapses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Pike1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Larson1">[83]</xref>, but memory formation in our network model is perhaps more easily equated with plasticity at CA3-CA3 synapses. Hippocampal region CA3 has long been hypothesized to support episodic memory by auto-association, owing to the dense lateral synaptic connectivity among CA3 neurons and to the well-established role of the hippocampus in episodic memory. For review of this hypothesis, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Standage4">[84]</xref>. The use of our plasticity model in this task seems reasonable, as there do not appear to be any substantial physiological or plasticity differences between CA3-CA3 and CA3-CA1 synapses (Alan Fine, personal correspondence). It is worth noting that temporally symmetric STDP is strikingly consistent with the hypothesis that CA3 supports auto-associative recall. For example, in the hippocampal models by Lisman, Jensen and colleagues, theta/gamma oscillations synchronize coupled neurons and memories are encoded when tight temporal coincidence of pre- and post-synaptic spiking leads to LTP and loose coincidence leads to LTD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Jensen1">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Jensen2">[85]</xref>. These conditions are captured by symmetric STDP data from hippocampal preparations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>. In this regard, it is perhaps surprising that the phenomenological implications of symmetric STDP have not received more attention.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Conclusions and Future Work</title>
<p>Our plasticity model builds on earlier work that identified the minimal mechanisms for NMDAR-dependent synaptic plasticity: markers for pre- and post-synaptic activation and a variable (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e484" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) to capture their timing correlations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Shouval2">[23]</xref>. We have augmented this well-established approach with a previously-unexplored computational mechanism, namely the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e485" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependence of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e486" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> decay. This dynamic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e487" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> time constant captures the saturation of the mechanisms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e488" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion from the post-synaptic spine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Sabatini1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Scheuss1">[35]</xref>. Our simulations of STDP experiments demonstrate that this mechanism is sufficient to explain the burst- and frequency-dependence of LTP at CA3-CA1 synapses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>. Our simulations of untried STDP protocols make testable predictions for the implications of the proposed mechanism and our simulations of associative learning demonstrate that our plasticity model is tractable at the network level.</p>
<p>A limitation of our minimalist approach is the requirement of the BAP for plasticity. As such, the present model cannot reproduce plasticity data obtained under protocols that hold post-synaptic neurons at fixed levels of depolarization for prolonged periods (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Conti1">[86]</xref>). Furthermore, BAPs are neither necessary nor sufficient for plasticity under some conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Lisman1">[21]</xref>. More generally, our <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e489" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-like variable is the product of the post-synaptic BAP and pre-synaptic activation, so our model is limited to homo-synaptic plasticity. These considerations point to the need for studies addressing the functional consequences of different plasticity phenomena. The suitability of symmetric STDP to auto-associative learning provides an example of such a functional consequence.</p>
<p>Our study points to several lines of enquiry for future work. Our implementation of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e490" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-dependence of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e491" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> decay is purposefully simplified and a detailed implementation of the mechanisms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e492" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion may reveal the limitations of our more abstract approach. If so, it may also reveal the computational properties of unexplored calcium dynamics and determine the conditions under which our present, efficient implementation is justifiable in network simulations.</p>
<p>Finally, our study is consistent with the hypothesis that synaptic plasticity is regulated by the modulation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e493" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion from dendritic spines. In support of this hypothesis, a recent study demonstrated that LTP is not expressed by pyramidal neurons in hippocampal region CA2 largely because rates of extrusion are significantly higher than in regions CA1 and CA3, which express LTP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Simons1">[48]</xref>. In these experiments, LTP was blocked in CA1 and induced in CA2 by interventions that speed up and ‘overwhelm’ <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e494" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion respectively. We hypothesize that LTP is <italic>only</italic> produced if the mechanisms of extrusion are overwhelmed. Biophysical mechanisms that may control the saturation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0086248.e495" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> extrusion constitute an exciting direction for future research on synaptic plasticity and its functional outcomes.</p>
</sec></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Gayle Wittenberg for thorough explanation of the STDP protocols used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1">[19]</xref>; Stefan Krueger, Alan Fine, Neil Magoski and Colin Lever for helpful discussions; and Michael Shepherd, Srinivas Sampalli and Evangelos Milios for financial support of this work during its early stages.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Hebb1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hebb DO (1949) The Organisation of Behaviour. John Wiley, New York.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Kohonen1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1972</year>) <article-title>Correlation matrix memories</article-title>. <source>IEEE Transactions on Computers</source> <volume>C-21</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Amari1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amari</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name> (<year>1972</year>) <article-title>Learning patterns and pattern sequences by self-organizing nets of threshold elements</article-title>. <source>IEEE Transactions on Computers</source> <volume>C-21</volume>: <fpage>1197</fpage>–<lpage>1206</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Hopfield1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopfield</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Neural networks and physical systems with emergent collective computational abilities</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>2554</fpage>–<lpage>2558</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Griniasty1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Griniasty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsodyks</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amit</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Conversion of temporal correlations between stimuli to spatial correlations between attractors</article-title>. <source>Neural Computation</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Lawrence1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trappenberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Rapid learning and robust recall of long sequences in modular associator networks</article-title>. <source>Neurocomputing</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>634</fpage>–<lpage>641</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Trappenberg1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trappenberg</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Fundamentals of Computational Neuroscience, Oxford University Press, chapter</article-title>. <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Bliss1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bliss</surname><given-names>TVP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lomo</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Long-lasting potentiation of synaptic transmission in the dentate area of the anaesthetized rabbit following stimulation of the perforant path</article-title>. <source>Journal of Physiology</source> <volume>232</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Dudek1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudek</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Homosynaptic long-term depression in area ca1 of hippocampus and effects of n-methyl-d-aspartate receptor blockade</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>4363</fpage>–<lpage>4367</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Artola1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Artola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brocher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Different voltage-dependent thresholds for inducing long-term depression and long-term potentiation in slices of rat visual cortex</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>347</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Ngezahayo1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngezahayo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schachner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Artola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Synaptic activity modulates the induction of bidirectional synaptic changes in adult mouse hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2451</fpage>–<lpage>2458</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Bi1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Synaptic modification by correlated activity: Hebb’s postulate revisited</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Neuroscience</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Markram1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Markram</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lubke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frotscher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Regulation of synaptic efficacy by coincidence of postsynaptic APs and EPSPs</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>275</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Bi2"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Synaptic modifications in cultured hippocampal neurons: Dependence on spike timing, synaptic strength, and postsynaptic cell type</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>10464</fpage>–<lpage>10472</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Nishiyama1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikoshiba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Calcium stores regulate the polarity and input specificity of synaptic modification</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>408</volume>: <fpage>584</fpage>–<lpage>588</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Sjostrom1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sjostrom</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turrigiano</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Rate, timing, and cooperativity jointly determine cortical synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1149</fpage>–<lpage>1164</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Froemke1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Froemke</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Spike-timing-dependent synaptic modification induced by natural spike trains</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>416</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>438</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Wang1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerkin</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nauen</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Coactivation and timing-dependent integration of synaptic potentiation and depression</article-title>. <source>Nature Neuroscience</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Wittenberg1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wittenberg</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SSH</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Malleability of spike-timing-dependent plasticity at the CA3-CA1 synapse</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>6610</fpage>–<lpage>6617</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Dan1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Spike timing-dependent plasticity of neural circuits</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Lisman1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lisman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spruston</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Postsynaptic depolarization requirements for LTP and LTD: a critique of spike timing-dependent plasticity</article-title>. <source>Nature Neuroscience</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>839</fpage>–<lpage>841</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Shouval1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shouval</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SSH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wittenberg</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Spike timing dependent plasticity: a consequence of more fundamental learning rules</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Computational Neuroscience</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Shouval2"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shouval</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A unified model of nmda receptor-dependent bidirectional synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>10831</fpage>–<lpage>10836</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Karmarkar1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karmarkar</surname><given-names>UR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buonomano</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A model of spike-timing dependent plasticity: one or two coincidence detectors?</article-title> <source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>507</fpage>–<lpage>513</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Abarbanel1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abarbanel</surname><given-names>HDI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibb</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huerta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rabinovich</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Biophysical model of synaptic plasticity dynamics</article-title>. <source>Biological Cybernetics</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>214</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Rubin1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerkin</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Calcium time course as a signal for spike-timing dependent plasticity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>2600</fpage>–<lpage>2613</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Hartley1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Understanding spike-time-dependent plasticity: A biologically motivated computational model</article-title>. <source>Neurocomputing</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>2005</fpage>–<lpage>2016</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Rackham1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rackham</surname><given-names>OJL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsaneva-Atanasova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mellor</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A Ca2+-based computational model for NMDA receptor dependent synaptic plasticity at individual post-synaptic spines in the hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Synaptic Neuroscience</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Graupner1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graupner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Calcium-based plasticity model explains sensitivity of synaptic changes to spike pattern, rate, and dendritic location</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>3991</fpage>–<lpage>3996</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Bush1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Calcium control of triphasic hippocampal STDP</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computational Neuroscience</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Artola2"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Artola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Long-term depression of excitatory synaptic transmission and its relationship to long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Trends in Neurosciences</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>480</fpage>–<lpage>487</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Malenka1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malenka</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Ltp and ltd: An embarrassment of riches</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Kumar1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Frequency-dependent changes in nmdar-dependent synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Computational Neuroscience</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Sabatini1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oertner</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The life cycle of Ca2+ ions in dendritic spines</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Scheuss1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheuss</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sobczyk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Nonlinear Ca2+. signaling in dendrites and spines caused by activity-dependent depression of [Ca2+] extrusion</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>8183</fpage>–<lpage>8194</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Pike1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olding</surname><given-names>AWA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Postsynaptic bursting is essential for ‘hebbian’ induction of associative long-term potentiation at excitatory synapses in rat hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Journal of Physiology</source> <volume>518</volume>: <fpage>571</fpage>–<lpage>576</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Lisman2"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lisman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>A mechanism for the hebb and the anti-hebb processes underlying learning and memory</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>9574</fpage>–<lpage>9578</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Pi1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pi</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lisman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Coupled phosphatase and kinase switches produce the tristability required for long-term potentiation and long-term depression</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>13132</fpage>–<lpage>13138</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Marr1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>Simple memory: A theory of archicortex</article-title>. <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London</source> <volume>262</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Alvarez1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Squire</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Memory consolidation and the medial temporal lobe: A simple network model</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>7041</fpage>–<lpage>7045</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Rosenkranz1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenkranz</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Kinase-dependent modification of dendritic excitability after long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Physiology</source> <volume>587</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Hestrin1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hestrin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicoll</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perkel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sah</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Analysis of excitatory synaptic action in pyramidal cells</article-title>. <source>Journal of Physiology</source> <volume>422</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Brigman1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brigman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad-Mulcare</surname><given-names>GTS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jinde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seabold</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Loss of GluN2B-containing NMDA receptors in CA1 hippocampus and cortex impairs long-term depression, reduces dendritic spine density, and disrupts learning</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>4590</fpage>–<lpage>4600</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Compte1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Compte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman-Rakic</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Synaptic mechanisms and network dynamics underlying spatial working memory in a cortical network model</article-title>. <source>Cerebral Cortex</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>910</fpage>–<lpage>923</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Wang2"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Probabilistic decision making by slow reverberation in cortical circuits</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>955</fpage>–<lpage>968</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Magee1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A synaptically controlled, associative signal for hebbian plasticity in hippocampal neurons</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>275</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Higley1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Calcium signaling in dendritic spines</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Simons1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Escobedo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dudek</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Regional differences in hippocampal calcium handling provide a cellular mechanism for limiting plasticity</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>14080</fpage>–<lpage>14084</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Tuckwell1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tuckwell H (1988) Introduction to theoretical neurobiology. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Jahr1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahr</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Voltage dependence of nmda-activated macroscopic conductances predicted by single-channel kinetics</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>3178</fpage>–<lpage>3182</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Brunel1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Effects of neuromodulation in a cortical network model of object working memory dominated by recurrent inhibition</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computational Neuroscience</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Albantakis1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albantakis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The encoding of alternatives in multiple-choice decision making</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>10308</fpage>–<lpage>10313</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Colquhoun1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Action of brief pulses of glutamate on ampa/kainate receptors in patches from different neurons of rat hippocampal slices</article-title>. <source>Journal of Physiology</source> <volume>458</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Collingridge1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collingridge</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Ihibitory post-synaptic currents in rat hippocampal ca1 neurons</article-title>. <source>Journal of Physiology</source> <volume>356</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>564</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Destexhe1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Destexhe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fellous</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sejnowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Fluctuating synaptic conductances recreate in vivo-like activity in neocortical neurons</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Jensen1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Idiart</surname><given-names>MAP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lisman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Physiologically realistic formation of autoassociative memory in networks with theta/gamma oscillations: Role of fast NMDA channels</article-title>. <source>Learning and Memory</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Hoffman1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colbert</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>K+ channel regulation of signal propagation in dendrites of hippocampal pyramidal neurons</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>387</volume>: <fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>875</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Buehlmann1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buehlmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Optimal information transfer in the cortex through synchronization</article-title>. <source>PLoS Computational Biology</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Kempter1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kempter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerstner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Hemmen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Hebbian learning and spiking neurons</article-title>. <source>Physical Review E</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>4498</fpage>–<lpage>4514</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-vanRossum1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Rossum</surname><given-names>MCW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turrigiano</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Stable hebbian learning from spike timing-dependent plasticity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>8812</fpage>–<lpage>8821</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Gutig1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutig</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aharonov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rotter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sompolinsky</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Learning input correlations through nonlinear temporally asymmetric hebbian plasticity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3697</fpage>–<lpage>3714</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Izhikevich1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Izhikevich</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Relating STDP to BCM</article-title>. <source>Neural Computation</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1511</fpage>–<lpage>1523</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Burkitt1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burkitt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meffin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grayden</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Spike-timing-dependent plasticity: The relationship to rate-based learning for models with weight dynamics determined by a stable fixed point</article-title>. <source>Neural Computation</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>940</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Standage1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Standage</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jalil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trappenberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Computational consequences of experimentally derived spike-time and weight dependent plasticity rules</article-title>. <source>Biological Cybernetics</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>615</fpage>–<lpage>623</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Song1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Competitive hebbian learning through spike-timing-dependent synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Nature Neuroscience</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>919</fpage>–<lpage>926</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Standage2"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Standage</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trappenberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The trouble with weight-dependent stdp</article-title>. <source>In: The International Joint Conference on Neural Networks</source> <volume>2007</volume>: <fpage>1359</fpage>–<lpage>1364</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Froemke2"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Froemke</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsay</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Contribution of individual spikes in burst-induced long-term synaptic modification</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>1620</fpage>–<lpage>1629</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Bauer1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schafe</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>LeDoux</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Nmda receptors and l-type voltage-gated calcium channels contribute to long-term potentiation and different components of fear memory formation in the lateral amygdala</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>5239</fpage>–<lpage>5249</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Golding1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staff</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spruston</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Dendritic spikes as a mechanism for cooperative long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>418</volume>: <fpage>326</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Bender1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brasier</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Two coincidence detectors for spike timing-dependent plasticity in somatosensory cortex</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>4166</fpage>–<lpage>4177</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Lee1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbarosie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kameyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huganir</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Regulation of distinct ampa receptor phosphorylation sites during bidirectional synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>405</volume>: <fpage>955</fpage>–<lpage>959</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Sjostrom2"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sjostrom</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hausser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A cooperative switch determines the sign of synaptic plasticity in distal dendrites of neocortical pyramidal neurons</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Pfister1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerstner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Triplets of spikes in a model of spike timing-dependent plasticity</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>9673</fpage>–<lpage>9682</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Mayr1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Partzsch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Rate and pulse based plasticity governed by local synaptic state variables</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Synaptic Neuroscience</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Mizuno1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanazawa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Differential induction of ltp and ltd is not determined solely by instantaneous calcium concentration: an essential involvement of a temporal factor</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>701</fpage>–<lpage>708</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Yang1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zucker</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Selective induction of LTP and LTD by postsynaptic [Ca2+]i elevation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>787</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-OConnor1"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wittenberg</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SSH</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Graded bidirectional synaptic plasticity is composed of switch-like unitary events</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>9679</fpage>–<lpage>9684</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Hansel1"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Artola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Different threshold levels of postsynaptic [Ca2+]i have to be reached to induce LTP and LTD in neocortical pyramidal cells</article-title>. <source>Journal of Physiology (Paris)</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Hansel2"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Artolal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Relation between dendritic Ca2+ levels and the polarity of synaptic long-term modifications in rat visual cortex neurons</article-title>. <source>Journal of Physiology (Paris)</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>2309</fpage>–<lpage>2322</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Wang3"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Synaptic basis of cortical persistent activity: the importance of nmda receptors to working memory</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>9587</fpage>–<lpage>9603</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Standage3"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Standage</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pare</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Persistent storage capability impairs decision making in a biophysical network model</article-title>. <source>Neural Networks</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1062</fpage>–<lpage>1073</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Buehlmann2"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buehlmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The neuronal basis of attention: Rate versus synchronization modulation</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>7679</fpage>–<lpage>7686</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Larson1"><label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Patterned stimulation at the theta frequency is optimal for the induction of hippocampal long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Brain Research</source> <volume>368</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Standage4"><label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Standage D, Trappenberg T (2012) Cognitive neuroscience. In: Frankish K, Ramsey WM, editors. The Cambridge Handbook of Cognitive Science. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Jensen2"><label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lisman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Theta/gamma networks with slow NMDA channels learn sequences and encode episodic memory: Role of NMDA channels in recall</article-title>. <source>Learning and Memory</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>264</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0086248-Conti1"><label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lisman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A large sustained Ca2+ elevation occurs in unstimulated spines during the LTP pairing protocol but does not change synaptic strength</article-title>. <source>Hippocampus</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>679</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>