<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-02169</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Metabolism</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Metabolic pathways</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Proteins</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Proteome</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Microbiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Mycology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Fungal physiology</subject>
                <subject>Fungi</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Microbiology</subject>
          <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Proteomic Analysis Reveals That Iron Availability Alters the Metabolic Status of the Pathogenic Fungus <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Iron Restriction in <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Parente</surname>
            <given-names>Ana F. A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bailão</surname>
            <given-names>Alexandre M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Borges</surname>
            <given-names>Clayton L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Parente</surname>
            <given-names>Juliana A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Magalhães</surname>
            <given-names>Adriana D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ricart</surname>
            <given-names>Carlos A. O.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Soares</surname>
            <given-names>Célia M. A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Laboratório de Biologia Molecular, Instituto de Ciências Biológicas, Universidade Federal de Goiás, Goiânia, Goiás, Brazil</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Laboratório de Química de Proteínas, Departamento de Biologia Celular, Universidade de Brasília, Brasília, Distrito Federal, Brazil</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Herrera-Estrella</surname>
            <given-names>Alfredo</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Cinvestav, Mexico</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">celia@icb.ufg.br</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CMAS. Performed the experiments: AFAP AMB CLB JAP ADM. Analyzed the data: AFAP CAOR CMAS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CMAS CAOR. Wrote the paper: AFAP CMAS.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e22810</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Parente et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p><italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> is a thermodimorphic fungus and the causative agent of paracoccidioidomycosis (PCM). The ability of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> to uptake nutrients is fundamental for growth, but a reduction in the availability of iron and other nutrients is a host defense mechanism many pathogenic fungi must overcome. Thus, fungal mechanisms that scavenge iron from host may contribute to <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> virulence. In order to better understand how <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> adapts to iron starvation in the host we compared the two-dimensional (2D) gel protein profile of yeast cells during iron starvation to that of iron rich condition. Protein spots were selected for comparative analysis based on the protein staining intensity as determined by image analysis. A total of 1752 protein spots were selected for comparison, and a total of 274 out of the 1752 protein spots were determined to have changed significantly in abundance due to iron depletion. Ninety six of the 274 proteins were grouped into the following functional categories; energy, metabolism, cell rescue, virulence, cell cycle, protein synthesis, protein fate, transcription, cellular communication, and cell fate. A correlation between protein and transcript levels was also discovered using quantitative RT-PCR analysis from RNA obtained from <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> under iron restricting conditions and from yeast cells isolated from infected mouse spleens. In addition, western blot analysis and enzyme activity assays validated the differential regulation of proteins identified by 2-D gel analysis. We observed an increase in glycolytic pathway protein regulation while tricarboxylic acid cycle, glyoxylate and methylcitrate cycles, and electron transport chain proteins decreased in abundance under iron limiting conditions. These data suggest a remodeling of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> metabolism by prioritizing iron independent pathways.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work at the Universidade Federal de Goiás was supported by grants from “Financiadora de Estudos e Projetos - FINEP - 0107055200”. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="14"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Iron is an essential nutrient for cellular function, but iron overload can be as detrimental as iron depletion. Thus, microorganisms use a complex network of systems to control iron levels in order to prevent free radical damage to proteins, ribonucleic acids, and cell membranes, keeping iron unavailable <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Doherty1">[1]</xref>. The absence of free iron in host tissues and host iron restriction mechanisms demand that pathogens develop an efficient iron uptake system in order to compete with the host for iron <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Johnson1">[2]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Iron deprivation responses in several fungi have been studied by transcriptional and proteomic analyses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Winters1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Lian1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Lan1">[5]</xref>. Iron homeostasis mechanisms including iron uptake, storage, and regulation have been extensively characterized especially in the fungal prototype <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. Iron levels in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> are controlled by two major transcriptional factors identified as Aft1p and Aft2p. These two orthologues are missing in the majority of fungal species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-YamaguchiIwai1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Blaiseau1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Haas1">[8]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The human fungal pathogen A<italic>spergillus fumigatus</italic> also has a well characterized iron acquisition system. Under iron starvation conditions <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> employs two high affinity iron uptake systems that include siderophore-assisted and reductive iron uptake <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Schrettl1">[9]</xref>. <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> iron acquisition under iron-depleted conditions is controlled by transcriptional factors encoded by the genes s<italic>reA</italic> and <italic>hapX</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Hortschansky1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Schrettl2">[11]</xref>. Under low iron conditions, the expression of the GATA factor SreA is reduced resulting in desrepression of the bZip transcription factor HapX. Genes involved in reductive iron assimilation, siderophore biosynthesis and uptake are also affected <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Schrettl2">[11]</xref>. This regulatory circuit is largely conserved and orthologs to <italic>sreA</italic> and <italic>hapX</italic> are found in most fungal species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Hortschansky1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Mercier1">[12]</xref>. Moreover, the <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> zinc cluster transcription factor AcuM suppresses <italic>sreA</italic> and induces <italic>hapX</italic> to stimulate expression of genes involved in reductive and siderophore mediated iron uptake <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Liu1">[13]</xref>.</p>
      <p><italic>Paracoccidoides brasiliensis</italic> is a dimorphic fungus and the etiologic agent of paracoccidioidomycosis (PCM). The disease is restricted to Latin America, and is the most prevalent systemic mycosis in the region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Restrepo1">[14]</xref>. PCM is a major public health concern in rural areas. Moreover, this infection can lead to potentially disabling injuries. Several studies indicate that the majority of PCM cases are reported in Brazil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Coutinho1">[15]</xref> with an annual mortality rate of 148 deaths per year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Prado1">[16]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Searching analyses on <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> genome database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/paracoccidioides_brasiliensis/MultiHome.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/paracoccidioides_brasiliensis/MultiHome.html</ext-link>) showed that this fungus possess genes that encode proteins with sequence similarity to host iron uptake systems which utilize heme while also employing siderophore-assisted iron uptake and reductive iron assimilation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Silva1">[17]</xref>. The fungal genome of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> contains sequences that potentially encode all the necessary enzymes for siderophore biosynthesis; <italic>sidA</italic>, <italic>sidF</italic>, <italic>sidC</italic> and s<italic>idD</italic> orthologs of <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Silva1">[17]</xref>. Putative <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> siderophore transporters were identified as orthologs to genes encoding the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Sit1p and the <italic>A. nidulans</italic> MirB and MirC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Silva1">[17]</xref>. Further investigation of the <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> genome revealed that it contains orthologs to <italic>hapx</italic> and <italic>sreA</italic>. Despite these advances the identity and total number of genes and proteins involved in <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> response to iron deprivation remains unclear.</p>
      <p>Different reports indicate that iron depletion in fungi promotes the metabolic remodeling of iron-dependent processes including oxidative respiration, amino acid biosynthesis, and fatty acid metabolism. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Winters1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Lian1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-ShakouryElizeh1">[18]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Jo1">[20]</xref>. Altered expression of heat shock proteins has also been found in fungi during iron limiting conditions most likely due to the accumulation of unfolded proteins in the cytoplasm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Seo1">[21]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In this study we utilized 2D gel electrophoresis coupled to mass spectrometry to identify <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> proteins sensitive to low iron levels. We discovered 274 differentially regulated proteins and 96 of these were identified, rendering an integrated view of metabolic and cellular processes reorganization during iron deprivation. Moreover, <italic>in vivo</italic> analysis confirmed the expression pattern of selected genes. These data suggest that the remodeling of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> metabolism is one way the fungus adapts and survives in a nutrient deficient environment.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Iron overload exacerbates <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> infection in BALB/c mice</title>
        <p>To investigate the effect of iron availability on <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> colonization we infected BALB/c mice that were iron supplemented. We observed an increased CFU recovery from liver and spleen of mice treated with an iron supplement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g001">Figure 1</xref>). The results suggest that iron availability increases the susceptibility of mice to <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> infection.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0022810-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Iron supplementation increases mice susceptibility to <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> infection.</title>
            <p>Colony forming units recovered from the spleen and liver of mice infected with <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic>. Mice were supplemented with iron (grey bars) or 0.9% (w/v) NaCl (black) for 15 days prior and during infection. Error bars represent standard deviation from four biological replicates while * represents <italic>p</italic>≤0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Expression of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> iron acquisition genes during iron starvation</title>
        <p>Before we began our proteomic analysis, we first sought to verify that our iron limiting conditions were restricting iron to the fungus by analyzing <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> gene expression. To investigate the transcriptional profile of iron responsive genes in <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> we used real-time RT-PCR. These genes included <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> orthologs to the transcriptional regulator <italic>hapX</italic>, siderophore transporter <italic>sit1</italic>, and the siderophore biosynthesis gene <italic>sidA</italic>, encoding L-ornithine N<sup>5</sup> –monooxygenase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g002">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0022810.s003">Table S1</xref>). In the first 10 minutes of iron deprivation, we observed an increased expression of the <italic>hapX</italic> and <italic>sidA</italic> orthologs. The level of <italic>hapX</italic> increased 2.3 times at 10 minutes of iron deprivation and the transcript level remained increased up to 1 hour in this condition. The <italic>sidA</italic> ortholog presented an expression level increased nine times compared to control following 30 minutes of iron starvation; transcript level remained at significant high levels in 24 hours of iron deprivation. The <italic>sit1</italic> ortholog was over expressed following 24 hours of iron deprivation. These results indicate that <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> was subjected to iron restriction conditions because the known siderophore iron uptake system is active upon iron restriction.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0022810-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Induction of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> iron acquisition genes following iron restriction.</title>
            <p>Quantitative RT-PCR determined <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> transcript levels of <italic>hapX</italic>, <italic>sidA</italic> and <italic>sit1</italic> during iron deprivation. Data were normalized to the L34 protein transcript. Student's t test was used for statistical comparisons. Error bars represent standard deviation from three biological replicates while * represents <italic>p</italic>≤0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> cell viability</title>
        <p>Because we did not want to measure a proteome response which would represent cell death, we next sought to determine whether iron deprivation influenced <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> cell viability. Using trypan blue staining we observed no significant differences in yeast cell viability up to 48 hours in iron deprivation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0022810.s001">Figure S1</xref>). We did not observe a decrease in <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> cell viability until 72 hours of exposure to iron limiting conditions (data not shown). These data show that the iron limiting incubation times selected for proteomic analysis did not influence <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> cell viability.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>2D-gel analysis of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> during iron starvation</title>
        <p>Based on the results described above 6 and 24 hours iron depletion incubation times were selected for proteomic analysis of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> yeast cells. Two-dimensional gel analysis was used to separate cytosolic fungal proteins while image analysis allowed for the quantification of proteins. Three independent experiments generate three replicates which included: 6 hours in iron depletion, 6 hours control, 24 hours in iron depletion, and 24 hours control. Using the gel image software a total of 1752 spots were successfully matched between control and iron depletion conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g003">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Statistical analysis revealed a difference in protein abundance for 165 and 109 protein spots following 6 and 24 hours of iron deprivation respectively. This yielded a total of 274 differentially regulated proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g003">Figure 3</xref>). A magnified gel region allows for visualization of representative spots with differential abundance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g005">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0022810-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Graphic summation of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> iron restriction proteomic analysis.</title>
            <p>Number of spots differentially expressed were determined using 2D-gel image analysis software. Statistical analysis of the matched spots were performed using ANOVA.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0022810-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> protein regulation during iron limiting conditions detected using 2D-gel analysis.</title>
            <p>2D-gel analysis of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> proteins extracted from yeast cells grown in iron depleted media for 6 hours (B) and 24 hours (D). Gels A and C represent iron rich conditions. Black and white arrows indicate up-regulated and down-regulated proteins respectively. Identified protein spots are numbered and listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t002">2</xref>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0022810-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Magnified regions of the protein spots exhibiting protein abundance changes in the 2D gels shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g004"><bold>Figure 4</bold></xref>.</title>
            <p>Protein spots correspond to the following proteins identified by mass spectrometry; Y20 protein (A), ATP synthase subunit beta (B), Tubulin alpha-1 chain (C), Conserved hypothetical protein (D). Black and white arrows indicate up-regulated and down-regulated proteins respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Identification iron-regulated proteins</title>
        <p>In order to determine the identities of the protein spots determined to be differentially regulated following 2D-gel analysis protein spots were subjected to in-gel digestion using trypsin and analyzed by mass spectrometry (MS). MS analysis following by protein database sequence matching resulted in the identification of 96 differentially expressed proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g004">4</xref>). Seventy three proteins/isoforms were identified by peptide mass fingerprinting (PMF) and confirmed by MS/MS analysis while 23 of protein spots yielded identification by PMF only.</p>
        <p>Among the 96 identified proteins 49 increased in abundance and 47 decreased. The <italic>p</italic>-values associated with each spot comparison are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0022810.s004">Tables S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0022810.s005">S3</xref>. Differences in protein spot intensity ranged from 1.2 to 3.6 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t002">2</xref>). GenBank general information identifiers (gi), Broad Institute <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> database accession numbers (PAAG), PMF and MS/MS mascot scores, protein molecular weights, and isoelectric points (<italic>p</italic>I) of each spot are also listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t002">2</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0022810-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> identified proteins with increased expression during iron starvation.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0022810-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Spot<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">1</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GenBank gi<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">3</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Protein identification</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PMF score</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MS/MS score</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MW<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">4</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p<italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">5</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥fold change<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">6</xref></td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>METABOLISM</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Nucleotide metabolism</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>1</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226280544</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adenosine kinase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">193</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.6/41.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.4/5.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>2</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226283962</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GMP synthase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.3/55.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.2/7.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>C-compound and carbohydrate metabolism</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>3</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295664927</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATP-citrate-lyase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">159</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">303</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.8/46.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.9/6.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Amino acid, nitrogen and sulfur metabolism</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>4</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226280080</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2-nitropropane dioxygenase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">163</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">107</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.8/41.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.4/5.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>5</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|27368050</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Formamidase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.1/46.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1/7.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>6</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226284927</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hydroxyacylglutathione hydrolase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.9/33.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1/7.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>7</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226282479</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">L-threonine 3-dehydrogenase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">129</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.0/40.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.8/6.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>8</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226293104</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Spermidine synthase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.6/36.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3/5.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Lipid, fatty-acid and isoprenoid metabolism</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>9</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226279101</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Carbonic anhydrase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.6/27.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.1/8.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Phosphate metabolism</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>10</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295672504</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inorganic pyrophosphatase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">141</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3/38.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1/4.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>ENERGY</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Electron transport and membrane-associated energy conservation</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>11</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226282053</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATP synthase subunit beta</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">199</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">118</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.1/33.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2/5.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Glycolysis and gluconeogenesis</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>12</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|146762537</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Enolase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">173</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.4/63.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6/6.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>13</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|29826036</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fructose 1,6-biphosphate aldolase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">163</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">174</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.7/41.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1/7.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>14</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAAG_01995</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fructose 1,6-biphosphate aldolase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.6/40.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0/6.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>15</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226279559</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Glucokinase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">113</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.7/52.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3/5.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>16</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226285327</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphoglycerate kinase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.3/43.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.4/7.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>17</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295669690</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphoglycerate kinase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">149</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.3/44.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.4/7.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>18</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295669690</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphoglycerate kinase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.3/42.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.8/7.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>19</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295670663</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Triosephosphate isomerase (Tpi)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">185</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.1/30.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3/5.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Tricarboxylic-acid pathway</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>20</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295673931</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pyruvate dehydrogenase protein X component</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.7/50.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.4/5.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>21</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226280161</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pyruvate dehydrogenase protein X component</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.7/50.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.4/5.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>CELL CYCLE AND DNA PROCESSING</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>22</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|225683196</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tubulin alpha-2 chain</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.5/52.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0/4.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>23</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|225683196</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tubulin alpha-2 chain</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">117</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.5/53.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0/4.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>24</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226285902</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tubulin beta chain</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.3/51.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8/4.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>25</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|154705473</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Septin-1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">123</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.1/44.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2/5.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>26</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226294796</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Actin</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.1/43.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.1/5.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>27</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|38569374</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14-3-3-like protein 2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.7/37.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6/4.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>28</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226282286</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DNA damage protein rad24 (14-3-3 protein)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">252</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.4/40.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.7/4.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>TRANSCRIPTION</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>29</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226280907</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mRNA binding post-transcriptional regulator (Csx1)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.6/44.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.3/6.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>30</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226284577</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type 2A phosphatase activator tip41</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.9/27.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3/4.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>31</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAAG_06891</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mRNA binding post-transcriptional regulator (Csx1)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.4/43.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.3/7.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>PROTEIN SYNTHESIS</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>32</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226280659</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60S ribosomal protein L5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.3/39.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.0/9.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>33</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226282202</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATP-dependent RNA helicase eIF4a</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.0/45.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1/4.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>34</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226280705</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Elongation factor 2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.6/37.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.4/7.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>35</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226283670</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Translation initiation factor eIF3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.0/62.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1/5.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>PROTEIN FATE (folding, modification, destination)</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>36</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAAG_05417</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mitochondrial-processing peptidase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.0/45.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.8/7.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>37</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295661059</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G-protein complex beta subunit cpcb</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">228</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.4/38.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.5/7.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>CELL RESCUE, DEFENSE AND VIRULENCE</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>38</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|60656557</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heat shock protein 90</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.3/73.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9/5.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>39</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226285144</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hsp90 co-chaperone AHA1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.5/42.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.4/5.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>40</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|31324921</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heat shock protein SSC1 (70 kDa)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">135</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">225</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.8/67.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.9/5.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>41</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295659116</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hsp70-like protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">244</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.9/42.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0/5.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>42</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226286087</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mitochondrial peroxiredoxin PRX1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">197</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.8/29.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2/4.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>43</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|17980998</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y20 protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.6/15.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0/8.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>UNCLASSIFIED PROTEINS</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>44</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226278304</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.0/38.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0/7.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>45</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226286114</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.7/40.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3/4.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>46</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226279849</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.8/13.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0/4.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>47</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAAG_06617</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">113</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.5/34.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.2/7.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>**Spots visualized only in iron-depleted condition;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label>1</label>
              <p>Spots numbers refers to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g003">Figure 3</xref>;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>2</label>
              <p>Time in iron starvation condition;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label>3</label>
              <p>GenBank general information identifier;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label>4</label>
              <p>Molecular weight (theoretical/experimental);</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt106">
              <label>5</label>
              <p>p<italic>I</italic> (theoretical/experimental).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt107">
              <label>6</label>
              <p>≥fold in iron depletion.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0022810-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> identified proteins with reduced expression during iron starvation.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0022810-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Spot<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">1</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">2</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GenBank gi<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt111">3</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Protein identification</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PMF score</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MS/MS score</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MW<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt112">4</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p<italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt113">5</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≤fold change<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt114">6</xref></td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>METABOLISM</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Nucleotide metabolism</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>48</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295672652</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bifunctional purine biosynthesis protein ADE17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">186</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.7/61.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.7/8.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>C-compound and carbohydrate metabolism</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>49</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226277934</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2-methylcitrate synthase (2-Mcs)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">254</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.5/46.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.0/8.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>50</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAAG_04550</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2-methylcitrate synthase (2-Mcs)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.4/44.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.0/8.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>51</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295666177</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mitochondrial 2-methylisocitrate lyase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.2/59.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7/8.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>52</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|116561512</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Isocitrate lyase (Icl)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">301</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.1/58.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.7/7.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>53</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|116561512</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Isocitrate lyase (Icl)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">233</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.1/57.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.7/7.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Amino acid, nitrogen and sulfur metabolism</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>54</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226281118</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pentafunctional AROM polypeptide</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">189</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">166/122</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.3/7.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>55</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226277980</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acetamidase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">177</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.2/52.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.8/6.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>56</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226285914</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adenylyl-sulfate kinase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">172</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.8/33.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.6/9.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>57</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|225679649</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adenylyl-sulfate kinase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">125</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.8/32.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.1/9.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>58</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295663176</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sulfate adenylyltransferase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">307</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">552</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.0/61.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.2/7.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>59</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295662426</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Aspartate aminotransferase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">137</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.8/41.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.3/8.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>ENERGY</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Electron transport and membrane-associated energy conservation</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>60</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226279655</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cytochrome c</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.2/14.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.2/10.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>61</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|225677786</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATP synthase gamma chain</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.4/36.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.7/6.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>62</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226282053</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATP synthase subunit beta</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">249</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">376</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.1/48.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2/4.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>63</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226279593</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATP synthase subunit 5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.6/23.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.7/10.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>64</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226291052</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATP synthase subunit 4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.7/26.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.4/8.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>65</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226278316</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Electron transfer flavoprotein subunit beta</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">136</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.6/34.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.3/10</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Tricarboxylic-acid pathway</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>66</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226293399</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Aconitase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">172</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">211</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79.1/77.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.4/7.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>67</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|225684009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Aconitase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">184</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.0/79.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2/7.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>68</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|225684009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Aconitase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.0/80.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2/7.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>69</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226278535</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATP-citrate synthase subunit 1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.4/65.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.0/8.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>70</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAAG_03330</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.6/47.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2/7.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Oxidation of fatty acids</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>71</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226278634</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Aldehyde dehydrogenase (Aldh)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">217</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">197</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.5/49.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.8/6.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>72</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226286163</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3-hydroxybutyryl CoA dehydrogenase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">165</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.3/36.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.4/7.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>73</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAAG_06224</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Carnitine O-acetyltransferase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.4/61.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2/8.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>CELL CYCLE AND DNA PROCESSING</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>74</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|154705473</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Septin-1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">151</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.1/44.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2/5.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>75</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|38569374</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14-3-3-like protein 2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.7/46.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6/4.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>76</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226278903</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cell division cycle protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">311</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90.5/118</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9/4.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>77</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAAG_01647</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tubulin alpha-1 chain</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0/50.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0/5.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>TRANSCRIPTION</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>78</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226277842</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prohibitin-1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">180</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.9/35.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7/9.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>79</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295673504</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cwfJ domain-containing protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.6/58.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1/7.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>PROTEIN SYNTHESIS</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>80</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226280705</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Elongation factor 2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">283</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">244</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.6/92.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.4/7.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>81</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226280705</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Elongation factor 2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">189</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.6/85.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.4/7.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>82</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|28395450</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40S ribosomal S12 protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.8/19.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0/4.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>83</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226282202</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATP-dependent RNA helicase eIF4a</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">142</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.0/64.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1/4.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>PROTEIN FATE (folding, modification, destination)</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>84</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226285231</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme variant MMS2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.7/16.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1/6.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>85</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|34979129</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peptidyl-prolyl cis/trans isomerase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.9/24.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0/9.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>86</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|295663176</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dipeptidyl-peptidase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">201</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86.2/70.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.9/7.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>CELLULAR TRANSPORT AND TRANSPORT MECHANISMS</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>87</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAAG_03137</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vacuolar protein sorting-associated protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.1/26.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0/4.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>CELLULAR COMMUNICATION/SIGNAL TRANSDUCTION MECHANISM</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>88</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226285275</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stomatin family protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.7/43.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.5/5.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>CELL RESCUE, DEFENSE AND VIRULENCE</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>89</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|60656557</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heat shock protein 90</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">173</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.3/104</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9/4.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>90</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|31324921</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heat shock protein SSC1 (70 kDa)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">214</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">263</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.8/96.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.9/5.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>91</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226278527</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 kDa heat shock protein, mitochondrial</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.1/12.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7/9.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>92</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226282384</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 kDa heat shock protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">142</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.6/24.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.8/6.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>93</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|17980998</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y20 protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">302</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.6/22.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0/7.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>94</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|24528587</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peroxissomal catalase</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.7/61.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.3/8.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>UNCLASSIFIED PROTEINS</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>95</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226285365</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">135</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">194</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.0/28.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.8/6.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>96</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 h</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gi|226286445</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115/109</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1/4.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt108">
              <label/>
              <p>**Spots visualized only in iron-replete condition;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt109">
              <label>1</label>
              <p>Spots numbers refers to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g003">Figure 3</xref>;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt110">
              <label>2</label>
              <p>Time in iron starvation condition;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt111">
              <label>3</label>
              <p>GenBank general information identifier;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt112">
              <label>4</label>
              <p>Molecular weight kDa (theoretical/experimental);</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt113">
              <label>5</label>
              <p>p<italic>I</italic> (theoretical/experimental);</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt114">
              <label>6</label>
              <p>≤fold in iron depletion.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>Identified proteins were grouped together based on their functionality according to the Munich Information Center for Protein Sequences (MIPS). Pie charts representing the distribution of the 96 identified spots according to their biological function are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0022810.s002">Figure S2</xref>. <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> differentially regulated proteins were involved in several cellular processes including energy (26%), metabolism (22.9%), cell rescue and virulence (12.5%), cell cycle (11.5%), protein synthesis (10.4%), transcription (5.2%), protein fate (3.1%), cellular communication (1%) and cell transport (1%). Unclassified proteins represented only a small fraction (6.2%) of the 96 protein spots analyzed by MS.</p>
        <p>Twenty six percent of the <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> identified proteins were grouped into energy processes. Glycolytic enzymes including enolase, fructose 1,6-biphosphate aldolase, glucokinase, phosphoglycerate kinase and triosephosphate isomerase were up regulated ranging in fold change from 1.2 to 2.8. The increased regulation of glycolytic enzymes was observed at 6 and 24 hours of iron deprivation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t001">Table 1</xref>). The abundance of hydroxyacylglutathione hydrolase was also increased correlating with the detected increase in glycolytic enzyme regulation because this enzyme plays role in detoxification of glycolysis products.</p>
        <p>While the abundance of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> glycolytic pathway enzymes increased during iron deprivation the tricarboxylic acid cycle (TCA) enzymes were decreased. TCA enzyme included aconitase, one subunit of ATP-citrate synthase, and dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0022810.s002">Figure S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t002">Table 2</xref>) depicted a decreased abundance during iron starvation. Four subunits of the electron transport ATP-synthase complex also decreased in abundance during iron restriction. Two other proteins related to electron transport were also down-regulated in <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> during iron deprivation. These proteins included cytochrome c and electron transfer flavoprotein beta-subunit.</p>
        <p><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> proteins involved in pathways using alternative sources of carbon, such as glyoxylate and methylcitrate cycles were also decreased in abundance during iron starvation. Two isoforms of the glyoxylate cycle enzyme isocitrate lyase, were decreased in abundance after 24 hours in iron depletion (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0022810.s002">Figure S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t002">Table 2</xref>). These isoforms play a regulatory role in glyoxylate cycle allowing fungi to use fatty acids to synthesize carbohydrates. Two <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> enzymes involved in the methylcitrate cycle were decreased in abundance following iron restriction. These enzymes were 2-methylisocitrate lyase and 2-methylcitrate synthase. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g006">Figure 6</xref> summarizes the <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> metabolic proteins regulated during iron starvation in this study.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0022810-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Overview of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> metabolic processes regulated during iron starvation revealed by proteomic analysis.</title>
            <p>Schematic representation of proteins involved in <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> carbon metabolism (glycolysis/TCA cycle/glyoxylate cycle/methylcitrate cycle). Proteins are colored according to their differences in abundance as detected by 2D-gel analysis of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> following iron starvation. Arrows indicate up or down regulation of metabolic pathways.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We also detected a decreased regulation of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> enzymes related to fatty acids metabolism including aldehyde dehydrogenase, 3-hydroxybutyryl CoA dehydrogenase, and carnitine-O-acetyltransferase (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t002">Table 2</xref>). Enzymes related to amino acid metabolism were also decreased in abundance during iron starvation, such as the pentafunctional AROM polypeptide, related to aromatic amino acids biosynthesis, and aspartate aminotransferase, the enzyme responsible for the amination of oxaloacetate to form aspartate. In contrast L-threonine 3-dehydrogenase was 1.9 times fold higher in abundance following iron deficiency (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t002">2</xref>). This enzyme is involved in threonine catabolism which produces glycine.</p>
        <p>Another <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> cellular process affected by iron starvation was cell rescue. Eight proteins, including isoforms, belonging to the heat shock protein family were altered in abundance following iron limitation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t002">2</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> mRNA and proteomic analysis correlate with in vivo infection</title>
        <p>In order to validate the significance of our proteomic results we next sought to determine if changes in protein levels could be correlated with changes in transcript levels <italic>in vivo</italic>. We determined that the differences observed in proteomic assay are in agreement with transcriptional findings, using quantitative RT-PCR to measure isocitrate lyase (<italic>icl</italic>), aldehyde dehydrogenase (<italic>aldh</italic>) and 2-methylcitrate synthase (<italic>2-mcs</italic>) transcripts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g007">Figure 7A</xref>). Protein and transcript levels of these enzymes decreased during iron limitation as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g007">Figure 7A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t002">Table 2</xref>. The triosephosphate isomerase (<italic>tpi</italic>) transcript level was correlated with protein levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g007">Figure 7A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0022810-t001">Table 1</xref>). The same oligonucleotides were next used to evaluate the transcriptional levels of these genes in <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> isolated from mouse spleens. We observed that the changes in transcriptional profile of the genes <italic>tpi</italic>, <italic>icl</italic>, <italic>2-mcs</italic> and <italic>aldh</italic> in yeast cells isolated from mice are similar to those observed in response to iron deprivation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g007">Figure 7 B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0022810-g007" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> transcripts of yeast cells isolated from infected mice correspond to <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> proteins differentially regulated under iron limiting conditions.</title>
            <p><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> transcript levels of genes encoding enzymes involved in energy processes; triosephosphate isomerase (<italic>tpi</italic>), isocitrate lyase (<italic>icl</italic>), 2-methylcitrate synthase (<italic>2-mcs</italic>) and aldehyde dehydrogenase (<italic>aldh</italic>), isolated from yeast cells following iron starvation (A), and from yeast cells recovered from the spleens of infected BALB/c mice (B). Transcript levels were measured using quantitative RT-PCR. Data were normalized to the L34 protein transcript and presented as log2 (fold change). Student's t test was used for statistical comparisons. Error bars represent standard deviation from three biological replicates while * represents <italic>p</italic>≤0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Western blot analysis and enzymatic activity correlates with proteomic data</title>
        <p>Western blot analysis was performed to confirm the <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> protein level changes detected in the proteomic analysis. This was accomplished using antibodies specific to four proteins affected by iron levels as determined by 2D gel analysis. <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> aconitase and isoctrate lyase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g008">Figure 8 A</xref>, panels a and b) levels following iron depletion were observed to decrease in abundance by western blot and 2D-gel analysis. Formamidase and triosephosphate isomerase also yielded similar increases in abundance following western blot analysis to that described by 2D-gel analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g008">Figure 8 A</xref> panels c and d).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0022810-g008" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g008</object-id>
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Western blot and enzymatic activity analysis validate proteomic data of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> yeast cells during iron-limiting condition.</title>
            <p>A) Western blot analysis of proteins probed with antibodies to (a) aconitase, (b) isocitrate lyase, (c) formamidase and (d) triosephosphate isomerase. B) Activity assay results from (a) formamidase, (b) catalases, (c) isocitrate lyase. Control represents yeast cells incubated for 24 hours in MMcM medium. −Fe represents yeast cells incubated for 24 hours in MMcM medium depleted of iron. Error bars represent standard deviation from three biological replicates while * represents <italic>p</italic>≤0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.g008" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Moreover, we performed enzymatic assays for formamidase, catalases, and isocitrate lyase using <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> protein extracts derived from yeast cells grown under iron deprivation in order further validate our proteomic data. We observed a statistically significant increase in formamidase activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g008">Figure 8 B</xref>, panel a) and a decrease in catalases and isocitrate lyase activity during iron starvation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g008">Figure 8 B</xref>, panels b and c, respectively). All data again are in agreement with the 2D-gel analysis.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study, the treatment of mice with an iron supplement made them more susceptible to <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> infection. Similar trends were also observed for the pathogenic fungi <italic>C. neoformans</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Barluzzi1">[22]</xref> and <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Kontoyiannis1">[23]</xref>. Moreover, we found that <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> regulated the abundance of 274 proteins following iron depletion. Host iron restriction is thought to be one part of the host defense mechanism. Our data suggest that a remodeling of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> metabolism by limiting the role of iron dependent pathways could be one mechanism in which the fungus adapts to the host environment.</p>
      <p>Because iron is not abundantly available in host tissues pathogenic microorganisms have developed mechanisms which enable them to survive in low iron environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Kosman1">[24]</xref>. These mechanisms include iron uptake from host sources, and metabolic switching to iron independent pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Kaplan1">[25]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Puig1">[31]</xref>. It is known that a component of the fungal cellular response to iron deficiency operates through the induction of a number of transcripts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-ShakouryElizeh1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Rutherford1">[32]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Schrettl3">[34]</xref>. Under our iron restriction conditions it was observed the induction of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> orthologs to the known iron dependent transcripts, such as the transcriptional regulator <italic>hapX</italic>, the siderophore biosynthetic enzyme <italic>sidA</italic> and the siderophore transporter <italic>sit1</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Silva1">[17]</xref>. These results suggest the activation of the siderophore pathway of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> under iron limiting conditions. Moreover, the induction of <italic>hapX</italic> suggests that this ortholog in <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> is also integral to the fungus response to iron starvation as previously described in other organisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Schrettl3">[34]</xref>. These data support our <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> iron restriction model for further analysis using proteomic technologies.</p>
      <p>Proteomic analysis revealed that during iron deprivation the majority of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> regulated proteins were related to energy and metabolic function. Among the pathways potentially repressed in <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> during iron depletion was the tricarboxylic acid cycle (TCA). TCA oxidative reactions are mediated by enzymes containing Fe/S clusters including aconitase, succinate dehydrogenase and fumarase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Imsande1">[35]</xref>. We observed that TCA enzymes: aconitase, an ATP-citrate synthase subunit and dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase, were regulated in <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> by iron availability. These data taken together suggest metabolic switching to pathways independent of enzymes with Fe/S clusters. The decreased expression of TCA enzymes observed in <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> during iron deprivation has also been reported in other pathogenic bacteria and fungi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Winters1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Lian1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Jo1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Oexle1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Kaplan2">[37]</xref>. The evidence of TCA repression during iron deprivation is further emphasized by a decreased expression of the <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> enzyme aspartate aminotransferase. A substrate for aspartate aminotransferase is the TCA intermediate metabolite oxaloacetate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Passarella1">[38]</xref>. A reduction in the amount of this substrate due to TCA repression may influence the decreased expression of aspartate aminotransferase. The correlation between aspartate biosynthesis and TCA was also reported in mice given acetate. The authors of this study observed an increase in TCA flux concurrent with an increase in aspartate aminotransferase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Weiss1">[39]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In addition to TCA cycle enzymes, a decrease in the abundance of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> glyoxylate cycle enzymes were also observed during iron depletion. The glyoxylate pathway provides cells with an alternative source of carbon allowing for the consumption of acetate and/or ethanol in place of glucose <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Ensign1">[40]</xref>. The reduced expression of enzymes involved in the glyoxylate pathway correlates with the decreased expression of TCA enzymes because these cycles are coupled. Two of the five reactions of the TCA cycle are catalyzed by enzymes unique to the glyoxylate cycle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Kornberg1">[41]</xref>. Reduced levels of isocitrate lyase, an enzyme with a key role in the glyoxylate cycle, correlate with the negative regulation of this pathway during iron deprivation. We could speculate that during iron limitation and with glucose as the carbon source, <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> reduces the glyoxylate cycle activity due to the requirement of aconitase which is an iron-dependent enzyme of this pathway. This speculation is proven stronger because of the induction of <italic>hapX</italic>. This transcription factor negatively regulates iron dependent energy metabolism.</p>
      <p>Two <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> enzymes involved in the methylcitrate cycle were also decreased in abundance following iron restriction. The methylcitrate cycle is another system that provides an alternative source of carbon through pyruvate production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Bramer1">[42]</xref>. Similar to the glyoxylate cycle this pathway functions using enzymes that are part of the TCA cycle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-MuozElas1">[43]</xref>. These data add further support to the overall metabolic adjustment of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> under iron deprivation.</p>
      <p><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> proteins involved in oxidative phosphorylation also decreased in abundance following iron limitation. Oxidative phosphorylation promotes ATP formation from NADH and FADH<sub>2</sub> produced by the TCA cycle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Saraste1">[44]</xref>. The suppression of pathways such as TCA that feed into oxidative phosphorylation may be associated with the decreased expression levels of enzymes that are part of oxidative phosphorylation. Moreover, <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> enzyme complexes part of the electron transport chain utilize iron as a prosthetic group. Thus, the maintenance of this pathway is iron dependent and with iron levels being low their production may be down regulated as we have detected in this study.</p>
      <p>Our data suggest that the suppression of oxidative pathways during iron deprivation in <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> is linked to an increase of glycolytic activity as demonstrated by the induction of most enzymes in the glycolytic pathway. The glucose concentration of the medium for all of our proteomic analysis remained above 0.8% (w/v) providing high glucose availability to the yeast cells (data not shown). Increased glycolysis activity from iron limitation has been observed in other bacteria and fungi including <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Jo1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Friedman1">[45]</xref>. Moreover, the increased expression of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> hydroxyglutatione hydrolase observed in this study is also linked to glycolysis induction. Hydroxyglutatione hydrolase is involved in methylglyoxal detoxification which is a toxic molecule generated from the degradation of glycolytic products <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Kalapos1">[46]</xref>. Hydroxyglutatione hydrolase prevents methylglyoxal accumulation by converting it to D-lactate in presence of glutathione <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Hoque1">[47]</xref>. These results suggest that <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> remodels its energy metabolism in response to iron starvation by increasing glycolytic activity to compensate for the decrease of aerobic pathways, that are iron dependent.</p>
      <p>It is important to note that the abundance changes detected by proteomic analysis for enzymes involved in energy processes during iron depletion were also observed following transcriptional analysis of selected genes of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> isolated from mouse spleens. Similar to what has been observed for other bacterial and fungal pathogens, these data suggest that iron deprivation treatment may mimic the environment <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> encounters in the host. To further support this theory, the induction of genes involved with glucose utilization under host conditions have been reported for other fungal pathogens. <italic>C. albicans</italic> over expresses <italic>pfk2</italic> that encodes for phosphofructokinase and <italic>pyk1</italic> that encodes for pyruvate kinase when growing within the kidney <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Barelle1">[48]</xref>.</p>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p>Proteomic analysis of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> revealed that the major cellular response affected by iron restriction was related to energy production. Our data suggest that under iron limiting condition glycolysis was the more favored energy pathway over oxidative pathways that are dependent on enzymes containing Fe-S groups. Thus, <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> relies more on the energy generated from glycolysis in order to compensate for the decrease in ATP production from oxidative phosphorylation. In addition to the activation of iron uptake systems, <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> metabolic adjustment may be an indispensable survival mechanism the fungus requires when in a nutrient deficient environment.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>All animal experiments were performed in accordance with the international rules for animal experimentation. The animal protocol was approved by the Universidade Federal de Goiás committee of the ethical treatment of animals (Number: 131/2008).</p>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title><italic>P.brasiliensis</italic> strain maintenance</title>
        <p><italic>P. brasiliensis Pb</italic> 01 (ATCC MYA-826) was used in all experiments. The yeast phase was maintained <italic>in vitro</italic> by sub culturing at 36°C in Fava Netto's semisolid medium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-FavaNetto1">[49]</xref> every 7 days. Fava Netto's semisolid medium components were as follows; 1% (w/v) peptone, 0.5% (w/v) yeast extract, 0.3% (w/v) proteose peptone, 0.5% (w/v) beef extract, 0.5% (w/v) NaCl, 4% (w/v) glucose, 1.2% (w/v) agar, pH 7.2.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>BALB/c mice infection</title>
        <p>Thirty day old female BALB/c mice (<italic>n</italic> = 4) were injected intraperitoneally with a solution containing Ferrodex diluted in 0.9% NaCl (w/v; 50 mg/kg; Tortuga Companhia Zootécnica Agrária, Brazil). Ferrodex is a ferric hydroxide solution containing dextran commonly used for animal supplementation experiments. The iron source was given every 2 days for 15 days prior to and during infection. For control experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 4) sterile 0.9% NaCl (w/v) was injected into mice at the same time intervals as iron supplementation. Mice were inoculated intraperitonially with 10<sup>7</sup> <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> yeast cells as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Bailo1">[50]</xref>. After 2 weeks of harboring the organism, mouse spleens and livers were removed and homogenized in 5 mL of sterile 0.9% (w/v) NaCl. The homogenized sample was plated in brain heart infusion agar supplemented with 4% (v/v) fetal calf serum and 2% (w/v) glucose. The plates were incubated at 36°C and colony forming units (CFUs) were determined after 20 days.</p>
        <p>Gene expression analyses of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> from infected mice were performed by isolating yeast cells from spleens as previously described with minor modifications <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Andes1">[51]</xref>. The spleens of infected mice were homogenized in water using a grinder. To remove large pieces of animal tissue the homogenate was then filtered using a nylon membrane. The sample was frozen in liquid nitrogen and then centrifuged at 500× <italic>g</italic> for 5 minutes to remove any remaining animal tissue. Next, the sample was centrifuged at 7000× <italic>g</italic> for 15 minutes in order to isolate fungal cells. The samples containing fungal cells were checked under the microscope to make sure that they were not cross-contaminated by spleen cells. RNA was extracted from the fungal cells by using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) following the manufacturer's protocol. It is important to note here that <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> yeast cells were not cultured <italic>in vitro</italic> prior RNA extraction.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Iron depletion experiments</title>
        <p><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> yeast cells were grown in McVeigh/Morton medium (MMcM) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Restrepo2">[52]</xref>. Iron depleted medium was supplemented with the iron chelator bathophenanthrolinedisulfonate (BPS; 50 µM; Sigma-Aldrich, Germany). <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> yeast cells were incubated at 36°C with shaking at 150 rpm. Using trypan blue the number of viable cells was determined at time intervals of 2, 4, 6, 24 and 48 hours.</p>
        <p>Protein extracts from yeast cells were prepared by inoculating 50 mL of Fava Neto's liquid medium with 10<sup>8</sup> cells/mL. Cultures were incubated overnight at 36°C under gentle shaking for 16 hours. Cells were centrifuged at 5000× <italic>g</italic> for 5 minutes and washed 5× in MMcM media <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Restrepo2">[52]</xref> containing limited iron. Control cells were incubated in MMcM supplemented with 3.5 µM Fe(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>, for 6 and 24 hours. Cells subjected to iron starvation were incubated in MMcM medium containing 50 µM of BPS with no iron supplementation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Quantitative real time reverse transcription PCR (qRT-PCR) analysis</title>
        <p>Following <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> growth in iron depleted media cells were centrifuged at 1500× <italic>g</italic>, frozen in liquid nitrogen, and disrupted by maceration. Cells were then treated with TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). The manufacturer's protocol was followed to extract total RNA. The RNA was reversibly transcribed using the high capacity RNA-to-cDNA kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). We confirmed the specificity of each primer pair for the target cDNA by the visualization of a single PCR product following agarose gel electrophoresis and melting curve analysis. Primer sequences are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0022810.s006">Table S4</xref>. The cDNA was quantified by qRT-PCR using a SYBR green PCR master mix (Applied Biosystems Step One Plus PCR System). qRT-PCR analysis was performed in triplicate for each cDNA sample as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Dantas1">[53]</xref>. Data were normalized to the ribosomal L34 gene (GenBank accession number EEH37825). Standard curves were generated by diluting the cDNA solution 1∶5. The standard curve method was used for relative quantification of genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Bookout1">[54]</xref>. Statistical comparisons were performed using the student's t test and <italic>p</italic>-values≤0.05 were considered statistically significant. The data were presented as fold change relation between iron deprivation and control conditions, plotted in a log2 scale of the fold change values (−Fe/Control).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>2D-gel electrophoresis</title>
        <p>Following <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> growth in iron depleted media as described above cells were centrifuged at 1500× <italic>g</italic>, frozen in liquid nitrogen, and disrupted by maceration. Cells were then resuspended in a solution containing 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.8, 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Fonseca1">[55]</xref>. Protein concentrations were determined using the Bradford reagent (Sigma-Aldrich) and bovine serum albumin (BSA) was utilized as a standard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Bradford1">[56]</xref>.</p>
        <p>For each sample 300 µg of total protein were loaded onto the gel. The 2-D Clean-up Kit (GE Healthcare, Uppsala, Sweden) was used according to the manufacturer's instructions. Proteins samples were treated with 250 µL of buffer containing 7 M urea, 2 M thiourea, 130 mM 3- [(3-Cholamidopropyl)dimethylammonio]-1-propanesulfonate (CHAPS), 0.002% (w/v) dithiothreitol (DTT), ampholyte-containing buffer (IPG buffer, GE Healthcare), and trace amounts of bromophenol blue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Shaw1">[57]</xref>. Samples were loaded onto a 13 cm Immobiline™ DryStrip gel (GE Healthcare) with a linear separation range of pH 3–11. Isoelectric focusing was conducted on a Multiphor-II electrophoresis system (GE Healthcare) using a step gradient from 500 V for 1 hour, 500–1000 V for 1 hour, 1000–8000 V over 12.5 hours, and 8000 V for 2.5 hours. The isoelectric focusing was preceded by a rehydration step at 30 V for 14 hours.</p>
        <p>Following isoelectric focusing strips were transferred to an equilibration buffer [50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.8, 6 M urea, 30% (v/v) glycerol, 2% (w/v) sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS), and 0.002% (w/v) bromophenol blue] containing 18 mM of DTT for 40 minutes as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Herbert1">[58]</xref>. The strips were next transferred to a fresh equilibration buffer containing 135 mM iodoacetamide. Strips were incubated for another 40 minutes. Each IPG strip was placed on top of a polyacrylamide SDS-PAGE gel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Laemmli1">[59]</xref> and covered with agarose [0.5% (w/v) agarose in running buffer, 25 mM Tris-HCl, 192 mM glycine, 0.1% (w/v) SDS]. SDS-PAGE gels were run at 10°C for 1 hour at 150 V and increased to 250 V for 3 hours. Proteins were stained using silver or Coomassie brilliant blue (PlusOne™ Silver Staining Kit or PlusOne Coomassie Tablets PhastGel Blue R-350, GE Healthcare) according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title>2D-gel image analysis</title>
        <p>Gel images were produced using the Image Scanner III (GE Healthcare). 2D gel spot detection, matching, and spot intensity calculations were performed using Image Master 2D Platinum v7.0 (GE Healthcare). Automated spot matching was also checked manually and corrected if needed. Spot intensity values for all protein spot matches within each analysis were calculated and normalized to the intensity of all the spots detected.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4g">
        <title>2D-gel statistical analysis</title>
        <p>ANOVA statistical analysis was used to compare the differences in intensity of each matched protein spot. A comparison with a <italic>p</italic>-value≤0.05 was considered statistically significant. The <italic>p</italic>-values were calculated using the Image Master 2D Platinum v7.0 software (GE Healthcare). To check population distribution the Shapiro-Wilk test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Shapiro1">[60]</xref> was applied using the software Statistical Package for Social Science (Version 13.0, SPSS Inc, Cary, NC, USA), considering that the hypothesis of the non-normality of the sample distribution could be rejected at <italic>p</italic>-value≤0. 05.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4h">
        <title>In-gel protein digestion</title>
        <p>Protein spots were excised from the 2D-gel and diced into small pieces. Spots were next incubated with 250 µL of a solution containing 50 mM sodium thiosulfate and 15 mM potassium ferricyanide for 5 minutes. Gel pieces were washed twice with water to remove reducing agents. Next, the gel pieces were dehydrated in 100 µL of acetonitrile (ACN) and dried in a speed vacuum. The gel pieces were incubated in 50 µL of 10 mM DTT for 1 hour. The DTT solution was removed and 50 µL of 55 mM iodoacetamide was added. The gel pieces were incubated in the dark for 45 minutes. Next, the gel pieces were washed with 100 µL of 25 mM ammonium bicarbonate followed vortexing for 10 minutes. The solution covering the gel pieces was removed and gel pieces were dehydrated in 100 µL of a solution containing 25 mM ammonium bicarbonate/ACN 50% (v/v). The gel pieces were vortexed for 5 minutes and centrifuged. This step was repeated one time. Next, the gel pieces were dried and 25 µL of a 12.5 ng/ml trypsin solution was added (Sequencing Grade Modified Trypsin Promega, Madison, WI, USA). The gel pieces were placed on ice for 10 minutes. The solution covering the gels was removed and 25 µL of 25 mM ammonium bicarbonate was added. The gel pieces were incubated at 37°C for 16 hours. Following digestion the solution covering the gel pieces was transferred to a clean tube. Next, 50 µL of a solution containing 50% (v/v) ACN and 5% (v/v) trifluoroacetic acid acid (TFA) was added to the gel pieces. The gel pieces were then vortexed for 10 minutes and sonicated for 3 minutes. Next, the solution covering the gel pieces was combined with the original aqueous extraction. The samples were dried in a speed vacuum and peptides were dissolved in 10 µL of water for MS analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Winters1">[3]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4i">
        <title>Mass Spectrometry analysis</title>
        <p>Two microliters of each peptide sample were deposited on a matrix assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS) target plate and dried at room temperature. Next, the peptide mixtures were covered with 2 µL of MALDI matrix solution (10 mg/mL alphacyano-4-hydroxycinammic acid in 50% (v/v) ACN, 5% (v/v) TFA). ZipTips were used to concentrate samples containing low amounts of digested protein (Milipore, Bedford, MA, USA). Dried peptides solutions were analyzed by MS. MALDI quadrupole time-of-flight (Q-TOF) MS, and MALDI-TOF-TOF MS (Synapt, Waters , Manchester, UK and Reflex IV, Bruker Daltonics, Karlsruhe, Germany, respectively). Mass spectra were collected and processed using X-TOF (Bruker Daltonics) and Mass Lynx (Waters). MS data were searched against the NCBI non redundant database and matched with their corresponding proteins sequences using MASCOT (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.matrixscience.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.matrixscience.com</ext-link>). The mass tolerance was set at 100 ppm for each MASCOT search. Each search was restricted to fungi while allowing for one missed trypsin cleavage.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4j">
        <title>Western blot analysis</title>
        <p><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> protein extracts of yeast cells were probed using aconitase, formamidase, isocitrate lyase, and triosephosphate isomerase antibodies. Ten micrograms of protein samples prepared as described above were loaded onto a 12% SDS PAGE gel and separated by electrophoresis. Gels were run at 150 V for ∼2 hours. Protein bands were transferred from gels to nitrocellulose membrane at 30 V for 16 hours in buffer containing 25 mM Tris-HCl, 190 mM glicine, 20% (v/v) methanol. Gels were stained with Ponceau red staining to confirm complete protein transfer. Next, each membrane was submerged in blocking buffer [Phosphate buffered saline solution 1× (PBS; 1.4 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 8 mM Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 140 mM NaCl, 2.7 mM KCl; pH 7.3), 5% (w/v) non-fat dried milk, 0.1% (v/v) Tween 20] for 1–2 hours. Membranes were washed with buffer [PBS 1×, 0.1% (v/v) Tween 20] and incubated with primary antibodies for 2 hours at room temperature. Primary antibodies were used at a 1/5000 (v/v) ratio of antibody to buffer. Primary polyclonal antibodies used were anti-aconitase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Brito1">[61]</xref>, anti-isocitrate lyase (protein molecular weight 60 KDa, unpublished), anti-formamidase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Borges1">[62]</xref> and anti-triosephosphate isomerase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Pereira1">[63]</xref>. This was followed by three 15 minutes washes in blocking buffer. Membranes were incubated with the appropriate conjugated secondary antibody [anti-rabbit or anti-mouse immunoglobulin G coupled to alkaline phosphatase (Sigma-Aldrich)] in a 1/5000 (v/v) ratio. Membranes were developed with 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolylphosphate–nitroblue tetrazolium (BCIP-NBT).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4k">
        <title>Enzyme activity assays</title>
        <p>Formamidase activity was determined by measuring the amount of ammonia formation as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Skouloubris1">[64]</xref>. One µg of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> total protein extract prepared as described above were added to 200 µl of a 100 mM formamide substrate solution in 100 mM phosphate buffer containing 10 mM of EDTA, pH 7.4. Samples were incubated at 37°C for 30 minutes. Following the 30 minutes incubation period 400 µl of phenol-nitroprusside and 400 µl of alkaline hypochlorite (Sigma Aldrich, Co.) were added. Next, samples were incubated for 6 minutes at 50°C and the absorbance was read at 625 nm. The amount of ammonia released for each sample was determined by comparing to a standard curve. One unit (U) of formamidase specific activity was defined as the amount of enzyme required to hydrolyze 1 µmol of formamide (corresponding to the formation of 1 µmol of ammonia) per minute per mg of total protein.</p>
        <p>Catalases activity was determined by measuring a decrease in the absorbance at 240 nm from the conversion of hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) to oxygen as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Aebi1">[65]</xref>. Catalases activity for each sample was calculated using a standard curve generated by five different concentrations of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. One unit of catalase activity was defined as the amount of enzyme required to catalyze the consumption of 1 µmol of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> per minute per mg of total protein.</p>
        <p>Isocitrate lyase activity was determined by measuring the formation of glyoxylate as its phenylhydrazone derivative <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0022810-Ebel1">[66]</xref>. Glyoxylate-phenylhydrazone formation was determined by measuring the absorbance at 324 nm, using an extinction coeficient of 16.8 mM<sup>−1</sup> cm<sup>−1</sup>, in a reaction mixture containing 2 mM threo-D,L-isocitrate (Sigma Aldrich, Co.), 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM phenylhydrazine HCl (Sigma Aldrich, Co.), 2 mM dithiothreitol, and 50 mM potassium phosphate at pH 7.0. Specific activity was determined as the amount of enzyme required to form 1 µmol of glyoxylate-phenylhydrazone per minute per mg of total protein.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0022810.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Iron starvation does not affect the viability of </bold><bold><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic></bold><bold> yeast cells.</bold> Viability of <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> yeast cells incubated in MMcM medium containing 3.5 µM iron (circles) and incubation of yeasts cells in MMcM iron depleted media containing 50 µM BPS (triangles). Viability was determined using trypan blue. Error bars represent standard deviation from three biological replicates while * represents <italic>p</italic>≤0.05.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0022810.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Categorical representation of regulated </bold><bold><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic></bold><bold> proteins following iron starvation.</bold> Identified proteins were classified according to their respective functional categories determined by MIPS. (A) Categorization of differentially expressed proteins during iron starvation. Classification of proteins with induced (B) and repressed expression (C) in iron limiting condition.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0022810.s003" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Relative fold induction of iron metabolism related genes in the time course of iron starvation using real time- RT-PCR.</bold> <sup>1</sup>Values represent the mean of each triplicate sample ± standard deviation.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0022810.s004" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Additional information about </bold><bold><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic></bold><bold> identified proteins with increased expression during iron starvation.</bold> ** Spots visualized only in iron-depleted condition. <sup>1</sup> Spots numbers refers to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g003">Figure 3</xref>. <sup>2</sup> <italic>p</italic> values were accessed by ANOVA statistical test.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0022810.s005" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.s005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Additional information about </bold><bold><italic>P. brasiliensis</italic></bold><bold> identified proteins with reduced expression during iron starvation.</bold> ** Spots visualized only in iron replete condition. <sup>1</sup> Spots numbers refers to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0022810-g003">Figure 3</xref>. <sup>2</sup> <italic>p</italic> values were accessed by ANOVA statistical test.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0022810.s006" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0022810.s006" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Oligonucleotide primers used in quantitative RT-PCR.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Mirelle Garcia Silva for the helpful suggestions.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Doherty1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Host-Pathogen Interactions: The Role of Iron.</article-title>             <source>J Nutr</source>             <volume>137</volume>             <fpage>1341</fpage>             <lpage>1344</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Johnson1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Iron and siderophores in fungal–host interactions.</article-title>             <source>Mycol Res</source>             <volume>112</volume>             <fpage>170</fpage>             <lpage>183</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Winters1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winters</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spellman</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title><italic>Histoplasma capsulatum</italic> proteome response to decreased iron availability.</article-title>             <source>Proteome Sci</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>36</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Lian1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simmer</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Souza</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steen</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuyderduyn</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Iron-regulated transcription and capsule formation in the fungal pathogen <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>55</volume>             <fpage>1452</fpage>             <lpage>1472</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Lan1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodarte</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murillo</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Regulatory networks affected by iron availability in <italic>Candida albicans</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>53</volume>             <fpage>1451</fpage>             <lpage>1469</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-YamaguchiIwai1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Iwai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stearman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dancis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klausner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Iron-regulated DNA binding by the AFT1 protein controls the iron regulon in yeast.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>3377</fpage>             <lpage>3384</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Blaiseau1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blaiseau</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lesuissse</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camadro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Aft2p, a novel iron-regulated transcription activator that modulates, with Aft1p, intracellular iron use and resistance to oxidative stress in yeast.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>276</volume>             <fpage>34221</fpage>             <lpage>34226</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Haas1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zadra</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoffler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angermayr</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>The <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> GATA factor SREA is involved in regulation of siderophore biosynthesis and control of iron uptake.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>274</volume>             <fpage>4613</fpage>             <lpage>4619</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Schrettl1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrettl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bignell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kragi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joechl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Siderophore biosynthesis but not reductive iron assimilation is essential for <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> virulence.</article-title>             <source>J Exp Med</source>             <volume>200</volume>             <fpage>1213</fpage>             <lpage>1219</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Hortschansky1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hortschansky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisendle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Abdallah</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Interaction of HapX with the CCAAT-binding complex-a novel mechanism of gene regulation by iron.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>157</fpage>             <lpage>3168</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Schrettl2">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrettl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisendle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kragl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nierman</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Sre-A mediated iron regulation in <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>70</volume>             <fpage>27</fpage>             <lpage>43</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Mercier1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labbé</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>A transcription factor cascade involving Fep 1 and the CCAAT-binding factor Php4 regulates gene expression in response to iron deficiency in the fission yeast <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>1866</fpage>             <lpage>1881</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Liu1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gravelat</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> AcuM regulates both iron acquisition and gluconeogenesis.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>78</volume>             <fpage>1038</fpage>             <lpage>1054</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Restrepo1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Restrepo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobón</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title><italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dismukes</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Principles and Practice of Infectious Diseases</source>             <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>             <fpage>3062</fpage>             <lpage>3068</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Coutinho1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Paracoccidioidomycosis mortality in Brazil (1980–1995).</article-title>             <source>Cad Saúde Pública</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>1441</fpage>             <lpage>1454</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Prado1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurenti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Travassos</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taborda</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Mortality due to systemic mycoses as a primary cause of death or in association with AIDS in Brazil: a review from 1996 to 2006.</article-title>             <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>513</fpage>             <lpage>521</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Silva1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrank</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailão</surname><given-names>EFLC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailão</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>The homeostasis of iron, copper and zinc in <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>, <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> var. <italic>grubii</italic>, and <italic>Cryptococcus gattii</italic>: a comparative analysis.</article-title>             <source>Frontiers Microbiol</source>             <comment>In press</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-ShakouryElizeh1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shakoury-Elizeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiedeman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashford</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferea</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demeter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Transcriptional remodeling in response to iron deprivation in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>1233</fpage>             <lpage>1243</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Philpott1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Philpott</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Protchenko</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Response to Iron Deprivation in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>20</fpage>             <lpage>27</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Jo1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Novel insight into iron metabolism by integrating deletome and transcriptome analysis in an iron deficiency model of the yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title>             <source>BMC Genomics</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>130</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Seo1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Proteomic analysis of recombinant <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> upon iron deficiency induced via human H-Ferritin production.</article-title>             <source>J Microbiol Biotechnol</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>1368</fpage>             <lpage>1376</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Barluzzi1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barluzzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleppico</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nocentini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boelaert</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neglia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Iron overload exacerbates experimental meningloencephalitis by <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Neuroimmunol</source>             <volume>132</volume>             <fpage>140</fpage>             <lpage>146</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Kontoyiannis1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kontoyiannis</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamilos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giralt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cortes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Increased bone marrow iron stores is an independent risk factor for invasive aspergillosis in patients with high-risk hematologic malignancies and recipients of allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation.</article-title>             <source>Cancer</source>             <volume>110</volume>             <fpage>1303</fpage>             <lpage>1306</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Kosman1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of iron uptake in fungi.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>47</volume>             <fpage>1185</fpage>             <lpage>1197</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Kaplan1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crisp</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philpott</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Iron-dependent metabolic remodeling in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>             <volume>1763</volume>             <fpage>646</fpage>             <lpage>651</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Foster1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Utilization and cell-surface binding of hemin by <italic>Histoplasma capsulatum</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Can J Microbiol</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>437</fpage>             <lpage>442</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Santos1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buisson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dancis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camadro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Haemin uptake and use as an iron source by <italic>Candida albicans</italic>: role of CaHMX1-encoded haem oxygenase.</article-title>             <source>Microbiology</source>             <volume>149</volume>             <fpage>579</fpage>             <lpage>588</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Weissman1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kornitzer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>A family of <italic>Candida</italic> cell surface haem-binding proteins involved in haemin and haemoglobin-iron utilization.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>53</volume>             <fpage>1209</fpage>             <lpage>1220</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Weissman2">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shemer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conibear</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kornitzer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>An endocytic mechanism for haemoglobin-iron acquisition in <italic>Candida albicans</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>69</volume>             <fpage>201</fpage>             <lpage>217</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Almeida1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thewes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>The hyphal-associated adhesin and invasin Als3 of <italic>Candida albicans</italic> mediates iron acquisition from host ferritin.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Pathog</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e1000217</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Puig1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Askeland</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Coordinated remodeling of cellular metabolism during iron deficiency through targeted mRNA degradation.</article-title>             <source>Cell</source>             <volume>120</volume>             <fpage>99</fpage>             <lpage>110</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Rutherford1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Metal-responsive transcription factors that regulate iron, zinc, and copper homeostasis in eukaryotic cells.</article-title>             <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>13</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Jung1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kronstad</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Iron regulation of the major virulence factors in the AIDS-associated pathogen <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e410</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Schrettl3">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrettl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinekamp</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>HapX-mediated adaptation to iron starvation is crucial for virulence of <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>.</article-title>             <source>PLos Pathog</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>e1001124</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Imsande1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imsande</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Iron-sulfur clusters: Formation, perturbation, and physiological functions.</article-title>             <source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source>             <volume>37</volume>             <fpage>81</fpage>             <lpage>97</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Oexle1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oexle</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gnaiger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Iron-dependent changes in cellular energy metabolism: influence on citric acid cycle and oxidative phosphorylation.</article-title>             <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>             <volume>1413</volume>             <fpage>99</fpage>             <lpage>107</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Kaplan2">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crisp</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philpott</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Iron-dependent metabolic remodeling in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>             <volume>1763</volume>             <fpage>646</fpage>             <lpage>651</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Passarella1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Passarella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atlante</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barile</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doonan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Uptake of aspartate aminotransferase into mitochondria <italic>in vitro</italic> causes efflux of malate dehydrogenase and vice versa.</article-title>             <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>             <volume>1022</volume>             <fpage>273</fpage>             <lpage>282</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Weiss1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Albuquerque</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandegaer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chacko</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Consequences of altered aspartate aminotransferase activity on <sup>13</sup>C-glutamate labelling by the tricarboxylic acid cycle in intact rat hearts.</article-title>             <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>             <volume>1243</volume>             <fpage>543</fpage>             <lpage>548</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Ensign1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ensign</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Revisiting the glyoxylate cycle: alternate pathways for microbial acetate assimilation.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>61</volume>             <fpage>274</fpage>             <lpage>276</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Kornberg1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kornberg</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1957</year>             <article-title>Synthesis of cell constituents from C2 units by a modified tricarboxylic acid cycle.</article-title>             <source>Nature (London)</source>             <volume>179</volume>             <fpage>988</fpage>             <lpage>991</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Bramer1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bramer</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Priefert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinbuchel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Identification of the 2-methylcitrate pathway involved in the catabolism of propionate in the polyhydroxyalkanoate-producing strain <italic>Burkholderia sacchari</italic> IPT101(T) and analysis of a mutant accumulating a copolyester with higher 3-hydroxyvalerate content.</article-title>             <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>             <volume>68</volume>             <fpage>271</fpage>             <lpage>279</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-MuozElas1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muñoz-Elías</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Upton</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKinney</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Role of the methylcitrate cycle in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> metabolism, intracellular growth, and virulence.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>60</volume>             <fpage>1109</fpage>             <lpage>1122</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Saraste1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saraste</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Oxidative phosphorylation at the fin de siècle.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>283</volume>             <fpage>1488</fpage>             <lpage>1493</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Friedman1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stauff</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pishchany</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitwell</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> redirects central metabolism to increase iron availability.</article-title>             <source>PLOS Pathog</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>777</fpage>             <lpage>789</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Kalapos1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalapos</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Methylglyoxal in living organisms. Chemistry, biochemistry, toxicology and biological implications.</article-title>             <source>Toxicol Lett</source>             <volume>110</volume>             <fpage>145</fpage>             <lpage>175</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Hoque1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uraji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banu</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>The effects of methylglyoxal on glutathione S-transferase from <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source>             <volume>74</volume>             <fpage>2124</fpage>             <lpage>2126</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Barelle1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barelle</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maccallum</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gow</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Odds</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Niche-specific regulation of central metabolic pathways in a fungal pathogen.</article-title>             <source>Cell Microbiol</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>961</fpage>             <lpage>971</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-FavaNetto1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fava Netto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vegas</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sciannamea</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guarnieri</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1969</year>             <article-title>Antígeno polissacarídeo do <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>. Estudo do tempo de cultura do <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> necessário ao preparo do antígeno.</article-title>             <source>Rev Inst Med Trop</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>177</fpage>             <lpage>181</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Bailo1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailão</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrank</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dutra</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molinari-Madlum</surname><given-names>EEWI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Differential gene expression by <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> in host interaction conditions: Representational difference analysis identifies candidate genes associated with fungal pathogenesis.</article-title>             <source>Microbes Infect</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>2686</fpage>             <lpage>2697</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Andes1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lepak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitula</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchillo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>A simple approach for estimating gene expression in <italic>Candida albicans</italic> directly from a systemic infection site.</article-title>             <source>J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>192</volume>             <fpage>893</fpage>             <lpage>900</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Restrepo2">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Restrepo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiménez</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1980</year>             <article-title>Growth of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> yeast phase in a chemically defined culture medium.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>279</fpage>             <lpage>281</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Dantas1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dantas</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira de Rezende</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailão</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taborda</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva Santos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Identification and characterization of antigenic proteins potentially expressed during the infectious process of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Microbes Infect</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>895</fpage>             <lpage>903</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Bookout1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bookout</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangelsdorf</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pesola</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>High-throughput real-time quantitative reverse transcription PCR.</article-title>             <source>Curr Protoc Mol Biol</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>28</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Fonseca1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jesuino</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felipe</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Two-dimensional electrophoresis and characterization of antigens from <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Microbes Infect</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>535</fpage>             <lpage>542</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Bradford1">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1976</year>             <article-title>A dye binding assay for protein.</article-title>             <source>Anal Biochem</source>             <volume>72</volume>             <fpage>248</fpage>             <lpage>254</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Shaw1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riederer</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Sample preparation for two-dimensional gel electrophoresis.</article-title>             <source>Proteomics</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>1408</fpage>             <lpage>1417</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Herbert1">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galvani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamdan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacCarthy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Reduction and alkylation of proteins in preparation of two-dimensional map analysis: why, when, and how?</article-title>             <source>Electrophoresis</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>2046</fpage>             <lpage>2057</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Laemmli1">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laemmli</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1970</year>             <article-title>Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>227</volume>             <fpage>680</fpage>             <lpage>685</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Shapiro1">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilk</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1965</year>             <article-title>An analysis of variance test for normality (complete samples).</article-title>             <source>Biometrika</source>             <volume>52</volume>             <fpage>591</fpage>             <lpage>611</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Brito1">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezende</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricart</surname><given-names>CAO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Sousa</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <article-title>Identification, characterization and regulation studies of the aconitase of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Fungal Biol</source>             <comment>In press</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Borges1">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Báo</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Detection of a homotetrameric structure and protein-protein interactions of formamidase lead to new functional insights.</article-title>             <source>FEMS Yeast Res</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>104</fpage>             <lpage>113</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Pereira1">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Báo</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>JLM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felipe</surname><given-names>MSS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Analysis of the <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> triosephosphate isomerase suggests the potential for adhesin function.</article-title>             <source>FEMS Yeast Res</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>1381</fpage>             <lpage>1388</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Skouloubris1">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skouloubris</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labigne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Reuse</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Identification and characterization of an aliphatic amidase in <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>989</fpage>             <lpage>998</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Aebi1">
        <label>65</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aebi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1984</year>             <article-title>Assays of catalase in vitro.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Catalase in vitro. Vol. 105</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>122</fpage>             <lpage>126</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0022810-Ebel1">
        <label>66</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwienbacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heesemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brakhage</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Analysis of the regulation, expression, and localization of the isocitrate lyase from <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>, a potential target for antifungal drug development.</article-title>             <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>476</fpage>             <lpage>489</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>