<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0153655</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-16-01256</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematical and statistical techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Meta-analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics (mathematics)</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Meta-analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Diagnostic medicine</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Research design</subject><subj-group><subject>Cohort studies</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics (mathematics)</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical data</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pediatrics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Research design</subject><subj-group><subject>Case-control studies</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Developmental biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Neonates</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Database and informatics methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Database searching</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Prenatal, Perinatal and Neonatal Risk Factors for Intellectual Disability: A Systemic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Prenatal, Perinatal and Neonatal Risk Factors for Intellectual Disability</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Jichong</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Tingting</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Qu</surname>
<given-names>Yi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Mu</surname>
<given-names>Dezhi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Pediatrics, West China Second University Hospital, Sichuan University, Chengdu, 610041, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Key Laboratory of Obstetric &amp; Gynecologic and Pediatric Diseases and Birth Defects of Ministry of Education, Sichuan University, Chengdu, 610041, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Pediatrics, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, 94143, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>Yiping</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Columbia University, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JH DM. Performed the experiments: JH TZ. Analyzed the data: JH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JH. Wrote the paper: JH TZ. Contributed to the critical review and final approval of the submitted manuscript: YQ DM.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">mudz@scu.edu.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>25</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<elocation-id>e0153655</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>13</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>2</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Huang et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Background</title>
<p>The etiology of non-genetic intellectual disability (ID) is not fully known, and we aimed to identify the prenatal, perinatal and neonatal risk factors for ID.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Method</title>
<p>PubMed and Embase databases were searched for studies that examined the association between pre-, peri- and neonatal factors and ID risk (keywords “intellectual disability” or “mental retardation” or “ID” or “MR” in combination with “prenatal” or “pregnancy” or “obstetric” or “perinatal” or “neonatal”. The last search was updated on September 15, 2015. Summary effect estimates (pooled odds ratios) were calculated for each risk factor using random effects models, with tests for heterogeneity and publication bias.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Seventeen studies with 55,344 patients and 5,723,749 control individuals were eligible for inclusion in our analysis, and 16 potential risk factors were analyzed. Ten prenatal factors (advanced maternal age, maternal black race, low maternal education, third or more parity, maternal alcohol use, maternal tobacco use, maternal diabetes, maternal hypertension, maternal epilepsy and maternal asthma), one perinatal factor (preterm birth) and two neonatal factors (male sex and low birth weight) were significantly associated with increased risk of ID.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This systemic review and meta-analysis provides a comprehensive evidence-based assessment of the risk factors for ID. Future studies are encouraged to focus on perinatal and neonatal risk factors and the combined effects of multiple factors.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<award-group id="award001">
<funding-source>
<institution>the National Science Foundation of China</institution>
</funding-source>
<award-id>No.81330016, 81300524, 81172174, 81270724 and 81200462</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Mu</surname>
<given-names>Dezhi</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<award-group id="award002">
<funding-source>
<institution>the State Commission of Science Technology of China</institution>
</funding-source>
<award-id>2013CB967404，2012BAI04B04</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Qu</surname>
<given-names>Yi</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<award-group id="award003">
<funding-source>
<institution-wrap>
<institution-id institution-id-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100002338</institution-id>
<institution>Ministry of Education of the People's Republic of China</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
<award-id>IRT0935，313037</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Mu</surname>
<given-names>Dezhi</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<award-group id="award004">
<funding-source>
<institution>the Science and Technology Bureau of Sichuan province</institution>
</funding-source>
<award-id>2014SZ0149</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Mu</surname>
<given-names>Dezhi</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<award-group id="award005">
<funding-source>
<institution>clinical discipline program (neonatology) from the Ministry of Health of China</institution>
</funding-source>
<award-id>1311200003303</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Mu</surname>
<given-names>Dezhi</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation of China (No. 81330016, 81300524, 81172174, 81270724 and 81200462), grants from the State Commission of Science Technology of China (2013CB967404, 2012BAI04B04), grants from the Ministry of Education of China (IRT0935, 313037), grants from the Science and Technology Bureau of Sichuan province (2014SZ0149, 2016TD0002), and a grant of clinical discipline program (neonatology) from the Ministry of Health of China (1311200003303).</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="3"/>
<table-count count="4"/>
<page-count count="12"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Intellectual disability (ID) or mental retardation (MR) is a developmental disability characterized by significant limitations in both intellectual functioning and adaptive behavior. Its onset occurs before 18 years of age[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref001">1</xref>], and its prevalence in the general population has been estimated at more than 1/100[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref002">2</xref>]. ID can be classified as genetic or non-genetic depending on its etiology. The causes of genetic ID, which accounts for only 30% to 50% of all ID cases[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref003">3</xref>], include chromosomal abnormalities (e.g. trisomy 21 syndrome), inherited genetic traits (e.g. fragile X syndrome) and single gene disorders (e.g. Prader—Willi syndrome)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref004">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref005">5</xref>]. However, the causes of non-genetic ID are not fully known. It is now suggested that the risk factors for non-genetic ID are extensive, and can be classified as prenatal, perinatal and neonatal factors according to the timing of suffering.</p>
<p>Numerous population-based studies have focused on specific non-genetic exposures as possible risk factors for ID. Many support the hypothesis that some prenatal (e.g. increasing maternal age, multiple gestation and maternal hypertension), perinatal (e.g. preterm birth and fetal distress) and neonatal (e.g. male sex, low birth weight and neonatal infection) exposures may increase the risk of ID[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref006">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref007">7</xref>]. However, the overall conclusions of these studies are inconsistent. For example, some studies found that maternal hypertension increased the risk of ID[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref008">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref009">9</xref>], whereas others did not[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref010">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref012">12</xref>]. The aim of the present study was to perform a meta-analysis of all pertinent available data to determine whether prenatal, perinatal, and neonatal exposures affect the onset of ID.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Material and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Study identification and selection</title>
<p>The study was conducted according to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses criteria (PRISMA) as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153655.s001">S1 File</xref>. The PubMed and Embase databases were searched using following keywords and subject terms: “intellectual disability”, “mental retardation”, “ID”, “MR” in combination with “prenatal”, “pregnancy”, “obstetric”, “perinatal”, “neonatal”. The last search was updated on September 15, 2015. There was no language restriction. All studies were initially screened by reading the titles and abstracts, and the full-texts of potential studies were independently assessed for eligibility by two reviewers (Jichong Huang and Tingting Zhu), who discussed disagreements to reach a consensus.</p>
<p>To be included in our analysis, the study had to: (1) evaluate the association between prenatal, perinatal, or neonatal factors and risk of ID, (2) have a cohort, case-control, or cross-sectional design, and (3) report odds ratios (ORs) and corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CIs) or other usable data. Studies were excluded if they: (1) did not eliminate the impact of genetic causes (e.g,. trisomy 21 syndrome, Prader-Willi syndrome and fragile X syndrome) on the risk of ID, (2) did not include a control group, or (3) overlapped with another study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Data extraction</title>
<p>The following data were independently collected by two reviewers (Jichong Huang and Tingting Zhu) from each of the included studies: name of the first author, year of publication, the country in which the study was conducted, study design, age at diagnosis, total number of cases and controls, exposure assessment methods, outcome assessment methods, ID diagnostic criteria, and risk factors.</p>
<p>We only included risk factors that were evaluated in two or more studies. For each risk factor, we extracted the OR together with the 95% CI. When the OR was not provided in the study, we computed a crude OR.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Quality assessment</title>
<p>The methodological quality of each included study was independently assessed by two reviewers (Jichong Huang and Tingting Zhu) using the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref013">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref014">14</xref>]. The quality score was evaluated based on three categories: group selection (four items), comparability between groups (one item), and outcome and exposure assessment (three items). And the maximum score was nine points. Studies were considered to be of high quality if they were scored above the median (&gt; five points). Disagreements between the two reviewers were discussed until a consensus was reached.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>A separate meta-analysis was conducted for each risk factor and the pooled OR was calculated by using the fixed-effects model (a P-value &gt;0.10 indicated heterogeneity) or the random-effects model (a P-value &lt;0.10 indicated heterogeneity) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref015">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref016">16</xref>]. Heterogeneity among studies was assessed by using the chi-square and I<sup>2</sup> tests. Data were considered statistically heterogeneous if I<sup>2</sup> &gt;50% and P was &lt;0.1. Publication bias was assessed by conducting tests for funnel plot asymmetry[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref017">17</xref>]. Begg’s test[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref018">18</xref>] and Egger’s test[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref019">19</xref>] were also used to assess publication bias. The statistical tests were performed by using Review Manager 5.3 and STATA 12.0 software.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Study selection and characteristics</title>
<p>A total of 1,263 studies (927 in PubMed and 336 in Embase) and an additional eight studies culled from other sources were identified after an initial search. After reading the titles and abstracts, 1227 studies were excluded for irrelevant to the prenatal, perinatal or neonatal factors and ID risk, and five studies were excluded because of duplication. After reading the full-texts of the remaining 39 studies, 22 studies were excluded because they did not assess the effect of genetic causes on the risk of ID (13 studies), did not include a control group (six studies), or lacked usable data (three studies). Consequently, our analysis ultimately included 17 studies with a total of 55,344 patients and 5,723,749 control individuals. The meta-analysis included 15 risk factors (12 prenatal, one perinatal, and two neonatal). The selection process is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153655.g001">Fig 1</xref>, and the characteristics of each included study are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0153655.t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone.0153655.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Flow gram of study selection process.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pone.0153655.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Characteristics of the included studies in meta-analysis.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0153655.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">First author</th>
<th align="left">Year</th>
<th align="left">Country</th>
<th align="left">Number(case/control)</th>
<th align="left">Age of diagnosis</th>
<th align="left">Study design</th>
<th align="left">Exposure assessment</th>
<th align="left">Outcome assessment</th>
<th align="left">ID diagnostic criteria</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Onicescu, G[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref020">20</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">2014</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">420/6859</td>
<td align="left">6–11</td>
<td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td>
<td align="left">Medical Record</td>
<td align="left">Medical and school records</td>
<td align="left">ICD9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Mann, JR[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref021">21</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">2013</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">3113/75562</td>
<td align="left">3–6</td>
<td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td>
<td align="left">Medical Record</td>
<td align="left">Registration data</td>
<td align="left">ICD9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Bilder, DA[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref011">11</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">2013</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">146/16936</td>
<td align="left">8</td>
<td align="left">Case-control study</td>
<td align="left">Birth Certificate</td>
<td align="left">School and health records</td>
<td align="left">ICD9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">O'Leary, C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref022">22</xref>](Non-Aboriginal births)</td>
<td align="left">2013</td>
<td align="left">Australia</td>
<td align="left">10576/30744</td>
<td align="left">0–6</td>
<td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td>
<td align="left">Medical record</td>
<td align="left">Registration data</td>
<td align="left">DSM-IV</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">O'Leary, C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref022">22</xref>](Aboriginal births)</td>
<td align="left">2013</td>
<td align="left">Australia</td>
<td align="left">7760/15762</td>
<td align="left">0–6</td>
<td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td>
<td align="left">Medical record</td>
<td align="left">Registration data</td>
<td align="left">DSM-IV</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Langridge, AT[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref008">8</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">2013</td>
<td align="left">Australia</td>
<td align="left">4576/376539</td>
<td align="left">0–6</td>
<td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td>
<td align="left">Medical Record; Birth Certificate</td>
<td align="left">Registration data</td>
<td align="left">DSM-IIIR/ IV/ IV-TR</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Griffith, MI[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref009">9</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">2011</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">1636/79230</td>
<td align="left">5–11</td>
<td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td>
<td align="left">Medical Record; Birth Certificate</td>
<td align="left">Registration data</td>
<td align="left">ICD9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Mann, JR[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref010">10</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">2012</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">5780/159531</td>
<td align="left">3–6</td>
<td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td>
<td align="left">Medical Record; Birth Certificate</td>
<td align="left">Registration data</td>
<td align="left">ICD9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Mann, JR[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref023">23</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">2009</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">5388/129208</td>
<td align="left">2–12</td>
<td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td>
<td align="left">Medical Record; Birth Certificate</td>
<td align="left">Registration data</td>
<td align="left">ICD9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Leonard, H[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref012">12</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">2006</td>
<td align="left">Australia</td>
<td align="left">2674/236964</td>
<td align="left">7–16</td>
<td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td>
<td align="left">Medical record</td>
<td align="left">Registration data</td>
<td align="left">DSM-IV</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Croen, LA[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref024">24</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">2001</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">11114/4590333</td>
<td align="left">0–12</td>
<td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td>
<td align="left">Birth Certificate</td>
<td align="left">Registration data</td>
<td align="left">ICD9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Drews, CD[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref025">25</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">1996</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">221/400</td>
<td align="left">10</td>
<td align="left">Case-control study</td>
<td align="left">Children's mother report</td>
<td align="left">Registration data;School and health records</td>
<td align="left">IQ≤70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Drews, CD[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref026">26</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">1995</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">316/563</td>
<td align="left">10</td>
<td align="left">Case-control study</td>
<td align="left">Birth Certificate</td>
<td align="left">Registration data;School and health records</td>
<td align="left">IQ≤70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Decoufle, F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref027">27</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">1995</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">314/562</td>
<td align="left">10</td>
<td align="left">Case-control study</td>
<td align="left">Birth Certificate</td>
<td align="left">Registration data;School and health records</td>
<td align="left">IQ≤70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Yeargin-Allsopp, M[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref028">28</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">1995</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">330/563</td>
<td align="left">10</td>
<td align="left">Case-control study</td>
<td align="left">Birth Certificate</td>
<td align="left">Registration data;School and health records</td>
<td align="left">IQ≤70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">McDermott, S[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref029">29</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">1993</td>
<td align="left">USA</td>
<td align="left">195/3098</td>
<td align="left">5/9-10</td>
<td align="left">Case-control study</td>
<td align="left">Cildren's mother report</td>
<td align="left">Registration data</td>
<td align="left">Raven Progressive Matrices score≤70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Roeleveld, N[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref030">30</xref>]</td>
<td align="left">1992</td>
<td align="left">Netherlands</td>
<td align="left">306/322</td>
<td align="left">0–15</td>
<td align="left">Case-control study</td>
<td align="left">Medical Record</td>
<td align="left">Medicaid Record;Registration data</td>
<td align="left">ICD</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>Abbreviation:</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p>ICD, International Classification of Diseases;</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn003"><p>DSM: The Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders;</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn004"><p>IQ, Intelligence Quotient.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Quality of the included studies</title>
<p>The methodological quality scores of the included studies ranged from four to seven points. The appraisal details are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153655.s003">S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153655.s004">S2</xref> Tables. Ten of the 17 studies had scores of more than five points and were considered high quality. Variations in methodological quality may reflect in part the disproportionate inclusion of low-income families in some cohort studies[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref009">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref010">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref021">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref023">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref024">24</xref>] owing to the participation of these families in health insurance programs; consequently, middle- and upper-income families may have been underrepresented. In some case-control studies[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref025">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref029">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref031">31</xref>], ID was only defined as intelligence quotient (IQ) ≤70, rather than via the diagnostic criteria of the International Classification of Diseases or the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders. Moreover, because ID can begin before the age of 18 years, the follow-up time was insufficient in most cohort studies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Prenatal, perinatal and neonatal risk factors</title>
<p>Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0153655.t002">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0153655.t004">4</xref> list the prenatal, perinatal, and neonatal risk factors included in the meta-analysis, as well as the summary effect estimate (ORs) with 95% CI and the P-value for each factor.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0153655.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Meta-analysis of prenatal risk factors for ID.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0153655.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Risk factor</th>
<th align="left">Authors</th>
<th align="left">No. of case/total</th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left">P-value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">*</xref></th>
<th align="left">P<sub>Het</sub></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Bilder 2013</td>
<td align="left">29/2086</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2012</td>
<td align="left">209/3583</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Advanced maternal age (≥35 vs.&lt;35)</td>
<td align="left">Mann 2009</td>
<td align="left">51/2213</td>
<td align="left"><bold>1.53(1.35, 1.72)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Croen 2001</td>
<td align="left">1420/504751</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Williams 1999</td>
<td align="left">26/50</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1996</td>
<td align="left">32/112</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Advanced maternal age (≥30 vs.&lt;30)</td>
<td align="left">Drews 1995</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left">0.81(0.62, 1.05)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.11</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.57</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Yeargin-Allsopp 1995</td>
<td align="left">53/152</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Bilder 2013</td>
<td align="left">19/2266</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2009</td>
<td align="left">10/906</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Maternal age&lt;20</td>
<td align="left">Williams 1999</td>
<td align="left">132/256</td>
<td align="left">1.15(0.98, 1.35)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.09</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1996</td>
<td align="left">60/129</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1995</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Yeargin-Allsopp 1995</td>
<td align="left">86/204</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Onicescu 2014</td>
<td align="left">1443/38204</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2013</td>
<td align="left">2892/81230</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2012</td>
<td align="left">321/4873</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Maternal black race</td>
<td align="left">Croen 2001</td>
<td align="left">1650/367611</td>
<td align="left"><bold>1.08(1.04, 1.13)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Williams 1999</td>
<td align="left">356/624</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1996</td>
<td align="left">170/351</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1995</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Yeargin-Allsopp 1995</td>
<td align="left">232/499</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2013</td>
<td align="left">2399/60184</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2012</td>
<td align="left">1312/29950</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Griffith 2011</td>
<td align="left">749/31988</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2009</td>
<td align="left">2247/47540</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Low maternal education (&lt;12 vs.≥12 years)</td>
<td align="left">Williams 1999</td>
<td align="left">439/848</td>
<td align="left"><bold>1.33(1.28, 1.37)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1996</td>
<td align="left">121/198</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1995</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Decoufle 1995</td>
<td align="left">176/332</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Yeargin-Allsopp 1995</td>
<td align="left">177/333</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p><bold>*</bold>: Significant positive results (P&lt;0.05).</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p>NR, Not Report.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0153655.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Meta-analysis of prenatal risk factors for ID (Continued).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0153655.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Risk factor</th>
<th align="left">Authors</th>
<th align="left">No. of case/total</th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left">P-value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001">*</xref></th>
<th align="left">P<sub>Het</sub></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Croen 2001</td>
<td align="left">3258/1412612</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Parity = 2 (2 vs.1)</td>
<td align="left">Drews 1996</td>
<td align="left">71/236</td>
<td align="left">1.11(0.96, 1.28)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.15</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1995</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Yeargin-Allsopp 1995</td>
<td align="left">95/307</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Croen 2001</td>
<td align="left">4148/1347012</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Parity≥3 (≥3 vs.1)</td>
<td align="left">Drews 1996</td>
<td align="left">79/158</td>
<td align="left"><bold>1.63(1.45, 1.84)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1995</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Yeargin-Allsopp 1995</td>
<td align="left">119/238</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Onicescu 2014</td>
<td align="left">8/85</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">O'leary 2013 (Non-Aboriginal births)</td>
<td align="left">265/676</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Maternal alcohol use</td>
<td align="left">O'leary 2013 (Aboriginal births)</td>
<td align="left">358/811</td>
<td align="left"><bold>1.63(1.49, 1.78)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2009</td>
<td align="left">68/1116</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1996</td>
<td align="left">39/104</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Roeleveld 1992</td>
<td align="left">204/383</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Onicescu 2014</td>
<td align="left">77/1180</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2013</td>
<td align="left">1177/30392</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Bilder 2013</td>
<td align="left">13/1389</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Maternal tobacco use</td>
<td align="left">Mann 2012</td>
<td align="left">629/14503</td>
<td align="left"><bold>1.10(1.06, 1.15)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2009</td>
<td align="left">1089/27169</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1996</td>
<td align="left">221/400</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Roeleveld 1992</td>
<td align="left">154/308</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Langridge 2013</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Maternal diabetes</td>
<td align="left">Mann 2013</td>
<td align="left">734/17988</td>
<td align="left"><bold>1.15(1.08, 1.23)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2012</td>
<td align="left">420/9784</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Leonard 2006</td>
<td align="left">47/2680</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Bilder 2013</td>
<td align="left">6/654</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Langridge 2013</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Maternal hypertension /pre-eclampsia/eclampsia</td>
<td align="left">Griffith 2011</td>
<td align="left">155/5169</td>
<td align="left"><bold>1.33(1.24, 1,42)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2012</td>
<td align="left">523/11416</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Leonard 2006</td>
<td align="left">17/1379</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Maternal epilepsy</td>
<td align="left">Mann 2012</td>
<td align="left">29/333</td>
<td align="left"><bold>2.76(2.16, 3.52)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Leonard 2006</td>
<td align="left">42/1147</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Maternal asthma</td>
<td align="left">Langridge 2013</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left"><bold>1.48(1.24, 1.75)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Leonard 2006</td>
<td align="left">126/7743</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p><bold>*</bold>: Significant positive results (P&lt;0.05).</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p>NR, Not Report.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0153655.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>Meta-analysis of peri- and neonatal risk factors for ID.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0153655.t004g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Risk factor</th>
<th align="left">Authors</th>
<th align="left">No. of case/total</th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left">P-value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001">*</xref></th>
<th align="left">P<sub>Het</sub></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Preterm birth (GA&lt;37 vs.≥37 weeks)</td>
<td align="left">Bilder 2013</td>
<td align="left">32/1359</td>
<td align="left"><bold>2.03(1.79, 2.31)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Griffith 2011</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Onicescu 2014</td>
<td align="left">284/3713</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Langridge 2013</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2013</td>
<td align="left">4028/83485</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2012</td>
<td align="left">2141/39669</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Griffith 2011</td>
<td align="left">1106/1174</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Male sex</td>
<td align="left">Croen 2001</td>
<td align="left">7027/2350287</td>
<td align="left"><bold>1.96(1.90, 2.01)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Mann 2009</td>
<td align="left">3620/68610</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Williams 1999</td>
<td align="left">289/566</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1996</td>
<td align="left">138/333</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1995</td>
<td align="left">NR</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Yeargin-Allsopp 1995</td>
<td align="left">199/466</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Bilder 2013</td>
<td align="left">30/868</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Griffith 2011</td>
<td align="left">349/7667</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Low birth weight (&lt;2500g vs.≥2500g)</td>
<td align="left">Croen 2001</td>
<td align="left">8537/4314859</td>
<td align="left"><bold>3.56(3.27, 3.89)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Drews 1996</td>
<td align="left">39/73</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">McDermott 1993</td>
<td align="left">195/3293</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p><bold>*</bold>: Significant positive results (P&lt;0.05).</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn002"><p>NR, Not Report.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The statistically significant prenatal risk factors identified in the meta-analysis were as follows: advanced maternal age (maternal age over 35) (OR, 1.54; 95% CI, 1.21 to 1.96), maternal black race (OR, 1.71; 95% CI, 1.33 to 2.20), low maternal education (OR, 2.09; 95% CI, 1.73 to 2.52), third or more parity (OR, 1.63; 95% CI, 1.45 to 1.84), maternal alcohol use (OR, 1.54; 95% CI, 1.30 to 1. 83), maternal tobacco use (OR, 1.10; 95% CI, 1.06 to 1.15), maternal diabetes (OR, 1.19; 95% CI, 1.00 to 1.41), maternal hypertension (OR, 1.28; 95% CI, 1.01 to 1.64), maternal epilepsy (OR, 2.63; 95% CI, 1.54 to 4.49) and maternal asthma (OR, 1.48; 95% CI, 1.24 to 1.75) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0153655.t002">Table 2</xref>). There was heterogeneity among the individual studies for most outcomes excepting those for third or more parity (I<sup>2</sup> = 32%, P = 0.22), maternal tobacco use (I<sup>2</sup> = 0%, P = 0.53), and maternal asthma (I<sup>2</sup> = 0%, P = 0.75) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0153655.t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<p>Significant positive associations were also found between ID risk and preterm birth (a prenatal factor) (OR, 2.50; 95% CI, 1.38 to 4.53) and between ID risk and two neonatal factors: male sex (OR, 1.84; 95% CI, 1.64 to 2.07) and low birth weight (OR, 3.43; 95% CI, 2.25 to 5.32) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0153655.t003">Table 3</xref>). Individual studies were heterogeneous for both neonatal outcomes (I<sup>2</sup> = 93%, P &lt;0.0001 for both) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0153655.t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Publication bias</title>
<p>Publication bias was assessed for the factors examined in the pooled analysis of more than two studies (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153655.g002">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153655.g003">3</xref>). Significant publication bias was found for maternal black race (Begg’s test, P = 0.048; Egger’s test, P = 0.006) and low maternal education (Begg’s test, P = 0.022; Egger’s test, P &lt;0.001).</p>
<fig id="pone.0153655.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Funnel plot for publication bias test.</title>
<p>The two oblique lines indicate the pseudo 95% confidence limits.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pone.0153655.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Funnel plot for publication bias test (Continued).</title>
<p>The two oblique lines indicate the pseudo 95% confidence limits.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Identifying patients with a high risk of non-genetic ID is important for early detection and intervention of ID, which would benefit both clinical practice and public health. To our knowledge, this study is the first systemic review and meta-analysis of the relationship between prenatal, perinatal, and neonatal factors and the risk of ID. This meta-analysis included 17 cohort or case-control studies with a total of 55,344 patients and 5,723,749 control individuals.</p>
<p>The factors strongly associated with ID risk were advanced maternal age (&gt;35 years), maternal black race, low maternal education, third or more parity, maternal alcohol use, maternal epilepsy, preterm birth, male sex, and low birth weight. Other significant factors with a lower strength of association (risk estimates less than 1.5) were maternal tobacco use, maternal diabetes, maternal hypertension and maternal asthma.</p>
<p>The fetus is highly susceptible to changes in maternal conditions. Risk factors such as maternal toxicant exposure and metabolic disorders can significantly affect the genetically programmed brain development of the fetus. Previous studies have shown that maternal tobacco exposure[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref032">32</xref>], alcohol exposure[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref033">33</xref>], diabetes[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref034">34</xref>] and hypertension[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref035">35</xref>] can result in abnormal brain development. These risk factors are therefore closely associated with intelligence development, as indicated by our meta-analysis. What’s more, Mann et al. have demonstrated that pre-pregnancy obesity contributes to maternal metabolic disorders, and is also associated with significantly increased risk of ID in the children[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref021">21</xref>]. Therefore, more epidemiological studies in a variety of geographic groups are needed in the future to test the consistency and generalisability of this association.</p>
<p>Before the 21st century, advanced maternal age was considered to be &gt;30 years. Several studies during that period investigated but could not confirm a relationship between maternal age and risk of ID owing to insignificant results[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref025">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref026">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref028">28</xref>]. In recent years, the maternal age at delivery has increased, and advanced maternal age has been redefined as &gt;35 years. Our meta-analysis demonstrates a positive association between maternal age &gt;35 years and the risk of ID. The father’s age at the time the of child’s birth is also increasing, and has been shown to correlate with ID risk[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref030">30</xref>]. However, most studies in our meta-analysis did not exclude the potential effects of this confounder. Further well-adjusted studies are needed and should explore the other cut-off criteria besides age over 35-year-old.</p>
<p>There were no significant associations between ID risk and young maternal age (under 20-year-old) or second parity. The reason may be the limited number of included studies and insufficient simple size. Young maternal age often indicates a low education level, which is also related to ID risk. However, some of the studies included in our meta-analysis did not control this confounder. Moreover, since young maternal age ranges from 16 to 20 years old[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref036">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref037">37</xref>], a more extensive age range should be taken into consideration in future investigations of ID risk.</p>
<p>Two previous meta-analyses examined the relationship between IQ score and preterm birth[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref038">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref039">39</xref>]. Both reported significantly lower IQ scores in preterm as compared with full-term infants, which is consistent with our results. In addition, Kerr-Wilson et al. reported a linear dose-response relationship between the IQ score and the gestation period: the IQ score decreased steadily for each 1-week decrease in the gestation period[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0153655.ref038">38</xref>]. Similarly, it is worthwhile to determine whether this relationship exists even in ID cases with different severity levels. Therefore, further studies should be performed to investigate the associations between different gestational weeks and the severity of ID in preterm infants.</p>
<p>Some limitations of this meta-analysis should be addressed. First, several studies presented only crude ORs and did not adjust for other potential confounders, which might have resulted in overestimation of the association between risk factors and ID. Second, the heterogeneity among studies was noted in most risk factors. This heterogeneity resulted from the different diagnostic criteria of ID, age of diagnosis, sample size, and exposure or outcome assessment methods among studies. Moreover, the number of studies in each meta-analysis limited our ability to investigate these factors. Third, only published data were included in this analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>This systemic review and meta-analysis identified prenatal, perinatal and neonatal risk factors for ID. The findings of this study indicate that prenatal factors have been the focus for studies on ID risk. In the future, more studies that focus on perinatal and neonatal factors are required, and researchers should be encouraged to investigate combinations of factors to a further study on the mechanisms leading to ID.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0153655.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 File</label>
<caption>
<title>PRISMA checklist.</title>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0153655.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 File</label>
<caption>
<title>Reasons for Exclusion.</title>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0153655.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.s003" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>New Castle Ottawa (NOS) quality assessment for cohort studies.</title>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0153655.s004" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0153655.s004" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>New Castle Ottawa (NOS) quality assessment for case-control studies.</title>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation of China (No.81330016, 81300524, 81172174, 81270724 and 81200462), grants from the State Commission of Science Technology of China (2013CB967404, 2012BAI04B04), grants from the Ministry of Education of China (IRT0935, 313037), grants from the Science and Technology Bureau of Sichuan province (2014SZ0149), and a grant of clinical discipline program (neonatology) from the Ministry of Health of China (1311200003303).</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">American Psychiatric Association (1994) Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders: DSM-IV Washington, DC.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maulik</surname> <given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mascarenhas</surname> <given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mathers</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dua</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saxena</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prevalence of intellectual disability: a meta-analysis of population-based studies</article-title>. <source>Research in developmental disabilities</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>419</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ridd.2010.12.018" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ridd.2010.12.018</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21236634</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curry</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aughton</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cassidy</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Evaluation of mental retardation: recommendations of a Consensus Conference: American College of Medical Genetics</article-title>. <source>American journal of medical genetics</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>468</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9375733</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayub</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vincent</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The genetic basis of non-syndromic intellectual disability: a review</article-title>. <source>Journal of neurodevelopmental disorders</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>182</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21124998</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rauch</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyer</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guth</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zweier</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kraus</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Diagnostic yield of various genetic approaches in patients with unexplained developmental delay or mental retardation</article-title>. <source>Am J Med Genet A</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>140A</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>2063</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyall</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauls</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santangelo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spiegelman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ascherio</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Maternal Early Life Factors Associated with Hormone Levels and the Risk of Having a Child with an Autism Spectrum Disorder in the Nurses Health Study II</article-title>. <source>J Autism Dev Disord</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>618</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10803-010-1079-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10803-010-1079-7</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20700638</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDermott</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durkin</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schupf</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Epidemiology and etiology of mental retardation</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobson</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulick</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rojahn</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Handbook of Intellectual Disabilities and Developmental Disabilities</source> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Press</publisher-name>. <year>2007</year>: p. <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langridge</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasson</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nassar</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacoby</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pennell</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Maternal conditions and perinatal characteristics associated with autism spectrum disorder and intellectual disability</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e50963</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0050963" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0050963</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23308096</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffith</surname> <given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDermott</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Risk of Intellectual Disability in Children Born to Mothers with Preeclampsia or Eclampsia with Partial Mediation by Low Birth Weight</article-title>. <source>Hypertens Pregnancy</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3109/10641955.2010.507837" xlink:type="simple">10.3109/10641955.2010.507837</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20846048</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDermott</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardin</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Children Born to Diabetic Mothers May be More Likely to Have Intellectual Disability</article-title>. <source>Matern Child Hlth J</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>928</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bilder</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinborough-Zimmerman</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bakian</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dorius</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nangle</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Prenatal and perinatal factors associated with intellectual disability</article-title>. <source>American journal on intellectual and developmental disabilities</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1352/1944-7558-118.2.156" xlink:type="simple">10.1352/1944-7558-118.2.156</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23464612</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leonard</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Klerk</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bourke</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bower</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Maternal health in pregnancy and intellectual disability in the offspring: A population-based study</article-title>. <source>Ann Epidemiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>448</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16182562</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">GA Wells BS, O'Connell D, Peterson J, Welch V, Losos M, Tugwell P. The Newcastle-Ottawa score for non-randomized studies. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wwwohrica" xlink:type="simple">http://wwwohrica</ext-link> Accessed November, 2015. 2015.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elyasi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abreu</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Badri</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saltaji</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flores-Mir</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impact of Sense of Coherence on Oral Health Behaviors: A Systematic Review</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e0133918</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0133918" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0133918</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26275064</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DerSimonian</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Controlled clinical trials</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3802833</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takkouche</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cadarso-Suarez</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spiegelman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of old and new tests of heterogeneity in epidemiologic meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>American journal of epidemiology</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>150</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10412966</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoshdel</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Attia</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carney</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Basic concepts in meta-analysis: A primer for clinicians</article-title>. <source>International journal of clinical practice</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1287</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16981972</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumdar</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7786990</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey Smith</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minder</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>Bmj</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>315</volume>(<issue>7109</issue>):<fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9310563</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onicescu</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDermott</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aelion</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bayesian importance parameter modeling of misaligned predictors: soil metal measures related to residential history and intellectual disability in children</article-title>. <source>Environmental science and pollution research international</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>10775</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11356-014-3072-8" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11356-014-3072-8</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24888618</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDermott</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pre-pregnancy body mass index, weight change during pregnancy, and risk of intellectual disability in children</article-title>. <source>BJOG: an international journal of obstetrics and gynaecology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>120</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Leary</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leonard</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bourke</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D'Antoine</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartu</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bower</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intellectual disability: population-based estimates of the proportion attributable to maternal alcohol use disorder during pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/dmcn.12029" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/dmcn.12029</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23241019</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mcdermott</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname> <given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trichomoniasis in Pregnancy and Mental Retardation in Children</article-title>. <source>Ann Epidemiol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>891</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.annepidem.2009.08.004" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.annepidem.2009.08.004</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19944351</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Croen</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grether</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selvin</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The epidemiology of mental retardation of unknown cause</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>art. no.-e86</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drews</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>YearginAllsopp</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Decoufle</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>The relationship between idiopathic mental retardation and maternal smoking during pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>547</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8632944</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drews</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yearginallsopp</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Decoufle</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Variation In the Influence Of Selected Sociodemographic Risk-Factors for Mental-Retardation</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>85</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7892914</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Decoufle</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>. <article-title>The relationship between maternal education and mental retardation in 10-year-old children</article-title>. <source>Ann Epidemiol</source>. <year>1995</year>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8653206</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yearginallsopp</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drews</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Decoufle</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mild Mental-Retardation In Black-And-White Children In Metropolitan Atlanta—a Case-Control Study</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>85</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>324</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7892913</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDermott</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cokert</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKeown</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Low birthweight and risk of mild mental retardation by ages 5 and 9 to 11</article-title>. <source>Paediatric and perinatal epidemiology</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8516192</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roeleveld</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vingerhoets</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zielhuis</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gabreels</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mental-Retardation Associated with Parental Smoking And Alcohol-Consumption before, during, And after Pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Prev Med</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1738762</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>LO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Decoufle</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Is maternal age a risk factor for mental retardation among children?</article-title> <source>American journal of epidemiology</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>149</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>814</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10221318</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekblad</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Korkeila</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehtonen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Smoking during pregnancy affects foetal brain development</article-title>. <source>Acta paediatrica</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/apa.12791" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/apa.12791</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25169748</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ebrahim</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Floyd</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Atrash</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prevalence of risk factors for adverse pregnancy outcomes during pregnancy and the preconception period—United States, 2002–2004</article-title>. <source>Matern Child Health J</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5 Suppl</issue>):<fpage>S101</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16710762</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagberg</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gressens</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mallard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inflammation during fetal and neonatal life: implications for neurologic and neuropsychiatric disease in children and adults</article-title>. <source>Annals of neurology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>444</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ana.22620" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/ana.22620</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22334391</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mattes</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oddy</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Klerk</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McLean</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Hypertensive Diseases of Pregnancy and the Development of Behavioral Problems in Childhood and Adolescence: The Western Australian Pregnancy Cohort Study</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr-Us</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>154</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rindfuss</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Offutt</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Education and the changing age pattern of American fertility: 1963–1989</article-title>. <source>Demography</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8875062</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruce</surname> <given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shulman</surname> <given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brogan</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pregnancy planning and pre-conception counseling. The PRAMS Working Group</article-title>. <source>Obstetrics and gynecology</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>82</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>955</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8233272</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr-Wilson</surname> <given-names>CO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mackay</surname> <given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pell</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of the association between preterm delivery and intelligence</article-title>. <source>Journal of public health</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/pubmed/fdr024" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/pubmed/fdr024</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21393308</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0153655.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhutta</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cleves</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casey</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cradock</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anand</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cognitive and behavioral outcomes of school-aged children who were born preterm: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Jama</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>288</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>728</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12169077</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>