<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-18055</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108196</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Metabolic disorders</subject><subj-group><subject>Diabetes mellitus</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Ophthalmology</subject><subj-group><subject>Retinal disorders</subject><subj-group><subject>Retinal degeneration</subject><subj-group><subject>Macular degeneration</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Diabetes Mellitus and Risk of Age-Related Macular Degeneration: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Diabetes and Risk of AMD</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>Shi Song</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Qihua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Fang Yao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>Pancy O. S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Li Jia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brelén</surname><given-names>Mårten E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>Chi Pui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Chen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Ophthalmology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University and State Key Laboratory of Reproductive Medicine, Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Ophthalmology &amp; Visual Sciences, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Ophthalmology, The Affiliated Jiangyin Hospital of Southeast University Medical College, Jiangyin, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Ophthalmology, Ningbo Medical Treatment Center Lihuili Hospital, Ningbo, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>Yuk Fai</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Purdue University, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">dr.zhaochen@gmail.com</email> (CZ); <email xlink:type="simple">cppang@cuhk.edu.hk</email> (CP)</corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CP CZ. Performed the experiments: XC SR. Analyzed the data: XC SR QX FT YL HG. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: PT LC MB. Wrote the paper: XC SR CP CZ.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<elocation-id>e108196</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Chen et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Age-related macular degeneration (AMD) is a major cause of severe vision loss in elderly people. Diabetes mellitus is a common endocrine disorder with serious consequences, and diabetic retinopathy (DR) is the main ophthalmic complication. DR and AMD are different diseases and we seek to explore the relationship between diabetes and AMD. MEDLINE, EMBASE, and the Cochrane Library were searched for potentially eligible studies. Studies based on longitudinal cohort, cross-sectional, and case-control associations, reporting evaluation data of diabetes as an independent factor for AMD were included. Reports of relative risks (RRs), hazard ratios (HRs), odds ratio (ORs), or evaluation data of diabetes as an independent factor for AMD were included. Review Manager and STATA were used for the meta-analysis. Twenty four articles involving 27 study populations were included for meta-analysis. In 7 cohort studies, diabetes was shown to be a risk factor for AMD (OR, 1.05; 95% CI, 1.00–1.14). Results of 9 cross-sectional studies revealed consistent association of diabetes with AMD (OR, 1.21; 95% CI, 1.00–1.45), especially for late AMD (OR, 1.48; 95% CI, 1.44–1.51). Similar association was also detected for AMD (OR, 1.29; 95% CI, 1.13–1.49) and late AMD (OR, 1.16; 95% CI, 1.11–1.21) in 11 case-control studies. The pooled ORs for risk of neovascular AMD (nAMD) were 1.10 (95% CI, 0.96–1.26), 1.48 (95% CI, 1.44–1.51), and 1.15 (95% CI, 1.11–1.21) from cohort, cross-sectional and case-control studies, respectively. No obvious divergence existed among different ethnic groups. Therefore, we find diabetes a risk factor for AMD, stronger for late AMD than earlier stages. However, most of the included studies only adjusted for age and sex; we thus cannot rule out confounding as a potential explanation for the association. More well-designed prospective cohort studies are still warranted to further examine the association.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by National Key Basic Research Program of China (2013CB967500); National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81222009 and 81170856); Thousand Youth Talents Program of China (to C.Z.); Jiangsu Outstanding Young Investigator Program (BK2012046); Jiangsu Province's Key Provincial Talents Program (RC201149); Jiangsu Province's Scientific Research Innovation Program for Postgraduates (CXZZ13_0590 to X.C.); an Endowment Fund for the Lim Por-Yen Eye Genetics Research Centre; the General Research Fund from the Research Grants Council of Hong Kong (No. 473410); and A Project Funded by the Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions (PAPD). The sponsor or funding organization had no role in the design or conduct of this research.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Age-related macular degeneration (AMD) has become a major cause of irreversible visual impairments in elderly people around the world, casting a heavy socio-economic burden on eye care <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Bressler1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Jager1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Lim1">[3]</xref>. AMD can be classified into the early and late stages. Patients with early AMD are usually asymptomatic, while severe vision loss frequently occurs in its late stage. Late AMD can be further categorized into two main subtypes: neovascular AMD (nAMD) and geographic atrophy (GA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Lim1">[3]</xref>. The estimated prevalence is 6.8% for early AMD and 1.5% for late AMD in Caucasians over the age of 40 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Lim1">[3]</xref>. It is estimated that 5% of early AMD patients will progress to late AMD over a 5-year period, increasing to nearly 15% over a 15-year period <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Cheung1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Mitchell1">[5]</xref>. Similar prevalence has been identified in Asians but not in the black population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Kawasaki1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Friedman1">[7]</xref>.</p>
<p>The pathogenesis of AMD is complicated with multiple risk factors, including age, ocular dysfunctions, systemic diseases, diet, smoking, genetic, and environmental factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Chakravarthy1">[8]</xref>. As a modifiable personal factor, whether diabetes play a role in the development and progression of AMD has been vigorously studied. While several reports presented positive correlations between diabetes and AMD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Topouzis1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Borger1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Karesvuo1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-McGwin1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Nitsch1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Vaicaitiene1">[14]</xref>, some other reports showed no such effect <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-FraserBell1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Xu1">[16]</xref>. Even inversed relationship has been reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Clemons1">[17]</xref>. To gain a clear insight into the relationship between AMD and diabetes, we conducted a meta-analysis to assess whether diabetes is a risk factor for AMD.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Eligibility Criteria for Considering Studies for This Review</title>
<p>Included studies were: (1) studies evaluating diabetes as an individual risk factor for AMD; (2) prospective or retrospective cohort study, or study of cross-sectional or case-control design; (3) studies using predefined criteria and procedures for diabetes diagnosis and AMD grading; and (4) relative risks (RRs), hazard ratios (HRs), and odds ratio (ORs) have been reported, or data provided that enabled calculations of these outcomes. Case reports, reviews, abstracts, conference proceedings, editorials, reports with incomplete data, and non-English articles were excluded. For serial publications from the same research team using overlapped subjects, we included those: (1) with the latest follow-up information; and (2) providing adjusted RRs, HRs, or ORs with 95% CIs. To come up with a more precise insight into whether diabetes is an independent risk factor for AMD, only studies investigating diabetes as the main exposure, or provides adjusted RRs, HRs, or ORs with 95% CIs were included. This study was approved and reviewed by the institutional ethics committee of The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University and adhered to the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Search Methods for Identifying Studies</title>
<p>We searched MEDLINE, EMBASE, and the Cochrane Library for all relevant articles starting from year 1946 to March 18, 2014. We followed the Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-XX1">[18]</xref> and Meta-analysis of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (MOOSE) guideline <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Stroup1">[19]</xref> in designing and reporting the current study. Our search strategies were detailed in <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0108196.s005">Appendix S1</xref></bold>. No language filters was applied. Additional studies were identified from reference lists of the retrieved reports. Retrieved records and eligibility status were managed using EndNote X5 software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://endnote.com/" xlink:type="simple">http://endnote.com/</ext-link>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Study Selection</title>
<p>Two investigators (X.C. and S.S.R.) independently screened all retrieved citations based on title, abstract, and complete document if necessary. All relevant full-text articles were obtained and reviewed to determine the eligibility of each study. Disagreements were resolved via consensus with a senior reviewer (C.Z.).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Data Collection and Risk of Bias Assessment</title>
<p>The two reviewers (X.C. and S.S.R.) extracted outcomes from each study separately with a customized datasheet. Data obtained included: first author, year of publication, title of the study (if any), duration of the study, country or region, races, study design, sample size, estimated ORs, RRs, or HRs, adjusted factors in multiple regression analysis, and clinical examinations and diagnostic criteria for AMD and diabetes. We used the Newcastle Ottawa Scale (NOS, accessed via <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK35156/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK35156/</ext-link>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Yuan1">[20]</xref> and the criteria recommended by Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ, accessed via <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK35156/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK35156/</ext-link>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Rostom1">[21]</xref> to evaluate the risk of biases for prospective cohorts or case-control studies, and cross-sectional studies, respectively. All data from these two reviewers were compared. Agreement among the reviewers was sought after completion of grading.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Data Synthesis and Analysis</title>
<p>We assessed the association between diabetes and AMD by combining ORs from case-control and cross-sectional studies, and RRs or HRs from cohort studies. Heterogeneity between studies were tested by Cochran's Q statistic, and evaluated by the proportion of variation attributable to among-study heterogeneity, <italic>I<sup>2</sup></italic>. Heterogeneity among studies was considered no, low, moderate, and high when <italic>I<sup>2</sup></italic> equals to 0% to 24%, 25% to 49%, 50% to 74%, and more than 75%, respectively. If <italic>p</italic> for Q&lt;0.1 or <italic>I<sup>2</sup></italic>&gt;50%, a random-effects model (the DerSimonian and Laird method) was used <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-DerSimonian1">[22]</xref>, otherwise we used a fixed-effects model(the Mantel-Haenszel method) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Kuritz1">[23]</xref>. Subgroup analysis was conducted by the study designs, AMD stages and clinical subtypes, and ethnic groups. The Asians were further divided into subgroups, including the East Asians (Japan, China, Taiwan, and Korea), Southeast Asians (Singapore), West Asians (Israel, Iran, and Turkey), and South Asians (Nepal, and India). As to the subgroup analysis concerning different AMD stages, we applied the widely accepted clinical classification system as described by the Age-Related Eye Disease Study Research Group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Davis1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Ferris1">[25]</xref>. Briefly, early AMD was defined by the appearance of drusen and pigmentary alterations within 2 disc diameters of the fovea. Late AMD was featured by the presence of large drusen (soft and/or indistinct) together with pigmentary abnormalities, or can be generally recognized as nAMD and/or GA. Moreover, sensitivity analysis was conducted to affirm the estimated association by removing studies with poor quality or prone to introducing biases. Publication bias and small-study effects were assessed with funnel plots <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Begg1">[26]</xref> and Egger's test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Egger1">[27]</xref>. All analyses were conducted with Review Manager version 5.2 (Cochrane Collaboration, Oxford, UK; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ims.cochrane.org/revman" xlink:type="simple">http://ims.cochrane.org/revman</ext-link>) and STATA software (version 12.0; StataCorp LP, College Station, TX). Alpha was set to 0.05 for two-sided test.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Literature</title>
<p>A total of 3205 records were yielded from digital search and manual screen of reference list. Thirty-eight articles, published from 1986 to 2013, were included for the systematic review. Workflow of literature screen and review was shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108196-g001"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>. In addition, to provide a better understanding in diabetes as an independent risk factor for AMD, fourteen studies that presented diabetes as a covariate and provided ORs/RRs/HRs from baseline data without any adjustment were excluded, involving 12 cross-sectional <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Karesvuo1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-FraserBell1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Clemons1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Wong1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Jeganathan1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Baker1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Pokharel1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Hu1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Weiner1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Cheung2">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Yang1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-LaTorre1">[36]</xref> and 2 case-control studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Mattes1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Vine1">[38]</xref>. The 24 articles included 1858350 participants in 27 independent study populations, comprising 7 cohort studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Hahn1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Shalev1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Leske1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Tomany1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Yasuda1">[43]</xref>, 9 cross-sectional studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Topouzis1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Vaicaitiene1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Xu1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Delcourt1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Duan1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Klein1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Choi1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-GemmyCheung1">[48]</xref>, and 11 case-control studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-McGwin1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Nitsch1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-LaTorre1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Blumenkranz1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Ross1">[50]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Monnier1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Alexander1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Kim1">[53]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Lin1">[54]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Cackett1">[55]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Sogut1">[56]</xref>. Among the 27 study populations, 10 were in Asia, 9 in North America (United States), 6 in Europe, 1 in Oceania (Australia), and 1 in South America (Barbados). Most studies used predefined criteria for AMD diagnosis and adopted standard grading system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Klein2">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Bird1">[58]</xref>. Samples sizes varied widely, from less than 50 to over 1.5 million (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108196-t001"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>). Only two of the earliest studies, in 1986 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Blumenkranz1">[49]</xref> and 1998 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Ross1">[50]</xref>, had sample sizes less than 100. Risk of bias assessments for cohort, cross-sectional, and case-control studies has been performed (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0108196.s001">Tables S1</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0108196.s003">S3</xref></bold>). Tan et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Tan1">[59]</xref> and Tomany et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Tomany1">[42]</xref> both involved the Blue Mountain Eye Study cohort, we included latter one in the analysis. The ORs/RRs/HRs with 95% CI and the corresponding adjusted variables for each study were listed in overall AMD, early AMD or late AMD (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108196-t002"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0108196-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Flow chart depicting the screening process for inclusion in the meta-analysis.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0108196-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Characteristics of Included Cohorts.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108196-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First Author (Publication Year)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Period</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample Size</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Diagnostic Criteria</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cohort Studies (Prospective &amp; Retrospective)</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomany et al (2004)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDES</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993–1995</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3562</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I &amp; W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGL &amp; S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMES</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997–1999</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2330</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I &amp; W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGL &amp; S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997–1999</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherlands</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3631</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I &amp; W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGL &amp; S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leske et al (2006)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BISED II</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1987–1992</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barbados</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2793</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M &amp; S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yasuda et al (2009)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hisayama Study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1401</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I &amp; W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M &amp; PGL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shalev et al (2011)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MHS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998–2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Israel</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108973</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hahn et al (2013)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1995–2005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16510</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cross-sectional Studies</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delcourt et al (2001)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POLA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1995–1997</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2584</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I &amp; W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interview</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaičaitienė et al (2003)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1995–1997</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lithuania</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">438</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duan et al (2007)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2000–2001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1519086</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Klein et al (2007)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHISE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993–2002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4288</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Topouzis et al (2009)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUREYE study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2000–2003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">¶</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4722</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xu et al (2009)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beijing Eye Study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2960</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGL &amp; S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Choi et al (2011)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006–2008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M &amp; PGL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cheung et al (2013)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIES</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007–2009</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Singapore</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southeast Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3337</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGL &amp; S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIEMS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006–2008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3422</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGL &amp; S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Case-control Studies</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blumenkranz et al (1986)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ross et al (1998)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detailed in paper.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">McGwin et al (2003)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997–2001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6050</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moeini et al (2005)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alexander et al (2007)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2001–2003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62179</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kim et al (2008)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998–2003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Questionnaire</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lin et al (2008)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002–2006</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taiwan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitsch et al (2008)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPRD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1987–2002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Readcodes &amp; OXMIS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cackett et al (2011)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007–2008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Singapore</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southeast Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1617</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Questionnaire</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sogut et al (2013)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Torre et al (2013)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">246</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Questionnaire</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>¶</label><p> Europe: Estonia, France, Greece, Italy, Norway, Spain, UK;</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Abbreviation: BDES: Beaver Dam Eye Study; BMES: Blue Mountains Eye Study; RS: Rotterdam Study; BISED II: Barbados Incidence Study of Eye Diseases; MHS: Maccabi Healthcare Services; NA: not available; POLA: Pathologies Oculaires Liées àl'Age Study; WHISE: Women's Health Initiative Sight Examination; SIES: Singapore Indian Eye Study; CIEMS: Central India Eye and Medical Study; GPRD: General Practice Research Database; AMD: Age Related Macular Degeneration; &amp;: represents a combination of two diagnostic methods; I: International Classification and Grading System for AMD; W: Wisconsin Age-Related Maculopathy Grading System; ICD9: International Classification of Diseases with Clinical Modifications, Ninth Revision; PGL: Plasma Glucose Level; S: Self-reported diabetic history or medications; M: Medical recorded diabetic history or medications; ADA: American Diabetes Association diagnostic criteria.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0108196-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Detailed Analytical Information for Included Cohorts.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108196-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First Author(Publication Year)</td>
<td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1">OR/RR/HR<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">Δ</xref> [95% CI]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted Variables</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Early AMD</italic></td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><italic>Late AMD</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AMD</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nAMD</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GA</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Total</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cohort Studies (Prospective &amp; Retrospective)</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomany (2004)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 [0.24, 1.86]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 [0.84, 4.99]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 [0.62, 2.36]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 [0.62, 2.36]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>BDES</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 [0.10, 6.31]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>BMES</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.31 [2.34, 29.50]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RS</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 [0.10, 6.19]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leske (2006)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 [0.60, 1.30]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70 [1.00, 7.30]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 [0.71, 1.47]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yasuda (2009)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 [0.37, 1.31]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 [0.16, 2.95]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 [0.39, 1.24]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple Factors<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">#</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shalev (2011)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 [1.01, 1.38]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutually adjusted</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hahn (2013)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 [0.97, 1.27]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 [0.97, 1.09]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 [0.99, 1.10]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 [0.99, 1.10]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple Factors<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cross-sectional Studies</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delcourt (2001)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 [0.45, 3.29]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 [0.45, 3.29]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaičaitienė (2003)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.61 [2.45, 8.67]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duan (2007)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 [1.44, 1.51]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 [1.44, 1.51]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 [1.16, 1.19]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex, Race</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Klein (2007)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 [0.67, 1.12]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.49 [1.17, 5.31]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28 [0.63, 8.28]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43 [1.26, 4.70]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 [0.74, 1.20]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Topouzis (2009)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 [0.83, 1.17]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 [1.10, 2.98]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 [0.28, 4.04]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 [0.90, 2.12]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 [0.85, 1.19]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple Factors<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">‡</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xu (2009)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 [0.69, 2.43]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 [0.14, 9.40]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 [0.70, 2.34]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Choi (2011)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 [1.07, 3.28]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 [1.07, 3.28]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple Factors<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">†</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cheung (2013)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SIES</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 [0.68, 1.28]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 [0.68, 1.28]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CIEMS</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 [0.47, 2.77]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 [0.47, 2.77]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Case-control Studies</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blumenkranz (1986)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 [0.06, 4.71]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 [0.06, 4.71]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use siblings</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ross (1998)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 [0.21, 5.59]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">McGwin Jr (2003)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78 [1.43, 2.20]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moeini (2005)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 [0.52, 3.21]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex, Risk factors</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alexander (2007)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 [1.11, 1.21]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 [1.11, 1.21]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 [1.11, 1.21]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex, Race, Database length</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kim (2008)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 [0.27, 1.39]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 [0.27, 1.39]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 [0.27, 1.39]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use siblings</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lin (2008)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 [0.44, 3.26]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 [0.36, 2.63]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 [0.45, 2.57]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 [0.45, 2.57]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitsch (2008)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 [1.29, 1.43]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex, Practice, Consultation Rate</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cackett (2011)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 [0.50, 1.70]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 [0.50, 1.70]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 [0.50, 1.70]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sogut (2013)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68 [0.76, 3.69]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68 [0.76, 3.69]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Torre (2013)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 [0.08, 8.07]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, Sex, Smoking</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label>Δ</label><p>OR is for cross-sectional and case-control studies, RR is for prospective cohort studies, HR is for retrospective cohort studies;</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>#</label><p>Age, Sex, Smoking habit, White blood cells;</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>*Age, Sex, Race, History of hypertension, Atherosclerosis, Stroke, Coronary heart disease, Hyperlipidemia, Charlson index;</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>‡</label><p>Age, Sex, Smoking, Education, BMI, Alcohol consumption, Cardiovascular disease, Aspirin use, Systolic blood pressure, Alpha-tocopherol ratio, Vitamin C, Lutein;</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label>†</label><p>Age, Sex, Current smoking, Obesity, Hypertension.</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label/><p>Abbreviations: OR: odds ratio; RR: risk ratio; HR: hazard ratio; CI: confidence interval; AMD: Age-related macular degeneration; nAMD: neovascular AMD; GA: geographic atrophy; WBC: white blood cell.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Meta-Analysis</title>
<p>The effects of diabetes on the risk of AMD in all these studies were found to be essentially consistent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108196-g002"><bold>Figure 2</bold></xref><bold> and </bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108196-t003"><bold>Table 3</bold></xref>). According to the meta-analysis of 7 cohort studies, diabetes was associated with AMD (OR, 1.05; 95% CI, 1.00–1.11). Subgroup analysis based on AMD stages revealed diabetes as a marginal risk factor for late AMD (OR, 1.05; 95% CI, 0.99–1.10), but not for its early form (OR, 0.83; 95% CI, 0.60–1.15). Subgroup analysis by AMD subtypes showed that the pooled OR of diabetes for risk of nAMD was 1.10 (95% CI, 0.96–1.26), for risk of GA was 1.63 (95% CI, 0.51–5.21). In the 9 cross-sectional study populations, diabetes was found increasing AMD risk (OR, 1.21; 95% CI, 1.00–1.45). Subgroup analysis confirmed this effect for late AMD (OR, 1.48; 95% CI, 1.44–1.51), and nAMD (OR, 1.48; 95% CI, 1.44–1.51), but not for early AMD (OR, 0.99; 95% CI, 0.88–1.12) or GA (OR, 1.58; 95% CI, 0.63–3.99). The results kept consistent in the analysis of 11 case-control studies. The pooled OR of diabetes for AMD was 1.29 (95% CI, 1.13–1.49). The pooled OR was 1.16 (95% CI, 1.11–1.21) for late AMD, and 1.15 (95% CI, 1.11–1.21) for nAMD. To reduce the methodological heterogeneity and the potential effect led by other risk factors, we also conducted meta-analysis solely using multivariate-adjusted outcomes. Only 3 cohort studies and 2 cross-sectional were included, and the results varied from the overall data, which was probably due to the limited number of included studies. However, in both groups, diabetes was found as a marginal risk factor for nAMD in cross-sectional studies (OR, 1.04; 95% CI, 0.99–1.10) and a solid risk factor for late AMD in cohort studies (OR, 1.81; 95% CI, 1.10–2.98). No association between diabetes and early AMD or GA was found in both groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108196-t004"><bold>Table 4</bold></xref>). Subgroup analyses by ethnic group were further performed. The associations of diabetes and overall and early AMD were similar between the Asian and Caucasian populations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108196-t005"><bold>Table 5</bold></xref>), while associations between diabetes and all subtypes of late AMD were suggested only for the Caucasian group, but not for the overall Asian population or any of its subgroups. No indication of any obvious asymmetry was observed according to the shapes of Begg's funnel plots and Egger's test for all groups as detailed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108196-t003"><bold>Tables 3</bold></xref><bold>–</bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108196-t005"><bold>5</bold></xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0108196-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Effects of diabetes on AMD risks.</title>
<p>Graphs showing the effects of diabetes on the risk of Age-related Macular Degenerations in longitudinal cohort studies (A), cross-sectional studies (B), and case-control studies (C). IV: inverse variance, CI: confidence interval.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0108196-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Analysis of Diabetes as a Risk Factor for AMD in Different AMD Types.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108196-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Design</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of Cohorts</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample Size</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Overall Effect</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterogeneity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Egger</italic>'<italic>s Test</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>OR/RR</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">*</xref> <italic>[95% CI]</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Z score</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p value</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I<sup>2</sup> (%)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Q (p)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cohort Studies</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139200</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 [1.00, 1.11]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.361</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.961</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4194</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 [0.60, 1.15]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.529</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Late AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30227</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 [0.99, 1.10]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.260</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.504</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nAMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26033</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 [0.96, 1.26]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.160</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.335</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26033</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63 [0.51, 5.21]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.407</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.523</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cross-sectional Studies</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1543845</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 [1.00, 1.45]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.813</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21737</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 [0.88, 1.12]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.883</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.205</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Late AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1533640</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 [1.44, 1.51]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.642</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.774</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nAMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1528096</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 [1.44, 1.51]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.287</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.154</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 [0.63, 3.99]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.333</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.419</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Case-control Studies</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175305</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 [1.13, 1.49]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.67</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.976</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Late AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64609</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 [1.11, 1.21]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.65</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.520</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.334</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nAMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62179</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 [1.11, 1.21]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.416</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 [0.36, 2.63]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.954</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt109"><label/><p>* OR is for cross-sectional and case-control studies, RR is for cohort studies.</p></fn><fn id="nt110"><label>†</label><p> Studies using random effect model.</p></fn><fn id="nt111"><label/><p>Abbreviations: OR: odds ratio; RR: risk ratio; CI: confidence interval; AMD: age related macular degeneration; nAMD: neovascular AMD; GA: geographic atrophy; NA: not available.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0108196-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>Analysis of Diabetes as a Risk Factor for AMD in Different AMD Types with Multivariate-adjusted ORs/RRs/HRs.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108196-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Design</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of Cohorts</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample Size</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Overall Effect</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterogeneity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egger's Test</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>OR/RR</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt112">*</xref> <italic>[95% CI]</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Z score</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p value</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I<sup>2</sup> (%)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Q (p)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cohort Studies</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126884</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 [0.93, 1.22]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt113">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.339</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.904</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1401</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 [0.37, 1.31]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Late AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17911</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 [0.99, 1.10]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.118</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.574</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nAMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16510</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 [0.97, 1.27]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.129</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16510</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 [0.97, 1.09]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.349</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cross-sectional Studies</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7730</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 [0.71, 2.35]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt113">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.397</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7730</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 [0.69, 2.39]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt113">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.640</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Late AMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4722</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 [0.90, 2.12]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nAMD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4722</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 [1.10, 2.98]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4722</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 [0.28, 4.04]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.928</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt112"><label/><p>* OR is for cross-sectional and case-control studies, RR is for cohort studies.</p></fn><fn id="nt113"><label>†</label><p> Studies using random effect model.</p></fn><fn id="nt114"><label/><p>Abbreviations: OR: odds ratio; RR: risk ratio; CI: confidence interval; AMD: age related macular degeneration; nAMD: neovascular AMD; GA: geographic atrophy; NA: not available.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0108196-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption>
<title>Analysis of Diabetes as a Risk Factor for AMD in Different Ethnic Groups.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108196-t005-5" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnic Group</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of cohorts</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample Size</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Overall Effect</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterogeneity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Egger</italic>'<italic>s Test</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>OR/RR</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt115">*</xref> <italic>[95% CI]</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Z score</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p value</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I<sup>2</sup> (%)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Q (p)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>AMD</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1730149</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 [1.12, 1.29]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt116">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.733</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125408</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 [1.01, 1.29]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.423</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.978</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> East Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7649</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 [0.86, 1.61]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.301</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.115</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> West Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109383</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 [1.03, 1.39]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.688</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.385</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> Southeast Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4954</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 [0.70, 1.23]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.616</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.973</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> South Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3422</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 [0.47, 2.77]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.771</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1858350</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 [1.11, 1.26]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt116">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.909</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Early AMD</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 [0.82, 1.09]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.442</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.422</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14128</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 [0.85, 1.34]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.588</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.626</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> East Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7369</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 [0.68, 2.14]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt116">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.517</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.385</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> Southeast Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3337</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 [0.68, 1.28]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.667</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> South Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3422</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 [0.47, 2.77]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.771</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25931</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 [0.86, 1.09]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.595</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.303</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.478</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Late AMD</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1619145</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 [1.05, 1.49]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt116">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.479</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6538</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 [0.73, 1.63]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.663</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.770</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.882</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> East Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4641</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 [0.48, 1.97]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.941</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.865</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.800</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> Southeast Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1617</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 [0.50, 1.70]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.795</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> West Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68 [0.76, 3.69]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.200</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1628476</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 [1.07, 1.46]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt116">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.454</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Neovascular AMD</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1616512</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 [1.09, 1.54]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt116">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.524</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1897</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 [0.59, 1.67]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.970</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.662</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> East Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 [0.44, 3.26]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.724</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> Southeast Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1617</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 [0.50, 1.70]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.795</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1618409</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 [1.07, 1.50]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt116">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.81</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.429</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Geographic Atrophy</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24408</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 [1.07, 3.64]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.172</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.178</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 [0.36, 2.63]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.954</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>East Asian</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 [0.36, 2.63]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.954</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24688</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62 [0.96, 2.74]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.166</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.687</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt115"><label/><p>* OR is for cross-sectional and case-control studies, RR is for prospective cohort studies.</p></fn><fn id="nt116"><label>†</label><p> Studies using random effect model.</p></fn><fn id="nt117"><label/><p>Abbreviations: OR: odds ratio; RR: relative risk; CI: confidence interval; AMD: age related macular degeneration.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Risk of Bias Assessment and Sensitivity Analysis</title>
<p>In our assessment, we found most studies have a robust design and reported in a clear manner, thus have lower risks in introducing bias (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0108196.s001">Tables S1</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0108196.s003">S3</xref></bold>). However, we did identify one cross-sectional study which had relative higher risk to introduce biases when used to evaluate risk-modifying effect of diabetes for AMD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Vaicaitiene1">[14]</xref> (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0108196.s002">Tables S2</xref></bold>), thus were subjected to sensitivity analysis. In sensitivity analysis, we sequentially omitted one study at a time and removed studies of higher risk of introducing bias to affirm the associations. Sensitivity analyses revealed that the study conducted by Alexander et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Alexander1">[52]</xref> contributed to the heterogeneity in the subgroup analysis of case-control studies, but did not alter the results in each subgroup. When removing the studies conducted by Shalev et al and Hahn et al in the subgroup analysis of cohort studies, respectively, although the <italic>p</italic> values for diabetes and AMD became insignificant, the direction of ORs was kept and associations of marginal significance were revealed (removing study by Shalev et al: OR, 1.04; 95% CI, 0.99–1.10; Hahn et al: OR, 1.12; 95% CI, 0.98–1.29). Similar findings were revealed by subgroup analyses involving cross-sectional and case-control studies. In the analysis of cross-sectional studies, the removal of studies by Vaičaitienė et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Vaicaitiene1">[14]</xref>, Duan et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Duan1">[45]</xref>, Xu et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Xu1">[16]</xref>, and Choi et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Choi1">[47]</xref> would also lead to borderline results (removing study by Vaičaitienė et al: OR, 1.10; 95% CI, 0.98–1.23; Duan et al: OR, 1.30; 95% CI, 0.97–1.73; Xu et al: OR, 1.21; 95% CI, 0.99–1.47; Choi et al: OR, 1.16; 95% CI, 0.96–1.41). In addition, in the subgroup analysis of case-control studies, an association of borderline significance between diabetes and AMD (OR, 1.23; 95% CI, 0.97–1.56) was presented if the study by Nitsch et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Nitsch1">[13]</xref> was excluded.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Diabetes is a major concern in ophthalmic care. Whether it contributes to the prevalence of AMD has been an unsolved dilemma targeted by a large number of studies. However, obvious inconsistencies between studies, including a few large cohorts, suggest the necessity to conduct an exhaustive review and quantitative analysis on all the evidences to determine its effect. In the present systemic review and meta-analysis, we reviewed 3205 published reports and completed analysis on 1858350 participants of 27 study populations from 24 original studies. We found that diabetes is a risk factor for AMD, especially for nAMD. To our knowledge, this is the first meta-analysis addressing the topic for AMD and all its subtypes, and by using data from a comprehensive collection of prospective and retrospective cohort, cross-sectional, and case-control studies.</p>
<p>Clinically, AMD can be classified based on drusen features and retinal pigment epithelial abnormalities, we found most included studies follow the Wisconsin Age-related Maculopathy Grading Scheme, according to 4 levels: level 1 (no AMD), level 2 and 3 (early AMD), and level 4 (late AMD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Klein2">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-XX2">[60]</xref>. The contribution of diabetes to early AMD is inconsistent in studies. Diabetic patients have increased occurrence of early AMD in a cross-sectional study of a Korean cohort of 3008 adults <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Choi1">[47]</xref>. No similar association has been observed in other studies. An inverse relationship is observed in the Age-Related Eye Disease Study (AREDS) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Clemons1">[17]</xref>. In the Beaver Dam Eye Study (BDES), diabetes was found to be a protective factor for incident reticular drusen based on a 15-year cumulative incidence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Klein3">[61]</xref>. In this meta-analysis, no clear association was detected between diabetes and early AMD based on 16 relevant cohorts.</p>
<p>The associations of diabetes with late AMD are also inconsistent among previous reports. According to analysis from 5 cross-sectional and 6 case-control studies, diabetes is significantly correlated with late AMD, especially with nAMD, but not for GA. Temporal relationships revealed by 7 cohort studies further supports diabetes as a potential risk factor for late AMD, only for nAMD but not for GA. However, an association between diabetes and GA was identified in Caucasians. Also, the Blue Mountains Eye Study (BMES) has revealed diabetes as a predictor of incident GA, but not incident nAMD. This is consistent with a cross-sectional baseline report <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Mitchell2">[62]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Smith1">[63]</xref>, to 5-year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Tomany1">[42]</xref> and 10-year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Tan1">[59]</xref> incident reports, providing evidence for a diabetes and GA association.</p>
<p>In the current meta-analysis, we found no obvious ethnic divergence regarding the association between the diabetes and risk of overall AMD and its early form. The results obtained from different Asian groups are consistent in all types of AMD. However, the association between diabetes and late AMD in the Caucasian population differs from that in the Asian population, which is probably due to the large variation of genetic factors among different ethnic groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Klein4">[64]</xref>, and the differences in dietary habits and lifestyles.</p>
<p>The biological interplay between diabetes and AMD is complicated and has not been fully elucidated. First, diabetic conditions may lead to the accumulation of the highly stable advanced glycation end products (AGEs) in multiple tissues, including the retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) cell layers and photoreceptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Monnier1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Stitt1">[65]</xref>. These AGEs would first contribute to the modification of molecules, leading to the activation of NFκB, NFκB nuclear translocation, and up-regulation in the expression of the receptor for AGEs (RAGE) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Hammes1">[66]</xref>. Further, the up-regulated RAGE, which usually localized to the neuroglia in the inner retina <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Soulis1">[67]</xref>, would integrate with AGE, thus leading to high levels of the nondegradable aggregates AGE-RAGE ligands in retina <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Stitt1">[65]</xref>. Therefore, accumulated AGEs would reduce the dosage dependent RAGE-mediated activation of RPE/photoreceptor cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Howes1">[68]</xref>. AGEs and RAGE were found in the RPE or both RPE and photoreceptors in the maculas of human donor retina from patients with AMD, but not in normal eyes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Hammes1">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Howes1">[68]</xref>, indicating that AGE deposition and RAGE up-regulation in diabetic conditions are implicated in the pathogenesis of AMD.</p>
<p>Second, hyperglycemia and dyslipidemia in diabetic patients will disturb homeostasis of the retina by inducing inflammatory responses in tissue cells, including oxidative stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Zhang1">[69]</xref>. Significantly elevated oxidative stress markers and total oxidative stress (TOS), as well as decreased total anti-oxidant capacity (TAC), are found in the serum of AMD patients when compared with age-matched controls free of AMD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Totan1">[70]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Venza1">[71]</xref>. Meanwhile, anti-oxidants and omega-3 fatty acids have been shown to help with the preservation of RPE health and prevent retinal degeneration in animal models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Cao1">[72]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Tuo1">[73]</xref>. Therefore, oxidative stress is recognized as one of the principle pathogenic elements in AMD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Ardeljan1">[74]</xref>. Oxidative stress may further activate NF-κB regulated inflammatory genes and lead to inflammation, which would in turn generate reactive oxygen species and aggregate oxidative stress. Inflammation disrupts the NF-κB, JUN N-terminal kinase (JNK), and the NADPH oxidase pathways, consequently dysregulations of many inflammatory cytokines and chemokines, involving the tumor necrosis factor (TNF), interleukin-6 (IL-6), IL-1β, C-reactive protein (CRP), CC-chemokine ligand 2 (CCL2), and adipokines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Donath1">[75]</xref>. These inflammatory activations would lead to the dysfunction and even death of the RPE/photoreceptor cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Zhang1">[69]</xref>. Thus, oxidative stress and inflammations in the retina are pre-requites for development of AMD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Ardeljan1">[74]</xref>.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, diabetic microangiopathy shares common pathogenic pathways with AMD. Hyperglycemia and dyslipidemia in diabetic patients will lead to multiple microvascular complications, including diabetic retinopathy (DR). AMD and DR share some common features in pathogenesis and treatment. In a longitudinal study over 10 years, individuals with DR, including both the nonproliferative and proliferative form, were at higher risk for nAMD when compared to diabetic patients without DR or normal controls <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Hahn1">[39]</xref>. Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) seems to play an important role in both DR and AMD, and anti-VEGF treatment are useful for both <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Ho1">[76]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Rofagha1">[77]</xref>. Apolipoproteins are also involved. Lower apoAI and higher apoB and apoB/AI levels, biomarkers for diabetic retinopathy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Sasongko1">[78]</xref>, are involved in the pathogenesis of cardiovascular diseases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-DiAngelantonio1">[79]</xref>, which is a risk factor for AMD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Chakravarthy1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Tan1">[59]</xref>. Meanwhile, mitochondrial dysfunctions have been reported to contribute to metabolic disorders as well as AMD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Ardeljan1">[74]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Turner1">[80]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Sorriento1">[81]</xref>. All these suggested that hyperglycemia probably affects the function and structure of the retinal pigment epithelium, Bruch membrane, and the choroidal circulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Choi1">[47]</xref>, thus increase the risk of AMD. Our study indicates a potential relationship between diabetes and late AMD, but further evidences from more epidemiological and biological investigations are required.</p>
<p>To enhance the reliability of our results, we adopted quality assessment tools recommended by the AHRQ and NOS for observational studies. Only studies discussing diabetes as the main exposure or providing adjusted ORs/HRs/RRs were included in the present meta-analysis for a more precise association of diabetes as a relatively independent risk factor for AMD. In addition, for studies reporting duplicated cohorts, only those with the latest follow-up information or provides better adjusted results were included. Subgroup analysis was performed to affirm the association and to explorer the sources of the heterogeneity. Meanwhile, our study entailed some limitations. Data obtained from prospective cohort studies would be more convincing. But the number of prospective cohort studies was quite limited. Retrospective cohort, cross-sectional, and case-control studies were also included in the present study, which may partly help to reflect the association between diabetes and AMD. However, these studies have limitation. Retrospective cohort studies use healthcare databases and have inherent methodological limitations, which may obscure the association between diabetes and AMD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Wu1">[82]</xref>. Cross-sectional does not establish temporality and case-control studies may introduce selection bias and established temporality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108196-Wu1">[82]</xref>. Early AMD can be further classified into more specific categories. Herein, we could only judge the relationship between diabetes and early AMD. Other than diabetic status, plenty of other risk factors have been suggested for AMD. Although we have tried to narrow down the influence of other risk factors by selecting studies with adjusted data, some included studies only reported data adjusted for age and sex, and the number of studies providing multivariate-adjusted data was quite limited. With the limited information provided by each individual study, therefore, this present meta-analysis only deals with the relationship between diabetic disease status and risk of AMD, but not the specific type of diabetes, the disease course, and blood glucose levels.</p>
<p>In conclusion, results of this meta-analysis indicate diabetes as a potential risk factor for AMD, especially for its late form. No clear association between diabetes and early AMD is identified. More longitudinal studies are needed to ascertain the association between diabetes and AMD. And biological studies involving the inflammatory pathways might help understand the molecular basis behind this association.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0108196.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Quality Assessment for Included Cohort Studies.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0108196.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Quality Assessment for Cross-Sectional Studies.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0108196.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Quality Assessment for Case-Control Studies.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0108196.s004" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Checklist S1</label><caption>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0108196.s005" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108196.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Appendix S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Search Terms Used in the Present Study in Different Databases.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Bressler1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bressler</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Age-related macular degeneration is the leading cause of blindness</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <volume>291</volume>: <fpage>1900</fpage>–<lpage>1901</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Jager1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mieler</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>358</volume>: <fpage>2606</fpage>–<lpage>2617</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Lim1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seddon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holz</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>379</volume>: <fpage>1728</fpage>–<lpage>1738</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Cheung1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Folsom</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couper</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Age-related macular degeneration and cancer mortality in the atherosclerosis risk in communities study</article-title>. <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source> <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>1241</fpage>–<lpage>1247</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Mitchell1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Five-year incidence of age-related maculopathy lesions: the Blue Mountains Eye Study</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>1092</fpage>–<lpage>1097</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Kawasaki1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The prevalence of age-related macular degeneration in Asians: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>921</fpage>–<lpage>927</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Friedman1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bressler</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rahmani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tielsch</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Racial differences in the prevalence of age-related macular degeneration: the Baltimore Eye Survey</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>1049</fpage>–<lpage>1055</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Chakravarthy1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakravarthy</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piault</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Clinical risk factors for age-related macular degeneration: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMC Ophthalmol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Topouzis1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Topouzis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anastasopoulos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Augood</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bentham</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chakravarthy</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Association of diabetes with age-related macular degeneration in the EUREYE study</article-title>. <source>Br J Ophthalmol</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1037</fpage>–<lpage>1041</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Borger1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borger</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hulsman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfs</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Kuip</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Is there a direct association between age-related eye diseases and mortality? The Rotterdam Study</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>1292</fpage>–<lpage>1296</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Karesvuo1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karesvuo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gursoy</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pussinen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suominen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huumonen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Alveolar bone loss associated with age-related macular degeneration in males</article-title>. <source>J Periodontol</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-McGwin1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGwin</surname><given-names>G</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Owsley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Curcio</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The association between statin use and age related maculopathy</article-title>. <source>Br J Ophthalmol</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>1121</fpage>–<lpage>1125</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Nitsch1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nitsch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smeeth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Age-related macular degeneration and complement activation-related diseases: a population-based case-control study</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>1904</fpage>–<lpage>1910</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Vaicaitiene1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaicaitiene</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luksiene</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paunksnis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cerniauskiene</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Domarkiene</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Age-related maculopathy and consumption of fresh vegetables and fruits in urban elderly</article-title>. <source>Medicina (Kaunas)</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1231</fpage>–<lpage>1236</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-FraserBell1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser-Bell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azen</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cardiovascular risk factors and age-related macular degeneration: the Los Angeles Latino Eye Study</article-title>. <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Xu1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Ocular and systemic factors associated with diabetes mellitus in the adult population in rural and urban China. The Beijing Eye Study</article-title>. <source>Eye (Lond)</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>682</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Clemons1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemons</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McBee</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Cognitive impairment in the Age-Related Eye Disease Study: AREDS report no. 16</article-title>. <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>543</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-XX1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">(2011) Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions. In: Julian PT Higgins, Green S, editors: The Cochrane Collaboration.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Stroup1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stroup</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olkin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis of observational studies in epidemiology: a proposal for reporting. Meta-analysis Of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (MOOSE) group</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>2008</fpage>–<lpage>2012</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Yuan1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The age-related maculopathy susceptibility 2 polymorphism and polypoidal choroidal vasculopathy in Asian populations: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>2051</fpage>–<lpage>2057</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Rostom1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rostom A, Dubé C, Cranney A, Saloojee N, Sy R, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2004) Evidence Reports/Technology Assessments, No. 104.Celiac Disease: Rockville (MD): Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (US). </mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-DerSimonian1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DerSimonian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Control Clin Trials</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Kuritz1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuritz</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>A general overview of Mantel-Haenszel methods: applications and recent developments</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Public Health</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Davis1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gangnon</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The Age-Related Eye Disease Study severity scale for age-related macular degeneration: AREDS Report No. 17</article-title>. <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>1484</fpage>–<lpage>1498</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Ferris1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clemons</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A simplified severity scale for age-related macular degeneration: AREDS Report No. 18</article-title>. <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>1570</fpage>–<lpage>1574</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Begg1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>1101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Egger1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Wong1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couper</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Age-related macular degeneration and risk for stroke</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>98</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Jeganathan1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Jeganathan VS, Kawasaki R, Wang JJ, Aung T, Mitchell P, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2008) Retinal vascular caliber and age-related macular degeneration: the Singapore Malay Eye Study. Am J Ophthalmol <volume>146</volume>: : 954–959 e951.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Baker1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuller</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Early age-related macular degeneration, cognitive function, and dementia: the Cardiovascular Health Study</article-title>. <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source> <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>673</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Pokharel1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pokharel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pradhananga</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A pattern of age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>JNMA J Nepal Med Assoc</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Hu1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Neovascular age-related macular degeneration and the risk of stroke: a 5-year population-based follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>617</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Weiner1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tighiouart</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seddon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Kidney function, albuminuria and age-related macular degeneration in NHANES III</article-title>. <source>Nephrol Dial Transplant</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>3159</fpage>–<lpage>3165</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Cheung2"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Prevalence of and risk factors for age-related macular degeneration in a multiethnic Asian cohort</article-title>. <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>480</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Yang1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Association of dilated retinal arteriolar caliber with early age-related macular degeneration: the Handan Eye Study</article-title>. <source>Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source> <volume>250</volume>: <fpage>741</fpage>–<lpage>749</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-LaTorre1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>La Torre</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pacella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saulle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giraldi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pacella</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The synergistic effect of exposure to alcohol, tobacco smoke and other risk factors for age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>446</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Mattes1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Renner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinbrugger</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shabrawi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Analysis of three pigment epithelium-derived factor gene polymorphisms in patients with exudative age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Mol Vis</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Vine1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vine</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stader</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Branham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Musch</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swaroop</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Biomarkers of cardiovascular disease as risk factors for age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>2076</fpage>–<lpage>2080</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Hahn1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Acquah</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cousins</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Ten-year incidence of age-related macular degeneration according to diabetic retinopathy classification among medicare beneficiaries</article-title>. <source>Retina</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>911</fpage>–<lpage>919</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Shalev1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shalev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sror</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldshtein</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kokia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chodick</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Statin use and the risk of age related macular degeneration in a large health organization in Israel</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmic Epidemiol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Leske1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leske</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hennis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nemesure</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Nine-year incidence of age-related macular degeneration in the Barbados Eye Studies</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Tomany1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomany</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Risk factors for incident age-related macular degeneration: pooled findings from 3 continents</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>111</volume>: <fpage>1280</fpage>–<lpage>1287</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Yasuda1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiyohara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arakawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yonemoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Nine-year incidence and risk factors for age-related macular degeneration in a defined Japanese population the Hisayama study</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>2135</fpage>–<lpage>2140</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Delcourt1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delcourt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colvez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lacroux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Associations of cardiovascular disease and its risk factors with age-related macular degeneration: the POLA study</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmic Epidemiol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Duan1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>IU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Age-related macular degeneration is associated with incident myocardial infarction among elderly Americans</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>732</fpage>–<lpage>737</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Klein1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seddon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Cardiovascular disease, its risk factors and treatment, and age-related macular degeneration: Women's Health Initiative Sight Exam ancillary study</article-title>. <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source> <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>483</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Choi1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lym</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Diabetes mellitus and early age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>196</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-GemmyCheung1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gemmy Cheung CM, Li X, Cheng CY, Zheng Y, Mitchell P, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2013) Prevalence and risk factors for age-related macular degeneration in Indians: a comparative study in Singapore and India. Am J Ophthalmol <volume>155</volume>: : 764–773, 773 e761–763.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Blumenkranz1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumenkranz</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robey</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kott-Blumenkranz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penneys</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Risk factors in age-related maculopathy complicated by choroidal neovascularization</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Ross1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barofsky</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baber</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palao</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Presumed macular choroidal watershed vascular filling, choroidal neovascularization, and systemic vascular disease in patients with age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source> <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Monnier1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monnier</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sell</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Genuth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Glycation products as markers and predictors of the progression of diabetic complications</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source> <volume>1043</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>–<lpage>581</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Alexander1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linde-Zwirble</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Werther</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Depperschmidt</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Annual rates of arterial thromboembolic events in medicare neovascular age-related macular degeneration patients</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>2174</fpage>–<lpage>2178</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Kim1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive analysis of CRP, CFH Y402H and environmental risk factors on risk of neovascular age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Mol Vis</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1487</fpage>–<lpage>1495</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Lin1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Pigment epithelium-derived factor gene Met72Thr polymorphism is associated with increased risk of wet age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>716</fpage>–<lpage>721</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Cackett1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cackett</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vithana</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Relationship of smoking and cardiovascular risk factors with polypoidal choroidal vasculopathy and age-related macular degeneration in Chinese persons</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>846</fpage>–<lpage>852</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Sogut1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sogut E, Ortak H, Aydogan L, Benli I (2013) Association of Paraoxonase 1 L55m and Q192r Single-Nucleotide Polymorphisms with Age-Related Macular Degeneration. Retina.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Klein2"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magli</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The Wisconsin age-related maculopathy grading system</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>1128</fpage>–<lpage>1134</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Bird1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bressler</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bressler</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chisholm</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coscas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>An international classification and grading system for age-related maculopathy and age-related macular degeneration. The International ARM Epidemiological Study Group</article-title>. <source>Surv Ophthalmol</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Tan1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Cardiovascular risk factors and the long-term incidence of age-related macular degeneration: the Blue Mountains Eye Study</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>1143</fpage>–<lpage>1150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-XX2"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><article-title>The Age-Related Eye Disease Study system for classifying age-related macular degeneration from stereoscopic color fundus photographs: the Age-Related Eye Disease Study Report Number 6</article-title>. <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>668</fpage>–<lpage>681</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Klein3"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meuer</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knudtson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iyengar</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The epidemiology of retinal reticular drusen</article-title>. <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Mitchell2"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Diabetes, fasting blood glucose and age-related maculopathy: The Blue Mountains Eye Study</article-title>. <source>Aust N Z J Ophthalmol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Smith1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leeder</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Plasma fibrinogen levels, other cardiovascular risk factors, and age-related maculopathy: the Blue Mountains Eye Study</article-title>. <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>587</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Klein4"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Klein R, Li X, Kuo JZ, Klein BE, Cotch MF, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2013) Associations of Candidate Genes to Age-Related Macular Degeneration Among Racial/Ethnic Groups in the Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis. Am J Ophthalmol.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Stitt1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>AGEs and diabetic retinopathy</article-title>. <source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>4867</fpage>–<lpage>4874</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Hammes1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammes</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoerauf</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schleicher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clausen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>N(epsilon)(carboxymethyl)lysin and the AGE receptor RAGE colocalize in age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1855</fpage>–<lpage>1859</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Soulis1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soulis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thallas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McWilliam</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Advanced glycation end products and their receptors co-localise in rat organs susceptible to diabetic microvascular injury</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>619</fpage>–<lpage>628</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Howes1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howes</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunaief</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frederick</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Receptor for advanced glycation end products and age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>3713</fpage>–<lpage>3720</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Zhang1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Shabrawey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Inflammation and diabetic retinal microvascular complications</article-title>. <source>J Cardiovasc Dis Res</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Totan1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Totan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yagci</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bardak</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ozyurt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kendir</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Oxidative macromolecular damage in age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Curr Eye Res</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>1089</fpage>–<lpage>1093</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Venza1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venza</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Visalli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cucinotta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Venza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Association between oxidative stress and macromolecular damage in elderly patients with age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Aging Clin Exp Res</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Cao1"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tuo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The effects of quercetin in cultured human RPE cells under oxidative stress and in Ccl2/Cx3cr1 double deficient mice</article-title>. <source>Exp Eye Res</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Tuo1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herzlich</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A high omega-3 fatty acid diet reduces retinal lesions in a murine model of macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol</source> <volume>175</volume>: <fpage>799</fpage>–<lpage>807</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Ardeljan1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ardeljan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Aging is not a disease: distinguishing age-related macular degeneration from aging</article-title>. <source>Prog Retin Eye Res</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Donath1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donath</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shoelson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Type 2 diabetes as an inflammatory disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>98</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Ho1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>IU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Anti-vascular endothelial growth factor pharmacotherapy for diabetic macular edema: a report by the American Academy of Ophthalmology</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>2179</fpage>–<lpage>2188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Rofagha1"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rofagha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhisitkul</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sadda</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Seven-Year Outcomes in Ranibizumab-Treated Patients in ANCHOR, MARINA, and HORIZON: A Multicenter Cohort Study (SEVEN-UP)</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source> <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>2292</fpage>–<lpage>2299</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Sasongko1"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasongko</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Serum apolipoproteins are associated with systemic and retinal microvascular function in people with diabetes</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1785</fpage>–<lpage>1792</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-DiAngelantonio1"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Angelantonio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarwar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaptoge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Major lipids, apolipoproteins, and risk of vascular disease</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <volume>302</volume>: <fpage>1993</fpage>–<lpage>2000</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Turner1"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Turner N, Robker RL (2014) Developmental programming of obesity and insulin resistance: does mitochondrial dysfunction in oocytes play a role? Mol Hum Reprod.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Sorriento1"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorriento</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pascale</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carillo</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Annunziata</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Targeting mitochondria as therapeutic strategy for metabolic disorders</article-title>. <source>ScientificWorldJournal</source> <volume>2014</volume>: <fpage>604685</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108196-Wu1"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uchino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sastry</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaumberg</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Age-related macular degeneration and the incidence of cardiovascular disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e89600</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>