<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-19353</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107013</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular types</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Stem cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancer stem cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancers and neoplasms</subject><subj-group><subject>Colorectal cancer</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Carcinogenesis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Prognostic Value of LGR5 in Colorectal Cancer: A Meta-Analysis</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">LGR5 and the Prognosis of Colorectal Cancer</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Qing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Wei-Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Yu-Qiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Hao-Zhe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Pengsheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Reproductive Medicine, the First Affiliated Hospital, Xi’an Jiaotong University Medical School, Xi’an, the People’s Republic of China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Gynaecology and Obstetrics, the Second Affiliated Hospital, Xi’an Jiaotong University Medical School, Xi’an, the People’s Republic of China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Nutrition, the First Affiliated Hospital, Xi’an Jiaotong University Medical School, Xi’an, the People’s Republic of China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Institute of Cardiovascular research, the First Hospital of Xi’an, Xi’an, the People’s Republic of China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerger</surname><given-names>Armin</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Medical University of Graz, Austria</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">zp_sheng@163.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: QC XZ PZ. Performed the experiments: QC XZ. Analyzed the data: WL YJ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: WL HC. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: QC. Screened the full text of selected studies to confirm eligibility, assess quality, and extract data: QC XZ.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<elocation-id>e107013</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Chen et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract><sec>
<title>Objective</title>
<p>Leucine-rich repeat-containing G protein-coupled receptor 5 (LGR5) has recently been reported to be a marker of cancer stem cells (CSCs) in colorectal cancer (CRC), and the prognostic value of LGR5 in CRC has been evaluated in several studies. However, the conclusions remain controversial. In this study, we aimed to evaluate the association between the expression of LGR5 and the outcome of CRC patients by performing a meta-analysis.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>We systematically searched for relevant studies published up to February 2014 using the PubMed, Web of Science, EMBASE and Wangfang databases. Only articles in which LGR5 expression was detected by immunohistochemistry were included. A meta-analysis was performed using STATA 12.0, and pooled hazard ratios (HRs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were used to estimate the strength of the association between LGR5 expression and the prognosis of CRC patients.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>A total of 7 studies comprising 1833 CRC patients met the inclusion criteria, including 6 studies comprising 1781 patients for overall survival (OS) and 3 studies comprising 528 patients for disease-free survival (DFS). Our results showed that high LGR5 expression was significantly associated with poor prognosis in terms of OS (HR: 1.87, 95% CI: 1.23–2.84; P = 0.003) and DFS (HR: 2.44, 95% CI: 1.49–3.98; P&lt;0.001). Further subgroup analysis revealed that many factors, including the study region, number of patients, follow-up duration and cutoff value, affected the significance of the association between LGR5 expression and a worse prognosis in patients with CRC. In addition, there was no evidence of publication bias, as suggested by Begg’s and Egger’s tests.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The present meta-analysis indicated that high LGR5 expression was associated with poor prognosis in patients with CRC and that LGR5 is an efficient prognostic factor in CRC.</p>
</sec></abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by a grant from the National Natural Science Fund for Distinguished Young Scientists (No. 30725043) and a grant from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 31201118). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the most common malignancy of the gastrointestinal tract worldwide. As one of the leading causes of cancer-related mortality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Jemal1">[1]</xref>, CRC accounts for more than 600,000 deaths every year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Ahlquist1">[2]</xref>. Despite advances in curative surgery and adjuvant therapy, as well as extensive CRC-focused research over the past 20 years, the 5-year survival rate is still poor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Jemal2">[3]</xref>. Relapse, metastasis and drug resistance are the main factors contributing to the high mortality and poor survival rate of this disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Kobayashi1">[4]</xref>. Increasing evidence suggests that a population of self-renewing tumor cells, known as cancer stem cells (CSCs), is responsible for tumor progression, relapse, metastases and therapeutic resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Reya1">[5]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Visvader1">[6]</xref>. Therefore, the identification of CSCs is crucial in the search for therapeutic targets and useful prognostic markers for CRC.</p>
<p>Becker et al. suggested that leucine-rich repeat-containing G protein-coupled receptor 5 (LGR5) may be a better marker of CSCs in CRC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Becker1">[7]</xref>. LGR5 was initially identified as an orphan G protein-coupled receptor (GPCR) that belongs to the subfamily of glycoprotein hormone receptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Hsu1">[8]</xref>, and it contains a large extracellular domain with 17 leucine-rich repeats and a seven-transmembrane domain. Recently, elevated LGR5 expression has been observed in several types of cancers, including hepatocellular carcinoma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Yamamoto1">[9]</xref>, CRC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Uchida1">[10]</xref>, ovarian cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Colon1">[11]</xref>, and basal cell carcinoma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Tanese1">[12]</xref>. In particular, many studies have suggested that LGR5 plays a key role in colorectal carcinogenesis and is associated with the poor outcome of CRC patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Liu1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-ValladaresAyerbes1">[18]</xref>. Although LGR5 allelic variation can affect LGR5 protein expression in colorectal cancers, the somatic LGR5 genotype seems to be relatively stable in primary tumors. Moreover, patients with variant alleles in SNPs of the LGR5 gene showed similar prognosis as patients with wild type LGR5, no significant difference was observed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Kleist1">[19]</xref>. Therefore, it was expected that LGR5 expression in CRC is an ideal prognostic marker that is correlated with low survival.</p>
<p>In fact, in recent years, many studies have shown that the expression of LGR5 is positively associated with poor prognosis in CRC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Liu1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Wu1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Saigusa2">[17]</xref>. However, no correlation was found between the expression of LGR5 and a poor clinical outcome in CRC in another previous study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Ziskin1">[20]</xref>. The prognostic value of LGR5 in CRC patients is controversial, and an insufficient sample size and several other factors likely resulted in the contrary results of different clinical studies. However, to date, there has been no meta-analysis of LGR5 expression and the prognosis of patients with CRC. To clarify the exact prognostic value of LGR5 in CRC, we performed a meta-analysis of eligible studies to investigate the relationship between LGR5 expression and the prognosis of CRC patients.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Literature search strategy</title>
<p>We searched the PubMed, Web of Science, EMBASE, and Wangfang databases for relevant articles published until March 31st, 2014. The search terms included “LGR5”, “colon cancer”, “rectal cancer”, “colorectal cancer” and “prognosis”. Bibliographies, review articles and pertinent studies were searched manually for additional pertinent studies.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Selection criteria</title>
<p>The inclusion criteria for the eligibility of a study were as follows: (1) patients with distinctive CRC diagnosis by pathology, (2) an assessment of the relationships between LGR5 expression and the prognosis of CRC patients, (3) sufficient information provided to estimate hazard ratio (HR) for overall survival (OS) or disease-free survival (DFS), and (4) publication with English or Chinese. The following studies were excluded from the analyses: (1) letters, reviews and conference abstracts, due to the limited data, and (2) articles about animal or cell lines. Regarding multiple publications from the same population, only the most recent or the most complete study was included in the analysis.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Data extraction and quality assessment</title>
<p>Two investigators (Qing Chen and Xin Zhang) reviewed each eligible article independently and extracted information from all the publications meeting the inclusion criteria. The following characteristics were collected from each study: the first author’s name, the year of publication, the country of origin, the number of patients, the age of the patients, the time of follow-up, the disease stage, the cutoff value, LGR5 expression levels and survival data. Disagreements were resolved by discussion until consensus was reached.</p>
<p>Quality assessment was conducted for each of the available studies using the Newcastle-Ottawa quality assessment scale <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Stang1">[21]</xref>. The score assessed eight items on methodology that were categorized into three dimensions, including selection, comparability and outcome. Interpretation of the scale is performed by awarding points, or “stars”, for high-quality elements. The stars are then added up and used to compare study quality in a quantitative manner. We specified a priori that a score of 7 or higher indicated high quality, a score of 5 or 6 indicated moderate quality, and a score of 4 or less indicated low quality.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Survival outcome data were synthesized using the HR and its 95% confidence interval (CI) to analyze the impact of LGR5 expression on the survival of CRC patients. Several of the included studies provided HRs and 95% CIs, which we pooled directly. Otherwise, we calculated the HR and its 95% CI from available data or a Kaplan-Meier survival curve using Engauge Digitizer version 4.1 (free software downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net" xlink:type="simple">http://sourceforge.net</ext-link>). By convention, an observed HR&gt;1 implied worse survival for a group with increased LGR5 expression. The impact of LGR5 expression on survival was considered to be statistically significant if there was no overlap of the 95% CI with 1. The heterogeneity among the studies was assessed by a chi-square-based Q statistic test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Handoll1">[22]</xref>, and the I<sup>2</sup> value was used to quantify the heterogeneity (I<sup>2</sup> = 0–50%, no or moderate heterogeneity; I<sup>2</sup>&gt;50%, significant heterogeneity) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Higgins1">[23]</xref>. If homogeneity was not significant (P&gt;0.10 for the Q test), the fixed-effect model was used; otherwise, the random-effect model was used. Publication bias was assessed using Egger’s test and Begg’s test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Egger1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Begg1">[25]</xref>. To adjust for multiple comparisons, we applied the stepdown Bonferroni method, which control for familywise error rate (FEW). In addition, sensitivity analysis was performed to examine the stability of the pooled results. The statistical analyses were conducted using STATA 12.0. All P values were two-sided, and P&lt;0.05 was considered to be statistically significant.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Study selection and characteristics</title>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107013-g001">Fig. 1</xref>, a total of 58 articles were initially retrieved from the above databases using the search strategy described above, and the details of search results in different databases were shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0107013.s001">Table S1</xref>. After reviewing the titles and abstracts of the articles, 41 articles that were irrelevant to our aim were excluded. The remaining 16 articles were then independently scrutinized by two of the authors. Of the articles, 10 articles were excluded: full text could not be found for 2 articles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Liu1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Pitule1">[26]</xref>, 1 article was about LGR5 expression in the peripheral blood <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-ValladaresAyerbes1">[18]</xref>, 4 articles did not provide OS or DFS data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Uchida1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Fan1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Chai1">[29]</xref>, 2 articles were about variants or polymorphisms of LGR5<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Chai1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Gerger1">[30]</xref>, and 1 article duplicated a cohort of patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Saigusa2">[17]</xref>. Eventually, 7 articles met the inclusion criteria and were included in the meta-analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Saigusa1">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Hsu2">[16]</xref>, .</p>
<fig id="pone-0107013-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Flow diagram showing the study selection procedure.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>All 7 eligible articles evaluated the correlation between LGR5 expression in CRC tissues and the prognosis of CRC. The major characteristics of the 7 studies are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0107013-t001">Table 1</xref>. These studies were published from 2010–2014 and conducted in 3 countries (the USA, Japan and China). The total number of enrolled patients was 1833, with individual samples ranging from 52–891 (median 180). The reported mean age of the patients ranged from 57–66.9 years across the eligible studies. The follow-up period ranged from 28.3–180 months. Several of the studies defined the cutoff value using complex scoring metrics combining the intensity and percentage of LGR5 expression, whereas other studies only used the percentage of LGR5 expression. Positive LGR5 expression was observed to range from 36–60%. There were 2 studies that utilized both OS and DFS to assess the prognostic value of LGR5 expression in CRC patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Hsu2">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Takahashi1">[32]</xref>. Additionally, 4 studies used only OS as an indicator <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Wu1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Ziskin1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-He1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Peng1">[33]</xref>, and 1 study used only DFS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Saigusa2">[17]</xref>. HRs and 95% CIs were directly obtained from 5 studies, and for the remaining 2 studies, HRs and 95% CIs were extrapolated from Kaplan-Meier curves. Overall, the studies included in mate-analysis were of high quality, and of the 7 studies, 3 (43%) scored 8, 3 (43%) scored 7 and 1 (14%) scored 6.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0107013-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Characteristics of included studies.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0107013-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number ofpatients</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age(mean)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up(mean)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor differentiation(W, M/P)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage (I II /III IV)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cutoff</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGR5(H/L)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcomes measuredHR (95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study quality<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">#</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">He <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-He1">[31]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 months</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34/19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30/23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38/15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS 2.48 (1.52–4.28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hsu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Hsu2">[16]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China (Taiwan)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">296</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3 months</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262/34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151/145</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥180<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121/175</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS 2.33 (1.45–3.86)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFS 2.46 (1.25–4.83)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saigusa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Saigusa2">[17]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 years</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44/8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6.62<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19/33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFS 3.94 (1.12–13.87)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ziskin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Ziskin1">[20]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">891</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 years</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">693/160</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">393/401</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">332/559</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS 1.09 (0.93–1.28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miss data 38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miss data 97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Wu1">[15]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 months</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129/63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117/75</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108/84</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS 2.77 (1.62–4.73)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Takahashi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Takahashi1">[32]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.93 years</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166/14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97/83</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90/90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS 1.42 (0.57–3.53)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFS 1.91 (0.80–4.52)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peng <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Peng1">[33]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 months</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137/32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107/62</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥10%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102/67</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS 1.84 (1.06–3.18)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>HR: Hazard ratio; OS: Overall survival; DFS: Disease free survival; H: High expression; L: Low expression; W: Well; M: Moderate; P: Poor; NA: Not available.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>a</label><p>complex scoring,</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>b</label><p>percentage;</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>*estimated by survival curves;</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>#</label><p>Study quality was judged based on the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (range, 1–9).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>LGR5 expression and prognosis of CRC</title>
<p>6 out of the total of 7 studies reported data on LGR5 expression and OS in CRC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Wu1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Hsu2">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Ziskin1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-He1">[31]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Peng1">[33]</xref>, so the combined data from all 6 studies were pooled in the meta-analysis. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107013-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, due to a significant degree of heterogeneity (I<sup>2</sup> = 80.1%, P&lt;0.001), the pooled HRs and 95% CIs were calculated using the random-effect model (REM). The results showed that high LGR5 expression was associated with poor OS in CRC (HR: 1.87, 95% CI: 1.23–2.84, P = 0.003, REM). Additionally, the pooled HR for OS was 1.34 (95% CI: 1.17–1.54, P&lt;0.001) calculated by the fixed-effect model (FEM). 3 of 7 studies reported data on LGR5 expression and DFS, and as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107013-g003">Fig. 3</xref>, high LGR5 expression was significantly correlated with DFS, with a pooled HR estimate of 2.44 (95% CI: 1.49–3.98, P&lt;0.001, FEM). No significant heterogeneity was observed (I<sup>2</sup> = 0%, P = 0.649).</p>
<fig id="pone-0107013-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Forest plot of the hazard ratio (HR) for the association of LGR5 expression with overall survival (OS) in colorectal cancer patients in 5 studies.</title>
<p>HR&gt;1 implied poor survival, and high LGR5 expression was significantly associated with worse OS in CRC patients.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0107013-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Forest plot of the hazard ratio (HR) for the association of LGR5 expression with disease-free survival (DFS) in colorectal cancer patients in 3 studies.</title>
<p>HR&gt;1 implied poor survival, and high LGR5 expression was significantly associated with worse DFS in CRC patients.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We conducted a subgroup analysis of the association of LGR5 expression with OS by study region, patient number, age, follow-up, tumor stage and cutoff value, and the main results are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0107013-t002">Table 2</xref>. The results showed that LGR5 expression was significantly correlated with OS (HR: 2.52, 95% CI: 1.75–2.89) in patients from Asian countries, but not in patients from non-Asian countries (HR: 1.09, 95% CI: 0.93–1.28), here, we should note the fact that only study from non-Asian countries (USA) was included. The subgroup analysis showed a significant correlation between LGR5 expression and OS in studies in which the number of patients was less than 200 (HR: 2.22, 95% CI: 1.66–2.98). The subgroup meta-analysis of the studies with a follow-up period of less than 60 months indicated that high LGR5 expression was a predictor of poor OS (HR: 2.38, 95% CI: 1.79–3.15). When grouped according to the stage of CRC, a significant relationship between LGR5 expression and OS was observed in both the early stage (HR: 2.27, 95% CI: 1.52–3.38) and the later stage (HR: 1.70, 95% CI: 1.01–2.87) of CRC. We also observed a statistically significant effect of LGR5 expression on OS based on the studies using a cutoff &gt;6, with an HR of 2.09 (95% CI: 1.36–3.21). Additionally, the results also showed that the high LGR5 expression was independent predictor of poor OS in CRC patients with the mean age ≤60 (HR: 2.27, 95% CI: 1.52–3.38). Because of the low number of studies, the subgroup analysis of the association of LGR5 expression with DFS was not further pursued.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0107013-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Stratified analysis of pooled hazard ratios for colorectal cancer patients with High LGR5expression.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0107013-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of studies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of patients</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">P value</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterogeneity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model used</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P (Z)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P (BON)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sup>2</sup> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total OS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1781</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 (1.23–2.84)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.1%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">890</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25 (1.75–2.89)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEM</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No-Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">891</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.93–1.28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.290</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not applicable</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of patients</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;200</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1187</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54 (0.73–3.22)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.256</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.256</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤200</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">594</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22 (1.66–2.98)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.532</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1367</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49 (0.85–2.62)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.159</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.318</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.5%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">361</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27 (1.52–3.38)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.297</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow up (month)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1060</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 (0.81–2.17)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.269</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.538</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.9%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">721</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38 (1.79–3.15)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.666</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage (I II /III IV)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">361</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27 (1.52–3.38)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.297</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤1.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1420</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70 (1.01–2.87)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.1%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cutoff</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">476</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09 (1.36–3.21)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.348</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1083</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68 (0.67–4.16)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.6%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt106"><label/><p>OS: Overall survival; HR: Hazard ratio; CI: Confidence intervals; REM: Random-effect model; FEM: Fixed-effect model.</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label/><p>P (Z): P value for significant test; P (BON): P value from stepdown Bonferroni testing.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Publication bias analysis</title>
<p>In this meta-analysis, publication bias was tested using Begg’s funnel plot and Egger’s test. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107013-g004">Figure 4</xref>, the funnel plot presented no proof of obvious publication bias in any of the included studies for OS or DFS, and Egger’s test also showed no obvious publication bias in the studies for either of the two outcomes (OS, P = 0.471; DFS, P = 0.749; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107013-g005">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0107013-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Begg’s funnel plot for all studies included in this meta-analysis.</title>
<p>(A) Begg’s funnel plot assessing LGR5 expression and OS in colorectal cancer patients. (B) Begg’s funnel plot assessing LGR5 expression and DFS in colorectal cancer patients.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0107013-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Egger’s test to detect publication bias.</title>
<p>(A) Egger’s test assessing LGR5 expression and OS in colorectal cancer patients. (B) Egger’s test assessing LGR5 expression and DFS in colorectal cancer patients.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Sensitivity analysis</title>
<p>To gauge the stability of the result, a sensitivity analysis was conducted, in which one study was deleted at a time. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0107013-t003">Table 3</xref>, the corresponding pooled HR for OS did not significantly change, regardless of which study was deleted, suggesting that the result was robust. However, the pooled HR for DFS appeared to be significantly altered, which may have been due to the insufficient number of studies.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0107013-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Sensitivity analysis for OS and DFS.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0107013-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study omitted</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">He (2014) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-He1">[31]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76 (1.12–2.77)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hsu (2013) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Hsu2">[16]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79 (1.12–2.84)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ziskin (2012) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Ziskin1">[20]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25 (1.75–2.89)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wu (2012) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Wu1">[15]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72 (1.12–2.65)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Takahashi (2011) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Takahashi1">[32]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 (1.22–3.09)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peng (2010) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Peng1">[33]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88 (1.15–3.08)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hsu (2013) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Hsu2">[16]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.07 (0.28–3.86)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saigusa (2013) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Saigusa2">[17]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 (0.91–3.49)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Takahashi (2011) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Takahashi1">[32]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57 (0.85–4.30)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>CRC is a malignant disease with high mortality worldwide, and its prognosis is still poor, although tremendous progress has been achieved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Kobayashi1">[4]</xref>. Recently, alteration of molecular biological markers in tumor tissues has become an important part of predicting the prognosis of patients with malignant tumors. LGR5, known as a target of the Wnt signaling pathway, has been reported to be a potential marker of stem cells in the small intestine and colon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Barker1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Haegebarth1">[35]</xref>. Accumulated studies have shown that LGR5 is closely associated with tumorigenesis and tumor invasion in CRC and is likely to be a relevant marker of CSCs in CRC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Tanese1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-MerlosSurez1">[36]</xref>. CSCs are thought to be responsible for the local invasion, metastasis and recurrence of malignant tumors because of their self-renewal and multi-differentiation potential and thus are also a major obstacle to improving overall cancer survival.</p>
<p>In recent years, the correlation between LGR5 expression and the survival of patients has been explored in many studies due to the key role of LGR5 in tumorigenesis. High LGR5 expression has been extensively reported to be an unfavorable prognostic indicator in various human cancers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Liu1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Wu1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Peng1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Nakata1">[37]</xref>. However, certain reports have also suggested contrary results for the correlation between LGR5 expression and the prognosis of CRC. For example, Ziskin et al. reported that LGR5 expression was not significantly associated with the outcome of tumors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Ziskin1">[20]</xref> and was not a prognostic marker of CRC (HR: 1.09, 95% CI: 0.93–1.28). To validate the exact relationship between LGR5 expression and the prognosis of patients with CRC, a meta-analysis was performed, including recent related studies and generally using a comprehensive search strategy. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first meta-analysis that has documented the prognostic value of LGR5 in CRC. In the present meta-analysis, through combining the outcomes of 6 published studies, comprising 1781 patients with CRC, we draw the conclusion that high LGR5 expression was significantly associated with poor OS (HR: 1.87, 95% CI: 1.23–2.84, P = 0.003), moreover, the high LGR5 expression was also significantly associated with worse DFS (HR: 2.44, 95% CI: 1.49–3.98, P&lt;0.001) by combining the outcomes of 3 studies comprising 528 patients with CRC. Additionally, the sensitivity analysis showed that the significant association between high LGR5 expression and poor OS was not altered, regardless of whether one of these studies was omitted, suggesting the robustness of this result. However, the significant association between high LGR5 expression and poor DFS was affected by omitting study, which may be due to the small number of studies. In this meta-analysis, the quality assessment was performed independently and reproducibly by two authors according to Newcastle-Ottawa guidelines. By evaluating the articles comprehensively and scientifically, we ensured that the included studies were of high-quality.</p>
<p>Warrants caution is because the baseline characteristics of patients might have affected the conclusion of each included report, including the sample size, follow-up period, clinical stage and cutoff scores for the definition of positive staining, among other aspects. Therefore, further subgroup analysis was performed by study region, patient number, age, follow-up duration, stage and cutoff value. We found that high LGR5 expression was significantly associated with poor OS in the studies performed in Asia (HR: 2.52, 95% CI: 1.75–2.89), but not in one study done outside Asia. Therefore, further investigation is needed to verify whether the prognostic value of LGR5 in CRC is associated with the region inhabited by patients. A significant association was observed between LGR5 expression and poor OS only when the follow-up period was ≤60 months; this finding should be interpreted cautiously due to increased mortality with the prolongation of follow-up time. In addition, the subgroup analysis by clinical stage revealed that high LGR5 expression was significantly associated with poor OS in patients, regardless of the stage (early or late) of CRC, indicating that LGR5 was an independent predictor of prognosis during the progression of CRC. This observation was consistent with the role of LGR5 in carcinogenesis, including enriching CSCs and promoting tumor formation and progression. As there is no uniform standard to define positive LGR5 expression, the cutoff greatly differed among the studies, and the results may also have changed due to the cutoff value. The subgroup analysis showed that LGR5 expression was significantly associated with an unfavorable prognosis in patients with CRC when studies set the cutoff score at &gt;6 (HR: 2.09, 95% CI: 1.36–3.21), suggesting that a higher cutoff score was more likely to lead to a differential conclusion. Previous studies have demonstrated that elevated LGR5 expression significantly correlates with lymphatic invasion, vascular invasion, tumor depth, lymph node metastasis, and tumor recurrence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Yamanoi1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107013-Uchida2">[39]</xref>.</p>
<p>Publication bias is a major concern in all forms of meta-analysis. In the present study, neither Egger’s test nor Begg’s funnel plot showed evidence of publication bias. However, there are several limitations to the current meta-analysis, as we could not prevent all potential bias among the studies. First, the studies included in our meta-analysis were restricted to only articles published in English or Chinese, and the number was relatively small. Second, heterogeneity among the studies were found in the main analysis, maybe due to the diversity of the techniques used to identify the expression of LGR5. For example, all of the included studies were required to detect LGR5 expression by IHC, but the results of IHC greatly depended on methodological factors such as primary antibody type and antibody concentration, leading to between-study heterogeneity. For this reason, random effect model and subgroup analysis were adopted to adjust for this shortcomings. Third, the method of HR and 95% CI extrapolation should be mentioned, as an HR and a 95% CI calculated from data or extracted from survival curves might be less reliable than those obtained by direct analysis of variance. Additionally, we need to consider the fact that studies with positive results are easily accepted, whereas studies with negative results are often rejected.</p>
<p>In summary, despite the limitations listed above, we found that high LGR5 expression may be an independent risk factor for patients with CRC. Based on currently published articles, high LGR5 expression is an unfavorable prognostic factor in CRC patients and could be helpful to optimize therapeutic schemes. Further, larger prospective studies are needed to validate our results.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0107013.s001" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>The search results of relevant articles in different databases.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0107013.s002" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107013.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Checklist S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>PRISMA Checklist.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Jemal1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <collab xlink:type="simple">Center MM, Ferlay J, Ward E, et al</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Global cancer statistics</article-title>. <source>CA: a cancer journal for clinicians</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Ahlquist1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahlquist</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Domanico</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yab</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Next-generation stool DNA test accurately detects colorectal cancer and large adenomas</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Jemal2"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Cancer statistics</article-title>. <source>CA: a cancer journal for clinicians</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Kobayashi1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kotake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Characteristics of recurrence and surveillance tools after curative resection for colorectal cancer: a multicenter study</article-title>. <source>Surgery</source> <volume>141</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Reya1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Stem cells, cancer, and cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>414</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Visvader1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Visvader</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindeman</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cancer stem cells in solid tumours: accumulating evidence and unresolved questions</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Cancer</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>755</fpage>–<lpage>768</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Becker1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mashimo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Immunostaining of Lgr5, an intestinal stem cell marker, in normal and premalignant human gastrointestinal tissue</article-title>. <source>TheScientificWorldJournal</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1168</fpage>–<lpage>1176</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Hsu1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsueh</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Characterization of two LGR genes homologous to gonadotropin and thyrotropin receptors with extracellular leucine-rich repeats and a G protein-coupled, seven-transmembrane region</article-title>. <source>Molecular endocrinology (Baltimore, Md)</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1830</fpage>–<lpage>1845</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Yamamoto1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuiji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kenetaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of orphan G-protein-coupled receptor, Gpr49, in human hepatocellular carcinomas with beta-catenin mutations</article-title>. <source>Hepatology (Baltimore, Md)</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>528</fpage>–<lpage>533</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Uchida1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of leucine-rich repeat-containing G protein-coupled receptor 5 in colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer science</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>1731</fpage>–<lpage>1737</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Colon1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tumors</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mcclanahan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koseoglu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Identification of Overexpression of Orphan G Protein-Coupled Receptor GPR49 in Human Colon and Ovarian Primary Tumors</article-title>. <source>Cancer biology &amp; therapy</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>419</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Tanese1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanese</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>G-protein-coupled receptor GPR49 is up-regulated in basal cell carcinoma and promotes cell proliferation and tumor formation</article-title>. <source>The American journal of pathology</source> <volume>173</volume>: <fpage>835</fpage>–<lpage>843</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Liu1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Over-expression of LGR5 correlates with poor survival of colon cancer in mice as well as in patients</article-title>. <source>Neoplasma</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Saigusa1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saigusa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toiyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsushita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Clinical significance of LGR5 and CD44 expression in locally advanced rectal cancer after preoperative chemoradiotherapy</article-title>. <source>International journal of oncology</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1643</fpage>–<lpage>1652</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Wu1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Lgr5 is a potential marker of colorectal carcinoma stem cells that correlates with patient survival</article-title>. <source>World journal of surgical oncology</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>244</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Hsu2"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of Lgr5 correlates with resistance to 5-FU-based chemotherapy in colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>International journal of colorectal disease</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1535</fpage>–<lpage>1546</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Saigusa2"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saigusa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toiyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Significant correlation between LKB1 and LGR5 gene expression and the association with poor recurrence-free survival in rectal cancer after preoperative chemoradiotherapy</article-title>. <source>Journal of cancer research and clinical oncology</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-ValladaresAyerbes1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valladares-Ayerbes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco-Calvo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reboredo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzo-Patiño</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iglesias-Díaz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of the Adenocarcinoma-Associated Gene AGR2 and the Intestinal Stem Cell Marker LGR5 as Biomarkers in Colorectal Cancer</article-title>. <source>International journal of molecular sciences</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>4367</fpage>–<lpage>4387</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Kleist1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleist</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kersten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Single nucleotide polymorphisms of the adult intestinal stem cell marker Lgr5 in primary and metastatic colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>American journal of translational research</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Ziskin1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ziskin JL, Dunlap D, Yaylaoglu M, Fodor IK, Forrest WF, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2012) In situ validation of an intestinal stem cell signature in colorectal cancer. Gut.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Stang1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Critical evaluation of the Newcastle-Ottawa scale for the assessment of the quality of nonrandomized studies in meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Epidemiology</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>603</fpage>–<lpage>605</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Handoll1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Handoll</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Systematic reviews on rehabilitation interventions</article-title>. <source>Archives of physical medicine and rehabilitation</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>875</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Higgins1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>BMJ: British Medical Journal</source> <volume>327</volume>: <fpage>557</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Egger1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>Bmj</source> <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Begg1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Begg CB, Mazumdar M (1994) Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias. Biometrics: 1088–1101.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Pitule1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitule</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vycital</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Differential expression and prognostic role of selected genes in colorectal cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Anticancer research</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>4855</fpage>–<lpage>4865</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Fan1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X-S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H-Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H-P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y-F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Expression of Lgr5 in human colorectal carcinogenesis and its potential correlation with beta-catenin</article-title>. <source>International journal of colorectal disease</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Kleist2"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleist</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kersten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Expression of the adult intestinal stem cell marker Lgr5 in the metastatic cascade of colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>International journal of clinical and experimental pathology</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Chai1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Lgr5 and CD44 expressions in different types of intestinal polyps and colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Nan fang yi ke da xue xue bao  =  Journal of Southern Medical University</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>972</fpage>–<lpage>976</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Gerger1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohanes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Common cancer stem cell gene variants predict colon cancer recurrence</article-title>. <source>Clinical cancer research: an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>6934</fpage>–<lpage>6943</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-He1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">He S, Zhou H, Zhu X, Hu S, Fei M, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2014) Expression of Lgr5, a marker of intestinal stem cells, in colorectal cancer and its clinicopathological significance. Biomedicine &amp; pharmacotherapy. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2014.03.016" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2014.03.016</ext-link> [pii: S0753-3322(14)00044-4, Epub ahead of print].</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Takahashi1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takemasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Significance of Lgr5 (+ve) cancer stem cells in the colon and rectum</article-title>. <source>Annals of surgical oncology</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1166</fpage>–<lpage>1174</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Peng1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Higher expression of Lgr5 predicts poor prognosis in human colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Modern Digestion &amp; Intervention</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>284</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Barker1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Es</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuipers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kujala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van den Born</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Identification of stem cells in small intestine and colon by marker gene Lgr5</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>449</volume>: <fpage>1003</fpage>–<lpage>1007</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Haegebarth1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haegebarth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clevers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Wnt signaling, lgr5, and stem cells in the intestine and skin</article-title>. <source>The American journal of pathology</source> <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>715</fpage>–<lpage>721</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-MerlosSurez1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merlos-Suárez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barriga</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Céspedes</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The intestinal stem cell signature identifies colorectal cancer stem cells and predicts disease relapse</article-title>. <source>Cell stem cell</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Nakata1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bageritz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bermejo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>LGR5 is a marker of poor prognosis in glioblastoma and is required for survival of brain cancer stem-like cells</article-title>. <source>Brain pathology</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Yamanoi1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanoi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kushima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of leucine-rich repeat-containing G protein-coupled receptor 5 in gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Pathology international</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107013-Uchida2"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of leucine-rich repeat-containing G protein-coupled receptor 5 in colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer science</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>1731</fpage>–<lpage>1737</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>