<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-54031</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100487</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic polymorphism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Human genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic association studies</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancer epidemiology</subject><subject>Genetic epidemiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancers and neoplasms</subject><subj-group><subject>Gastrointestinal tumors</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cancer risk factors</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics (mathematics)</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Meta-analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Research design</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical research design</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Association between CYP1A2 and CYP1B1 Polymorphisms and Colorectal Cancer Risk: A Meta-Analysis</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Gene Polymorphism and Colorectal Cancer Risk</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Xiao-Feng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¶</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¶</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Zhi-Zhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Jian-Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Ya-Ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Si</surname><given-names>Hui-Qiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Qing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Li-Xia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Wu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Research, Peace Hospital of Changzhi Medical College, Changzhi, Shanxi Province, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Clinical laboratory, Sun Yat-Sen Memorial Hospital, Sun Yat-Sen University, Guangzhou, Guangdong Province, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Gastroenterology, The Second People's Hospital of Zhuhai, Zhuhai, Guangdong Province, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Hematology, Peace Hospital of Changzhi Medical College, Changzhi, Shanxi Province, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shedden</surname><given-names>Kerby</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Michigan, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">393120823@qq.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: XFH. Performed the experiments: XFH JW. Analyzed the data: XFH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: XFH JW ZZL JJX W. Wang YPD YC HQS QL LXW W. Wei. Wrote the paper: XFH.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn1" fn-type="other"><p>¶ These authors are co-first authors.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e100487</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>He et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract><sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>The previous published data on the association between CYP1A2*F (rs762551), CYP1B1 Leu432Val (rs1056836), Asn453Ser (rs180040), and Arg48Gly (rs10012) polymorphisms and colorectal cancer risk remained controversial.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methodology/Principal Findings</title>
<p>The purpose of this study is to evaluate the role of CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly genotypes in colorectal cancer susceptibility. We performed a meta-analysis on all the eligible studies that provided 5,817 cases and 6,544 controls for CYP1A2*F (from 13 studies), 9219 cases and 10406 controls for CYP1B1 Leu432Val (from 12 studies), 6840 cases and 7761 controls for CYP1B1 Asn453Ser (from 8 studies), and 4302 cases and 4791 controls for CYP1B1Arg48Gly (from 6 studies). Overall, no significant association was found between CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly and colorectal cancer risk when all the eligible studies were pooled into the meta-analysis. And in the subgroup by ethnicity and source of controls, no evidence of significant association was observed in any subgroup analysis.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusions/Significance</title>
<p>In summary, this meta-analysis indicates that CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms do not support an association with colorectal cancer, and further studies are needed to investigate the association. In addition, our work also points out the importance of new studies for CYP1A2*F polymorphism in Asians, because high heterogeneity was found (dominant model: <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 81.3%; heterozygote model: <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 79.0).</p>
</sec></abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>There were no funding sources for this study.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Sporadic colorectal cancer (CRC) is considered to be a multifactorial disease, in which multiple exposures to endogenous factors and dietary carcinogens interact with individual genetic background in a complex manner resulting in modulation of the risk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Ishibe1">[1]</xref>. In 2010, an estimated 142,570 new cases will be diagnosed and 51,370 deaths will occur in the whole world <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Jemal1">[2]</xref>. Epidemiologic studies on Western populations have emphasized the large contribution of food and lifestyle to sporadic CRC risk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-GerhardssondeVerdier1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Kushi1">[7]</xref>. High-fat and low-fiber diets, as well as alcohol, tobacco, and red or processed meat consumption, have been shown to produce high levels of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons and heterocyclic aromatic amines. These procarcinogenic agents are potentially very harmful and may play a key role in the malignant transformation of cells by interacting with DNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Potter1">[8]</xref>. It has been proposed that this risk may be due to carcinogenic polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) and heterocyclic amines produced when meat is cooked at high temperatures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Norat1">[9]</xref>.</p>
<p>CYP1B1 gene is located on chr2p22-p21, which is involved in the metabolic activation of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) including benzo(a)pyrene and dimethylbenz(a)anthracene (DMBA), but with a product distribution that is distinct from CYP1A1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Buters1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Shimada1">[11]</xref>. Several lines of evidence suggest that CYP1B1 plays a role in carcinogenesis. CYP1B1 is commonly over-expressed inhumanmalignancies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Murray1">[12]</xref> and activates a variety of carcinogens. For example, CYP1B1 catalyzes both the formation of dihydrodiols of specific PAHs and their subsequent oxidation to carcinogenic dihydrodiol epoxides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Kim1">[13]</xref>. In humans, CYP1B1 is genetically polymorphic and more than 50 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) have been reported so far, of which certain deleterious mutations are associated with primary congenital glaucoma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Stoilov1">[14]</xref>. Of the most common SNPs of CYP1B1 gene, four have been reported to result in amino acid substitutions including Arg by Gly at codon 48 (rs10012), Leu by Val at codon 432 (rs1056836) and Asn by Ser at codon 453 (rs1800440). CYP 1A2 is an important gene in catalyzing 2- and 4-hydroxylations of estrogens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Yamazaki1">[40]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Tsuchiya1">[42]</xref> and metabolism of carcinogens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Nebert2">[43]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Eaton1">[45]</xref>. CYP1A2*1C, located in the 5′-non-coding promoter region of CYP1A2, was reported to be associated with decreased enzyme inducibility in Japanese smokers but seems to be very rare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Nakajima1">[46]</xref>.</p>
<p>To date, a number of molecular epidemiological studies have been done to evaluate the association between CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms and colorectal cancer risk in diverse populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Wang1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Sainz2">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Hlavata1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Trubicka1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Cotterchio1">[34]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Wang2">[39]</xref>. However, the results were inconsistent or even contradictory. Therefore, we performed a comprehensive meta-analysis by including the most recent and relevant articles to identify statistical evidence of the association between CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms and risk of colorectal cancer that have been investigated. Meta-analysis is a powerful tool for summarizing the different studies. It can not only overcome the problem of small size and inadequate statistical power of genetic studies of complex traits, but also provide more reliable results than a single case–control study.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Identification and eligibility of relevant studies</title>
<p>A comprehensive literature search was performed using the PubMed, CNKI, and Medline database for relevant articles published (the last search update was Sep 10, 2013) with the following key words “CYP1A2”, “CYP1B1”, “polymorphism”, “Variant”, or “Mutation”, and “Colorectal”. In addition, studies were identified by a manual search of the reference lists of reviews and retrieved studies. We included all the case–control studies and cohort studies that investigated the association between CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms and colorectal cancer risk with genotyping data. All eligible studies were retrieved, and their bibliographies were checked for other relevant publications.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Inclusion criteria</title>
<p>The included studies have to meet the following criteria: (1) only the case–control studies or cohort studies were considered; (2) evaluated the CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms and the risk of colorectal cancer; (3) the genotype distribution of the polymorphism in cases and controls were described in details and the results were expressed as odds ratio (OR) and corresponding 95% confidence interval (95% CI). Major reasons for exclusion of studies were as follows: (1) not for cancer research; (2) only case population; (3) duplicate of previous publication (When the same patient population was used in several publications, only the most recent, largest or complete study was included following careful examination).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Data extraction</title>
<p>Information was carefully extracted from all eligible studies independently by two investigators according to the inclusion criteria listed above. The following data were collected from each study: first author's name, year of publication, country of origin, ethnicity, source of controls (population-based controls, hospital-based controls, and family-based controls), and numbers of cases and controls in the CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly genotypes whenever possible. Ethnicity was categorized as “Caucasian” and “Asian”. When one study did not state which ethnic groups was included or if it was impossible to separate participants according to phenotype, the sample was termed as “mixed population”. We did not define any minimum number of patients to include in this meta-analysis. Articles that reported different ethnic groups and different countries or locations, we considered them different study samples for each category cited above.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Crude odds ratios (ORs) together with their corresponding 95% confidence intervals (95% CIs) were used to assess the strength of association between the CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms and colorectal cancer risk. The pooled ORs were performed for dominant model (CYP1A2*F: CY + YY vs. CC; CYP1B1 Leu432Val: Leu/Val + Val/Val vs. Leu/Leu; CYP1B1 Asn453Ser: Asn/Ser + Ser/Ser vs. Asn/Asn; CYP1B1 Arg48Gly: Arg/Gly + Gly/Gly vs. Arg/Arg), recessive model (CYP1A2*F: YY vs. CC + CY; CYP1B1 Leu432Val: Val/Val vs. Leu/Leu + Leu/Val; CYP1B1 Asn453Ser: Ser/Ser vs. Asn/Asn + Asn/Ser; CYP1B1 Arg48Gly: Gly/Gly vs. Arg/Arg + Arg/Gly), co-dominant model (CYP1A2*F: YY vs. CC and CY vs. CC; CYP1B1 Leu432Val: Val/Val vs. Leu/Leu and Leu/Val vs. Leu/Leu; CYP1B1 Asn453Ser: Ser/Ser vs. Asn/Asn and Asn/Ser vs. Asn/Asn; CYP1B1 Arg48Gly: Gly/Gly vs. Arg/Arg and Arg/Gly vs. Arg/Arg), and additive model (CYP1A2*F: Y vs. C; CYP1B1 Asn453Ser: Ser/Asn; CYP1B1 Asn453Ser: Ser vs. Asn; CYP1B1 Arg48Gly: Gly vs. Arg), respectively. Between-study heterogeneity was assessed by calculating <italic>Q</italic>-statistic (Heterogeneity was considered statistically significant if <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.10) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Davey1">[47]</xref> and quantified using the <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> value, Venice criteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Ioannidis1">[48]</xref> for the <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> test included: “<italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&lt;25% represents no heterogeneity, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 25–50% represents moderate heterogeneity, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 50–75% represents large heterogeneity, and <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&gt;75% represents extreme heterogeneity”. If results were not heterogeneous, the pooled ORs were calculated by the fixed-effect model (we used the <italic>Q</italic>-statistic, which represents the magnitude of heterogeneity between-studies) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Mantel1">[49]</xref>. Otherwise, a random effect model was used (when the heterogeneity between-studies were significant) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-DerSimonian1">[50]</xref>. We also performed subgroup analysis by ethnicity and source of controls were conducted. Moreover, sensitivity analysis was performed by excluding a single study each time. We also ranked studies according to sample size, and then repeated this meta-analysis. Sample size was classified according to a minimum of 200 participants and those with fewer than 200 participants. The cite criteria were previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Klug1">[51]</xref>. HWE was calculated by using the goodness-of-fit test, and deviation was considered when <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05. Begg's funnel plots <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Begg1">[52]</xref> and Egger's linear regression test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Egger1">[53]</xref> were used to assess publication bias. We opted for using ethnicity, source of controls, menopausal status, and sample size as possible different sources of heterogeneity. All of the calculations were performed using STATA version 10.0 (STATA Corporation, College Station, TX).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Literature search and meta-analysis databases</title>
<p>Relevant publications were retrieved and preliminarily screened. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0100487-g001"><bold>Fig. 1</bold></xref>, 43 publications were identified, among which 6 irrelevant papers were excluded. Thus, 37 publications were eligible. Among these publications, 14 articles were excluded because they were review articles, case reports, and other polymorphisms of CYP1A2 and CYP1B1. As summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0100487-t001"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>, 23 articles with 39 studies were selected in this meta-analysis, including 5,817 cases and 6,544 controls for CYP1A2*F (from 13 studies), 9,219 cases and 10,406 controls for CYP1B1 Leu432Val (from 12 studies), 6,840 cases and 7,761 controls for CYP1B1 Asn453Ser (from 8 studies), and 4,302 cases and 4,791 controls for CYP1B1 Arg48Gly (from 6 studies). Among these studies, eight were Caucasians, four were Asians, and 1 mixed populations for CYP1A2*F. All studies were Caucasians except for one study was mixed population for CYP1B1 polymorphisms. The distribution of genotypes in the controls was consistent with Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium in all studies. All of the cases were pathologically confirmed.</p>
<fig id="pone-0100487-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Study flow chart explaining the selection of the 23 eligible articles included in the meta-analysis.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0100487-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Main characteristics of all studies included in the meta-analysis.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0100487-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author/Year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Genotype distribution</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of case/control</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Cases</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Controls</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CY</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YY</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CY</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YY</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="11" align="left" rowspan="1">CYP1A2*F</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Wang1">[15]</xref> 2012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">305/357</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rudolph <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Rudolph1">[16]</xref> 2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">German</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">354</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">353</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">678/680</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sainz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Sainz1">[17]</xref> 2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">German</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">872</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">735</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">887</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">732</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1764/1786</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cleary <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Cleary1">[18]</xref> 2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">598</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">461</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">648</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">517</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1165/1290</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kobayashi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Kobayashi1">[19]</xref> 2009</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104/225</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saebø <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Saeb1">[20]</xref> 2008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Norway</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198/222</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sachse <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Sachse1">[21]</xref> 2002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">264</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">325</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">490/593</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yoshida <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Yoshida1">[22]</xref> 2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64/111</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kiss <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Kiss1">[23]</xref> 2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hungary</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500/500</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Küry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Kry1">[24]</xref> 2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">514</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">420</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">553</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">480</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1013/1118</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Bae1">[25]</xref> 2006</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111/93</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Chen1">[26]</xref> 2005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138/340</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Landi1">[27]</xref> 2005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">361/321</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="11" align="left" rowspan="1">CYP1B1 Leu432Val (rs1056836)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author/Year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Genotype distribution</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of case/control</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Cases</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Controls</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leu/Leu</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leu/Val</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Val/Val</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leu/Leu</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leu/Val</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Val/Val</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Wang2">[39]</xref> 2012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300/350</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rudolph et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Rudolph2">[28]</xref> 2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">German</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">339</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">668/669</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sainz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Sainz2">[29]</xref> 2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">German</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">339</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">358</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">719/713</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cleary et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Cleary1">[18]</xref> 2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">391</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">547</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">424</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">617</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1162/1291</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hlavata et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Hlavata1">[31]</xref> 2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Czech</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">495/495</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trubicka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Trubicka1">[32]</xref> 2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">275</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">597/598</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sachse et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Sachse1">[21]</xref> 2002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">258</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">490/593</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cotterchio et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Cotterchio1">[34]</xref> 2008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">382</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">407</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">604</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">831/1248</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Küry et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Kry2">[35]</xref> 2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">317</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">507</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">576</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1013/1118</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bethke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Bethke1">[36]</xref> 2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">519</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1277</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">763</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">538</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1365</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">792</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2559/2695</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Huber1">[37]</xref> 2005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/337</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Landi2">[38]</xref> 2005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">343/299</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="11" align="left" rowspan="1">Asn453Ser (rs1800440)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author/Year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Genotype distribution</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of case/control</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Cases</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Controls</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asn/Asn</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asn/Ser</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ser/Ser</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asn/Asn</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asn/Ser</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ser/Ser</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rudolph <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Rudolph2">[28]</xref> 2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">German</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">467</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">452</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">676/680</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sainz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Sainz2">[29]</xref> 2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">German</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">505</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">473</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">731/722</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cleary <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Cleary1">[18]</xref> 2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">775</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">354</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">897</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">349</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1163/1292</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hlavata <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Hlavata1">[31]</xref> 2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Czech</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">353</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">495/495</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cotterchio <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Cotterchio1">[34]</xref> 2008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">549</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">867</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">340</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">832/1249</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bethke <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Bethke1">[36]</xref> 2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1734</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">739</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,790</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">828</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2559/2694</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Huber1">[37]</xref> 2005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/332</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Landi2">[38]</xref> 2005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">342/297</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="11" align="left" rowspan="1">Arg48Gly (rs10012)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author/Year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Genotype distribution</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of case/control</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Cases</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Controls</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arg/Arg</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arg/Gly</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gly/Gly</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arg/Arg</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arg/Gly</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gly/Gly</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rudolph <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Rudolph2">[28]</xref> 2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">German</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">329</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">322</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">299</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">679/675</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sainz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Sainz2">[29]</xref> 2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">German</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">354</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">318</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">342</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">732/720</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cleary <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Cleary1">[18]</xref> 2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">593</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">478</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">651</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">529</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1163/1292</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trubicka <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Trubicka1">[32]</xref> 2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">597/597</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cotterchio <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Cotterchio1">[34]</xref> 2008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">424</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">347</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">624</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">518</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">832/1249</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Landi2">[38]</xref> 2005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">299/258</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>PB population-based studies, HB hospital-based studies, FB family-based studies, Y yes, N no, SC source of control, HWE Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Meta-analysis results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0100487-t002"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref> lists the main results of the meta-analysis of CYP1A2*F polymorphism and colorectal cancer risk. Overall, no significant association was found between CYP1A2*F polymorphism and colorectal cancer risk (dominant model: OR = 1.05, 95% CI = 0.94–1.18, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.010, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 54.1%; recessive model: OR = 1.01, 95% CI = 0.90–1.13, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.426, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 2.0%; homozygote model: OR = 1.04, 95% CI = 0.93–1.17, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.144, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 30.0%; heterozygote model: OR = 1.05, 95% CI = 0.94–1.17, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.023, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 49.2%; additive model: OR = 1.03, 95% CI = 0.95–1.11, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.026, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 48.2%, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0100487-g002"><bold>Fig. 2</bold></xref>). Significant between-study heterogeneity was detected. Hence, we performed the stratified analyses according to ethnicity and source of controls. In the stratified analysis by ethnicity, no significant association was found among Caucasians (dominant model: OR = 1.02, 95% CI = 0.95–1.10, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.233, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 24.6%; recessive model: OR = 1.06, 95% CI = 0.94–1.20, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.387, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 5.6%; homozygote model: OR = 1.07, 95% CI = 0.94–1.21, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.224, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 25.6%; heterozygote model: OR = 1.01, 95% CI = 0.94–1.09, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.403, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 3.5%; additive model: OR = 1.03, 95% CI = 0.97–1.08, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.157, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 34.0%, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0100487-g003"><bold>Fig. 3</bold></xref>) and Asians (recessive model: OR = 0.78, 95% CI = 0.57–1.05, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.681, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.0%; homozygote model: OR = 0.91, 95% CI = 0.49–1.68, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.076, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 56.5%; additive model: OR = 0.98, 95% CI = 0.69–1.42, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.009, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 74.3%, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0100487-g004"><bold>Fig. 4</bold></xref>). In addition, high heterogeneity was found among Asians (dominant model: <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 81.3%; heterozygote model: <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 79.0). When grouped by source of control, there was still no evidence of significant association.</p>
<fig id="pone-0100487-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Forest plot of CYP1A2*F polymorphism and colorectal cancer risk among overall analysis (additive model).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0100487-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Forest plot of CYP1A2*F polymorphism and colorectal cancer risk among Caucasians (additive model).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0100487-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Forest plot of CYP1A2*F polymorphism and colorectal cancer risk among Asians (additive model).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0100487-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Results of meta-analysis for CYP1A2 and CYP1B1 polymorphisms on colorectal cancer risk.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">1</xref></title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0100487-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Generic model</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Recessive model</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Dominant model</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Homozygote</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterozygote</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Additive model</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CYP1A2*F</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (case/control)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (6891/7636)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.90–1.13)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.426</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.94–1.18)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.93–1.17)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.94–1.17)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.95–1.11)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="17" align="left" rowspan="1">Ethnicity</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (6169/6510)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.94–1.20)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.387</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.95–1.10)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.94–1.21)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.94–1.09)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.403</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.97–1.08)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (417/769)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.57–1.05)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.681</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.49–1.68)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.69–1.42)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="17" align="left" rowspan="1">Source of controls</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (4235/4689)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.85–1.13)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.329</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.91–1.08)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.982</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.86–1.17)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.566</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.91–1.09)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.929</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.93–1.06)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.795</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (2351/2590)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.88–1.28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.303</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.91–1.53)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.82–1.59)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 (0.93–1.55)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.92–1.30)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leu432Val</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (case/control)</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Recessive model</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Dominant model</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Homozygote</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterozygote</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Additive model</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (9219/10406)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.98–1.13)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.251</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.94–1.06)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.770</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.96–1.13)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.91–1.04)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.687</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.98–1.06)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.498</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asn453Ser</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (case/control)</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Recessive model</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Dominant model</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Homozygote</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterozygote</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Additive model</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (6840/7761)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.76–1.11)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.617</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.87–1.08)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.76–1.11)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.685</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.86–1.11)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.91–1.03)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.135</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="17" align="left" rowspan="1">Source of controls</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3402/3943)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.62–1.05)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.988</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.86–1.19)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.63–1.07)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.996</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.81–1.01)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.275</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.86–1.03)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.183</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3438/3818)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.81–1.40)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.332</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.83–1.02)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.79–1.37)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.310</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.87–1.23)*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.92–1.09)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.8</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arg48Gly</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (case/control)</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Recessive model</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Dominant model</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Homozygote</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterozygote</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Additive model</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>h</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">2</xref> (%)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4302/4791)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.86–1.16)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.91–1.08)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.780</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.86–1.16)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.91–1.08)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.989</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.93–1.06)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.286</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label>1</label><p>All summary ORs were calculated using fixed-effects models. In the case of significant heterogeneity (indicated by *), ORs were calculated using random-effects models.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>2</label><p>The results were excluded due to high heterogeneity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0100487-t002"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref> also lists the main results of the meta-analysis of CYP1B1 Leu432Val polymorphism and colorectal cancer risk. Overall, no significant association was found between CYP1B1 Leu432Val polymorphism and colorectal cancer susceptibility (dominant model: OR = 1.00, 95% CI = 0.94–1.06, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.770, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.0%; recessive model: OR = 1.05, 95% CI = 0.98–1.13, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.251, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 20.3%; homozygote model: OR = 1.04, 95% CI = 0.96–1.13, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.383, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 6.3%; heterozygote model: OR = 0.98, 95% CI = 0.91–1.04, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.687, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.0%; additive model: OR = 1.02, 95% CI = 0.98–1.06, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.498, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.0%).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0100487-t002"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref> also lists the main results of the meta-analysis of CYP1B1 Asn453Ser polymorphism and colorectal cancer risk. Overall, no significant association was found between CYP1B1 Asn453Ser polymorphism and colorectal cancer susceptibility (dominant model: OR = 0.97, 95% CI = 0.87–1.08, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.053, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 49.6%; recessive model: OR = 0.92, 95% CI = 0.76–1.11, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.617, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.0%; homozygote model: OR = 0.92, 95% CI = 0.76–1.11, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.685, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.0%; heterozygote model: OR = 0.97, 95% CI = 0.86–1.11, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.016, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 61.8%; additive model: OR = 0.97, 95% CI = 0.91–1.03, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.135, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 38.6%). Significant between-study heterogeneity was detected. Hence, we performed the stratified analysis according to source of controls. And in the subgroup analysis by source of controls, there was still no significant association detected in any genetic model.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0100487-t002"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref> also lists the main results of the meta-analysis of CYP1B1 Arg48Gly polymorphism and colorectal cancer risk. Overall, no significant association was found between CYP1B1 Arg48Gly polymorphism and colorectal cancer susceptibility (dominant model: OR = 0.99, 95% CI = 0.91–1.08, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.780, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.0%; recessive model: OR = 1.00, 95% CI = 0.86–1.16, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.138, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 40.1%; homozygote model: OR = 1.00, 95% CI = 0.86–1.16, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.124, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 42.1%; heterozygote model: OR = 0.99, 95% CI = 0.91–1.08, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.989, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.0%; additive model: OR = 0.97, 95% CI = 0.91–1.03, <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.135, <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 38.6%).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Test of heterogeneity and sensitivity</title>
<p>There was significant heterogeneity among these studies for dominant model comparison (<italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.008 for CYP1A2*F and <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.053 for CYP1B1 Asn453Ser), heterozygote model comparison (<italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.020 for CYP1A2*F and <italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.016 for CYP1B1 Asn453Ser) and additive model comparison (<italic>P</italic><sub>h</sub> = 0.022 for CYP1A2*F). Then, we assessed the source of heterogeneity by ethnicity and source of controls. We found that ethnicity and source of controls (<italic>data not shown</italic>) did not contribute to substantial heterogeneity. Sensitivity analysis was conducted to determine whether modification of the inclusion criteria of this meta-analysis affected the results. Although the sample size for cases and controls in all eligible studies ranged from 175 to 2,455, the corresponding pooled ORs were not qualitatively altered with or without the study of small sample. In addition, a single study involved in the meta–analysis was deleted each time to reflect the influence of individual data set to the pooled ORs. The results were also not qualitatively altered.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Publication bias</title>
<p>Both Begg's funnel plot and Egger's test were performed to assess the publication bias of literatures. The Egger's test results and Begg's funnel plot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0100487-g005"><bold>Fig. 5</bold></xref><bold>, </bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0100487-g006"><bold>6</bold></xref>) suggested no evidence of publication bias in the meta-analysis of CYP1A2*F (<italic>P</italic> = 0.160 for dominant model, <italic>P</italic> = 0.714 for recessive model, <italic>P</italic> = 0.862 for homozygote model; <italic>P</italic> = 0.248 for heterozygote model; <italic>P</italic> = 0.462 for additive model) and Leu432Val (<italic>P</italic> = 0.749 for dominant model, <italic>P</italic> = 0.864 for recessive model, <italic>P</italic> = 0.991 for homozygote model; <italic>P</italic> = 0.721 for heterozygote model; <italic>P</italic> = 0.689 for additive model), although possible publication bias was suggested for Asn453Ser polymorphism with colorectal cancer risk in additive model and recessive model and for Arg48Gly with colorectal cancer risk in any genetic model. This might be a limitation for meta-analysis of Arg48Gly and Asn453Ser polymorphisms, especially those with small sample size, are less likely to be published. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0100487-g007"><bold>Figure 7</bold></xref><bold>, </bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0100487-g008"><bold>8</bold></xref> lists the Duval and Tweedie nonparametric “trim and fill” methods funnel plot in additive model and recessive model. Adjusting for possible publication bias using the Duval and Tweedie nonparametric “trim and fill” method for overall studies, the results did not change between Arg48Gly and Asn453Ser polymorphism with colorectal cancer risk.</p>
<fig id="pone-0100487-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Begg's funnel plot of the meta-analysis of colorectal cancer risk and CYP1A2*F polymorphism (homozygote model and dominant model).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0100487-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Begg's funnel plot of the meta-analysis of colorectal cancer risk and CYP1B1 Leu432Val polymorphism (homozygote model and dominant model).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0100487-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>The Duval and Tweedie nonparametric “trim and fill” method's funnel plot funnel plot of the meta-analysis of colorectal cancer risk and CYP1B1 Arg48Gly polymorphism (additive model and dominant model).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0100487-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>The Duval and Tweedie nonparametric “trim and fill” method's funnel plot funnel plot of the meta-analysis of colorectal cancer risk and CYP1B1 Asn453Ser polymorphism (additive model and dominant model).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>CYP1B1 is commonly over-expressed inhumanmalignancies and activates a variety of carcinogens. For example, CYP1B1 catalyzes both the formation of dihydrodiols of specific PAHs and their subsequent oxidation to carcinogenic dihydrodiol epoxides. The importance of CYP1B1 in chemical carcinogens is well illustrated in animal models in which metabolites of CYP1B1 were shown to induce Prostate cancer risk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Williams1">[54]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Cavalieri1">[55]</xref>. CYP 1A2 is an important gene in catalyzing 2- and 4-hydroxylations of estrogens and metabolism of carcinogens. A major reason for the limited number of studies of heterocyclic amine (HCA) and cancer risk is the difficulty of assessing human exposure to HCAs. HCA concentrations depend on cooking methods and the “doneness” level of the meat or fish, hampering the development of a complete and standardized database of concentrations; any estimation of dietary intake from food-frequency questionnaires (FFQs) is thus likely to result in misclassification. Like other environmental chemical carcinogens, HCAs require metabolic activation by host enzymes to become genotoxic. Phase I enzymes, including cytochrome P450 1A2, can metabolically activate carcinogens to form genotoxic electrophilic intermediates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-McManus1">[56]</xref>. The relative activity of these metabolizing enzymes, which is in large part genetically determined, is thought to be an important host determinant of cancer incidence. A number of epidemiological studies have evaluated the association between CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms and colorectal cancer risk, but the results remain inconclusive. In order to resolve this conflict, this meta-analysis of 39 eligible studies including 5,817 cases and 6,544 controls for CYP1A2*F (from 13 studies), 9,219 cases and 10,406 controls for CYP1B1 Leu432Val (from 12 studies), 6,840 cases and 7,761 controls for CYP1B1 Asn453Ser (from 8 studies), and 4,302 cases and 4,791 controls for CYP1B1 Arg48Gly (from 6 studies) was performed to derive a more precise estimation of the association between CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms and risk of colorectal cancer.</p>
<p>Overall, no significant association was found between CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly when all the eligible studies were pooled into the meta-analysis. And in the subgroup, no evidence of significant association was also observed in any subgroup. Sachse et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Zhao1">[33]</xref> in 2002 and Küry et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Kry1">[24]</xref> in 2007 reported that CYP1B1 Leu432Val was not associated with increased the risk of colorectal cancer. Landi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Landi1">[27]</xref> and Huber et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Huber1">[37]</xref> in 2005 reported that CYP1B1 Leu432Val and Asn453Ser polymorphisms were also not associated with increased the risk of colorectal cancer. Cleary et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Cleary1">[18]</xref> in 2010 found that CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly were not associated with increased the risk of colorectal cancer. Sachse et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Sachse1">[21]</xref> in 2002, Yoshida et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Yoshida1">[22]</xref> in 2007, Kiss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Kiss1">[23]</xref> in 2007, and Cleary et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Cleary1">[18]</xref> reported that CYP1A2*F, was not associated with increased the risk of colorectal cancer. The results of our meta-analysis supported the negative association between CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms and colorectal cancer risk. However, a careful matching should be considered in future larger genetic association studies including multiple ethnic groups.</p>
<p>We noticed that 3 previous meta-analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Zhao1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Mei1">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Xie1">[58]</xref> had been reported on the colorectal cancer risk with CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, and Asn453Ser polymorphisms. We have read with great interest the meta-analysis by Mei et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Mei1">[57]</xref> and Xie et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Xie1">[58]</xref>. Mei et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Kry2">[35]</xref> had 7 studies including 6,375 cases and 7,003 controls. The pooled analysis suggested that no significant association was found between the CYP1B1 Asn453Ser polymorphism and the risk of colorectal cancer among Caucasians. Xie et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Xie1">[58]</xref> had 10 studies including 8,466 cases and 9,301 for Leu432Val. Their meta-analyses suggested that CYP1B1 Leu432Val were not associated with colorectal cancer risk. However, the study of Northwood et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Northwood1">[30]</xref> should be excluded in the meta-analyses of Mei et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Mei1">[57]</xref> and Xie et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Xie1">[58]</xref> because they performed CYP1B1 Leu432Val with colorectal adenoma risk but not colorectal cancer. Adopting the same search strategy as Mei et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Mei1">[57]</xref> and Xie et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Xie1">[58]</xref>, we identified 4 additional eligible studies, which have not been included in the meta-analysis of Xie et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Bethke1">[36]</xref>. Worthy of note, these 4 studies included 3,638 samples. Zhao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Zhao1">[33]</xref> included 11 studies. Their meta-analysis suggests that the CYP1A2*F polymorphism is a protective factor against CRC among Asians. The OR (95% CI) reported by Zhao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Zhao1">[33]</xref> for the study by Bae et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Bae1">[25]</xref> do not seem in line with the OR (95% CI) provided by Bae et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Bae1">[25]</xref> in their original publication. The OR (95% CI) reported by Zhao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Zhao1">[33]</xref> in additive model are 0.56 (0.38–0.84). Interestingly enough, after carefully studying the OR (95% CI) presented by Bae et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Bae1">[25]</xref>, The OR (95% CI) were 1.77 (1.18–2.66). In addition, the study of Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Wang3">[59]</xref> should be excluded in the meta-analysis of Zhao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Zhao1">[33]</xref> because the data on CYP1A2*F polymorphism with colorectal cancer risk did not be found in the study of Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Wang3">[59]</xref>. Adopting the same search strategy as Zhao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Zhao1">[33]</xref>, we identified 3 additional eligible studies, which have not been included in the meta-analysis of Zhao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Zhao1">[33]</xref>. Worthy of note, these 3 studies included 2687 samples. Having analyzed an almost twofold larger number of studies than the previous meta-analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Zhao1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Mei1">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Xie1">[58]</xref>, our results seem to confirm and establish the trend in the meta-analysis of CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms that the data by the previous meta-analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Zhao1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Mei1">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Xie1">[58]</xref> had indicated. The results of the present meta-analysis are not in accordance with those reported by Zhao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0100487-Zhao1">[33]</xref>. Our meta-analysis indicates that CYP1A2*F are not associated with colorectal cancer risk.</p>
<p>There are several limitations in this meta-analysis. First, the controls were not uniformly defined. Although most of them were common populations, some controls were population-based; other controls were hospital-based. Hence, non–differential misclassification bias is possible. Second, in the subgroup analysis may have had insufficient statistical power to check an association, Third, we were also unable to examine the interactions among gene-environment, lacking of the original data of the included studies limited our further evaluation of potential interactions, which may be an important component of the association between CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms and environment and colorectal cancer risk. Last, our results were based on unadjusted published estimates. Because of data limitations, we were unable to adjust them such as age and alcohol consumption et al.</p>
<p>In summary, this meta-analysis indicates that CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly are not associated with colorectal cancer. However, it is necessary to conduct large sample studies using standardized unbiased genotyping methods, homogeneous cancer patients and well-matched controls. Moreover, further studies estimating the effect of gene–gene and gene–environment interactions may eventually lead to our better, comprehensive understanding of the association between the CYP1A2*F, CYP1B1 Leu432Val, Asn453Ser, and Arg48Gly polymorphisms and colorectal cancer risk.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0100487.s001" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0100487.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Checklist S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>PRISMA Checklist.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Ishibe1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishibe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kulldorff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strickland</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Genetic polymorphisms in heterocyclic amine metabolism and risk of colorectal adenomas</article-title>. <source>Pharmacogenetics</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Jemal1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Cancer statistics, 2010</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-GerhardssondeVerdier1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerhardsson de Verdier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagman</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steineck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rieger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norell</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Diet, body mass and colorectal cancer: a case-referent study in Stockholm</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>832</fpage>–<lpage>838</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Cope1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinder</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heatley</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Alcohol consumption in patients with colorectal adenomatous polyps</article-title>. <source>Gut</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Levin1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Nutrition and colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>1723</fpage>–<lpage>1726</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Ishibe2"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishibe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kulldorff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strickland</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Physical activity in relation to cancer of the colon and rectum in a cohort of male smokers</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Kushi1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kushi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giovannucci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Dietary fat and cancer</article-title>. <source>Am J Med</source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>63S</fpage>–<lpage>70S</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Potter1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Nutrition and colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Causes Control</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Norat1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Norat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slimani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jenab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Meat, fish, and colorectal cancer risk: the European Prospective Investigation into cancer and nutrition</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Indy</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>906</fpage>–<lpage>916</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Buters1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buters</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pineau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Cytochrome P450 CYP1B1 determines susceptibility to 7, 12-dimethylbenz (a) anthraceneinduced lymphomas</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>1977</fpage>–<lpage>1982</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Shimada1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Activation of chemically diverse procarcinogens by human cytochrome P-450 1B1</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>2979</fpage>–<lpage>2984</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Murray1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McFadyen</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenlee</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Tumor-specific expression of cytochrome P450 CYP1B1</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>3026</fpage>–<lpage>3031</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Kim1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stansbury</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trush</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strickland</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Metabolism of benzo[a]pyrene and benzo[a]pyrene-7,8-diol by human cytochrome P450 1B1</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1847</fpage>–<lpage>1853</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Stoilov1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoilov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akarsu</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alozie</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Child</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barsoum-Homsy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Sequence analysis and homology modeling suggest that primary congenital glaucoma on 2p21 results from mutations disrupting either the hinge region or the conserved core structures of Cytochrome P4501B1</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>584</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Wang1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corral</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegmund</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Carcinogen metabolism genes, red meat and poultry intake, and colorectal cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>1898</fpage>–<lpage>1907</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Rudolph1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sainz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Modification of menopausal hormone therapy-associated colorectal cancer risk by polymorphisms in sex steroid signaling, metabolism and transport related genes</article-title>. <source>Endocr Relat Cancer</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Sainz1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sainz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Association of genetic polymorphisms in ESR2, HSD17B1, ABCB1, and SHBG genes with colorectal cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Endocr Relat Cancer</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Cleary1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cotterchio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Cigarette smoking, genetic variants in carcinogen-metabolizing enzymes, and colorectal cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>172</volume>: <fpage>1000</fpage>–<lpage>1014</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Kobayashi1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Natsukawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Association between dietary heterocyclic amine levels, genetic polymorphisms of NAT2, CYP1A1, and CYP1A2 and risk of colorectal cancer: a hospital-based case-control study in Japan</article-title>. <source>Scand J Gastroenterol</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>952</fpage>–<lpage>959</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Saeb1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saebø</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skjelbred</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brekke Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowitz Lothe</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>CYP1A2 164 A-&gt;C polymorphism, cigarette smoking, consumption of well-done red meat and risk of developing colorectal adenomas and carcinomas</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Res</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2289</fpage>–<lpage>2295</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Sachse1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sachse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkie</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waxman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A pharmacogenetic study to investigate the role of dietary carcinogens in the etiology of colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1839</fpage>–<lpage>1849</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Yoshida1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kasahara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miyaishi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Association of CYP1A1, CYP1A2, GSTM1 and NAT2 gene polymorphisms with colorectal cancer and smoking</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>438</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Kiss1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orsós</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gombos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bogner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Csejtei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Association between allelic polymorphisms of metabolizing enzymes (CYP 1A1, CYP 1A2, CYP 2E1, mEH) and occurrence of colorectal cancer in Hungary</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Res</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>2931</fpage>–<lpage>2937</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Kry1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Küry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buecher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robiou-du-Pont</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scoul</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sébille</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Combinations of cytochrome P450 gene polymorphisms enhancing the risk for sporadic colorectal cancer related to red meat consumption</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1460</fpage>–<lpage>1467</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Bae1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Effects of genetic polymorphisms of MDR1, FMO3 and CYP1A2 on susceptibility to colorectal cancer in Koreans</article-title>. <source>Cancer Sci</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>774</fpage>–<lpage>779</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Chen1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>QT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A case–control study on the association between genetic polymorphisms of metabolic enzymes and the risk of colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>659</fpage>–<lpage>664</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Landi1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gemignani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gioia-Patricola</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chabrier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A comprehensive analysis of phase I and phase II metabolism gene polymorphisms and risk of colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Pharmacogenet Genomics</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>546</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Rudolph2"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sainz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Modification of menopausal hormone therapy-associated colorectal cancer risk by polymorphisms in sex steroid signaling, metabolism and transport related genes</article-title>. <source>Endocr Relat Cancer</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Sainz2"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sainz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Association of genetic polymorphisms in ESR2, HSD17B1, ABCB1, and SHBG genes with colorectal cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Endocr Relat Cancer</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Northwood1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Northwood</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkie</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Polymorphisms in xenobiotic metabolizing enzymes and diet influence colorectal adenoma risk</article-title>. <source>Pharmacogenet Genomics</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Hlavata1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hlavata</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vrana</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smerhovsky</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pardini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naccarati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Association between exposure-relevant polymorphisms in CYP1B1, EPHX1, NQO1, GSTM1, GSTP1 and GSTT1 and risk of colorectal cancer in a Czech population</article-title>. <source>Oncol Rep</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1347</fpage>–<lpage>1353</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Trubicka1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trubicka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grabowska-Kłujszo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suchy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masojć</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano-Fernandez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Variant alleles of the CYP1B1 gene are associated with colorectal cancer susceptibility</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>420</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Zhao1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rewuti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Quantitative Assessment of the Influence of Cytochrome P450 1A2 Gene Polymorphism and Colorectal Cancer Risk</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e71481</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Cotterchio1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cotterchio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okey</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Red meat intake, doneness, polymorphisms in genes that encode carcinogen-metabolizing enzymes, and colorectal cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>3098</fpage>–<lpage>3107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Kry2"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Küry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buecher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robiou-du-Pont</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scoul</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sébille</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Combinations of cytochrome P450 gene polymorphisms enhancing the risk for sporadic colorectal cancer related to red meat consumption</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1460</fpage>–<lpage>1467</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Bethke1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bethke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sellick</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penegar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Polymorphisms in the cytochrome P450 genes CYP1A2, CYP1B1, CYP3A4, CYP3A5, CYP11A1, CYP17A1, CYP19A1 and colorectal cancer risk</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Huber1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bentz</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneeberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hefler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Ten polymorphisms of estrogen-metabolizing genes and a family history of colon cancer-an association study of multiple gene-gene interactions</article-title>. <source>J Soc Gynecol Investig</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>e51</fpage>–<lpage>e54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Landi2"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gemignani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gioia-Patricola</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chabrier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A comprehensive analysis of phase I and phase II metabolism gene polymorphisms and risk of colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Pharmacogenet Genomics</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>546</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Wang2"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corral</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegmund</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Carcinogen metabolism genes, red meat and poultry intake, and colorectal cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>1898</fpage>–<lpage>1907</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Yamazaki1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guengerich</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Role of cytochromes P450 1A2 and 3A4 in the oxidation of estradiol and estrone in human liver microsomes</article-title>. <source>Chem Res Toxicol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>659</fpage>–<lpage>665</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Nebert1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nebert</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The role of cytochrome P450 enzymes in endogenous signalling pathways and environmental carcinogenesis</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>947</fpage>–<lpage>960</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Tsuchiya1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Cytochrome P450-mediated metabolism of estrogens and its regulation in human</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source> <volume>227</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Nebert2"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nebert</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okey</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Role of aryl hydrocarbon receptor-mediated induction of the CYP1 enzymes in environmental toxicity and cancer</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>23847</fpage>–<lpage>23850</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Nebert3"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nebert</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKinnon</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Puga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Human drugmetabolizing enzyme polymorphisms: effects on risk of toxicity and cancer</article-title>. <source>DNA Cell Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Eaton1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bammler</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunze</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Role of cytochrome P4501A2 in chemical carcinogenesis: implications for human variability in expression and enzyme activity</article-title>. <source>Pharmacogenetics</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>27420</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Nakajima1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Funayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Genetic polymorphism in the 5′-flanking region of humanCYP1A2 gene: effect on theCYP1A2 inducibility in humans,</article-title>. <source>J Biochem</source> <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>803</fpage>–<lpage>808</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Davey1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Meta-analyses of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>350</volume>: <fpage>1182</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Ioannidis1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boffetta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uitterlinden</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Assessment of cumulative evidence on genetic associations: interim guidelines</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>120</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Mantel1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haenszel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1959</year>) <article-title>Statistical aspects of the analysis of data from retrospective studies of disease</article-title>. <source>Natl Cancer Inst</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage>–<lpage>778</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-DerSimonian1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DerSimonian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Control Clin Trials</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Klug1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klug</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ressing</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abba</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agorastos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>TP53 codon 72 polymorphism and cervical cancer: a pooled analysis of individual data from 49 studies</article-title>. <source>Lancet Oncol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>772</fpage>–<lpage>784</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Begg1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>1101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Egger1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Williams1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Metabolic activation of carcinogens and expression of various cytochromes P450 in human prostate tissue</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1683</fpage>–<lpage>1689</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Cavalieri1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalieri</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devanesan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bosland</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Badawi</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogan</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Catechol estrogen metabolites and conjugates in different regions of the prostate of Noble rats treated with 4-hydroxyestradiol: implications for estrogen-induced initiation of prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>333</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-McManus1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veronese</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huggett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quattrochi</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Metabolism of 2-acetylaminofl uorene and benzo(a)pyrene and activation of food-derived heterocyclic amine mutagens by human cytochromes P-450</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>3367</fpage>–<lpage>3376</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Mei1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>CYP1B1 Asn453Ser polymorphism and colorectal cancer risk: a meta-analysis. Metabolism</article-title>. <source>2012</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1321</fpage>–<lpage>1329</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Xie1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>CYP1B1 Leu432Val polymorphism and colorectal cancer risk among Caucasians: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Tumour Biol</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>809</fpage>–<lpage>816</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0100487-Wang3"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caberto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saltzman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genetic variation in the bioactivation pathway for polycyclic hydrocarbons and heterocyclic amines in relation to risk of colorectal neoplasia</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>