<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-11787</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102910</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Pediatric epidemiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neurology</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurological tumors</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Pediatric oncology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Pediatrics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Meta-Analysis of Parental Smoking and the Risk of Childhood Brain Tumors</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Parental Smoking and Childhood Brain Tumors</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Jianrong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>Huan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>GuanYan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ChunZhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Department of Neurosurgery, Guangxi Minzu Hospital, Nanning, Guangxi Province, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Jeffrey S.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>National Health Research Institutes, Taiwan</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">yhuang1966@163.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YH. Performed the experiments: YH JH CH. Analyzed the data: YH HL GZ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YH HL GZ CH. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: YH JH.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<elocation-id>e102910</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Huang et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract><sec>
<title>Objective</title>
<p>Previous studies regarding the association between parental smoking and the risk of childhood brain tumors (CBT) have reported inconsistent results. We performed a meta-analysis to summarize evidence on this association and to quantify the potential dose-response relationship.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>A systematic literature search was conducted in the Medline and Embase databases. The summary relative risks (RRs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated. Dose–response meta-analysis was also performed for studies that reported categorical risk estimates for a series of smoking exposure levels.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>A total of 17 studies fulfilled the inclusion criteria. In the meta-analyses, the summary RRs (95% CIs) of CBT for maternal smoking during pregnancy, paternal smoking during pregnancy, maternal smoking before pregnancy, and paternal smoking before pregnancy were 0.96 (0.86–1.07), 1.09 (0.97–1.22), 0.93 (0.85–1.00), and 1.09 (1.00–1.20), respectively. Dose-response meta-analysis also showed no significant association between parental smoking and the risk of CBT.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Findings from our meta-analysis indicate that parental smoking may not be associated with a risk of CBT.</p>
</sec></abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Childhood brain tumors (CBT) are one of the most common types of cancers in infants and children (behind hematological malignancies) and they account for approximately 20 to 25% of total primary pediatric tumor diagnoses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Mueller1">[1]</xref>. Their 5-year survival ranges from &gt;90% to &lt;10% for various histological subtypes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Gajjar1">[2]</xref>. A small percentage of these tumors are found in the setting of an identifiable cancer predisposition syndrome, such as neurofibromatosis and melanoma–astrocytoma syndrome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Kyritsis1">[3]</xref>. However, for most sporadic cases, little is known about the genetic or environmental etiologies.</p>
<p>Cigarette smoking is a major cause of illness and death worldwide. The first phase of Global Adult Tobacco Survey (GATS) reported that a high percentage of men smoke, women begin smoking early, and few successfully quit smoking <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Giovino1">[4]</xref>. It has been hypothesized that some cancers may begin during the early stages of fetal development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Klip1">[5]</xref>. The exposure to environmental cigarette smoke during pregnancy could lead to DNA mutations and cytogenetic damage and has been shown to act as a transplacental carcinogen in animal studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Anderson1">[6]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Izzotti1">[8]</xref>. Increased levels of carcinogenic tobacco-specific nitrosamines could be detected in the urine samples of newborns and the amniotic fluid in early pregnancy of parents who smoked cigarettes during pregnancy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Lackmann1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Milunsky1">[11]</xref>. Therefore, parental smoking, which is relatively frequent, may play a role in tumorigenesis of CBT and require further exploration.</p>
<p>However, epidemiological studies on a possible association between parental smoking and the risk of CBT have provided no definitive answers. Overall, the published literature remains inconclusive and inconsistent. For example, a Sweden cohort study and an Italian case–control study suggested a positive association between maternal smoking during pregnancy and the risk of CBT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Brooks1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Filippini1">[13]</xref>, whereas a UK case–control study reported a negative association between them <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Pang1">[14]</xref>. Because of the relatively small number of cases included in the individual studies, we performed a comprehensive meta-analysis to summarize the evidence on whether parental smoking is associated with the risk of CBT.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Search Strategy</title>
<p>We conducted a literature search (up to January 2014) of Medline and Embase for studies examining the association between parental smoking and the risk of CBT. The search terms were (case-control OR cohort OR epidemiolog*) AND (cancer OR carcinoma OR neoplasms OR tumor OR tumour) AND (brain OR cerebral OR intracranial OR central nervous system OR glioma OR glioblastoma OR astrocytoma OR craniopharyngioma OR medulloblastoma OR PNET OR ependymomas) AND (smoke OR smoking OR cigarette OR tobacco) for Medline. Similar search terms were used for Embase. We searched articles published in any language and scrutinized references cited by these studies to identify further pertinent studies. This meta-analysis followed the standard criteria for conducting meta-analyses of observational studies and reporting the results <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Stroup1">[15]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Study selection</title>
<p>We applied the following inclusion criteria: the study used a cohort or case-control design, the exposure of interest was parental smoking, the outcome was CBT and the investigators provided the minimum information necessary to estimate the relative risk (RR) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs). We excluded animal studies, cross sectional studies, reviews, editorials, commentaries, and letters without sufficient data. If data sets overlapped or were duplicated, the most up-to-date or comprehensive information was included.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Data extraction</title>
<p>Data were extracted independently by two authors and any disagreements were resolved by consensus. The following information was recorded: the first author's last name, year of publication, study location, types of CBT, sample size (cases and controls or cohort size), exposure (smoking levels for each category) assessment method, outcome (CBT) ascertainment, covariates adjusted for in the analysis, and RR estimates with corresponding 95% CIs for each category. If available, we used the RRs that reflected the greatest degree of control for potential confounders.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>RR was used as a measure of the association between parental smoking and the risk of CBT. For case-control studies, the odds ratio (OR) was used as a surrogate measure of the corresponding RR. Because the absolute risk of CBT is low, the OR approximates the RR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Greenland1">[16]</xref>.</p>
<p>Summary RRs (95% CI) were calculated by combining the study-specific RR estimates with the DerSimonian Laird method (random effects model) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-DerSimonian1">[17]</xref>. In the dose–response meta-analysis, we used the method described by Greenland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Greenland2">[18]</xref> and Orsini <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Orsini1">[19]</xref> to calculate the trend from the correlated estimates for relative risk across smoking categories. The midpoint of the upper and lower boundaries in each category was assigned as the corresponding dose of consumption. If the highest category was open ended, we assumed the width of the interval to be the same as the width in the preceding category. We explored a potential curvilinear relationship between parental smoking and the risk of CBT using restricted cubic splines with three knots at percentiles 25%, 50%, and 75% of the distribution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Harrell1">[20]</xref>. A <italic>P</italic> value for nonlinearity was calculated by testing the null hypothesis that the coefficient of the second spline was equal to 0.</p>
<p>We calculated the Q statistic (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.1 was considered to be indicative of statistically significant heterogeneity) and I<sup>2</sup> statistic (I<sup>2</sup>&lt;25% no heterogeneity; I<sup>2</sup> = 25% to 50% low heterogeneity; I<sup>2</sup> = 50% to 75% moderate heterogeneity; I<sup>2</sup>&gt;75% large or extreme heterogeneity) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Higgins1">[21]</xref> to assess heterogeneity across studies. We also conducted analyses stratified by study design, study location, histological subtype, number of cases and publication year. Influence analysis was performed, in which the summary estimates were computed after the omission of each study in turn. An estimation of potential publication bias was evaluated by Begg's adjusted rank correlation test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Begg1">[22]</xref> and Egger's regression asymmetry test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Egger1">[23]</xref>. All statistical tests were conducted with the STATA software (version 11.0; Stata Corporation, College Station, Texas). <italic>P</italic> values were two sided with a significance level of 0.05.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Literature search</title>
<p>A flow diagram of our literature search and study selection is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102910-g001">Figure 1</xref>. We identified 843 unique citations from Medline and Embase. After excluding studies that did not meet our inclusion criteria, 29 remaining articles appeared to be potentially relevant for this meta-analysis. After evaluating the full texts of these publications, we further excluded 14 articles for the following reasons: duplicate reports from the same study population (n = 8); no data on CBT (n = 3); lack of sufficient data to calculate RR and 95% CIs (n = 2); adult patients included (n = 1). A manual search of references cited by these papers yielded 2 new eligible articles. Therefore, we finally included 17 articles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Brooks1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Pang1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Milne1">[24]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Stjernfeldt1">[37]</xref> in the meta-analysis.</p>
<fig id="pone-0102910-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Flowchart of study assessment and selection.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Study Characteristics</title>
<p>The 17 studies were published between 1986 and 2013, involving a total of 5,098 cases. Of these studies, 6 were conducted in North America <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-BarringtonTrimis1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Bunin1">[32]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Howe1">[36]</xref>, 6 in Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Brooks1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Pang1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Plichart1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Schuz1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Stjernfeldt1">[37]</xref>, 2 in Australia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Milne1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Stavrou1">[26]</xref>, 2 in China <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Hu1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Ji1">[31]</xref> and 1 was multi-centered <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Filippini2">[28]</xref>. 2 studies were cohort studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Brooks1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Stavrou1">[26]</xref>, and 15 were case-control studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Filippini1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Pang1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Milne1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-BarringtonTrimis1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Plichart1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Stjernfeldt1">[37]</xref>. Of the 17 studies, 16 had information on maternal smoking during pregnancy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Brooks1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Pang1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Milne1">[24]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Hu1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Bunin1">[32]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Stjernfeldt1">[37]</xref>, 7 had data on maternal smoking before pregnancy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Filippini1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Pang1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Milne1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Filippini2">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Hu1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Gold1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-John1">[34]</xref>, 9 on paternal smoking during pregnancy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Milne1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-BarringtonTrimis1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Plichart1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Schuz1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Hu1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Bunin1">[32]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-John1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Howe1">[36]</xref>, and 7 on paternal smoking before pregnancy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Filippini1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Pang1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Milne1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Filippini2">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Hu1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Ji1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Gold1">[33]</xref>. 8 studies considered all brain cancers together only <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Milne1">[24]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Stavrou1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Hu1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Ji1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-John1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Howe1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Stjernfeldt1">[37]</xref>, 1 considered astrocytoma only <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Kuijten1">[35]</xref>, and 8 considered several subtypes of CBT and provided separate analyses for these cancer subtypes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Brooks1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Pang1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Plichart1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Schuz1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Bunin1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Gold1">[33]</xref>. In 12 of the 15 incident case-control studies, controls were matched for age and sex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Filippini1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Pang1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Milne1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-BarringtonTrimis1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Plichart1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Ji1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Gold1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-John1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Howe1">[36]</xref>. The numbers of cases and controls or cohort, types of CBT, exposure assessment method, and outcome ascertainment were shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102910-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0102910-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Study characteristics of published cohort and case–control studies on parental smoking and the risk of childhood brain tumors.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0102910-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure assessment</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome ascertainment</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis criteria</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matched factors</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Types of CBT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls or cohort</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barrington-Trimis et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In-person interview</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEER registries</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD-O-1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex, center</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astroglial</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">285</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNET</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Milne et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mailed questionnaire</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pediatric oncology center</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex, state</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gliomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">941</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embryonal tumors</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germ cell tumors</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ependymomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stavrou et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midwives Data Collection</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Cancer Registry</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD-O-3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total CBT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,045,966</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plichart et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Telephone interview</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">French National Registry</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD-O-3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embryonal tumors</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,681</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ependymomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brooks et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swedish Birth Register</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swedish Cancer Register</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ependymoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,441,942</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medulloblastoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pang et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interview</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pediatric oncology units</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD-O-2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex, residence area</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total CBT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">635</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,987</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filippini et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multicenter</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interviewed in person</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer registries</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD-O-2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astroglial tumor</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">623</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,223</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNET</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schuz et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Questionnaire, telephone interview</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood Cancer Registry</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,458</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medulloblastoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ependymoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filippini et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Telephone interview</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital records</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD-9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex, residence area</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astroglial tumours</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">502</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNET</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hu et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interview</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Six major hospitals</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex, residence area</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">246</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medulloepithelioma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Craniopharyngioma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ji et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct interview</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer Registry</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICD-9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total CBT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bunin et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1994</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA and Canada</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Telephone interview</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Children's Cancer Group</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, race, residence area</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNET</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gold et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Structured interview</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEER program registries</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex, mother's race</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,083</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medulloblastoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">John et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1991</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Structured interviews</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer Registry</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex, residence area</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total CBT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kuitjen et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1990</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Telephone interview</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor registries</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, race, residence area</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Howe et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1989</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In-person interview</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital records</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, sex</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medulloblastoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ependymoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stjernfeldt et al</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1986</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total CBT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>PCC population based case-control, HCC hospital based case-control, NR not reported.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Quantitative synthesis</title>
<p>The pooled RRs between parental smoking and the risk of CBT were not statistically significant and close to unity (RR = 0.96, 95% CI 0.86–1.07 for maternal smoking during pregnancy; RR = 1.09, 95% CI 0.97–1.22 for paternal smoking during pregnancy; RR = 0.93, 95% CI 0.85–1.00 for maternal smoking before pregnancy; RR = 1.09, 95% CI 1.00–1.20 for paternal smoking before pregnancy) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102910-g002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102910.s002">S1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0102910-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Forest plot of maternal smoking during pregnancy and the risk of CBT.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>In the stratified analysis by study region, histological subtype, number of cases, and publication year, no significant associations were observed in any of the categories (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102910-t002">Tables 2</xref>–<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102910-t005">5</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0102910-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Results of subgroup analyses of the association between maternal smoking during pregnancy and the risk of childhood brain tumors.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0102910-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterogeneity test</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR (95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sup>2</sup> (95%CI) (%)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (12–14,24–30,32–37)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.86–1.07)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2 (1.6–60.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study design</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (12,26)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.72–1.58)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.0 (-)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case–control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (13,14,24,25,27–30,32–37)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.84–1.00)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 (0.0–56.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographical region</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.816</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North America</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (25,32–36)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.76–1.11)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–74.62)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (12–14,27,29,37)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.84–1.27)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.2 (16.3–85.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (24,26)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.64–1.16)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (-)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (30)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 (0.45–3.23)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological subtype</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNET</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (12–14,27–29,32,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.74–1.06)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.58</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–67.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (12–14,27–29,32,33,35)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.93–1.18)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.69</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–64.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ependymomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (12,14,27,29)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.72–1.66)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9 (0.0–73.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of cases</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.492</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤ 300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (13,25–27,30,34–37)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.83–1.25)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1 (0.0–58.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (12,14,24,28,29,32,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.83–1.06)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.2 (0.0–75.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publication year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.289</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (13,30,32–37)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.88–1.24)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–67.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (12,14,24–29)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.80–1.06)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.1 (0.0–77.7)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>* <italic>P</italic> for heterogeneity of the stratum-specific summary RRs.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0102910-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Results of subgroup analyses of the association between paternal smoking during pregnancy and the risk of childhood brain tumors</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0102910-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterogeneity test</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR (95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sup>2</sup> (95%CI) (%)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (24,25,27,29,30,32–34,36)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.97–1.22)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–64.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographical region</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.892</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North America</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (25,32–34,36)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.85–1.25)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–79.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (27,29)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (0.96–1.34)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (-)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (24)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.74–1.46)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (30)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.67–2.04)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological subtype</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNET</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (27,29,32,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (0.88–1.37)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–84.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (27,29,32,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (0.79–1.61)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.1 (0.0–84.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ependymomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (27,29)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 (0.99–2.20)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (-)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of cases</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.160</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤ 300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (25,27,30,34,36)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.96–1.45)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–79.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (24,29,32,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.91–1.20)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–84.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publication year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.673</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (30,32–34,36)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.86–1.28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–79.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (24,25,27,29)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.96–1.28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–84.7)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>* <italic>P</italic> for heterogeneity of the stratum-specific summary RRs.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0102910-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>Results of subgroup analyses of the association between maternal smoking before pregnancy and the risk of childhood brain tumors.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0102910-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterogeneity test</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR (95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sup>2</sup> (95%CI) (%)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (13,14,24,28,30,33,34)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.85–1.00)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–70.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographical region</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.839</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North America</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33,34)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.69–1.15)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (-)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (13,14)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.79–1.31)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.6 (-)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (24)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.70–1.40)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (30)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 (0.10–3.80)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological subtype</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNET</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (14,28,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.69–1.09)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–89.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (14,28,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.80–1.03)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–89.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ependymomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 (0.40–1.35)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of cases</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.427</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (13,30,34)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.85–1.53)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–89.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (14,24,28,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.83–0.99)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–84.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publication year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.962</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤ 2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13,30,33,34)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.82–1.21)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–84.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (14,24,28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.83–1.00)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–89.6)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>* <italic>P</italic> for heterogeneity of the stratum-specific summary RRs.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0102910-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption>
<title>Results of subgroup analyses of the association between paternal smoking before pregnancy and the risk of childhood brain tumors.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0102910-t005-5" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Heterogeneity test</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR (95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sup>2</sup> (95%CI) (%)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (13,14,24,28,30,31,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (1.00–1.20)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–70.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographical region</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.605</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North America</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.83–1.41)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (13,14)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.93–1.25)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (-)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (24)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.71–1.38)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (30,31)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 (0.90–2.24)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 (-)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological subtype</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNET</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (14,28,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.77–1.16)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–89.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrocytomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (14,28,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.95–1.28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–89.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ependymomas</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.59–1.78)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of cases</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤ 300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (13,30,31)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 (0.98–1.64)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–89.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (14,24,28,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.97–1.18)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–84.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publication year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤ 2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13,30,31,33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.98–1.41)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–84.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (14,24,28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.96–1.19)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0–89.6)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>* <italic>P</italic> for heterogeneity of the stratum-specific summary RRs.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Dose-response analysis</title>
<p>Using a restricted cubic splines model, we did not find a curvilinear association between parental smoking and the risk of CBT (<italic>P</italic> = 0.619, 0.638, 0.924, and 0.749 for non-linearity, respectively). The summary RRs of CBT for an increase of 10 cigarettes per day were 0.98 (95% CI 0.92-1.04; <italic>P</italic> = 0.506 for linear trend), 1.04 (95% CI 0.98-1.11; <italic>P</italic> = 0.196 for linear trend), 0.95 (95% CI 0.89-1.02; <italic>P</italic> = 0.179 for linear trend), and 1.02 (95% CI 0.96-1.07; <italic>P</italic> = 0.598 for linear trend) for maternal smoking during pregnancy, paternal smoking during pregnancy, maternal smoking before pregnancy, and paternal smoking before pregnancy, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102910-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102910.s003">S2</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0102910-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Dose-response analysis of maternal smoking during pregnancy and the risk of CBT.</title>
<p>The solid line represents point estimates of association between maternal smoking during pregnancy and CBT risk; dashed lines are 95% CIs. Circles are the dose-specific RR estimates. The relative size of each circle is proportional to the inverse variance of the RR.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Influence analysis</title>
<p>In the influence analysis, the influence of each study on the pooled RR was examined by repeating the meta-analysis while omitting each study, one at a time. The study-specific RRs ranged from the lowest values of 0.91 (95% CI 0.83-0.99), 1.06 (95% CI 0.94-1.21), 0.91 (95% CI 0.93-0.99), and 1.08 (95% CI 0.99-1.19) to the highest values of 0.99 (95% CI 0.89-1.10), 1.12 (95% CI 0.98-1.27), 0.96 (95% CI 0.85-1.08), and 1.11 (95% CI 1.00-1.24) for maternal smoking during pregnancy, paternal smoking during pregnancy, maternal smoking before pregnancy, and paternal smoking before pregnancy, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102910.s004">Figure S3</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3f">
<title>Evaluation of heterogeneity</title>
<p>For maternal smoking during pregnancy, low to moderate between-study heterogeneity was observed for the pooled RR (I<sup>2</sup> = 28.2%, 95% CI 1.6%-60.7%) and several subgroup results, including cohort studies (I<sup>2</sup> = 59.0%), studies conducted in Europe (I<sup>2</sup> = 65.2%, 95% CI 16.3%-85.5%), Ependymomas (I<sup>2</sup> = 28.9%, 95% CI 0.0%-73.8%), studies of cases &gt; 300 (I<sup>2</sup> = 42.2%, 95% CI 0.0%-75.7%), and studies published after 2000 (I<sup>2</sup> = 50.1%, 95% CI 0.0%-77.7%).</p>
<p>For paternal smoking during pregnancy, there was no obvious heterogeneity between studies, except for Astrocytomas (I<sup>2</sup> = 52.1%, 95% CI 0.0%-84.2%); for maternal smoking before pregnancy, moderate heterogeneity was observed for studies conducted in Europe (I<sup>2</sup> = 51.6%); for paternal smoking before pregnancy, no heterogeneity was found in any of the categories.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3g">
<title>Publication bias</title>
<p>There was no evidence of significant publication bias according to the Begg and Egger tests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102910-g004">Figure 4</xref>, Begg, <italic>P</italic> = 0.528, Egger, <italic>P</italic> = 0.790 for maternal smoking during pregnancy; Begg, <italic>P</italic> = 0.348, Egger, <italic>P</italic> = 0.420 for paternal smoking during pregnancy; Begg, <italic>P</italic> = 0.764, Egger, <italic>P</italic> = 0.610 for maternal smoking before pregnancy; Begg, <italic>P</italic> = 0.368, Egger, <italic>P</italic> = 0.189 for paternal smoking before pregnancy).</p>
<fig id="pone-0102910-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Funnel plot of maternal smoking during pregnancy and the risk of CBT.</title>
<p>The area of each square is proportional to the study's weight (inverse of variance).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this systematic review of epidemiological studies, no clear relationship was found between parental smoking and the risk of CBT. Similar results were obtained in dose-response analysis and stratified analysis. Although some of the summary RRs (maternal smoking before pregnancy and paternal smoking before pregnancy) were borderline significant, the magnitudes of these associations were quite modest and within the range in which various sources of bias could explain them. Our findings were based on a total of 17 studies (including over 5,000 cancer cases) without obvious heterogeneity and publication bias. However, limited data were available for certain subgroups (e.g., cohort studies, studies conducted in Asia). Therefore, these results should be interpreted with caution.</p>
<p>Low to moderate between-study heterogeneity was observed for several pooled RRs and subgroup results. For example, low between-study heterogeneity was observed (I<sup>2</sup> = 28.2%, 95% CI 1.6%-60.7%) for maternal smoking during pregnancy, which was not surprising given the differences in study design, characteristics of populations, histological subtypes, and adjustment for confounding factors. Influence analysis suggested that after omitting some specific studies, the pooled RRs of remaining studies became significant, which indicated that some combined RRs of this meta-analysis were not very steady. For example, the omission of the study conducted by Brooks et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Brooks1">[12]</xref> led to a significant inverse association between maternal smoking during pregnancy and CBT risk. This may be because Brooks et al's study is a prospective cohort study, which included large samples (1,441,942 Swedish births) and reported a significant positive association between maternal smoking during pregnancy and CBT risk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Brooks1">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>Currently, a variety of genetic syndromes, including NF1, NF2, TSC1, TSC2, and VHL, have been causally linked to CBT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Pollack1">[38]</xref>. However, the environmental risk factors of brain tumors have not been fully established. The only recognized factor is exposure to ionizing radiation, which has been widely reported as significantly increasing the risk of CBT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Vinchon1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Baldwin1">[40]</xref>. Other environmental factors, such as cured meats, certain viruses (e.g., JC virus, SV40, etc.), parental heat exposure before pregnancy and fertility treatment, have shown inconsistent associations with CBT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Baldwin1">[40]</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Hargreave1">[42]</xref>. Although the relationship between parental smoking and CBT risk is biologically plausible, the epidemiological data are complex. Meta-analysis is a useful tool for revealing trends that might not be apparent in individual studies. Using this method, our study doesn't support that parental smoking is an environmental risk factor of CBT.</p>
<p>The largest number of available studies on a specific type of parental smoking was for maternal smoking during pregnancy (n = 16). Consistent with a previous meta-analysis published in 2002 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Huncharek1">[43]</xref>, our meta-analysis also found no association between maternal smoking during pregnancy and the risk of CBT. Previous studies have reported that maternal smoking during pregnancy is a possible risk factor for stillbirth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Flenady1">[44]</xref>, child overweight <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Oken1">[45]</xref> and childhood NHL <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Antonopoulos1">[46]</xref> but not for childhood HL <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Antonopoulos1">[46]</xref>, leukemia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Klimentopoulou1">[47]</xref> or testicular cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Tuomisto1">[48]</xref>. Therefore, maternal smoking may have different effects on offspring through multiple mechanisms, specific and non-specific.</p>
<p>Our meta-analysis also explored the relationship between paternal smoking before and during pregnancy and the risk of CBT. A relationship between paternal smoking and CBT risk is biologically plausible. Linschooten et al reported that paternal smoking could affect the chance of heritable mutations in unstable repetitive DNA sequences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Linschooten1">[49]</xref>. The study of Laubenthal et al also supported that cigarette smoke was a human germ cell mutagen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Laubenthal1">[50]</xref>. Additionally, paternal smoking may play a role through the mother's passive exposure to secondhand smoke during pregnancy. Previous studies found that certain compounds in environmental tobacco smoke may pass through the placental barrier and interact with fetal DNA, resulting in DNA damage and mutation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Rice1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Tredaniel1">[52]</xref>. However, the epidemiological evidence on this topic is very controversial. Our meta-analysis, including all the published studies, doesn't support a link between paternal smoking before and during pregnancy and the risk of CBT.</p>
<p>Overall, our meta-analysis did not support the relationship between parental smoking and the risk of CBT, regardless of the source of parental exposure. These similar results between maternal and paternal smoking before and during pregnancy were consistent with the findings of Milne et al, Hu et al, and Gold et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Milne1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Hu1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Gold1">[33]</xref>, who also investigated all four types of parental smoking. Clearly identifying and classifying the source of smoke exposure may help conduct unbiased assessments of parental smoking, which will help strengthen the conclusion and provide a comprehensive evaluation.</p>
<p>Our study has several strengths. Our meta-analysis of 17 studies involving a large number of cases and participants enhanced the statistical power to detect potential associations and provided more reliable estimates. A dose-response relationship between parental smoking and the risk of CBT was investigated, which further strengthened the conclusion. Half of the included studies considered several subtypes of CBT, allowing us to conduct separate analyses for these cancer subtypes. The absence of important heterogeneity and publication bias supported the robustness of the study findings.</p>
<p>However, several limitations of our meta-analysis should also be acknowledged. First, in this meta-analysis, the vast majority of the included studies were case-control studies. As mentioned previously, recall bias and selection bias might cause a decrease in quality of smoking exposure data. Mothers of children with CBT may be more reluctant to report harmful events during pregnancy than mothers of healthy children <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Florescu1">[53]</xref>. Therefore, this misclassification may lead to biased or spurious results. In recent years, several studies reported that cotinine measured in the dried blood spots was a reliable and accurate marker of maternal smoking close to the time of delivery <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-SearlesNielsen1">[54]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Yang1">[56]</xref>. Therefore, this low-cost and objective method could be adapted in future relevant etiologic studies to overcome a moderate amount of exposure measurement error. Second, a meta-analysis is unable to solve problems with confounding factors that could be inherent in the included studies. Inadequate control of all known confounders can produce bias in either direction, toward exaggeration or underestimation of risk estimates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Larsson1">[57]</xref>. Although we included the data from the most fully adjusted models, residual confounding cannot be completely excluded as a potential interpretation of the observed findings. Third, the results of this study were mainly based on information from western populations, while only two studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Hu1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102910-Ji1">[31]</xref> from other populations. Different races may have different genetic backgrounds that may affect CBT risk. Thus to generalize the findings, further study in other populations is warranted.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the results from this meta-analysis suggest that, based on available information, parental smoking is not associated with the risk of CBT. Because our meta-analysis has several limitations and the influence analysis suggests that some of the combined results are not very steady, future large well-designed prospective cohort studies with better exposure assessment are warranted to confirm the findings from our study and provide a higher level of evidence.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0102910.s001" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Checklist S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>PRISMA checklist.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0102910.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Forest plot of paternal smoking during pregnancy (A), maternal smoking before pregnancy (B), paternal smoking before pregnancy (C), and the risk of CBT.</bold></p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0102910.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Dose-response analysis of paternal smoking during pregnancy (A), maternal smoking before pregnancy (B), paternal smoking before pregnancy (C), and the risk of CBT.</bold> The solid line represents point estimates of association between parental smoking and CBT risk; dashed lines are 95% CIs. Circles are the dose-specific RR estimates. The relative size of each circle is proportional to the inverse variance of the RR.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0102910.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102910.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Influence analysis of maternal smoking during pregnancy (A), paternal smoking during pregnancy (B), maternal smoking before pregnancy (C), paternal smoking before pregnancy (D), and the risk of CBT.</bold></p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Mueller1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Pediatric brain tumors: current treatment strategies and future therapeutic approaches</article-title>. <source>Neurotherapeutics</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>570</fpage>–<lpage>586</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Gajjar1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gajjar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Packer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foreman</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haas-Kogan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Children's Oncology Group's 2013 blueprint for research: central nervous system tumors</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1022</fpage>–<lpage>1026</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Kyritsis1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kyritsis</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bondy</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sioka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Inherited predisposition to glioma</article-title>. <source>Neuro Oncol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Giovino1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giovino</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Tobacco use in 3 billion individuals from 16 countries: an analysis of nationally representative cross-sectional household surveys</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>380</volume>: <fpage>668</fpage>–<lpage>679</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Klip1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klip</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Kraker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Risk of cancer in the offspring of women who underwent ovarian stimulation for IVF</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>2451</fpage>–<lpage>2458</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Anderson1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dove</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kovatch</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of the transplacental tumorigenicity of the tobacco-specific carcinogen 4-(methylnitrosamino)-1-(3-pyridyl)-1-butanone in mice</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>3770</fpage>–<lpage>3775</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Balansky1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balansky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganchev</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iltcheva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Differential carcinogenicity of cigarette smoke in mice exposed either transplacentally, early in life or in adulthood</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>1001</fpage>–<lpage>1010</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Izzotti1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Izzotti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balansky</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cartiglia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camoirano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longobardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Genomic and transcriptional alterations in mouse fetus liver after transplacental exposure to cigarette smoke</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1127</fpage>–<lpage>1129</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Lackmann1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lackmann</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tollner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carmella</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Metabolites of a tobacco-specific carcinogen in urine from newborns</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Florek1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Florek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piekoszewski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basior</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazela</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Effect of maternal tobacco smoking or exposure to second-hand smoke on the levels of 4-(methylnitrosamino)-1-(3-pyridyl)-1-butanol (NNAL) in urine of mother and the first urine of newborn</article-title>. <source>J Physiol Pharmacol</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>383</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Milunsky1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Milunsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carmella</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A tobacco-specific carcinogen in the fetus</article-title>. <source>Prenat Diagn</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Brooks1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mucci</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hatch</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cnattingius</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Maternal smoking during pregnancy and risk of brain tumors in the offspring. A prospective study of 1.4 million Swedish births</article-title>. <source>Cancer Causes Control</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>997</fpage>–<lpage>1005</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Filippini1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Filippini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farinotti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrarini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Active and passive smoking during pregnancy and risk of central nervous system tumours in children</article-title>. <source>Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Pang1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Parental smoking and childhood cancer: results from the United Kingdom Childhood Cancer Study</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Stroup1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stroup</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olkin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis of observational studies in epidemiology: a proposal for reporting. Meta-analysis Of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (MOOSE) group</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>2008</fpage>–<lpage>2012</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Greenland1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Quantitative methods in the review of epidemiologic literature</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Rev</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-DerSimonian1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DerSimonian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Control Clin Trials</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Greenland2"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longnecker</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Methods for trend estimation from summarized dose-response data, with applications to meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>1301</fpage>–<lpage>1309</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Orsini1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orsini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khudyakov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis for linear and nonlinear dose-response relations: examples, an evaluation of approximations, and software</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>175</volume>: <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Harrell1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrell</surname><given-names>FE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Regression models in clinical studies: determining relationships between predictors and response</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>1198</fpage>–<lpage>1202</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Higgins1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Quantifying heterogeneity in a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1539</fpage>–<lpage>1558</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Begg1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>1101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Egger1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Milne1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenop</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Parental smoking and risk of childhood brain tumors</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-BarringtonTrimis1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrington-Trimis</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Searles Nielsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Preston-Martin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gauderman</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holly</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Parental smoking and risk of childhood brain tumors by functional polymorphisms in polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon metabolism genes</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e79110</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Stavrou1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stavrou</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Maternal smoking during pregnancy and childhood cancer in New South Wales: a record linkage investigation</article-title>. <source>Cancer Causes Control</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1551</fpage>–<lpage>1558</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Plichart1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plichart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Menegaux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lacour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frappaz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Parental smoking, maternal alcohol, coffee and tea consumption during pregnancy and childhood malignant central nervous system tumours: the ESCALE study (SFCE)</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer Prev</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>376</fpage>–<lpage>383</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Filippini2"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Filippini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maisonneuve</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCredie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peris-Bonet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Modan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Relation of childhood brain tumors to exposure of parents and children to tobacco smoke: the SEARCH international case-control study. Surveillance of Environmental Aspects Related to Cancer in Humans</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Schuz1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaletsch</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaatsch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meinert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michaelis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Risk factors for pediatric tumors of the central nervous system: results from a German population-based case-control study</article-title>. <source>Med Pediatr Oncol</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Hu1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ugnat</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Parental cigarette smoking, hard liquor consumption and the risk of childhood brain tumors—a case-control study in northeast China</article-title>. <source>Acta Oncol</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>984</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Ji1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>XO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linet</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wacholder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Paternal cigarette smoking and the risk of childhood cancer among offspring of nonsmoking mothers</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Bunin1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bunin</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boesel</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rorke</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meadows</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Risk factors for astrocytic glioma and primitive neuroectodermal tumor of the brain in young children: a report from the Children's Cancer Group</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Gold1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leviton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedley-Whyte</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Parental smoking and risk of childhood brain tumors</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>620</fpage>–<lpage>628</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-John1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Savitz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Prenatal exposure to parents' smoking and childhood cancer</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Kuijten1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuijten</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bunin</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nass</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meadows</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Gestational and familial risk factors for childhood astrocytoma: results of a case-control study</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>2608</fpage>–<lpage>2612</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Howe1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burch</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiarelli</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Risch</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>An exploratory case-control study of brain tumors in children</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>4349</fpage>–<lpage>4352</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Stjernfeldt1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stjernfeldt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ludvigsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindsten</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Maternal smoking during pregnancy and the risk of childhood cancer</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>688</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Pollack1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jakacki</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Childhood brain tumors: epidemiology, current management and future directions</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>506</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Vinchon1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinchon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leblond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delestret</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baroncini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Radiation-induced tumors in children irradiated for brain tumor: a longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>Childs Nerv Syst</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>453</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Baldwin1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Preston-Martin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology of brain tumors in childhood—a review</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source> <volume>199</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>131</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Bunin2"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bunin</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robison</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biegel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rorke-Adams</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Parental heat exposure and risk of childhood brain tumor: a Children's Oncology Group study</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>164</volume>: <fpage>222</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Hargreave1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hargreave</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toender</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kjaer</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Fertility treatment and childhood cancer risk: a systematic meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Fertil Steril</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Huncharek1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huncharek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kupelnick</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klassen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Maternal smoking during pregnancy and the risk of childhood brain tumors: a meta-analysis of 6566 subjects from twelve epidemiological studies</article-title>. <source>J Neurooncol</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Flenady1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flenady</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koopmans</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Middleton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Froen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Major risk factors for stillbirth in high-income countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>377</volume>: <fpage>1331</fpage>–<lpage>1340</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Oken1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oken</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levitan</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gillman</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Maternal smoking during pregnancy and child overweight: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes (Lond)</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Antonopoulos1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antonopoulos</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sergentanis</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papadopoulou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dessypris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Maternal smoking during pregnancy and childhood lymphoma: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>2694</fpage>–<lpage>2703</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Klimentopoulou1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klimentopoulou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antonopoulos</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papadopoulou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanavidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tourvas</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Maternal smoking during pregnancy and risk for childhood leukemia: a nationwide case-control study in Greece and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Tuomisto1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuomisto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rantakokko</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koskela</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hallmans</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Maternal smoking during pregnancy and testicular cancer in the sons: a nested case-control study and a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>1640</fpage>–<lpage>1648</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Linschooten1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linschooten</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verhofstad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gutzkow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yauk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Paternal lifestyle as a potential source of germline mutations transmitted to offspring</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>2873</fpage>–<lpage>2879</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Laubenthal1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laubenthal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zlobinskaya</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poterlowicz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gdula</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Cigarette smoke-induced transgenerational alterations in genome stability in cord blood of human F1 offspring</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>3946</fpage>–<lpage>3956</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Rice1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Causation of nervous system tumors in children: insights from traditional and genetically engineered animal models</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source> <volume>199</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Tredaniel1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tredaniel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boffetta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saracci</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Exposure to passive smoking during pregnancy and childhood, and cancer risk: the epidemiological evidence</article-title>. <source>Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Florescu1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Florescu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrence</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Einarson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soldin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Methods for quantification of exposure to cigarette smoking and environmental tobacco smoke: focus on developmental toxicology</article-title>. <source>Ther Drug Monit</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-SearlesNielsen1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Searles Nielsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dills</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Accuracy of prenatal smoking data from Washington State birth certificates in a population-based sample with cotinine measurements</article-title>. <source>Ann Epidemiol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>236</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Murphy1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Cotinine and trans 3'-hydroxycotinine in dried blood spots as biomarkers of tobacco exposure and nicotine metabolism</article-title>. <source>J Expo Sci Environ Epidemiol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Yang1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pearl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>P</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeLorenze</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benowitz</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Levels of cotinine in dried blood specimens from newborns as a biomarker of maternal smoking close to the time of delivery</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>178</volume>: <fpage>1648</fpage>–<lpage>1654</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102910-Larsson1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orsini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Vitamin B6 and risk of colorectal cancer: a meta-analysis of prospective studies</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <volume>303</volume>: <fpage>1077</fpage>–<lpage>1083</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>