<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-13781</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102484</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cerebral ischemia</subject><subject>Cerebrovascular diseases</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancer treatment</subject><subj-group><subject>Antiangiogenesis therapy</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Increased Risk of Cerebrovascular Events in Patients with Cancer Treated with Bevacizumab: A Meta-Analysis</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Bevacizumab and Cerebrovascular Events</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>Pei-Yuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xing-Lin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yu-Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Chang-Liang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Cheng-Yun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Key Laboratory of Geriatrics of Health Ministry, Department of Geriatrics, Union Hospital, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>William B.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of North Carolina School of Medicine, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">lcyun@medmail.com.cn</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: PYZ CYL. Performed the experiments: PYZ XLC. Analyzed the data: PYZ XLC CYL YWL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: PYZ YWL CLX. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: PYZ XLC CYL.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<elocation-id>e102484</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Zuo et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Arterial ischemia and hemorrhage are associated with bevacizumab, an inhibitor of vascular endothelial growth factor that is widely used to treat many types of cancers. As specific types of arterial ischemia and hemorrhage, cerebrovascular events such as central nervous system (CNS) ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage are serious adverse events. However, increased cerebrovascular events have not been uniformly reported by previous studies. New randomized controlled trials (RCTs) have been reported in recent years and we therefore conducted an up-to-date meta-analysis of RCTs to fully characterize the risk of cerebrovascular events with bevacizumab. We searched the databases of PubMed, Web of Science, and the American Society of Clinical Oncology conferences to identify relevant clinical trials up to February 2014. Eligible studies included prospective RCTs that directly compared patients with cancer treated with and without bevacizumab. A total of 12,917 patients from 17 RCTs were included in our analysis. Patients treated with bevacizumab had a significantly increased risk of cerebrovascular events compared with patients treated with control medication, with a relative risk of 3.28 (95% CI, 1.97–5.48). The risks of CNS ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage were increased compared with control, with RRs of 3.22 (95% CI, 1.71–6.07) and 3.09 (95% CI, 1.36–6.99), respectively. Risk varied with the bevacizumab dose, with RRs of 3.97 (95% CI, 2.15–7.36) and 1.96 (95% CI, 0.76–5.06) at 5 and 2.5 mg/kg/week, respectively. Higher risks were observed in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer (RR, 6.42; 95% CI, 1.76–35.57), and no significant risk was observed in other types of tumors. In conclusion, the addition of bevacizumab significantly increased the risk of cerebrovascular events compared with controls, including CNS ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage. The risk may vary with bevacizumab dose and tumor type.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This study is supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No81370468). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The overexpression of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) has been observed in several tumor types and is associated with a poorer patient prognosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Ebbers1">[1]</xref>. VEGF binds to and activates a receptor tyrosine kinase, stimulating the growth of blood vessels, which plays a central role in the growth, invasion and metastasis of tumors. Disruption of VEGF signaling is a major focus of new cancer therapeutics. Bevacizumab, a humanized recombinant monoclonal antibody against VEGF, was first authorized in the USA in 2004 for the treatment of metastatic colon and rectal cancer. To date, bevacizumab has been approved by the US Food and Drug Administration for the treatment of metastatic colorectal cancer (mCRC), advanced non-squamous non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC), glioblastoma and metastatic renal cell carcinoma (mRCC).</p>
<p>Bevacizumab has been shown to increase the risk of arterial ischemia and serious hemorrhage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Schutz1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Hapani1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Scappaticci1">[4]</xref>. However, there is no evidence supporting an association with increased CNS ischemic events or CNS hemorrhage, the specific types of arterial ischemia and hemorrhage. Ranpura et al. conducted a meta-analysis in 2010 and found that bevacizumab increased the risk of cardiac ischemia; however, the risk of ischemic stroke with bevacizumab was not significantly different from that of controls <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Ranpura1">[5]</xref>. Likewise, in 2010, Hapani et al. reported that the risk of CNS hemorrhage with bevacizumab appeared to be low <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Hapani1">[3]</xref>. Carden et al. concluded that no trial reported evidence supporting an increased risk of intracranial bleeding during anti-VEGF therapy, even in the presence of CNS metastases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Carden1">[6]</xref>. Cerebrovascular events are adverse events leading to morbidity and mortality in patients with malignancy, and although infrequent, they are life threatening. CNS bleeding was reported to be the cause of death in one-third of patients who experienced a bleed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Letarte1">[7]</xref>. Therefore, it is imperative to find out whether such cerebrovascular disorders develop as a result of bevacizumab treatment.</p>
<p>New RCTs have been performed during the past three years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Chinot1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kelly1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Price1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Okines1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Aghajanian1">[12]</xref>. Although not significantly different when compared with controls, several studies have reported a higher incidence of CNS ischemia or CNS hemorrhage with bevacizumab <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Chinot1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kelly1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Price1">[10]</xref>. We consider that individual trials may be limited in patient number and that the previous meta-analyses were not sufficiently large to reveal a significantly increased risk of cerebrovascular events in patients with bevacizumab. To further understand these issues, we conducted an up-to-date, thorough literature search and meta-analysis to characterize the impact of bevacizumab on the occurrence of cerebrovascular events in cancer patients.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Data Source</title>
<p>We performed a comprehensive search of citations from PubMed between January 1966 and February 2014, using the keywords “bevacizumab”, “avastin”, and “carcinoma/cancer”. The search was limited to randomized clinical trials. We also searched abstracts and virtual meeting presentations from the American Society of Clinical Oncology conferences held between January 2004 and November 2013, using the keywords “bevacizumab” or “avastin” and “randomized”. An independent search using the citation database Web of Science was also conducted to ensure that no clinical trials were missed. The search was limited initially to English publications in humans. We screened the reference lists of the included studies and related publications. The results were then hand searched for eligible trials. The results were double-checked and arbitrated by a second investigator.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Study Selection</title>
<p>The purpose of this study was to determine whether bevacizumab contributes to the development of CNS ischemic events or CNS hemorrhage in patients with cancer. Therefore, we selected for analysis only those randomized clinical trials that directly compared patients with cancer treated with and without bevacizumab. Trials that met the following criteria were included: (1) prospective phase II and III randomized clinical trials in patients with cancer, (2) randomized assignment of participants to bevacizumab treatment or control in addition to current chemotherapy and/or biological agent, (3) direct comparison of patients with and without bevacizumab therapy with data available for CNS ischemic events or CNS hemorrhage.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Data Extraction and Quality Assessment</title>
<p>Data abstraction was conducted independently by two investigators (P.Y.Z. and Y.W.L.) to avoid bias in the data-abstraction process, and any discrepancies between reviewers were resolved by consensus. For each study, we extracted the following information: first author’s name, year of publication, trial phase, underlying malignancy, number of enrolled patients, treatment arms, median follow-up and bevacizumab dose. CNS ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage were defined and assessed according to the National Cancer Institute’s common terminology criteria for adverse events (version 1, 2 or 3), which has been widely used in cancer clinical trials (Additional file, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102484.s001">Table S1</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-NCI1">[13]</xref>. Version 1 was used in 1 trial <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kabbinavar1">[14]</xref>; version 2 was used in 3 trials <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Sandler1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Miller1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Giantonio1">[17]</xref>; version 3 was used in 12 trials <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Chinot1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kelly1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Price1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Okines1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Aghajanian1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kindler1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Allegra1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Rini1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kindler2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Herbst1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kim1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Burger1">[24]</xref>, and the one of the trials did not specify <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Perren1">[25]</xref>. Minor variation exists among these versions in grading CNS ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage. Data regarding the occurrence of cerebrovascular events were obtained from the safety profile of each study. Criteria were assessed for quality including randomization and allocation concealment, blinding, sample size, exclusions after randomization, and different lengths of follow-up <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Meade1">[26]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>STATA 12.0 (STATA Corp, College Station, Texas) and RevMan 5 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ims.cochrance.org/revman/download" xlink:type="simple">http://ims.cochrance.org/revman/download</ext-link>) were used for statistical analysis. For the calculation of incidence, the number of patients with cerebrovascular events and the number of patients treated with bevacizumab were extracted from the safety profiles of the selected clinical trials. The proportion of patients with cerebrovascular events and the 95% CIs were derived from each trial. We also calculated the RRs and CIs of cerebrovascular events in patients assigned to bevacizumab versus controls. To explore a dose–effect relationship, bevacizumab therapy was further divided into low dose (2.5 mg/kg per week) and high dose (5 mg/kg per week). The designation of low vs. high dose is relatively arbitrary. We also conducted subgroup analyses type of cerebrovascular events and underlying malignancy.</p>
<p>Statistical heterogeneity among trials included in the meta-analysis was quantified with the <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> statistic (100%*[Q-<italic>df</italic>]/Q), which estimates the percentage of total variation across studies due to heterogeneity rather than chance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Higgins1">[27]</xref>. If the <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> value was greater than 50%, the assumption of homogeneity was deemed invalid, and the random-effects model was reported after exploring the causes of heterogeneity. Otherwise, the fixed-effects model was reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-DerSimonian1">[28]</xref>. Publication bias was evaluated with Begg’s and Egger’s tests <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Begg1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Egger1">[30]</xref>. A two-tailed P-value&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Population Characteristics and Quality</title>
<p>Our initial search yielded a total of 376 clinical studies relevant to bevacizumab. After excluding review articles, phase I, single-arm phase II studies, case reports, meta-analyses, observational studies, RCTs with both arms containing bevacizumab, and data not adequate to evaluate cerebrovascular events, we selected 17 randomized controlled trials. The detailed selection process is represented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102484-g001">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0102484-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Selection process for the randomized clinical trials included in the meta-analysis.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The characteristics of each RCT are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102484-t001">Table 1</xref>. The baseline Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status for most patients was between 0 and 1. Patients were required to have adequate organ function, coagulation and hematologic parameters. Patients were excluded if they had significant cardiovascular disease, uncontrolled hypertension, serious non-healing wounds, major surgery within the previous 28 days, bleeding diathesis or significant coagulopathy, brain metastasis, or known CNS disease; if they required parenteral hydration or nutrition; or if they were receiving specific drugs thought to increase the risk of bleeding.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0102484-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Characteristics of randomised controlled clinical trials included in the meta-analysis.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0102484-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Firstauthor,year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trialphase</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patientsenrolled</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients foranalysis</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medianfollow-up(months)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Underlyingmalignancy</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concurrenttreatment</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reportedcerebrovascular events</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bevacizumabdose(mg/kg Per week)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aghajanian, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Aghajanian1">[12]</xref> 2012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">543</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">480</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">recurrent ovarian, primary peritoneal, or fallopian tube cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gemcitabine and carboplatin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNS hemorrhage</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allegra, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Allegra1">[19]</xref> 2009</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2710</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2647</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluorouracil, leucovorin, and oxaliplatin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNS ischemia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burger, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Burger1">[24]</xref> 2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1873</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1209</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovarian cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paclitaxel and carboplatin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNS bleeding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinot, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Chinot1">[8]</xref> 2014</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">921</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">921</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glioblastoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radiotherapy, temozolomide</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNS bleeding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Giantonio, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Giantonio1">[17]</xref> 2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">829</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">572</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxaliplatin, fluorouracil, and Leucovorin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular ischemia/hemorrhage</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herbst, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Herbst1">[22]</xref> 2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">636</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">626</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-small-cell lung cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erlotinib</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNS hemorrhage</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kabbinavar, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kabbinavar1">[14]</xref> 2003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluorouracil and leucovorin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular accident</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kelly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kelly1">[9]</xref> 2012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1050</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1009</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostatic cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Docetaxel and prednisone</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular ischemia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kim, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kim1">[23]</xref> 2012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melanoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carboplatin and paclitaxel</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNS hemorrhage</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kindler, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kindler1">[18]</xref> 2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesothelioma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gemcitabine and cisplatin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular accident</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kindler, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kindler2">[21]</xref> 2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">602</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pancreatic cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gemcitabine</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular accident</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miller, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Miller1">[16]</xref> 2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">722</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">711</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paclitaxel</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular ischemia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Okines, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Okines1">[11]</xref> 2013</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastro-oesophageal adenocarcinoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epirubicin, cisplatin and capecitabine</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular thromboembolic event</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perren, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Perren1">[25]</xref> 2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1528</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1528</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovarian cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paclitaxel and carboplatin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNS bleeding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Price, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Price1">[10]</xref> 2012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">471</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">471</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capecitabine and Mitomycin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular ischemia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rini, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Rini1">[20]</xref> 2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">732</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">709</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal cell carcinoma</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interferon alfa</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular ischemia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sandler, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Sandler1">[15]</xref> 2006</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">878</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">867</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-small-cell lung cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paclitaxel and carboplatin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNS hemorrhage/accident</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Abbreviations and notes: NA, data not available; CNS, central nervous system.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Founding sources: three trials were sponsored by Genentech <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Aghajanian1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kabbinavar1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kim1">[23]</xref>, eleven trials were supported by National Cancer Institute and National Institute of Health <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kelly1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Sandler1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Herbst1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Burger1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Perren1">[25]</xref>, One trial was supported by Roche Australia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Price1">[10]</xref>, One trial was supported by Cancer Research UK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Okines1">[11]</xref>, One trial was supported by F. Hoffmann–La Roche <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Chinot1">[8]</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>a</label><p>The dose schedule was converted from mg/kg per schedule.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>We did not differentiate between high- and all-grade CNS ischemic events or CNS hemorrhage, as very few studies reported on all-grade or low-grade (grade 1–2) CNS ischemia or bleeding. All the RCTs reported CNS ischemic events as high (grade 3–5). One RCT reported all-grade CNS bleeding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Aghajanian1">[12]</xref>, and one RCT did not mention any grade <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Burger1">[24]</xref>, all other RCTs reported CNS bleeding as high grade.</p>
<p>In all trials, patients were randomly assigned to either a control or bevacizumab group, with two three–arm studies each having two bevacizumab-treatment groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Price1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Giantonio1">[17]</xref>, in which patients received different combinations. Eight trials were placebo-controlled, double-blinded studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Chinot1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kelly1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Aghajanian1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kindler1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kindler2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Herbst1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kim1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Burger1">[24]</xref>, and the rest of the trials had active controls <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Price1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Okines1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kabbinavar1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Sandler1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Miller1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Giantonio1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Allegra1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Rini1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Perren1">[25]</xref>. The quality of all the trials was acceptable.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Risk of Cerebrovascular Events</title>
<p>A total of 12,917 patients from 17 RCTs were identified and included for analysis. Among the patients who were administered bevacizumab, the meta-analysis revealed that the summary incidence of cerebrovascular events was 0.5% (95% CI, 0.3%–0.7%), as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102484-t002">table 2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0102484-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Incidence and RR of cerebrovascular events with bevacizumab among patients with various tumor types.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0102484-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subgroup</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. ofstudies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CVE no./total noBevacizumab</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence(95% CI), %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR (95% CI), P</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59/6421</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/6284</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.3–0.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.28 (1.97–5.48), &lt;0.00001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/1960</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/1877</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.2–0.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28 (0.90–5.73), 0.37</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Metastatic colorectal cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/634</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/556</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.1–1.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.42 (1.16–35.57), 0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NSCLC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/740</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/753</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (−0.1–0.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.14 (0.88–57.60), 0.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovarian cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/1600</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1587</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (0–0.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42 (0.72–16.35), 0.84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/2121</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/2067</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.6–0.12)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59 (1.75–7.38), 0.0005</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>NSCLC, non-small-cell lung cancer; CVE, cerebrovascular events; CI, confidence interval; RR, relative risk.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>The observed incidences of cerebrovascular events with bevacizumab may have been influenced by other confounding factors, such as concurrent chemotherapy, underlying malignancy, hypertension, diabetes, hyperlipidemia, and medications. To assess the particular contribution of bevacizumab to the risk of cerebrovascular events and to exclude the influence of confounding factors, we determined the overall RR of cerebrovascular events from the RCTs in which patients were treated with or without bevacizumab in combination with concurrent standard antineoplastic therapy.</p>
<p>We performed a meta-analysis of 16 RCTs (one trial was not included in the final calculation of relative risk because neither the control nor bevacizumab groups had cerebrovascular events). No heterogeneity was found among the studies included in the analysis despite clear disparity in tumor type and related treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102484-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Using a fixed-effects model, the summary overall RR for bevacizumab versus control was 3.28 (95% CI, 1.97–5.48). Thus, bevacizumab was found to increase the risk of cerebrovascular events significantly.</p>
<fig id="pone-0102484-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Relative risk (RR) of cerebrovascular events associated with bevacizumab versus control.</title>
<p>The overall RR of cerebrovascular events was calculated using a fixed-effects model. The areas of the squares are proportional to the weights used for combining the data. The diamond plot represents the overall results of the included trials. One trial was not included in the final calculation of relative risk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kim1">[23]</xref> because neither the control nor the bevacizumab groups had events.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Risk of CNS Ischemic Events and CNS Hemorrhage</title>
<p>Among the patients who were administered bevacizumab, meta-analysis revealed that the incidence of CNS ischemic events was 0.5% (95% CI, 0.3%–0.7%), with the highest incidence (1.9%) observed in the malignant mesothelioma trial <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kindler1">[18]</xref> and the lowest incidence (0.2%) found in a colorectal cancer trial <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Giantonio1">[17]</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102484-t002">Table 2</xref>). The incidence of CNS hemorrhage was 0.3% (95% CI, 0.1%–0.5%), with the highest incidence (1.4%) observed in a glioblastoma trial <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Chinot1">[8]</xref> and the lowest incidence (0.1%) found in an ovarian cancer trial <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Perren1">[25]</xref>.</p>
<p>Using a fixed-effects model, the RR of CNS ischemic events was determined to be 3.22 (95% CI: 1.71–6.07) in comparison with controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102484-g003">Figure 3</xref>). The RR of CNS hemorrhage was determined to be 3.09 (95% CI: 1.36–6.99) in comparison with controls. Therefore, the RRs of CNS ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage in patients receiving bevacizumab were 222% and 209% greater than control treatment, respectively. This finding suggested that bevacizumab significantly increased the risk of CNS ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage.</p>
<fig id="pone-0102484-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Relative risk (RR) of CNS ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage associated with bevacizumab versus controls.</title>
<p>The RRs of CNS ischemic events (A) and CNS hemorrhage (B) were calculated using a fixed-effects model. The areas of the squares are proportional to the weights used for combining the data. The diamond plot represents the overall results of the included trials.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Risk of Cerebrovascular Events and Tumor Type</title>
<p>Patients with different tumors might be at different risks of cerebrovascular events due to differences in tumor biology and associated treatments. As an exploratory analysis, stratified analysis was performed based on the underlying malignancy. The highest incidence of cerebrovascular events was found in patients with malignant mesothelioma (1.9%, 95% CI 0.7–4.4), while the lowest incidence was observed in patients with ovarian cancer (0.1%, 95% CI 0.1–0.3).</p>
<p>Notably, the relative risk of cerebrovascular events was 6.42 (95% CI, 1.76–35.57) for metastatic colorectal cancer treated with bevacizumab compared with control (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102484-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Cerebrovascular Events and Bevacizumab Dose</title>
<p>We assessed whether the dose of bevacizumab is related to the risk of cerebrovascular events. A meta-analysis was performed to calculate the RR associated with bevacizumab at 2.5 or 5 mg/kg/week when compared with controls. The RR of cerebrovascular events for bevacizumab at 2.5 mg/kg/week was 1.96 (95% CI, 0.76–5.06) when using four RCTs including 4896 patients. The RR of cerebrovascular events at 5 mg/kg/week was 3.97 (95% CI, 2.15–7.36) when using 12 RCTs including 7809 patients. This finding suggests that the risk of cerebrovascular events with bevacizumab was dose dependent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102484-g004">figure 4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0102484-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Relative risk (RR) of cerebrovascular events associated with bevacizumab at 2.5 or 5 mg/kg/week when compared to controls.</title>
<p>Summary of the RRs of cerebrovascular events for patients receiving bevacizumab at 2·5 mg/kg per week (A) or 5 mg/kg per week (B), which were calculated using a fixed-effects model. The areas of the squares are proportional to the weights used for combining the data. The diamond plot represents the overall results of the included trials.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3f">
<title>Publication Bias</title>
<p>We used Begg’s and Egger’s tests to determine the presence of publication bias regarding our primary end point (RR of cerebrovascular events). The two-tailed p-values were 0.452 and 0.187 for Begg’s and Egger’s tests, respectively. Thus, no publication bias was detected.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Most previous studies have focused on the development of arterial thromboembolic events, such as pulmonary embolism and myocardial infarction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Chen1">[31]</xref>, following bevacizumab treatment. Limited information is available on the effects of bevacizumab on the cerebral vasculature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Seet1">[32]</xref>. Our study demonstrated that bevacizumab was associated with a significantly increased risk of cerebrovascular events (RR, 3.28; 95% CI, 1.97–5.48), including CNS ischemic events (RR, 3.22; 95% CI, 1.71–6.07) and CNS hemorrhage (RR, 3.09; 95% CI, 1.36–6.99). The clinical significance of cerebrovascular events in cancer patients is evident because of their association with significant morbidity and mortality. As bevacizumab is used extensively in routine cancer treatment and clinical trials, it is important to improve the diagnosis and management of the cerebrovascular side effects of bevacizumab. This study may help physicians and patients to properly understand the risk of cerebrovascular events in bevacizumab therapy.</p>
<p>Mechanisms were involved in the predisposition to thrombosis and bleeding after the inhibition of VEGF signaling. VEGF not only promotes endothelial cell proliferation but also stimulates endothelial cell survival. Inhibition of VEGF could thereby impair the endothelial cells regenerative capacity, leading to thrombosis or hemorrhage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kamba1">[33]</xref>. VEGF also plays a role in vascular protection, with effects on endothelial cells mediated through its anti-apoptotic, anti-inflammatory and pro-survival effects. Bevacizumab may increase the expression of proinflammatory cytokines, damaging blood vessels in the brain. VEGF increases the production of NO and prostacyclin and suppresses pathways involved in endothelial cell activation, apoptosis, and coagulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Zachary1">[34]</xref>. Reductions in NO and prostacyclin may predispose patients to thromboembolic events. In addition, bevacizumab significantly increases the risk of hypertension in cancer patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Ranpura2">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Zhu1">[36]</xref>. The incidence of all-grade hypertension in patients receiving bevacizumab is 23.6%, and sustained hypertension permanently changes the architecture of the blood vessels, making them narrow, stiff, deformed and uneven and therefore more vulnerable to fluctuations in blood pressure. High blood pressure greatly contributes to CNS hemorrhage.</p>
<p>At present, controversy remains as to whether Bevacizumab increases the risk of cerebrovascular events. The association of bevacizumab with increased risks of CNS ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage may have been underestimated by previous meta-analyses. Ranpura et al. included five RCTs reporting ischemic stroke from 2003 to 2010 and demonstrated that the RR of developing stroke with bevacizumab was 1.37 (95% CI: 0.67–2.79) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Ranpura1">[5]</xref>. Carden et al. demonstrated that even in the presence of known brain metastases, anti-VEGF therapy appears to be safe, with no recorded episodes of intracerebral hemorrhage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Carden1">[6]</xref>. In a meta-analysis conducted by Hapani et al. including two RCTs in 2010, the RR of CNS hemorrhage with bevacizumab was 6.01 (95% CI 0.72–50.0) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Hapani1">[3]</xref>. We considered that the failure to detect the increased risk with bevacizumab in CNS ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage was likely due to the limited number of clinical trials included in these subgroup analyses.</p>
<p>New RCTs have been performed during the past several years. We collected a total of 17 RCTs reporting cerebrovascular events. Eleven of these RCTs reported CNS ischemic events, and eight reported CNS hemorrhage. Our analysis demonstrated that the risks of CNS ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage were increased over three-fold in patients treated with bevacizumab compared with controls. Importantly, the risk of cerebrovascular events in patients with CNS metastases receiving bevacizumab was not fully evaluated. Evidence is lacking in the metastatic setting because patients with brain metastases have largely been excluded from phase II and phase III clinical trials.</p>
<p>We explored the relationship between bevacizumab dose and cerebrovascular events. We showed that high-dose bevacizumab (5 mg/kg/week) significantly increased the risk of cerebrovascular events, with an RR of 3.26 (95% CI, 1.81–5.86) in comparison with controls, whereas low-dose bevacizumab (2.5 mg/kg/week) did not, with an RR of 1.71 (95% CI, 0.62–4.70). This result suggests that the increased risk of bevacizumab-associated cerebrovascular events is dose dependent.</p>
<p>This study also showed that the risk of cerebrovascular events with bevacizumab can vary with tumor type. The risk was significantly increased in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer who received bevacizumab (RR, 6.42; 95% CI, 1·16–35.57). This result is consistent with that addressed in a cohort study in patient with stage IV colorectal cancer published in 2012 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Meyerhardt1">[37]</xref>. The higher risk of cerebrovascular events observed in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer might be associated with the adjuvant therapies that the patients received, which have known cerebrovascular side effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Kabbinavar1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Giantonio1">[17]</xref>. Another possible explanation is that the VEGF level was highest in patients with mCRC in comparison with other cancers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Becker1">[38]</xref>. No significant risk was found for other tumor types. In patients with glioblastoma, the incidence of CNS hemorrhage was high (1.4%; 95% CI, 0.7%–2.2%) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Chinot1">[8]</xref>. Surgery or radiotherapy may contribute to this high incidence in glioblastoma patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Narita1">[39]</xref>. To establish definitively that bevacizumab increases the risk of cerebrovascular events in tumor types except mCRC, further large-scale RCTs are needed.</p>
<p>Phase II or III RCTs have tight inclusion and exclusion criteria. Patients were excluded if they do not have adequate organ function, coagulation and hematologic parameters. Therefore, the RCTs from our report rarely included patients with baseline significant uncontrolled hypertension or a prior history of cerebrovascular events. It is conceivable that the rate of cerebrovascular events could be even higher in a real-life with underlying vascular comorbidities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102484-Schutz1">[2]</xref>. For patients receiving bevacizumab, physicians should be highly vigilant for any signs of cerebrovascular disorders. If a cerebrovascular event is detected, prompt assessment and treatment are warranted.</p>
<p>Our study had several limitations. First, because of the number of RCTs in each tumor type was limited, we did not determine the exact tumor type associated with significant risk. Several tumor types only included one RCT, such as prostate cancer, mesothelioma, pancreatic cancer, breast cancer and renal cell carcinoma. Further RCTs are needed. Second, all the studies were conducted at various institutions, and the ability to detect cerebrovascular events might vary among these institutions, which could result in a potential bias of recording adverse events. The incidence of cerebrovascular events showed significant heterogeneity among the included studies. Calculation using the random-effects model for incidence estimation may minimize this issue. The RRs reported by all of the studies were remarkably non-heterogeneous. Third, this was a meta- analysis conducted at the study level, and confounding factors and specific risk factors at the patient level could therefore not be assessed and incorporated into the analysis. Substantial variation exists among these trials due to patient selection (localized disease in the Allegra trial and metastatic disease in other trials), tumor type, trial phase, and concurrent treatment. Finally, there could be a potential observation time bias because bevacizumab is often associated with prolonged progression-free survival.</p>
<p>In conclusion, our study indicates that the novel anti-angiogenic agent bevacizumab is associated with a significantly increased risk of cerebrovascular events, including both CNS ischemic events and CNS hemorrhage, in patients with cancer receiving concurrent chemotherapy. The risk might vary with tumor type, with higher risks observed in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer. The risk was increased in patients receiving higher doses of bevacizumab. Future studies are recommended to investigate risk reduction.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0102484.s001" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>National Cancer Institute’s common terminology criteria versions 1–3 for cerebrovascular events.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0102484.s002" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102484.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Checklist S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>PRISMA 2009 Checklist.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Ebbers1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebbers</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Meer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moors</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mantel-Teeuwisse</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leufkens</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Measures of biosimilarity in monoclonal antibodies in oncology: the case of bevacizumab</article-title>. <source>Drug Discov Today</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>872</fpage>–<lpage>879</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Schutz1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schutz</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Je</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azzi</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choueiri</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Bevacizumab increases the risk of arterial ischemia: a large study in cancer patients with a focus on different subgroup outcomes</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1404</fpage>–<lpage>1412</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Hapani1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hapani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Increased risk of serious hemorrhage with bevacizumab in cancer patients: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Oncology</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Scappaticci1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scappaticci</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skillings</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Arterial thromboembolic events in patients with metastatic carcinoma treated with chemotherapy and bevacizumab</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>1232</fpage>–<lpage>1239</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Ranpura1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranpura</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hapani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Risk of cardiac ischemia and arterial thromboembolic events with the angiogenesis inhibitor bevacizumab in cancer patients: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Acta Oncol</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Carden1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carden</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>What is the risk of intracranial bleeding during anti-VEGF therapy?</article-title> <source>Neuro Oncol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>624</fpage>–<lpage>630</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Letarte1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Letarte</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bressler</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Villano</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Bevacizumab and central nervous system (CNS) hemorrhage</article-title>. <source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1561</fpage>–<lpage>1565</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Chinot1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chinot</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henriksson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saran</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Bevacizumab plus radiotherapy-temozolomide for newly diagnosed glioblastoma</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>370</volume>: <fpage>709</fpage>–<lpage>722</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Kelly1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halabi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carducci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase III trial comparing docetaxel and prednisone with or without bevacizumab in men with metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer: CALGB 90401</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1534</fpage>–<lpage>1540</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Price1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zannino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cassidy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Bevacizumab is equally effective and no more toxic in elderly patients with advanced colorectal cancer: a subgroup analysis from the AGITG MAX trial: an international randomised controlled trial of Capecitabine, Bevacizumab and Mitomycin C. Ann Oncol</article-title>. <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1531</fpage>–<lpage>1536</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Okines1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okines</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stenning</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Bevacizumab with peri-operative epirubicin, cisplatin and capecitabine (ECX) in localised gastro-oesophageal adenocarcinoma: a safety report</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>702</fpage>–<lpage>709</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Aghajanian1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aghajanian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blank</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Judson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teneriello</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>OCEANS: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase III trial of chemotherapy with or without bevacizumab in patients with platinum-sensitive recurrent epithelial ovarian, primary peritoneal, or fallopian tube cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>2039</fpage>–<lpage>2045</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-NCI1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">NCI. National Cancer institute’s common toxicity criteria. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ctep.cancer.gov/protocolDevelopment/electronic_applications/ctc.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://ctep.cancer.gov/protocolDevelopment/electronic_applications/ctc.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 26 February 2014.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Kabbinavar1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabbinavar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fehrenbacher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meropol</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novotny</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Phase II, randomized trial comparing bevacizumab plus fluorouracil (FU)/leucovorin (LV) with FU/LV alone in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Sandler1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brahmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Paclitaxel-carboplatin alone or with bevacizumab for non-small-cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>355</volume>: <fpage>2542</fpage>–<lpage>2550</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Miller1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gralow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dickler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cobleigh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Paclitaxel plus bevacizumab versus paclitaxel alone for metastatic breast cancer</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>357</volume>: <fpage>2666</fpage>–<lpage>2676</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Giantonio1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giantonio</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meropol</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Dwyer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Bevacizumab in combination with oxaliplatin, fluorouracil, and leucovorin (FOLFOX4) for previously treated metastatic colorectal cancer: Results from the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Study E3200</article-title>. <source>JOURNAL OF CLINICAL ONCOLOGY</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1539</fpage>–<lpage>1544</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Kindler1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kindler</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karrison</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gandara</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guterz</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Final analysis of a multi-center, double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized phase II trial of gemcitabine/cisplatin (GC) plus bevacizumab (B) or placebo (P) in patients with malignant mesothelioma</article-title>. <source>JOURNAL OF THORACIC ONCOLOGY</source> <volume>2S</volume>: <fpage>S374</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Allegra1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allegra</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yothers</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Connell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharif</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colangelo</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Initial safety report of NSABP C-08: A randomized phase III study of modified FOLFOX6 with or without bevacizumab for the adjuvant treatment of patients with stage II or III colon cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>3385</fpage>–<lpage>3390</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Rini1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rini</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halabi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaena</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Phase III trial of bevacizumab plus interferon alfa versus interferon alfa monotherapy in patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma: final results of CALGB 90206</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2137</fpage>–<lpage>2143</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Kindler2"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kindler</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niedzwiecki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hollis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schrag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Gemcitabine plus bevacizumab compared with gemcitabine plus placebo in patients with advanced pancreatic cancer: phase III trial of the Cancer and Leukemia Group B (CALGB 80303)</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>3617</fpage>–<lpage>3622</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Herbst1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bustin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Efficacy of bevacizumab plus erlotinib versus erlotinib alone in advanced non-small-cell lung cancer after failure of standard first-line chemotherapy (BeTa): a double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial</article-title>. <source>LANCET</source> <volume>377</volume>: <fpage>1846</fpage>–<lpage>1854</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Kim1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sosman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fruehauf</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linette</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Markovic</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>BEAM: a randomized phase II study evaluating the activity of bevacizumab in combination with carboplatin plus paclitaxel in patients with previously untreated advanced melanoma</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Burger1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bookman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monk</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Incorporation of bevacizumab in the primary treatment of ovarian cancer</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>365</volume>: <fpage>2473</fpage>–<lpage>2483</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Perren1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perren</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swart</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pfisterer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ledermann</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pujade-Lauraine</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A phase 3 trial of bevacizumab in ovarian cancer</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>365</volume>: <fpage>2484</fpage>–<lpage>2496</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Meade1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meade</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Selecting and appraising studies for a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Higgins1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>327</volume>: <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-DerSimonian1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DerSimonian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Control Clin Trials</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Begg1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>1101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Egger1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Chen1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chen XL, Lei YH, Liu CF, Yang QF, Zuo PY, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2013) Angiogenesis Inhibitor Bevacizumab Increases the Risk of Ischemic Heart Disease Associated with Chemotherapy: A Meta-Analysis. PLOS ONE 8.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Seet1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seet</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rabinstein</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindell</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uhm</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wijdicks</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Cerebrovascular events after bevacizumab treatment: an early and severe complication</article-title>. <source>Neurocrit Care</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Kamba1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms of adverse effects of anti-VEGF therapy for cancer</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>1788</fpage>–<lpage>1795</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Zachary1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zachary</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Signaling mechanisms mediating vascular protective actions of vascular endothelial growth factor</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source> <volume>280</volume>: <fpage>C1375</fpage>–<lpage>C1386</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Ranpura2"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranpura</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pulipati</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Increased risk of high-grade hypertension with bevacizumab in cancer patients: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Hypertens</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>460</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Zhu1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dahut</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Risks of proteinuria and hypertension with bevacizumab, an antibody against vascular endothelial growth factor: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Kidney Dis</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Meyerhardt1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyerhardt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanoff</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schrag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Effectiveness of bevacizumab with first-line combination chemotherapy for Medicare patients with stage IV colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>608</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Becker1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlakovic</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ludewig</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilting</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weich</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Neuroblastoma progression correlates with downregulation of the lymphangiogenesis inhibitor sVEGFR-2</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1431</fpage>–<lpage>1441</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102484-Narita1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Narita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Drug review: Safety and efficacy of bevacizumab for glioblastoma and other brain tumors</article-title>. <source>Jpn J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>