<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-47225</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095048</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Nutrition</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancer epidemiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancer risk factors</subject><subj-group><subject>Nutritional correlates of cancer</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cancer prevention</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oral medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Oral diseases</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics (mathematics)</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Meta-analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Confidence intervals</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Research assessment</subject><subj-group><subject>Systematic reviews</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research design</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical research design</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Meat Consumption and Risk of Oral Cavity and Oropharynx Cancer: A Meta-Analysis of Observational Studies</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Meat and Oral Cancer: A Meta-Analysis</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Xin-xin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Yun-gang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xiao-yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Gynecology, The Affiliated Hospital of Jining Medical University, Jining, Shandong Province, People’s Republic China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of ENT, The Affiliated Hospital of Jining Medical University, Jining, Shandong Province, People’s Republic China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Physiology, Jining Medical University, Jining, Shandong Province, People’s Republic China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Novelli</surname><given-names>Giuseppe</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Tor Vergata University of Rome, Italy</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">lixiaoyu1969@126.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JX XXY. Performed the experiments: JX XXY YGW XYL BB. Analyzed the data: JX XXY YGW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JX BB. Wrote the paper: JX.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<elocation-id>e95048</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Xu et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract><sec>
<title>Purpose</title>
<p>High meat consumption, especially red and processed meat consumption is associated with an increased risk of several cancers, however, evidence for oral cavity and oropharynx cancer is limited. Thus, we performed this meta-analysis to determine the association between intakes of total meat, processed meat, red meat, and white meat, and the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Electronic search of Pubmed, Embase, and Cochrane Library Central database was conducted to select relevant studies. Fixed-effect and random-effect models were used to estimate summary relative risks (RR) and the corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CIs). Potential sources of heterogeneity were detected by meta-regression. Subgroup analyses and sensitivity analysis were also performed.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>12 case–control studies and one cohort study were included in the analyses, including 501,730 subjects and 4,104 oral cavity and oropharynx cancer cases. Pooled results indicated that high consumption of total meat, red meat, and white meat were not significantly associated with increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer (RR = 1.14, 95% CI[0.78–1.68]; RR = 1.05, 95% CI[0.66, 1.66] and RR = 0.81, 95% CI[0.54, 1.22], respectively), while the high consumption of processed meat was significantly associated with a 91% increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer (RR = 1.91, 95% CI [1.19–3.06]). Sensitivity analysis indicated that no significant variation in combined RR by excluding any of the study, confirming the stability of present results.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The present meta-analysis suggested that high consumption of processed meat was significantly associated with an increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer, while there was no significantly association between total meat, red meat or white meat and the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer. More prospective cohort studies are warranted to confirm these associations.</p>
</sec></abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>The present work was supported by Shandong Provincial Natural Science Foundation of China (No. ZR2010HL045, ZR2010HL057), Jining city science and technology development plan program of jining science and technology bureau (No. 2012jnfs02; 2012jnfs11; 2012jnfs13), Youth Fund of Jining Medical University (No. JYQ2011KZ005), and a Project of Shandong Province Higher Educational Science and Technology Program (No. J12LE10). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Oral cavity and oropharynx cancer are the tenth most common cancer and seventh most common cause of cancer-related mortality worldwide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Jemal1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Mehanna1">[2]</xref>. The primary risk factors for oral cavity and oropharynx cancer have been well documented, including betel-quid chewing, tobacco smoking, and alcohol consumption <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Mehanna1">[2]</xref>. However, the roles of many putative risk factors in etiology of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer remain unclear. Numerous studies have shown that diet may also be of etiologic importance. As we know, meat plays an important part in a healthy, balanced diet, and high meat consumption, especially red and processed meat consumption has been found to be associated with an increased risk of several malignancies, such as colorectal cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Xu1">[3]</xref>, esophageal cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Salehi1">[4]</xref>, lung cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Yang1">[5]</xref>, bladder cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Wang1">[6]</xref>, and renal cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Faramawi1">[7]</xref>. The association of meat consumption as a potential risk for oral cavity and oropharynx cancer has been studied in several observational studies, however, these studies yielded different or even controversial results. For example, Lissowska J et al found that consumption of total meat, processed meat were inversely associated with the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Lissowska1">[8]</xref>, however, other investigators found that meat consumption was significantly associated with increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Toporcov1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Garrote1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Rajkumar1">[11]</xref>. Therefore, to better characterize the association between meat consumption and the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer, we conducted a comprehensive meta-analysis of the current observational studies.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Literature Search</title>
<p>The present meta-analysis was conducted following the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses guidelines(PRISMA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Moher1">[12]</xref>, and the meta-analysis of observational studies in epidemiology (MOOSE) guidelines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Stroup1">[13]</xref>. A literature search was carried out using Pubmed, Embase, and Cochrane Library Central database between January 1966 and May 2013. There was no restriction of origin and language. Search terms included: “meat” or “lamb” or “beef” or “pork” or “bacon” or “poultry” or “chicken” and ‘‘cancer(s)’’ or ‘‘neoplasm(s)’’ or ‘‘malignancy(ies)’’ and “oral” or “mouth” or “pharynx” or “pharyngeal” or “oropharyngeal”. The reference lists of each study included in this meta-analysis and previous reviews were manually examined to identify additional relevant studies.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Study selection</title>
<p>Two reviewers independently selected eligible studies. Disagreement between the two reviewers was settled by discussing with the third reviewer. Studies were selected if they met our criteria (i) had a case-control or cohort design; (ii) evaluated the association between meat (total meat, red meat, processed meat, or white meat) consumption and the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer, and (iii) presented odds ratio (OR), relative risk (RR), or hazard ratio (HR) estimates with its 95% confidence interval (CI).When there were multiple publications from the same population, only data from the most recent report was included in the meta-analysis and the others were excluded. Studies reporting different measures of RR like risk ratio, rate ratio, hazard ratio, and odds ratio were included in the meta-analysis. In practice, these measures of effect yield a similar estimate of RR, since the absolute risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer is low.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Data extraction and methodological quality assessment</title>
<p>The following data was collected by two reviewers independently using a purpose-designed form: name of the first author, publishing time, study region, study design, study period, number of cancer cases and subjects, dietary assessment method, the exposure of meat intake, quantity of intake, the study-specific adjusted ORs, RRs, or HRs with their 95% CIs for the highest category of meat consumption versus the lowest, confounding factors for matching or adjustments.</p>
<p>We used Newcastle-Ottawa scale to assess the methodologic quality of cohort and case-control studies. The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale contains eight items that are categorized three categories: selection (four items, one star each), comparability (one item, up to two stars), and exposure/outcome (three items, one star each). A ‘‘star’’ presents a ‘‘high-quality’’ choice of individual study. The full score was 9 stars, and the high-quality study was defined as a study with≥6 awarded stars.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Data synthesis and analysis</title>
<p>Heterogeneity was assessed using the Cochran Q and I<sup>2</sup> statistics. For the Q statistic, a P value&lt;0.10 was considered statistically significant for heterogeneity; for the I<sup>2</sup> statistic, heterogeneity was interpreted as absent (I<sup>2</sup>: 0%–25%), low (I<sup>2</sup>: 25.1%–50%), moderate (I<sup>2</sup>: 50.1%–75%), or high (I<sup>2</sup>: 75.1%–100%) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Higgins1">[14]</xref>. The overall analysis including all eligible studies was performed first, and subgroup analyses were performed according to (i) Study location(South America, North America, Europe, and Asia), and (ii)number of confounding factors (n≥7, n≤6), adjustment for alcohol intake (yes, no), adjustment for BMI (yes, no), adjustment for education(yes, no), adjustment for fruit and/or vegetable intake(yes, no), to examine the impact of these factors on the associations. When substantial heterogeneity was detected, the summary estimate based on the random-effect model (DerSimonian –Laird method) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-DerSimonian1">[15]</xref> was reported, which assumed that the studies included in the meta-analysis had varying effect sizes. Otherwise, the summary estimate based on the fixed-effect model (the inverse variance method) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Woolf1">[16]</xref> was reported, which assumed that the studies included in the meta-analysis had the same effect size. To test the robustness of the associations and characterize possible sources of statistical heterogeneity, sensitivity analysis was carried out by excluding studies one-by-one and analyzing the homogeneity and effect size for all of the rest studies. To better investigate the possible sources of between-study heterogeneity, a meta-regression analysis was performed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Higgins2">[17]</xref>. An univariate model was established, and then variables with P values ≥0.1 were entered into a multivariable model. Publication bias was assessed using Begg and Mazumdar adjusted rank correlation test and the Egger regression asymmetry test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Begg1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Egger1">[19]</xref>. All analyses were performed using Stata version 11.0 (StataCorp, College Station, TX).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Literature search and study characteristics</title>
<p>The detailed steps of our literature search are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0095048-g001">Figure 1</xref>. The search strategy generated 637 citations. On the basis of the titles and abstracts, we identified 17 relevant articles. After further evaluation, three studies were excluded for lack of available data, and two studies were excluded because they were from the same population. One study was identified from the reference lists. At last, a total of 13 eligible studies published between 1992 and 2012 were identified, including 12 case–control studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Lissowska1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Toporcov1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Garrote1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Rajkumar1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-DeStefani1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-EscribanoUzcudun1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Levi1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Petridou1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Sanchez1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Sapkota1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Zheng1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Zheng2">[27]</xref> and one cohort study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Daniel1">[28]</xref>(Baseline data and other details of included studies are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095048-t001">Table 1</xref>). A total of 501,730 subjects, including 4,104 oral cavity and oropharynx cancer cases were involved. Of the 13 included studies, six studies were conducted in Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Lissowska1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-EscribanoUzcudun1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Levi1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Petridou1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Sanchez1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Sapkota1">[25]</xref>, three studies in Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Rajkumar1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Zheng1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Zheng2">[27]</xref>, three studies in South America <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Toporcov1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Garrote1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-DeStefani1">[20]</xref>, and the remaining one study in North America <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Daniel1">[28]</xref>. Among the 12 case-control studies, only one study was population based <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Zheng2">[27]</xref>, and the others were hospital based. Most studies used food frequency questionnaires(FFQ) for the assessment of meat consumption. All studies adjusted for smoking, and most studies adjusted for some potential confounders, including age, sex, and alcohol consumption. The NOS scores for the included studies ranged from 4 to 8; nine studies were deemed to be of a high quality (≥6) (shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095048-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0095048-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Flow diagram of screened, excluded, and analysed publications.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0095048-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Characteristics of observational studies of the relation between meat intakes and risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer included in the meta-analysis.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0095048-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publication year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study design</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study period</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietary assessments</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases/Subjects</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Units and comparison groups</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confounders for adjustment</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NOS score</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">De Stefani E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uruguay</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hospital-based case–control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996–2004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFQ 64 items</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56/940</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">processed meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">g/day 11.5–28.2 vs ≤11.4 ≥28.3 vs ≤11.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">age, residence, BMI, smoking status, alcohol drinking, mate consumption, total energy, total vegetables and fruits, total white meat, and red meat intakes.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daniel CR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1995–1996</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFQ 124 items</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,305/492,186</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poultry</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q5 vs Q1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">age, sex, education, marital status, family history of cancer, race, BMI, smoking status, frequency of vigorous physical activity, menopausal hormone therapy in women, intake of alcohol, fruit, vegetables, fish, red meat, and total energy</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sapkota A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">central and eastern Europe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hospital-based case–control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1999–2003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFQ 23 items</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">378/1,606</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poultry, red meats</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tertile 3 vs Tertile 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">age, country, gender, tobacco pack-years, education, BMI, frequency of alcohol consumption, tertiles of total vegetable consumption, and tertiles of total fruit consumption</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levi F</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Switzerland</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hospital-based case–control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1992–2002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFQ 79 items</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">316/1,587</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Processed meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency/week 0.8–1.5 vs &lt;0.8 1.6–3.2 vs &lt;0.8 &gt;3.2 vs &lt;0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">age, sex, education, tobacco smoking, alcohol drinking, total energy intake, fruit and vegetable intake,BMI, and physical activity .</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toporcov TN</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hospital-based case–control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFQ 41 items</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70/140</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pepperoni,bacon, red meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">high vs low</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sex, age, smoking status, frequency for the use of dental prosthesis</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lissowska J</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hospital-based case–control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997–2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFQ 25 items</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122/246</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total meat, processed meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tertile 3 vs Tertile 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gender, age, residence, drinking and smoking habits</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rajkumar T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hospital-based case–control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996–1999</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFQ 21 items</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">591/1,773</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total meat, processed meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Servings/week 1-2 vs &lt;1 &gt;2 vs &lt;1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sex, age, centre, education, chewing, smoking and drinking habits</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sánchez MJ</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hospital-based case–control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996–1999</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFQ 25 items</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">375/750</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total meat, processed meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Servings/week 2-5 vs &lt;1 6 vs &lt;1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gender, age, centre, years of schooling, smoking and drinking habits</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Escribano Uzcudun A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hospital-based case–control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1990–1995</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interview-administered questionnaire</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232/464</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">high vs low</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tobacco smoking, and alcohol consumption</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petridou E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hospital-based case–control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFQ 110 items</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106/212</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meats and meat products</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">high vs low</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">energy intake, tobacco smoking, and alcohol consumption</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Garrote LF</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cuba</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hospital-based case–control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996–1999</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dietary questionnaire</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200/400</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total meat, processed meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Servings/week 3-5 vs &lt;3 &gt;6 vs &lt;3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gender, age, area of residence, education, smoking and drinking habits</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zheng T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hospital-based case–control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1989</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFQ 63 items</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">404/808</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Servings/month 1-2 vs &lt;1 &gt;3 vs &lt;1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tobacco smoking, alcohol drinking, inadequate dentition, years of education, Quetelet Index, sex and age</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zheng W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1992</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population-based case-control study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1988–1990</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFQ 42 items</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204/618</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salted meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">daily/weekly vs seldom</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">smoking and education.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>BMI =  body mass index; FFQ =  Food Frequency Questionnaire.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Total meat intake and the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer</title>
<p>Nine case–control studies of total meat distinction were included in the meta-analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Lissowska1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Toporcov1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Garrote1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Rajkumar1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-EscribanoUzcudun1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Petridou1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Sanchez1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Sapkota1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Zheng1">[26]</xref>. We found that the high consumption of total meat was not significantly associated with the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer (RR = 1.14, 95% CI[0.78–1.68]) (shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095048-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0095048-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Statistically significant heterogeneity was detected (I<sup>2</sup> = 82.9%, Q = 46.87, P&lt;0.001). There was no indication of a publication bias, either from Egger ’s test (P = 0.780) or from Begg ’ s test (P = 0.835 )(shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0095048-g004">Figure 4</xref> A). In subgroup analyses, when stratified the various studies by study location, no significant association was noted among studies conducted in Europe (RR = 0.93, 95%CI [0.55, 1.59]), and Asia (RR = 0.98, 95%CI [0.42, 2.29]), however, high consumption of total meat was significantly associated with a 118% increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer in South America (RR = 2.18, 95%CI [1.49, 3.20]). When we examined whether the associations were affected by adjustment for alcohol, BMI, education, and fruit and/or vegetable intake, the associations were not affected by these factors(shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095048-t002">Table 2</xref>). Further, it was observed that studies with higher control for potential confounders (n≥7) as well as studies with lower control (n≤6) presented no significant association (RR = 1.02, 95% CI[0.59, 1.74] and RR = 1.21, 95% CI[0.70, 2.09], respectively). Sensitivity analysis indicated that no significant variation in combined RR by excluding any of the study, confirming the stability of present results. Meta-regression analysis was performed to investigate the possible sources of between-study heterogeneity. Geographic area, sex, age, study quality, publication year, control for confounding factors(alcohol, BMI, education, and fruit and/or vegetable intake) which may be potential sources of heterogeneity, were tested by a meta-regression method. We found that study quality( P = 0.029) had statistical significance in a multivariate model.</p>
<fig id="pone-0095048-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Forest plot: estimates (95% CIs) of total meat consumption and risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer.</title>
<p>Squares indicated study-specific risk estimates (size of square reflects the study-statistical weight, i.e. inverse of variance); horizontal lines indicate 95% confidence intervals; diamond indicates summary relative risk estimate with its corresponding 95% confidence interval.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0095048-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Forest plot: estimates (95% CIs) of processed meat consumption and risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer.</title>
<p>Squares indicated study-specific risk estimates (size of square reflects the study-statistical weight, i.e. inverse of variance); horizontal lines indicate 95% confidence intervals; diamond indicates summary relative risk estimate with its corresponding 95% confidence interval.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0095048-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Begger's funnel plot of publication.</title>
<p>A: Funnel plot for studies investigating total meat consumption and risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer; B: Funnel plot for studies investigating processed meat consumption and risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0095048-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Summary relative risks of the association between meat consumption and risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0095048-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of studies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR (95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value for heterogeneity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sup>2</sup> value (%)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall studies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Total meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.78–1.68)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Processed meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91 (1.19–3.06)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Red meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.66–1.66)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81(0.54–1.22)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subgroup analyses for total meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Continent</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Europe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.55–1.59)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  South America</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18 (1.49–3.20)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Asia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.42–2.29)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted for confounders</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">   n≥7 confounders</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.59–1.74)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">   n≤6 confounders</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 (0.70–2.09)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Major confounders adjusted</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12(0.73–1.71)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14(0.73–1.78)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Alcohol</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15(0.77–1.73)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17(0.36–3.84)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Education</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18(0.75–1.88)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04(0.48–2.28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fruit and/or vegetable intake</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12(0.73–1.71)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14(0.73–1.78)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subgroup analyses for processed meat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Continent</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Europe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64(0.59–4.60)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  South America</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93(1.25–3.00)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Asia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09(0.70–6.29)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Adjusted for confounders</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">   n≥7 confounders</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94(0.97–3.88)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">   n≤6 confounders</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86(0.92–3.74)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Major confounders adjusted</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00(0.94–4.24)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86(0.96–3.23)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Alcohol</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71(0.97–3.00)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.91(1.81–4.67)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Education</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88(1.02–3.46)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98(0.95–4.13)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fruit and/or vegetable intake</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> yes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00(0.94–4.24)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> no</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86(0.96–3.23)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.70</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>BMI =  body mass index; CI = confidence interval; RR = relative risk.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Processed meat intake and risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer</title>
<p>Nine case–control studies of processed meat distinction were included in the meta-analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Toporcov1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Garrote1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Rajkumar1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-DeStefani1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Levi1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Sanchez1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Sapkota1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Zheng1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Zheng2">[27]</xref>. We found that the high consumption of processed meat was significantly associated with a 91% increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer (RR = 1.91, 95% CI [1.19–3.06]) (shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095048-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0095048-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Statistically significant heterogeneity was detected (I<sup>2</sup> = 85.9%, Q = 46.87, P&lt;0.001). There was no indication of a publication bias, either from Egger ’s test ( P = 0.999) or from Begg ’ s test ( P = 0.297) (shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0095048-g004">Figure 4</xref> B). In subgroup analyses, when stratified the various studies by study location, high consumption of total meat was significantly associated with a 93% increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer in South America (RR = 1.93, 95%CI [1.25, 3.00]), however, no significant association was noted among studies conducted in Europe (RR = 1.64, 95%CI [0.59, 4.60]), and Asia (RR = 2.09, 95%CI [0.70, 6.29]). When we examined if thorough adjustment of potential confounders could affect the combined RR, it was observed that studies with higher control for potential confounders (n≥7) as well as studies with lower control (n≤6) presented no significant association (RR = 1.94, 95% CI[0.97, 3.88] and RR = 1.86, 95% CI[0.92, 3.74], respectively). However, we found that the associations were significantly affected by adjustment for alcohol consumption and education (shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095048-t002">Table 2</xref>). Sensitivity analysis indicated that no significant variation in combined RR by excluding any of the study, confirming the stability of present results. Meta-regression analysis was performed to investigate the possible sources of between-study heterogeneity. Geographic area, sex, age, study quality, publication year, control for confounding factors(alcohol, BMI, education, and fruit and/or vegetable intake) which may be potential sources of heterogeneity, were tested by a meta-regression method. However, meta-regression revealed that none of the above factors was responsible for the between-study heterogeneity.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Red, white meat intake and the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer</title>
<p>Three case–control studies of red meat distinction were included in the meta-analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Toporcov1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Sapkota1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Zheng1">[26]</xref>. And two case–control studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Sapkota1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Zheng1">[26]</xref> and one cohort study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Daniel1">[28]</xref> of white meat distinction were included in the meta-analysis. It was founded that neither red meat nor white meat was associated with an increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer(RR = 1.05, 95% CI[0.66, 1.66] and RR = 0.81, 95% CI[0.54, 1.22], respectively).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>To our knowledge, it was the first meta-analysis evaluating the association between meat consumption and oral cavity and oropharynx cancer risk. Twelve case-control studies and one cohort study were included in the present analysis, involving 501,730 participants and 4,104 oral cavity and oropharynx cancer cases. In the present study, we found that the total meat consumption was not significantly associated with the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer. When we investigated different types of meat and the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer, we found that processed meat consumption was significantly associated with an increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer, however, no statistically significant association was observed between red meat or white meat intake and the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer.</p>
<p>Processed meat (meat preserved by smoking, curing, salting, or by addition of chemical preservatives) has been found to be associated with several tumors, such as colorectal adenomas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Xu1">[3]</xref>, esophageal cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Salehi1">[4]</xref>, bladder cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Wang1">[6]</xref>, and renal cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Faramawi1">[7]</xref>. The finding of our meta-analysis was in line with these meta-analyses. Processed meat has been hypothesized to play a important role in carcinogenesis, owing to their high levels of saturated fat and heme iron content, and potent mutagens produced during high temperature cooking and meat processing or preservation, including N –nitroso compounds (NOCs) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Haorah1">[29]</xref>, polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons(PAHs) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Phillips1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Kazerouni1">[31]</xref>, and heterocyclic amines (HCAs) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Puangsombat1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Sinha1">[33]</xref>. NOCs intake may contribute to carcinogenesis at a variety of anatomic sites in animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Mirvish1">[34]</xref>. PAHs and HCAs, which can form DNA adducts and induce genetic alterations characteristic of tumors, have been shown to be carcinogens in animal studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Ohgaki1">[35]</xref>. During subgroup analyses, after being stratified by study location, it demonstrated that processed meat consumption had a significant association with increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer in south Americans, however, it could not be validated in Asians or Europeans. So, the strength of the association varied greatly across ethnic groups. The possible reasons were considerable differences in genetic background, life styles and environmental factors. In addition, we should notice that there were only two included studies investigating meat intake and the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer among Asians, and limited number of patients may limit us to detect stable effects in this population. Additional studies are warranted to further validate ethnic difference in the effect of meat intake on oral cavity and oropharynx cancer risk, especially in Asians.</p>
<p>Red meat is a source of heme iron, which is more bioavailable than non-heme iron. Heme iron is contributed to carcinogenesis in rodents by generating free radicals and inducing oxidative stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Huang1">[36]</xref>. Heme iron has also been shown to induce endogenous formation of NOCs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Cross1">[37]</xref>. Previous meta-analyses have shown that red meat intake was associated with an increased risk of colorectal adenomas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Xu1">[3]</xref>, esophageal cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Salehi1">[4]</xref>, lung cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Yang1">[5]</xref>, bladder cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Wang1">[6]</xref>, and renal cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095048-Faramawi1">[7]</xref>. However, the result of the present meta-analysis showed that red meat consumption was not significantly associated with an increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer. We should notice that there were only three studies investigating the relationship between red meat intake and oral cavity and oropharynx cancer risk, which limited us to get a narrow confidence interval and detect stable effects. So, more studies focusing on red meat and oral cavity and oropharynx cancer risk are needed in the future.</p>
<p>The strength of the present meta-analysis lies in a large sample size (501,730 subjects and 4,104 oral cavity and oropharynx cancer cases) and no significant evidence of publication bias. All studies adjusted for smoking, and most studies adjusted for some potential confounders, including age, sex, and alcohol consumption. Furthermore, our findings were stable and robust in sensitivity analyses. However, several limitations to this meta-analysis should be noted. Firstly, as a meta-analysis of observational data, the possibility of recall and selection biases can’t be ruled out. Compared with case-control studies, cohort studies are less susceptible to bias due to their nature. However, the present meta-analysis included only one cohort study, so more prospective cohort studies are needed to confirm the association in the future. Secondly, we did not search for unpublished studies, so only published studies were included in our meta-analysis. Therefore, publication bias may have occurred although no publication bias was indicated from both visualization of the funnel plot and Egger’s test. Thirdly, none of the included studies adjusted for betel-quid chewing, which is one of the primary risk factors for oral cavity and oropharynx cancer. Lastly, due to different methods used to report meat intake among studies, we failed to carry out a dose-response analysis between meat intake and the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the present meta-analysis suggested that a high intake of processed meat was significantly associated with an increased risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer, while there was no significantly association between total meat, red meat or white meat and the risk of oral cavity and oropharynx cancer. More prospective cohort studies are warranted to confirm these associations.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0095048.s001" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095048.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Checklist S1</label><caption>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Jemal1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Center</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Global cancer statistics</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Mehanna1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehanna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paleri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nutting</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Head and neck cancer-part 1: epidemiology, presentation, and preservation</article-title>. <source>Clin Otolaryngol</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Xu1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Red and processed meat intake and risk of colorectal adenomas: a meta-analysis of observational studies</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Salehi1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moradi-Lakeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nojomi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolahdooz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Meat, fish, and esophageal cancer risk: a systematic review and dose-response meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Nutr Rev</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Yang1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vogtmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>RQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Meat consumption and risk of lung cancer: evidence from observational studies</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3163</fpage>–<lpage>3170</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Wang1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Meat intake and risk of bladder cancer: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Med Oncol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>848</fpage>–<lpage>855</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Faramawi1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faramawi</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Consumption of different types of meat and the risk of renal cancer: meta-analysis of case-control studies</article-title>. <source>Cancer Causes Control</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Lissowska1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lissowska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pilarska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pilarski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samolczyk-Wanyura</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piekarczyk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Smoking, alcohol, diet, dentition and sexual practices in the epidemiology of oral cancer in Poland</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer Prev</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Toporcov1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toporcov</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tavares</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Fat food habitual intake and risk of oral cancer</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>925</fpage>–<lpage>931</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Garrote1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrote</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaccarella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anta</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Risk factors for cancer of the oral cavity and oro-pharynx in Cuba</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Rajkumar1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajkumar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balaram</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaccarella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gajalakshmi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Oral cancer in Southern India: the influence of body size, diet, infections and sexual practices</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer Prev</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Moher1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Group</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Stroup1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stroup</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olkin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis of observational studies in epidemiology: a proposal for reporting. Meta-analysis Of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (MOOSE) group</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>2008</fpage>–<lpage>2012</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Higgins1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>327</volume>: <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-DerSimonian1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DerSimonian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Control Clin Trials</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Woolf1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1955</year>) <article-title>On estimating the relation between blood group and disease</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Genet</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Higgins2"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Controlling the risk of spurious findings from meta-regression</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1663</fpage>–<lpage>1682</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Begg1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>1101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Egger1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-DeStefani1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Stefani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boffetta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronco</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deneo-Pellegrini</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Processed meat consumption and risk of cancer: a multisite case-control study in Uruguay</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>1584</fpage>–<lpage>1588</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-EscribanoUzcudun1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Escribano Uzcudun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rabanal Retolaza</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia Grande</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miralles Olivar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia Garcia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Pharyngeal cancer prevention: evidence from a case—control study involving 232 consecutive patients</article-title>. <source>J Laryngol Otol</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>531</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Levi1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pasche</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lucchini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bosetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>La Vecchia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Processed meat and the risk of selected digestive tract and laryngeal neoplasms in Switzerland</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>346</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Petridou1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petridou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zavras</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lefatzis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dessypris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laskaris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The role of diet and specific micronutrients in the etiology of oral carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>2981</fpage>–<lpage>2988</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Sanchez1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castellsague</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quintana</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Oral and oropharyngeal cancer in Spain: influence of dietary patterns</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer Prev</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Sapkota1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sapkota</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaridze</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shangina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szeszenia-Dabrowska</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dietary risk factors for squamous cell carcinoma of the upper aerodigestive tract in central and eastern Europe</article-title>. <source>Cancer Causes Control</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1161</fpage>–<lpage>1170</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Zheng1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>A case-control study of oral cancer in Beijing, People's Republic of China. Associations with nutrient intakes, foods and food groups</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer B Oral Oncol</source> <volume>29B</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Zheng2"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blot</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>XO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Risk factors for oral and pharyngeal cancer in Shanghai, with emphasis on diet</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Daniel1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graubard</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hollenbeck</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Prospective investigation of poultry and fish intake in relation to cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Cancer Prev Res (Phila)</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1903</fpage>–<lpage>1911</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Haorah1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haorah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirvish</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Determination of total N-nitroso compounds and their precursors in frankfurters, fresh meat, dried salted fish, sauces, tobacco, and tobacco smoke particulates</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>6068</fpage>–<lpage>6078</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Phillips1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in the diet</article-title>. <source>Mutat Res</source> <volume>443</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Kazerouni1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazerouni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of 200 food items for benzo[a]pyrene and estimation of its intake in an epidemiologic study</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>423</fpage>–<lpage>436</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Puangsombat1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puangsombat</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gadgil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Houser</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Heterocyclic amine content in commercial ready to eat meat products</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Sinha1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knize</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Heterocyclic amine content of pork products cooked by different methods and to varying degrees of doneness</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Mirvish1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirvish</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Role of N-nitroso compounds (NOC) and N-nitrosation in etiology of gastric, esophageal, nasopharyngeal and bladder cancer and contribution to cancer of known exposures to NOC</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Ohgaki1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohgaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kusama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsukura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Carcinogenicity in mice of a mutagenic compound, 2-amino-3-methylimidazo[4,5-f]quinoline, from broiled sardine, cooked beef and beef extract</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>921</fpage>–<lpage>924</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Huang1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Iron overload and its association with cancer risk in humans: evidence for iron as a carcinogenic metal</article-title>. <source>Mutat Res</source> <volume>533</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095048-Cross1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Meat-related mutagens/carcinogens in the etiology of colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Environ Mol Mutagen</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>