<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-03703</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093938</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics of the immune system</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical genetics</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Surgical and invasive medical procedures</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Combined Effects of <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C and +915 G/C Polymorphisms on Acute Rejection Risk in Solid Organ Transplant Recipients: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>TGFB1</italic> Haplotypes and Acute Rejection</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>Yu-Zheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Ran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Tian-Ze</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Rui-Peng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Ming-Hao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Xiao-Fei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Xiao-Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Xian-Bo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Liang-Peng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Si-Jia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Qun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Wen-Cheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Jia-Geng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Center for Renal Transplantation, Nanjing First Hospital, Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Urology, Nanjing First Hospital, Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Cardiology, Nanjing First Hospital, Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of General Surgery, Nanjing First Hospital, Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery, Nanjing First Hospital, Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>William B.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of North Carolina School of Medicine, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">ruipeng_jia@yeah.net</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YZG RPJ. Performed the experiments: YZG RW TZL MHL XFG XMJ XBZ LPL SJT QS WCL JGZ. Analyzed the data: YZG RW TZL WCL JGZ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YZG MHL XFG XBZ LPL. Wrote the paper: YZG RW LPL. Proofread and revised the paper: RPJ.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<elocation-id>e93938</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Ge et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract><sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>Transforming growth factor-beta 1(TGF-β1) is involved in the development of acute rejection (AR) episodes in solid organ transplant recipients; and a number of studies have been conducted to investigate the combined effects of human TGF-β1 gene (<italic>TGFB1</italic>) +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms on AR risk. However, the results obtained are inconclusive.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Eligible studies that investigated the haplotypic association between <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms and AR risk were comprehensively searched in the PUBMED, EMBASE, China National Knowledge Infrastructure, and Wanfang Database. Statistical analyses were performed by using STATA 12.0 and Review Manager 5.0.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>Fourteen eligible studies with 565 AR cases and 1219 non-AR cases were included. Overall, a significantly decreased risk was detected in patients carried with intermediate producer (IP) haplotypes (T/C G/C, T/T G/C, and C/C G/G) and/or low producer (LP) haplotypes (C/C G/C, C/C C/C, T/T C/C, and T/C C/C) compared with high producer (HP) haplotypes (T/T G/G and T/C G/G; IP vs. HP: OR = 0.75, 95% CI, 0.58–0.96, P <sub>heterogeneity</sub>  = 0.238; IP/LP vs. HP: OR  = 0.77, 95% CI, 0.61–0.98, P <sub>heterogeneity</sub>  = 0.144). In addition, subgroup analysis by transplant types demonstrated a similar association in patients receiving heart transplant (IP vs. HP: OR  = 0.32, 95% CI, 0.14–0.73, P <sub>heterogeneity</sub>  = 0.790; IP/LP vs. HP: OR  = 0.41, 95% CI, 0.20–0.85, P <sub>heterogeneity</sub>  = 0.320).</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The current meta-analysis and systematic review indicated that recipient <italic>TGFB1</italic> HP haplotypes were significantly associated with an increased risk for AR in solid organ transplant recipients, particularly patients receiving cardiac allograft.</p>
</sec></abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This project was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81070597, 81370853), Science and Education Development Program of the Jiangsu Province Health Board (LJ201107), Six Talent Peaks of the Jiangsu Province Health Bureau (2011-WS-093) and Research and Innovation Program for Graduates of Jiangsu Province (CXZZ13_0583). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Transforming growth factor-beta 1 (TGF-β1) is a multifunctional cytokine ubiquitously produced by a wide variety of cells, including T lymphocytes, monocytes, vascular endothelium, and renal tubular cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Li1">[1]</xref>. Functionally, TGF-β1 has been proven to be of fundamental importance in the development of various disorders <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Blobe1">[2]</xref>, including coronary heart disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Edgley1">[3]</xref>, human cancers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Massague1">[4]</xref>, rheumatoid arthritis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Hussein1">[5]</xref>, asthma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Gagliardo1">[6]</xref> and transplant rejection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Hutchinson1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-MorrisStiff1">[8]</xref>. In the setting of solid organ transplants, TGF-β1 has been conventionally recognized as a guardian against acute rejection (AR), as higher level of TGF-β1 in the graft tissue and serum was found in non-AR recipients than those suffering AR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Tambur1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Benza1">[11]</xref>. However, several novel lines of evidence have challenged the beneficial effects of TGF-β1 on transplant recipients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Hoffmann1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-DiFilippo1">[13]</xref>. Although the functional role of TGF-β1 in AR initiation remains elusive, this cytokine is believed to exert pivotal and complicated functions in AR episodes.</p>
<p>The human TGF-β1 gene (<italic>TGFB1</italic>) is mapped on the chromosome 19q13.1–13.3 with seven exons and six introns, whose regulation and expression is influenced by the presence of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Shah1">[14]</xref>. Among these SNPs, +869 T/C (also known as rs1800470, T29C, or Leu10Pro) and +915 G/C (also termed as rs1800471, G74C, or Arg25Pro) polymorphisms in the first exon of <italic>TGFB1</italic> have been the focus of extensive researches and donor <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C polymorphism has been proven to be significantly associated with AR risk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Ge1">[15]</xref>. These two SNPs together result in nine potential inherited haplotypes, which could be categorized into three groups according to the <italic>in vitro</italic> production levels: high producer (HP) (T/T G/G and T/C G/G), intermediate producer (IP) (T/C G/C, T/T G/C, and C/C G/G) and low producer (LP) (C/C G/C, C/C C/C, T/T C/C and T/C C/C) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Awad1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Perrey1">[17]</xref>. Since the first study conducted by Pelletier et al to evaluate the haplotypic association of <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms with AR risk in kidney transplant recipients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Pelletier1">[18]</xref>, numerous molecular epidemiological studies have been conducted in different solid organ transplants, including kidney transplants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Tian1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Dhaouadi1">[26]</xref>, liver transplants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Tambur1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Karasu1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-GomezMateo1">[28]</xref>, and heart transplants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-DiFilippo1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Gourley1">[29]</xref>. However, the results of these studies were inconclusive.</p>
<p>In this meta-analysis, we integrated the data from all eligible studies to explore 1) the combined effects of recipient <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms on AR risk after solid organ transplantation and 2) the potential influence of covariants such as ethnicity, transplantation types, and immunosuppressive protocols.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Identification of eligible studies</title>
<p>This meta-analysis was conducted and reported in accordance with the PRISMA (Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses) guidelines (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093938.s004">Checklist S1</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Moher1">[30]</xref>. To identify all eligible studies that investigated the haplotypic association of <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms with AR risk in solid organ transplantation, a comprehensive electronic search of PUBMED, EMBASE, China National Knowledge Infrastructure (CNKI), and Wanfang databases was performed until November 29, 2013. To search and include as many related studies as possible, we applied various combinations of the following medical subject headings and key words: transforming growth factor beta-1, TGFβ-1, or <italic>TGFB1</italic>; acute rejection, early allograft outcome, or graft rejection; transplantation or organ transplantation; polymorphisms or variants. Furthermore, the reference lists of reviews and retrieved articles were manually screened for additional studies No restrictions were placed on language, and only published studies with full-text articles were included.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title>
<p>The studies identified from the above mentioned databases were screened by two independent authors (Yu-Zheng Ge and Ran Wu) according to the following predesigned inclusion criteria: 1) case-control design; 2) evaluating the correlation of <italic>TGFB1</italic> haplotypes (at position +869 and +915) with AR risk; and 3) providing sufficient data to calculate the odds ratio (OR) and its corresponding 95% confidence interval (CI). When several studies with overlapping data were eligible, those with smaller sample size or less reliability were excluded. In addition, studies without detailed information were excluded, after the efforts to extract data from the original paper or contact the corresponding authors failed.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Data extraction</title>
<p>Data of eligible studies were extracted by two reviewers (Yu-Zheng Ge and Tian-Ze Lu) independently and in duplicate according to the predesigned data-collection form. The following information was extracted: last name of first author, publication year, country of origin, ethnicity, transplantation type, immunosuppressive protocol, number of both ARs and non-ARs and phenotypic distribution in both groups. Different ethnic descents were categorized as Asian, Caucasian, African and Mixed (which included more than one ethnic descent). Transplantation types were characterized as renal, liver, and heart transplantation. Based on different calcineurin inhibitors (CNIs) within the immunosuppressive protocol, the studies were divided into two subgroups: Cyclosporine A (CsA) group and CsA/tacrolimus (FK506) group. Discrepancies occurring during the process of study inclusion and data extraction were resolved by discussion with a third reviewer (Wen-Cheng Li), and consensus on each item was achieved eventually.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Crude OR and its corresponding 95% CI were used to assess the strength of association between the haplotypes of +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms in <italic>TGFB1</italic> gene and AR risk. The HP haplotypes (T/T G/G and T/C G/G) were used as the baseline for calculation of ORs in three different comparisons (LP vs. HP, IP vs. HP and LP/IP vs. HP). Stratified analyses were also conducted based on ethnicity, transplant types, and immunosuppressive protocols. The statistical significance of the pooled OR was assessed with the Z test, and P&lt;0.05 was considered significant.</p>
<p>Chi-square based Q-test was performed to measure between-study heterogeneity, and the presence of heterogeneity was considered significant if P&lt;0.10 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Higgins1">[31]</xref>. When the heterogeneity was absent, the fixed-effect model (Mantel-Haenszel method) was used to pool the data from different studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Mantel1">[32]</xref>; otherwise, the random-effects model (DerSimonian and Laird method) was applied <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-DerSimonian1">[33]</xref>. Sensitivity analyses were conducted to identify the effect of individual study on pooled results and to test the reliability of results by deleting a single study each time <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Thakkinstian1">[34]</xref>. To determine the presence of publication bias, both Begg's funnel plot and Egger's linear regression test were conducted, and P&lt;0.05 was considered significant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Begg1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Egger1">[36]</xref>.</p>
<p>All statistical analyses were performed with STATA software (version 12.0; Stata Corporation, College Station, Texas, USA) and Review Manager (version 5.0; Cochrane Collaboration, Oxford, UK).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Characteristics of eligible studies</title>
<p>Fourteen eligible articles were identified according to the predesigned selection criteria, and the detailed screening process was shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093938-g001">Figure 1</xref>. Among the 14 eligible studies, 9 were renal transplantation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Pelletier1">[18]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Dhaouadi1">[26]</xref>, 3 were liver transplantation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Tambur1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Karasu1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-GomezMateo1">[28]</xref>, and 2 were heart transplantation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-DiFilippo1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Gourley1">[29]</xref>. As for ethnicity, 7 were studies of Caucasians <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Tambur1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Lacha1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Canossi1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Karasu1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-GomezMateo1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Seyhun2">[37]</xref>, 3 studies were of Asians <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Tian1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Gu1">[21]</xref>, and 4 studies of mixed ethnicity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-DiFilippo1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Pelletier1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Dhaouadi1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Gourley1">[29]</xref>. Regarding the immunosuppressive protocols, patients were uniformly prescribed with CsA in 5 studies<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Pelletier1">[18]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Tian2">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Canossi1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Gourley1">[29]</xref> while in the remaining 9 studies were applied with either CsA or FK506<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Tambur1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-DiFilippo1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Gu1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Lacha1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Kocierz1">[24]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-GomezMateo1">[28]</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093938-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0093938-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Flow diagram for study selection.</title>
<p>Description: A total of 14 studies were included in this meta-analysis and systematic review after a comprehensive study selection.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0093938-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Characteristics and haplotypes distribution of eligible studies included in the meta-analysis.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0093938-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transplant types</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNIs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR/non-AR</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">AR cases</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Non-AR</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LP</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelletier</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tambur</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA/FK506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19/72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gu</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA/FK506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karasu</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA/FK506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gourley</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lacha</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Czech</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA/FK506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117/228</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Di Filippo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA/FK506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39/72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gómez-Mateo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA/FK506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/108</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canossi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kocierz</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA/FK506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49/150</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seyhun</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA/FK506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19/71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dhaouadi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tunisia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA/FK506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80/151</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Abbreviations: RTx, renal transplantation; LTx, liver transplantation; HTx, heart transplantation; CNIs, calcineurin inhibitors; CsA, cyclosporine A; FK506, tacrolimus; AR, acute rejection; LP, low producer; IP, intermediate producer; HP, high producer.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Quantitative data synthesis</title>
<p>A total of 14 studies including 565 AR and 1219 non-AR cases were identified to assess the haplotypic association of <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms with AR risk of solid organ transplantation. Overall, a significantly decreased risk was detected in two comparisons (IP vs. HP: OR  = 0.75, 95% CI, 0.58–0.96, P <sub>heterogeneity</sub>  = 0.238, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093938-g002">Figure 2</xref>; IP/LP vs. HP: OR  = 0.77, 95% CI, 0.61–0.98, P <sub>heterogeneity</sub>  = 0.144, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093938-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Subgroup analyses based on ethnicity, transplant types, and immunosuppressive protocols were subsequently conducted, and the results demonstrated a remarkably decreased risk in heart transplant recipients (IP vs. HP: OR  = 0.32, 95% CI, 0.14–0.73, P <sub>heterogeneity</sub>  = 0.790, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093938-g002">Figure 2</xref>; IP/LP vs. HP: OR  = 0.41, 95% CI, 0.20–0.85, P <sub>heterogeneity</sub>  = 0.320, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093938-g003">Figure 3</xref>) and in patients uniformly administrated with CsA (IP vs. HP: OR = 0.57, 95% CI, 0.34–0.94, P <sub>heterogeneity</sub> = 0.491). <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093938-t002">Table 2</xref> represents the strength of association between <italic>TGFB1</italic> haplotypes (at position +869 and +915) and AR risk in transplant recipients.</p>
<fig id="pone-0093938-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Forest plot for risk of acute rejection associated with <italic>TGFB1</italic> haplotypes (IP vs. HP) stratified by transplant types.</title>
<p>For each study, the estimate of OR and its 95% CI is plotted with a <italic>box</italic> and a <italic>horizontal line</italic>. <italic>Filled diamond</italic> pooled OR and its 95% CI.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0093938-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Forest plot for risk of acute rejection associated with <italic>TGFB1</italic> haplotypes (LP/IP vs. HP) stratified by transplant types.</title>
<p>For each study, the estimate of OR and its 95% CI is plotted with a <italic>box</italic> and a <italic>horizontal line</italic>. <italic>Filled diamond</italic> pooled OR and its 95% CI.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0093938-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Stratification analyses of combined effects of <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms on acute rejection risk.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0093938-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category</td>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">LP vs. HP</td>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">IP vs. HP</td>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">LP/IP vs. HP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR(95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR(95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR(95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10(0.71,1.71)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.665</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.373</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.75(0.58,0.96)</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.021</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.238</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.77(0.61,0.98)</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.030</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Ethnicity</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14(0.05,29.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.938</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76(0.36,1.60)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.466</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.242</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74(0.35,1.55)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.425</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.303</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93(0.54,1.61)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.807</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.165</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80(0.58,1.10)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.251</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78(0.58,1.06)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.094</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58(0.72,3.49)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.258</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.507</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65(0.42,1.03)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77(0.51,1.16)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.214</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.160</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Transplantation Types</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23(0.75,2.01)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.406</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.401</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88(0.66,1.17)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.377</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.290</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91(0.69,1.19)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.473</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.154</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33(0.07,1.69)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.185</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.996</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64(0.35,1.16)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.142</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.737</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59(0.33,1.06)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.774</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HTx</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50(0.34,6.57)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.594</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.180</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.32(0.14,0.73)</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.006</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.790</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.41(0.20,0.85)</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.017</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.320</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Immunosuppressive protocol</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37(0.41,4.59)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.607</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.462</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.57(0.34,0.94)</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.027</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.491</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62(0.38,1.01)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsA/FK506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07(0.66,1.71)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.793</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82(0.62,1.09)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.194</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83(0.64,1.08)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Abbreviations: RTx, renal transplantation; LTx, liver transplantation; HTx, heart transplantation; CsA, cyclosporine A; FK506, tacrolimus; LP, low producer; IP, intermediate producer; HP, high producer.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>—, cannot be calculated;</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>a</label><p>Number of eligible studies;</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>b</label><p>P value of Z-test for significance of OR;</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>c</label><p>P value of Q-test for heterogeneity test;</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label>d</label><p><bold>Statistically significant results (in bold).</bold></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Heterogeneity test and sensitivity analysis</title>
<p>No significant between-study heterogeneity was observed in this meta-analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093938-t002">Table 2</xref>). Sensitivity analysis was also performed to explore the potential influence of each individual study on the overall results by deleting one single study each time from the pooled analysis. NO substantial change was demonstrated in the overall studies, indicating that no individual study could affect the pooled OR significantly (data not shown).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Publication bias</title>
<p>To examine the publication bias of the currently available literature, both Begg's funnel plot and Egger's test were conducted. The shape of the funnel plots did not reveal any evidence of obvious asymmetry in all comparison models (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093938.s001">Figures S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093938.s002">S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093938.s003">S3</xref>). Then, the Egger's test was used to provide statistical evidence for funnel plot symmetry. The results also did not show any evidence of publication bias (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093938.s005">Table S1</xref>).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Organ transplantation has been recommended as the most optimal treatment choice for patients suffering end-stage disease. However, AR still remains a crucial determining factor which influences the short-term function and long-term outcome of both recipients and allografts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Opelz1">[38]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Thurairajah1">[40]</xref>. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first meta-analysis focusing on the combined effects of <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms on AR risk. In the current study, we provide evidence that patients carried with <italic>TGFB1</italic> HP haplotypes (T/T G/G and T/C G/G) are more likely to suffer from AR after solid organ transplantation (specifically heart transplantation), which could be utilized to identify patients predisposed to AR and potentially benefiting from tailored immunosuppressive protocol.</p>
<p>After pooling the data from 14 eligible studies, we shown that patients with <italic>TGFB1</italic> IP and/or LP haplotypes were less likely to suffer from AR than those with HP haplotypes (IP vs. HP: OR  = 0.75, 95% CI, 0.58–0.96; IP/LP vs. HP: OR  = 0.77, 95% CI, 0.61–0.98). Considering that ethnic background could influence the frequency of genotypes and haplotypes in some context, we conducted subgroup analysis based on ethnicities but failed to detect any significant association. Further stratified analysis by transplant types demonstrated a remarkably decreased AR risk for heart transplant recipients carried with <italic>TGFB1</italic> IP and/or LP haplotypes, which was in agreement with the study conducted in a cohort of 111 pediatric cardiac transplant recipients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-DiFilippo1">[13]</xref>. With respect to various CNIs applied in suppressive protocols, CsA and FK506 have been proven to influence the serum level of TGF-β1 differentially <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Dai1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Pakosz1">[42]</xref>; thus, we intended to investigate the various impacts of different CNIs on the relationship between the <italic>TGFB1</italic> haplotypes and AR risk. However, FK506 has never been administrated as a unique CNI in any included studies. Therefore, we divided the studies into two subgroups: CsA arm and CsA/FK506 arm, and then conducted a subgroup analysis. As a result, patients with <italic>TGFB1</italic> IP haplotypes were less likely to be affected by AR in CsA arm (IP vs. HP: OR  = 0.57, 95% CI, 0.34–0.94), which could be interpreted as a clue that the recipients with <italic>TGFB1</italic> IP haplotypes can benefit from CsA after organ transplantation.</p>
<p>TGF-β1 is a pleiotropic and multifunctional cytokine with immunosuppressive and fibrogenic properties, which may play a central role in both the initiation and propagation of AR and chronic rejection (CR) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Hutchinson1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-MorrisStiff1">[8]</xref>. The expression of TGF-β1 has been proven to be regulated by the two SNPs (+869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms), whose combination could be divided into three groups (LP, IP, and HP). However, the results obtained have challenged the conventional concept that TGF-β1 may inhibit the initiation of AR episodes. Our team previously demonstrated that donor <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C HP genotype (TT) was significantly associated with decreased AR risk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Ge1">[15]</xref>. Considering the obvious discrepancies, several questions have been raised: 1) The impact of various haplotypes of <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms on actual production levels of TGF-β1. The effects of the nine potential haplotypes on TGF-β1 expression levels have been previously studied <italic>in vitro</italic> and among patients without organ transplant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Awad1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Yamada1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Suthanthiran1">[44]</xref>. However, no significant association between <italic>TGFB1</italic> SNPs and TGF-β1 plasma levels or intragraft mRNA levels was detected in a cohort of renal transplant recipients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Hueso1">[45]</xref>. 2) The influence of various immunosuppressive protocols on the expression level of TGF-β1. CsA and FK506 were found to influence the serum level of TGF-β1 differentially <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Dai1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Pakosz1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Hueso1">[45]</xref>, while the impact of other immunosuppressive regimens still remains elusive. 3) The potential effects of donor and/or donor-recipient pair <italic>TGFB1</italic> haplotypes on AR risk. The current study is confined to recipient SNPs; however, in some context, donor polymorphisms may contribute much more to AR risk than recipient SNPs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Ge1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Lv1">[46]</xref>. 4) The exact etiology of AR episodes and the biological functions of TGF-β1 in the development of AR still remain unclear.</p>
<p>The current meta-analysis focused on the combined effects of <italic>TGFB1</italic> +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms rather than one single SNP on AR risk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093938-Ge1">[15]</xref>, which could help to derive a precise estimation of the roles of <italic>TGFB1</italic> SNPs in the development of AR episodes. However, several limitations should be considered when interpreting the results. First, considering the unavailability of other detailed information, we did not conduct stratified analysis based on some cofactors such as follow-up time, gender, age, panel reactive antibodies level, human leukocyte antigens mismatch and donor source, which may influence the results. Second, the limited number of AR cases and non-AR cases may lead to a relatively small power. Third, only published studies with sufficient data were included, thus, publication bias may have occurred even though results of both Begg's test and Egger's test did not detect it. Last but not least, the meta-analysis is retrospective due to the methodological limitations.</p>
<p>In summary, this meta-analysis suggested that recipient <italic>TGFB1</italic> HP haplotypes of +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms (T/T G/G and T/C G/G) might be a possible genetic susceptibility locus for AR after solid organ transplantation, which could be utilized to identify patients predisposed to AR and potentially benefiting from personalized immunosuppressive protocol. In addition, monitoring TGFB1 could help manage CR to some extent, as TGFB1 triggers fibrogenesis linked to chronic rejection (CR). Further well-designed and unbiased studies with larger sample size, diverse ethnicities, donor-recipient pairing and various applications of CNIs should be conducted to verify our findings. Furthermore, functional studies of <italic>TGFB1</italic> gene polymorphism are warranted to understand the underlying mechanisms.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0093938.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Begg's funnel plot for publication bias test (LP vs. HP for </bold><bold><italic>TGFB1</italic></bold><bold> haplotypes).</bold></p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093938.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Begg's funnel plot for publication bias test (IP vs. HP for </bold><bold><italic>TGFB1</italic></bold><bold> haplotypes).</bold></p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093938.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Begg's funnel plot for publication bias test (LP/IP vs. HP for </bold><bold><italic>TGFB1</italic></bold><bold> haplotypes).</bold></p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093938.s004" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Checklist S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>PRISMA checklist.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093938.s005" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093938.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Statistical analyses of publication bias for </bold><bold><italic>TGFB1</italic></bold><bold> haplotypes at +869 T/C and +915 G/C polymorphisms.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Li1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flavell</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>TGF-beta: a master of all T cell trades</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>392</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Blobe1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blobe</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schiemann</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lodish</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Role of transforming growth factor beta in human disease</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>342</volume>: <fpage>1350</fpage>–<lpage>1358</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Edgley1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edgley</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Targeting fibrosis for the treatment of heart failure: a role for transforming growth factor-beta</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Ther</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>e30</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Massague1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massague</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>TGFbeta in Cancer</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Hussein1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shahawy</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alzahrani</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Interaction between TGF-beta1 (869C/T) polymorphism and biochemical risk factor for prediction of disease progression in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>536</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Gagliardo1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gagliardo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chanez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gjomarkaj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>La Grutta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonanno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The role of transforming growth factor-beta1 in airway inflammation of childhood asthma</article-title>. <source>Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>725</fpage>–<lpage>738</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Hutchinson1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The role of transforming growth factor-beta in transplant rejection</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>9S</fpage>–<lpage>13S</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-MorrisStiff1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris-Stiff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>TGFbeta-1 and the development of chronic graft nephropathy: relative roles of gene, mRNA and protein</article-title>. <source>Ann R Coll Surg Engl</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>326</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Tambur1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tambur</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ortegel</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Ari</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shabtai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Role of cytokine gene polymorphism in hepatitis C recurrence and allograft rejection among liver transplant recipients</article-title>. <source>Transplantation</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1475</fpage>–<lpage>1480</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-PribylovaHribova1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pribylova-Hribova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kotsch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lodererova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viklicky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vitko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>TGF-beta1 mRNA upregulation influences chronic renal allograft dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1872</fpage>–<lpage>1879</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Benza1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benza</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pekarek</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barchue</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tallaj</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Transforming growth factor-beta polymorphisms and cardiac allograft rejection</article-title>. <source>J Heart Lung Transplant</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1057</fpage>–<lpage>1062</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Hoffmann1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muehrer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lorentzen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Donor genomics influence graft events: the effect of donor polymorphisms on acute rejection and chronic allograft nephropathy</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>1686</fpage>–<lpage>1693</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-DiFilippo1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Filippo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeevi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDade</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bastien</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Impact of TGFbeta1 gene polymorphisms on acute and chronic rejection in pediatric heart transplant allografts</article-title>. <source>Transplantation</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>934</fpage>–<lpage>939</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Shah1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rahaman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Posch</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Allelic diversity in the TGFB1 regulatory region: characterization of novel functional single nucleotide polymorphisms</article-title>. <source>Hum Genet</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Ge1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ge YZ, Yu P, Jia RP, Wu R, Ding AX, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2014) Association between transforming growth factor beta-1 +869T/C polymorphism and acute rejection of solid organ allograft: A meta-analysis and systematic review. Transpl Immunol <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.trim.2014.01.001" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.trim.2014.01.001</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Awad1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El-Gamel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hasleton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinnott</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Genotypic variation in the transforming growth factor-beta1 gene: association with transforming growth factor-beta1 production, fibrotic lung disease, and graft fibrosis after lung transplantation</article-title>. <source>Transplantation</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>1014</fpage>–<lpage>1020</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Perrey1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pravica</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinnott</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Genotyping for polymorphisms in interferon-gamma, interleukin-10, transforming growth factor-beta 1 and tumour necrosis factor-alpha genes: a technical report</article-title>. <source>Transpl Immunol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Pelletier1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pravica</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perrey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Evidence for a genetic predisposition towards acute rejection after kidney and simultaneous kidney-pancreas transplantation</article-title>. <source>Transplantation</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>674</fpage>–<lpage>680</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Tian1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>[Influence of cytokine gene polymorphism on renal transplantation]</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Yi Xue Za Zhi</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage>–<lpage>721</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Tian2"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>[Influence of cytokine gene polymorphism on renal transplantation]</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Wai Ke Za Zhi</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Gu1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>[Cytokine gene polymorphism in sensitized kidney transplant recipients and its association with acute rejection episodes]</article-title>. <source>Di Yi Jun Yi Da Xue Xue Bao</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1211</fpage>–<lpage>1213</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Lacha1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hribova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kotsch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brabcova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartosova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Effect of cytokines and chemokines (TGF-beta, TNF-alpha, IL-6, IL-10, MCP-1, RANTES) gene polymorphisms in kidney recipients on posttransplantation outcome: influence of donor-recipient match</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>764</fpage>–<lpage>766</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Canossi1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Canossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piazza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poggi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ozzella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Rocco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Renal allograft immune response is influenced by patient and donor cytokine genotypes</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1805</fpage>–<lpage>1812</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Kocierz1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kocierz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siekiera</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolonko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karkoszka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chudek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>-174G/C interleukin-6 gene polymorphism and the risk of transplanted kidney failure or graft loss during a 5-year follow-up period</article-title>. <source>Tissue Antigens</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Seyhun1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seyhun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mytilineos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turkmen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oguz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kekik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Influence of cytokine gene polymorphisms on graft rejection in Turkish patients with renal transplants from living related donors</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1670</fpage>–<lpage>1678</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Dhaouadi1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhaouadi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sfar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bardi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jendoubi-Ayed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Cytokine gene polymorphisms in kidney transplantation</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>2152</fpage>–<lpage>2157</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Karasu1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karasu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ulukaya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayanoglu</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basturk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ulukaya</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Cytokine gene polymorphism and early graft rejection in liver transplant recipients</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>2791</fpage>–<lpage>2795</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-GomezMateo1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Mateo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Alvarez</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moya-Quiles</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miras</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>TGF-beta1 gene polymorphism in liver graft recipients</article-title>. <source>Transpl Immunol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Gourley1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gourley</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denofrio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The effect of recipient cytokine gene polymorphism on cardiac transplantation outcome</article-title>. <source>Hum Immunol</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Moher1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1000097</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Higgins1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>327</volume>: <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Mantel1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haenszel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1959</year>) <article-title>Statistical aspects of the analysis of data from retrospective studies of disease</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage>–<lpage>748</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-DerSimonian1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DerSimonian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Control Clin Trials</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Thakkinstian1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thakkinstian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McElduff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D'Este</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Attia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A method for meta-analysis of molecular association studies</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1291</fpage>–<lpage>1306</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Begg1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>1101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Egger1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Seyhun2"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seyhun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mytilineos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turkmen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oguz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kekik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Influence of cytokine gene polymorphisms on graft rejection in Turkish patients with renal transplants from living related donors</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1241</fpage>–<lpage>1249</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Opelz1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Opelz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dohler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Influence of time of rejection on long-term graft survival in renal transplantation</article-title>. <source>Transplantation</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>661</fpage>–<lpage>666</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Stehlik1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stehlik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kucheryavaya</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benden</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Registry of the International Society for Heart and Lung Transplantation: 29th official adult heart transplant report—2012</article-title>. <source>J Heart Lung Transplant</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1052</fpage>–<lpage>1064</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Thurairajah1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thurairajah</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bridgestock</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hebbar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Late acute liver allograft rejection; a study of its natural history and graft survival in the current era</article-title>. <source>Transplantation</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>955</fpage>–<lpage>959</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Dai1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michineau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desgranges</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becquemin</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Long term stabilization of expanding aortic aneurysms by a short course of cyclosporine A through transforming growth factor-beta induction</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e28903</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Pakosz1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pakosz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zakliczynski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krol</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pyka</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zakliczynska</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Association of transforming growth factor beta1 (TGF- beta1) with gingival hyperplasia in heart transplant patients undergoing cyclosporine-A treatment</article-title>. <source>Ann Transplant</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Yamada1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miyauchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okuizumi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Association of a polymorphism of the transforming growth factor-beta1 gene with genetic susceptibility to osteoporosis in postmenopausal Japanese women</article-title>. <source>J Bone Miner Res</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1569</fpage>–<lpage>1576</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Suthanthiran1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suthanthiran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Transforming growth factor-beta 1 hyperexpression in African-American hypertensives: A novel mediator of hypertension and/or target organ damage</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>3479</fpage>–<lpage>3484</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Hueso1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hueso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreso</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beltran-Sastre</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Relationship between subclinical rejection and genotype, renal messenger RNA, and plasma protein transforming growth factor-beta1 levels</article-title>. <source>Transplantation</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>1463</fpage>–<lpage>1466</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093938-Lv1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Association between IL-6 -174G/C polymorphism and acute rejection of renal allograft: evidence from a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Transpl Immunol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>