<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>
		<journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
    <publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
    <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
    </journal-meta><article-meta>
			<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-37649</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081050</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
    <subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group>
				<article-title>Prognostic Value of Cancer Stem Cell Marker Aldehyde Dehydrogenase in Ovarian Cancer: A Meta-Analysis</article-title>
			<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">ALDH Predicts Poor Prognosis in Ovarian Cancer</alt-title>
      </title-group>
			<contrib-group>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Liu</surname>
						<given-names>Shuyan</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref>
					</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Liu</surname>
						<given-names>Chengfei</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
					</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Min</surname>
						<given-names>Xiaoyun</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Ji</surname>
						<given-names>Yuanyuan</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Wang</surname>
						<given-names>Na</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Liu</surname>
						<given-names>Dan</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Cai</surname>
						<given-names>Jiangyi</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Li</surname>
						<given-names>Ke</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
					<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
			</contrib-group>
			<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Core Research Laboratory, The Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Xi’an Jiaotong University, Xi’an, China</addr-line></aff>
			<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Department of Reproductive Medicine, The First Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Xi’an Jiaotong University, Xi’an, China</addr-line></aff>
			<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Pathology, Aerospace General Hosipital, Xi’an, China</addr-line></aff>
			<contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Katoh</surname>
            <given-names>Masaru</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
        </contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>National Cancer Center, Japan</addr-line></aff><author-notes>
				<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">ke.li@mail.xjtu.edu.cn</email></corresp>
				<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SL CL KL. Performed the experiments: SL CL. Analyzed the data: SL CL XM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YJ NW DL. Wrote the manuscript: SL CL. Screened the full text of selected studies to confirm eligibility, assess quality, and extract data: JC. </p></fn></author-notes>
			<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e81050</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history><permissions>
    <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Liu et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license>
    </permissions><abstract>
				<sec sec-type="headed">
					<title>Objective</title><p>Aldehyde dehydrogenase (ALDH) has recently been reported as a marker of cancer stem-like cells in ovarian cancer. However, the prognostic role of ALDH in ovarian cancer still remains controversial. In this study, we aimed to evaluate the association between the expression of ALDH and the outcome of ovarian cancer patients by performing a meta-analysis.</p>
				</sec>
				<sec sec-type="headed">
					<title>Methods</title><p>We systematically searched for studies investigating the relationships between ALDH expression and outcome of ovarian cancer patients. Only articles in which ALDH expression was detected by immunohistochemical staining were included. A meta-analysis was performed to generate combined hazard ratios (HRs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) for overall survival (OS) and disease-free survival (DFS).</p>
				</sec>
				<sec sec-type="headed">
					<title>Results</title><p>A total of 1,258 patients from 7 studies (6 articles) were included in the analysis. Our results showed that high ALDH expression in patients with ovarian cancer was associated with poor prognosis in terms of Os (HR, 1.25; 95% CI, 1.07-1.47; P = 0.005) and DFS (HR, 1.58; 95% CI, 1.00-2.49; P = 0.052), though the difference for DFS was not statistically significant. In addition, there was no evidence of publication bias as suggested by Begg’s and Egger’s tests (Begg’s test, P = 0.707; Egger’s test, P = 0.355).</p>
				</sec>
				<sec sec-type="headed">
					<title>Conclusion</title><p>The present meta-analysis indicated that elevated ALDH expression was associated with poor prognosis in patients with ovarian cancer.</p>
				</sec>
			</abstract>
		<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by grant from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81000922) and the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (No. 2010jdgz09).  The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta>
	</front>
	<body>
		<sec id="s1" sec-type="introduction">
			<title>Introduction</title>
			<p>Ovarian cancer is the most lethal of all gynecological malignancies and the seventh leading cause of cancer death among women worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Over 90% of ovarian cancers arise from the epithelial surface of the ovary, the rest from germ cells or stromal cells. The epithelial ovarian cancers are classified as serous (30–70%), endometrioid (10–20%), mucinous (5–20%), clear cell (3–10%), and undifferentiated (1%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. It is disproportionally deadly due to the absence of either specific symptoms or effective screening and early detection strategies, leading to over 70% of patients being diagnosed with advanced stage disease, in which the 5-year survival rate is only 30% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Hence, it is necessary to identify prognostic factors to predict the outcomes of patients, which could be effective in making strategies and improving survival for ovarian cancer. Age, performance status, tumor histology and residual tumor volume are considered as independent predictors of prognosis in ovarian cancer patients with advanced stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. However, these factors are insufficient to predict the outcomes for the individual patient. Identifying molecular biological prognostic factors could enable to predict patients' outcomes more accurately and provide novel therapeutic targets.</p>
			<p>The cancer stem cell model suggests that in many cancers, tumor initiation and propagation is driven by a population of self-renewing tumor cells known as cancer stem cells (CSCs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Accumulating evidence has proposed that CSCs are responsible for tumor progression, relapse, metastases, and therapeutic resistance, thus indicating poor prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Therefore, the identification of CSCs has become an important issue particularly in the context of potential therapeutic targeting. Aldehyde dehydrogenase (ALDH) has been one of the most frequently used biomarkers in CSC-related research, with a career that started with the isolation of ALDH+ CSCs from breast cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Since then, the isolation of putative CSCs by ALDH activity has been reported from a wide range of solid tumors, including those of colon, bladder, prostate, lung, pancreas, head and neck, endometrium and melanoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p>
			<p>Landen et al. were the first to isolate putative CSCs in ovarian cancer by high ALDH activity and showed that high ALDH expression predicts poor outcome of ovarian cancer patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Consistence with that, other studies also found that ALDH was a predictor of poor prognosis in ovarian cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. However, Chang et al. showed that ALDH expression correlates with favorable prognosis in ovarian cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Moreover, Ricci et al. showed that no correlation was found between the expression of ALDH and survival of ovarian cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Insufficient samples and some other factors have resulted in controversial results of different clinical studies. The present meta-analysis aims to determine the value of ALDH as a prognostic marker for ovarian cancer.</p>
		</sec>
		<sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
			<title>Methods</title>
			<sec id="s2.1">
				<title>Literature search strategy</title>
				<p>We comprehensively searched PubMed, Cochrane library, EMBASE, Web of Science and CBM electronic databases for relevant articles published until August 1st, 2013. Search terms included terms for Ovarian Cancer (“Ovarian Neoplasm”, “Ovarian Carcinoma”, “Ovarian Cancer”, “Ovarian Tumor”) and Aldehyde Dehydrogenase ( “Aldehyde Dehydrogenase”, “ALDH”). The reference lists of relative articles were also screened manually to further identify potential studies.</p>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s2.2">
				<title>Criteria for inclusion and exclusion</title>
				<p>The following inclusion criteria were used in order to ensure the high quality of this article: (1) patients with distinctive Ovarian Cancer diagnosis by pathology; (2) full length paper with sufficient data on survival and ALDH expression; (3) ALDH expression was measured by immunohistochemistry (IHC) method. The following studies were excluded: (1) articles about cell lines or animals; (2) review articles without original data; (3) studies lacking information on survival.</p>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s2.3">
				<title>Data extraction and quality assessment</title>
				<p>The following information were retrieved independently by 2 authors (SY Liu and CF Liu)  from the final set of literatures: publication year, first author, number of patients enrolled, histology and disease stage, cutoff value, Hazard ratio (HR) and 95% confidence interval (CI) as well as the other related events. Discrepancies were resolved by discussion and consensus. If the above information were not mentioned in the original study, the item was treated as “Not Available (NA)”. </p>
				<p>Quality assessment was conducted in each of the available studies by using the Newcastle-Ottawa quality assessment scale for cohort studies. This scale allows for assessment of patient population and selection, study comparability, follow-up, and outcome of interest. Interpretation of the scale is performed by awarding points, or ‘‘stars,’’ for high-quality elements. Stars are then added up and used to compare study quality in a quantitative manner.</p>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s2.4">
				<title>Statistical analysis</title>
				<p>HR and 95% CI were used as the effective value to measure the impact of ALDH expression on survival of ovarian cancer patients in this meta-analysis. In the individual study, some of them provided HR and 95% CI directly. For some other studies not given these data clearly, we calculated from available data or Kaplan-Meier survive cure by using Engauge Digitizer version 4.1 (free software down-loaded from http://sourceforge.net). If a study provided both the results of multivariate analysis and univariate analysis, we chose the former. Heterogeneity was assessed by the Chi-squared test. The I<sup>2</sup> value was used to evaluate the heterogeneity (I<sup>2</sup> = 0-50%, no or moderate heterogeneity; I<sup>2</sup> &gt; 50%, significant heterogeneity) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Begg's test and Egger's test were performed to identify the possibility of publication bias [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Fixed-effect model was used if there was no significant heterogeneity. Otherwise, the random-effect model was used. Sensitivity analysis was performed to examine the stability of the pooled results. By convention, an observed HR &gt; 1 implied a poor survival for the group with increased ALDH expression. The impact of increased ALDH expression on survival was considered statistically significant if the 95% CI did not overlap with 1. All the p-values were two sided, and p &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. All statistical analyses were conducted with STATA 12.0.</p>
			</sec>
		</sec>
		<sec id="s3" sec-type="results">
			<title>Results</title>
			<sec id="s3.1">
				<title>Study selection and characteristics</title>
				<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081050-g001">Figure 1</xref>, a total of 37 articles were identified initially using the search strategy above. Titles and abstracts of all identified studies were reviewed to exclude those that were clearly irrelevant. A total of 9 potentially relevant articles were fully reviewed with the full text. Among them, 3 articles were excluded because of the detection method for ALDH expression: 1 was by flow cytometry analysis, 1 by immunofluorescence and 1 by enzyme activity assay. Finally, 7 studies (6 articles) were selected for the present meta-analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>].</p>
				<fig id="pone-0081050-g001" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Flow diagram showing inclusion and exclusion of studies.</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:type="simple" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g001"/>
				</fig>
				<p>All the 7 studies were performed for detection of ALDH isoform 1A1 expression in the cytoplasm of tumor cells in ovarian cancer tissues by IHC analysis. Other main characteristics of the included studies were shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081050-t001">Table 1</xref>. The studies were conducted in 4 countries (USA, Taiwan, Germany and Japan) and published between 2009 and 2013. A total of 1,258 patients with a median of 84 (ranged from 37 to 440) were included. The reported median age of patients ranged from 21 to 89 years across the eligible studies. The follow-up period ranged from 4 to 475 months. 1 study defined the cut off value by complex score combining intensity and percentage of ALDH expression, while other studies only used the percentage of ALDH expression to define positive expression with the cut off value varied from 1% to 50%. There were 6 studies utilized both overall survival (OS) and disease-free survival (DFS) to assess the prognostic value of ALDH expression in ovarian cancer patients and 1 study used only OS as the indicator. Among all of the included studies, HR and 95%CI were obtained from the original articles directly in 2 studies. For the remaining 5 studies, HR and 95% CI were extrapolated from Kaplan-Meier curves. Out of the 7 studies, 3 studies provided the results of multivariate analysis and 3 studies provided HRs from univariate analysis and another one did not provide information of statistical method.</p>
				<table-wrap id="pone-0081050-t001" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Characteristics of the included studies.</title>
					</caption>
					<table>
						<colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>First author</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Year</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Country</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No. of Patients</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age (y)</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Follow-up (month)</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Histologic type</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FIGO disease stage</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Study quality<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.1"><italic>#</italic></xref></sup></bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cutoff scores</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ALDH high/low</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Survival analysis</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HR (95% CI)</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Analysis</bold></th>
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chang</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">440</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (21–89)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median 96</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S 266, E35, M5, C14, T6, O 116</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I 32, II 30, III 305, IV 72, unknown 3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;20%</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87/353</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92(0.67-1.27) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2">*</xref></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariate</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79(0.61-1.02) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2">*</xref></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deng</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">439</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (4-475)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S 439</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥10%</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175/264</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27(1.03-1.56) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2">*</xref></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77(1.37-2.29) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2">*</xref></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landen</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.2 (34-89)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;100</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S 65</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">III 48, IV 17</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1%</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48/17</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39(0.69-2.80) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2">*</xref></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03(1.16-3.57) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2">*</xref></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taiwan</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤50% (52.0±1.9)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S 61, M 14, E 3, C 6</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I –II 27, III–IV 57</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;50%</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28/56</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43(1.12-5.28)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariate</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;50% (57.0±2.8)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70(0.77-3.77)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liebscher</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.6 (34-87.1)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;100</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S 131</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I 9, II 6, III 105, IV 11</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRS≥4</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/89</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01(1.03-3.93)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariate</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kuroda</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.6±11.4</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S 62</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I –II 10, III–IV 52</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;20%</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34/28</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63(0.34-7.89) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2">*</xref></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95(0.95-4.00) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2">*</xref></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kuroda</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.2±9.4</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C 37</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I –II 23, III–IV 14</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;15%</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/19</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62(0.47-27.88) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2">*</xref></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFS</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.97(0.60-26.19) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2">*</xref></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<table-wrap-foot>
						<fn>
							<p>FIGO, International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics; IRS, immunoreactivity score; OS, overall survival; DFS, disease-free survival; NA, not available; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; S, serous; M, mucinous; E, endometrioid; C, clear cell; T, transitional cell; O, others.</p>
						</fn>
						<fn id="ngtab1.1">
							<p><sup>#</sup> Study quality was judged based on the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (range, 1-9 stars).</p>
						</fn>
						<fn id="ngtab1.2">
							<p>* estimated.</p>
						</fn>
					</table-wrap-foot>
				</table-wrap>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s3.2">
				<title>ALDH expression and prognosis of ovarian cancer</title>
				<p>All 7 studies investigating OS were pooled into the meta-analysis. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081050-g002">Figure 2</xref>, high ALDH expression correlates with poor OS (HR, 1.25; 95% CI, 1.07-1.47). No significant heterogeneity was observed among the studies (I<sup>2</sup> = 37.2%, p = 0.145). Data on DFS were available from 6 studies. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081050-g003">Figure 3</xref>, high ALDH expression was not significantly associated with poor DFS (HR, 1.58, 95% CI, 1.00-2.49, I<sup>2</sup> = 80.3%).</p>
				<fig id="pone-0081050-g002" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Meta-analysis of 7 evaluable studies assessing OS according to methods of analysis by a fixed-effects model.</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:type="simple" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g002"/>
				</fig>
				<fig id="pone-0081050-g003" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Meta-analysis of 6 evaluable studies assessing DFS according to methods of analysis by a random-effects model.</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:type="simple" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g003"/>
				</fig>
				<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081050-t002">Table 2</xref> shows the results of the subgroup meta-analyses. The subgroup of studies from univariate analysis showed that high ALDH expression predicts poor DFS (HR, 2.07; 95% CI, 1.35-3.19), but not OS (HR, 1.55; 95% CI, 0.84-2.86); while the subgroup of studies from multivariate analysis showed no association of ALDH expression with OS or DFS. When grouped according to study region of individual studies, the combined HRs of Asian studies in OS and DFS were 2.36 (1.22-4.56) and 1.94 (1.16-3.24), respectively, indicating ALDH is an indicator of poor prognosis of OS and DFS in Asian patients. The subgroup meta-analysis of studies with the cutoff score &lt; 20% showed high ALDH expression was associated with poor OS (HR, 1.29; 95% CI, 1.06-1.57; I<sup>2</sup>=0%) and DFS (HR, 1.83; 95% CI, 1.45-2.31; I<sup>2</sup>=0%) of ovarian cancer patients. When grouped according to follow-up period, both subgroups showed that ALDH expression was a predictor for poor OS (HR, 1.21; 95% CI, 1.02-1.42 and HR, 2.36; 95% CI, 1.22-4.56). Subgroup meta-analysis of studies with follow-up period of less than 60 months showed that high ALDH expression was also a predictor for poor DFS (HR, 1.94; 95% CI, 1.16-3.24) in ovarian cancer. When restricted to studies about the specific histological type of serous carcinoma, high ALDH expression was significantly associated with poor OS (HR, 1.33; 95% CI, 1.10-1.61; I<sup>2</sup>=0%) and DFS (HR, 1.83; 95% CI, 1.46-2.28; I<sup>2</sup>=0%). Among studies with median age of &lt; 60 y, we also observed a statistically significant effect of ALDH expression on OS (HR, 2.18; 95% CI, 1.36-3.49; I<sup>2</sup>=0%) and DFS (HR, 1.94; 95% CI, 1.16-3.24; I<sup>2</sup>=0%) in ovarian cancer patients.</p>
				<table-wrap id="pone-0081050-t002" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Associations between ALDH expression and ovarian cancer prognosis grouped by selected factors.</title>
					</caption>
					<table>
						<colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Variables</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No. of studies</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No. of patients</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HR (95% CI)</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>I<sup>2</sup> (%)</bold></th>
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>OS</italic></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1258</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (1.07-1.47)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.2</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariate</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">655</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.90-1.54)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.3</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 (0.84-2.86)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36 (1.22-4.56)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Asian</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1075</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 (0.94-1.60)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.3</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cutoff</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;20%</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">586</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 (0.67-2.92)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.2</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;20%</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">541</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 (1.06-1.57)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up (m)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1075</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 (1.02-1.42)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.3</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36 (1.22-4.56)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological type</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">697</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 (1.10-1.61)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62 (0.47-27.88)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">524</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 (0.54-3.59)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.6</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age ( y)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">505</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.72-1.39)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">314</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18 (1.36-3.49)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>DFS</italic></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1157</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 (1.00-2.49)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.3</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariate</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">524</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.51-2.18)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.1</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.07 (1.35-3.19)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 (1.16-3.24)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Asian</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">944</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 (0.74-2.59)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cutoff</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;20%</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">586</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (0.66-2.48)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.5</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;20%</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">541</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 (1.45-2.31)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up (m)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">944</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 (0.74-2.59)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 (1.16-3.24)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological type</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">566</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 (1.46-2.28)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.97 (0.60-26.19)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">524</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.51-2.18)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.1</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age ( y)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">505</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 (0.49-3.08)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.8</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 (1.16-3.24)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<table-wrap-foot>
						<fn>
							<p>OS, overall survival; DFS, disease-free survival; HR, hazard ratios; CI, confidence intervals; S, serous; C, clear cell; M, mixed.</p>
						</fn>
					</table-wrap-foot>
				</table-wrap>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s3.3">
				<title>Publication bias analysis</title>
				<p>The funnel plots presented no proof of obvious publication bias for studies in either of the two outcomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081050-g004">Figure 4 and Figure 5</xref>). There was no evidence for significant publication bias in OS (Begg’s test, P = 0.707; Egger’s test, P = 0.355) and DFS (Begg’s test, P = 0.230; Egger’s test, P = 0.162) studies.</p>
				<fig id="pone-0081050-g004" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Funnel plot of the meta-analysis assessing ALDH Expression and OS in ovarian cancer.</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:type="simple" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g004"/>
				</fig>
				<fig id="pone-0081050-g005" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Funnel plot of the meta-analysis assessing ALDH Expression and DFS in ovarian cancer.</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:type="simple" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g005"/>
				</fig>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s3.4">
				<title>Sensitivity analysis</title>
				<p>In order to gauge results stability, a sensitivity analysis, in which one study was deleted at a time, was performed. The results were shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081050-g006">Figure 6 and Figure 7</xref>. Both of the corresponding pooled HRs of OS and DFS were not significantly changed, suggesting the robustness of our results.</p>
				<fig id="pone-0081050-g006" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Sensitivity analysis of all the studies assessing OS.</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:type="simple" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g006"/>
				</fig>
				<fig id="pone-0081050-g007" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Sensitivity analysis of all the studies assessing DFS.</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:type="simple" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.g007"/>
				</fig>
			</sec>
		</sec>
		<sec id="s4" sec-type="discussion">
			<title>Discussion</title>
			<p>According to the CSC hypothesis, only a small fraction of cells, namely the CSCs, within a tumor is multipotent and has the capability of indefinite proliferative potential that drive the formation and growth of tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The first evidence for the existence of CSCs came from acute myeloid leukemia, in which a rare subset comprising 0.01–1% of the total population could induce leukemia when transplanted into immunodeficient mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. This concept was then extended to solid tumors. The first solid malignancy from which CSCs were identified and isolated was breast cancer. Al-Hajj et al. described a CD44<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>-/low</sup> cell population that was significantly enriched for tumor-initiating capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. There is now increasing evidence for CSCs in a variety of solid tumors. This new paradigm has remarkable implications for cancer therapy because it suggests that our current therapies are more successful at eradicating non-CSCs than CSCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. Consequently, the purification and characterization of CSCs could lead to the identification of better targets for therapeutic intervention. </p>
			<p>A number of cell surface and function markers have proved useful for the isolation of subsets enriched for CSCs, including CD133, CD44, CD24, CD90, epithelial cell adhesion molecule (EpCAM), and ATP-binding cassette B5 (ABCB5), cytosolic detoxifying enzyme ALDH as well as Hoechst 33342 exclusion by the side population cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Among these markers, ALDH was a widely used marker for isolating CSCs in a range of solid tumors, including ovarian cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Moreover, high ALDH expression was reported to be associated with poor prognosis in breast cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>].</p>
			<p>Although high expression of CSC markers are usually considered as a prognosis of poor outcome, several contradictions to this generalization exist in published studies on the putative CSC-marker ALDH. 5 studies in this meta-analysis concluded that high ALDH expression is a predictor for poor prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Ricci et al. showed no correlation between the expression of ALDH and survival of ovarian cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. However, Chang et al. found that high percentage of cells expressing ALDH was associated with a longer overall survival time and disease-free survival time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. In contrast to its function in breast cancer, ALDH was a favorable prognostic factor in ovarian cancer. They also found that high expression of ALDH was associated with early-stage disease. Furthermore, multivariate Cox proportional hazards regression analysis showed that the early stage of disease was strongly associated with longer overall survival and disease-free survival.</p>
			<p>This meta-analysis showed that estimates of the significance of ALDH expression vary substantially between studies. However, we found that high ALDH expression was associated with poor OS and DFS in patients with ovarian cancer, although not significant for DFS. The results increase the likelihood that high ALDH expression is an independent risk factor for ovarian cancer.</p>
			<p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first meta-analysis to evaluate the prognostic role of ALDH expression in ovarian cancer. Sub-group analysis identified several important findings. A prominent association was observed between ALDH and poor OS and DFS when studies set the cutoff score at &lt; 20%. It was reported that ALDH expression was limited to a small subpopulation of tumor cells. In breast cancer, ALDH-positive cells represented an average of 5% of cells in tumors expressing ALDH, which was consistent with the idea that cancer stem cells constitute a minority of the tumor population. Only two of the 481 tumors had ALDH staining in the vast majority of the cell population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. We speculate that when the cutoff was &gt; 20%, a majority of cases with high ALDH expression were excluded and assigned to the group of low ALDH expression. Subgroup analysis by histological type showed that high ALDH expression was significantly associated with poor OS and DFS in serous ovarian carcinomas. In addition, subgroup analysis by study region revealed that higher ALDH expression was associated with poor OS and DFS in studies performed in Asia. This finding should be interpreted with caution owing to the small number of studies. Further studies are needed to evaluate whether the prognostic role of ALDH differs with patient ethnicity.</p>
			<p>There are several limitations to the current meta-analysis. First, the number of studies included is relatively small. Second, heterogeneity was found in the main analysis. This may have arisen from the different characteristics of the subjects and the various histological types of ovarian cancer. Furthermore, the methodology for immunohistochemistry could affect heterogeneity due to the various detecting antibodies against ALDH and the application of different cutoff values for determining high ALDH levels. Third, we were unable to perform subgroup analysis by FIGO stage, grade, and histological type to evaluate the pooled HR for OS and DFS because diverse subjects were included in each study.</p>
			<p>In conclusion, we found that high ALDH expression may be an independent risk factor for ovarian cancer prognosis. Based on the current findings, assessing ALDH expression could provide better prognostic information for patients with ovarian cancer and be used as a novel therapeutic target. Further large-scale cohort studies are needed to validate our results.</p>
		</sec>
		<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
			<title>Supporting Information</title>
			<supplementary-material xlink:type="simple" position="float" id="pone.0081050.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0081050.s001" mimetype="application/msword">
				<label>Checklist S1</label>
				<caption>
					<p><bold>PRISMA checklist.</bold>
				</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption>
				</supplementary-material>
		</sec>
	</body>
	<back>
		<ref-list>
			<title>References</title>
			<ref id="B1">
				<label>1</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Center</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Global cancer statistics</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3322/caac.20107" xlink:type="simple">10.3322/caac.20107</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21296855" xlink:type="simple">21296855</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B2">
				<label>2</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mercado-Uribe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Ovarian cancer: pathology, biology, and disease models. Front Biosci</article-title> <comment>(Landmark Ed) 14: 2089-2102</comment></mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B3">
				<label>3</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kipps</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Meeting the challenge of ascites in ovarian cancer: new avenues for therapy and research</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>-<lpage>282</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrc3432" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrc3432</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23426401" xlink:type="simple">23426401</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B4">
				<label>4</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>WE</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ozols</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Prognostic factors for stage III epithelial ovarian cancer: a Gynecologic Oncology Group Study</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>3621</fpage>-<lpage>3627</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1200/JCO.2006.10.2517" xlink:type="simple">10.1200/JCO.2006.10.2517</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17704411" xlink:type="simple">17704411</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B5">
				<label>5</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Stem cells, cancer, and cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>414</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>-<lpage>111</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/35102167" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/35102167</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11689955" xlink:type="simple">11689955</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B6">
				<label>6</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>355</volume>: <fpage>1253</fpage>-<lpage>1261</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1056/NEJMra061808" xlink:type="simple">10.1056/NEJMra061808</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16990388" xlink:type="simple">16990388</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B7">
				<label>7</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Visvader</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindeman</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cancer stem cells in solid tumours: accumulating evidence and unresolved questions</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>755</fpage>-<lpage>768</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrc2499" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrc2499</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18784658" xlink:type="simple">18784658</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B8">
				<label>8</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ginestier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charafe-Jauffret</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monville</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dutcher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>ALDH1 is a marker of normal and malignant human mammary stem cells and a predictor of poor clinical outcome</article-title>. <source>Cell Stem Cell</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>-<lpage>567</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.stem.2007.08.014" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.stem.2007.08.014</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18371393" xlink:type="simple">18371393</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B9">
				<label>9</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ginestier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dontu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Aldehyde dehydrogenase 1 is a marker for normal and malignant human colonic stem cells (SC) and tracks SC overpopulation during colon tumorigenesis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>3382</fpage>-<lpage>3389</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-08-4418" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-08-4418</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19336570" xlink:type="simple">19336570</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B10">
				<label>10</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpentino</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Appelman</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steindler</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Aldehyde dehydrogenase-expressing colon stem cells contribute to tumorigenesis in the transition from colitis to cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>8208</fpage>-<lpage>8215</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-1132" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-1132</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19808966" xlink:type="simple">19808966</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B11">
				<label>11</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Aldehyde dehydrogenase 1 A1-positive cell population is enriched in tumor-initiating cells and associated with progression of bladder cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>-<lpage>337</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-09-0865" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-09-0865</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20142235" xlink:type="simple">20142235</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B12">
				<label>12</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Hoogen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Horst</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buijs</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lippitt</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>High aldehyde dehydrogenase activity identifies tumor-initiating and metastasis-initiating cells in human prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>5163</fpage>-<lpage>5173</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-3806" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-3806</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20516116" xlink:type="simple">20516116</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B13">
				<label>13</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spinola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dodge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raso</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Behrens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Aldehyde dehydrogenase activity selects for lung adenocarcinoma stem cells dependent on notch signaling</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>9937</fpage>-<lpage>9948</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-10-0881" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-10-0881</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21118965" xlink:type="simple">21118965</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B14">
				<label>14</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abbruzzese</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>ALDH activity selectively defines an enhanced tumor-initiating cell population relative to CD133 expression in human pancreatic adenocarcinoma</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e20636</fpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0020636" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0020636</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21695188" xlink:type="simple">21695188</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B15">
				<label>15</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tabor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Single-marker identification of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma cancer stem cells with aldehyde dehydrogenase</article-title>. <source>Head Neck</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1195</fpage>-<lpage>1201</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/hed.21315" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/hed.21315</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20073073" xlink:type="simple">20073073</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B16">
				<label>16</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahadiani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mamat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuzaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Expression of aldehyde dehydrogenase 1 (ALDH1) in endometrioid adenocarcinoma and its clinical implications</article-title>. <source>Cancer Sci</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>903</fpage>-<lpage>908</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1349-7006.2011.01864.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1349-7006.2011.01864.x</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21231983" xlink:type="simple">21231983</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B17">
				<label>17</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clanton</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snipas</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Characterization of a subpopulation of colon cancer cells with stem cell-like properties</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>1312</fpage>-<lpage>1321</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ijc.24061" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/ijc.24061</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19072981" xlink:type="simple">19072981</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B18">
				<label>18</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laffin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The PSA(-/lo) prostate cancer cell population harbors self-renewing long-term tumor-propagating cells that resist castration</article-title>. <source>Cell Stem Cell</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>556</fpage>-<lpage>569</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.stem.2012.03.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.stem.2012.03.009</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22560078" xlink:type="simple">22560078</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B19">
				<label>19</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dallaglio</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>ALDH1A isozymes are markers of human melanoma stem cells and potential therapeutic targets</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>2100</fpage>-<lpage>2113</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/stem.1193" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/stem.1193</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22887839" xlink:type="simple">22887839</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B20">
				<label>20</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landen</surname><given-names>CN</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katre</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steg</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nick</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Targeting aldehyde dehydrogenase cancer stem cells in ovarian cancer</article-title>. <source>Mol Cancer Ther</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>3186</fpage>-<lpage>3199</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-10-0563" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-10-0563</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20889728" xlink:type="simple">20889728</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B21">
				<label>21</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liebscher</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prinzler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinn</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budczies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denkert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Aldehyde dehydrogenase 1/epidermal growth factor receptor coexpression is characteristic of a highly aggressive, poor-prognosis subgroup of high-grade serous ovarian carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Hum Pathol</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1465</fpage>-<lpage>1471</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.humpath.2012.12.016" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.humpath.2012.12.016</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23465277" xlink:type="simple">23465277</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B22">
				<label>22</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yo</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>ALDH1-bright epithelial ovarian cancer cells are associated with CD44 expression, drug resistance, and poor clinical outcome</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol</source> <volume>180</volume>: <fpage>1159</fpage>-<lpage>1169</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ajpath.2011.11.015" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ajpath.2011.11.015</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22222226" xlink:type="simple">22222226</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B23">
				<label>23</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lassus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Distinct expression levels and patterns of stem cell marker, aldehyde dehydrogenase isoform 1 (ALDH1), in human epithelial cancers</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e10277</fpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0010277" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0010277</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20422001" xlink:type="simple">20422001</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B24">
				<label>24</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirohashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torigoe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>ALDH1-high ovarian cancer stem-like cells can be isolated from serous and clear cell adenocarcinoma cells, and ALDH1 high expression is associated with poor prognosis</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e65158</fpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0065158" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0065158</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23762304" xlink:type="simple">23762304</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B25">
				<label>25</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>ALDH1 expression correlates with favorable prognosis in ovarian cancers</article-title>. <source>Mod Pathol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>817</fpage>-<lpage>823</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19329942" xlink:type="simple">19329942</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B26">
				<label>26</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernasconi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porcu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erba</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>ALDH enzymatic activity and CD133 positivity and response to chemotherapy in ovarian cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Am J Cancer Res</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>229</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23593543" xlink:type="simple">23593543</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B27">
				<label>27</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>327</volume>: <fpage>557</fpage>-<lpage>560</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.327.7414.557" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/bmj.327.7414.557</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12958120" xlink:type="simple">12958120</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B28">
				<label>28</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>-<lpage>634</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.315.7109.629" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/bmj.315.7109.629</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9310563" xlink:type="simple">9310563</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B29">
				<label>29</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1088</fpage>-<lpage>1101</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/2533446" xlink:type="simple">10.2307/2533446</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7786990" xlink:type="simple">7786990</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B30">
				<label>30</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Human acute myeloid leukemia is organized as a hierarchy that originates from a primitive hematopoietic cell</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>730</fpage>-<lpage>737</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nm0797-730" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nm0797-730</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9212098" xlink:type="simple">9212098</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B31">
				<label>31</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Hajj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wicha</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benito-Hernandez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Prospective identification of tumorigenic breast cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>3983</fpage>-<lpage>3988</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0530291100" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0530291100</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12629218" xlink:type="simple">12629218</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B32">
				<label>32</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeulen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sprick</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stassi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medema</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cancer stem cells--old concepts, new insights</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>947</fpage>-<lpage>958</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/cdd.2008.20" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/cdd.2008.20</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18259194" xlink:type="simple">18259194</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B33">
				<label>33</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The biology of cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>675</fpage>-<lpage>699</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.cellbio.22.010305.104154" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.22.010305.104154</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17645413" xlink:type="simple">17645413</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B34">
				<label>34</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charafe-Jauffret</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ginestier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iovino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tarpin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diebel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Aldehyde dehydrogenase 1-positive cancer stem cells mediate metastasis and poor clinical outcome in inflammatory breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-1630" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-1630</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20028757" xlink:type="simple">20028757</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B35">
				<label>35</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumeister</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bordeaux</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camp</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rimm</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>In situ identification of putative cancer stem cells by multiplexing ALDH1, CD44, and cytokeratin identifies breast cancer patients with poor prognosis</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol</source> <volume>176</volume>: <fpage>2131</fpage>-<lpage>2138</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2353/ajpath.2010.090712" xlink:type="simple">10.2353/ajpath.2010.090712</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20228222" xlink:type="simple">20228222</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B36">
				<label>36</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Novel prognostic markers for patients with triple-negative breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Hum Pathol</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>2180</fpage>-<lpage>2187</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.humpath.2013.03.021" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.humpath.2013.03.021</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23845466" xlink:type="simple">23845466</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
		</ref-list>
		
	</back>
</article>