<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-20587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047769</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Human genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genetic association studies</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genetic polymorphism</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Drugs and devices</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Adverse reactions</subject>
              <subject>Pharmacogenetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Epidemiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genetic epidemiology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Infectious diseases</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Bacterial diseases</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Tuberculosis</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Multi-drug-resistant tuberculosis</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology</subject>
          <subject>Infectious Diseases</subject>
          <subject>Pharmacology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pharmacogenetic Study of Drug-Metabolising Enzyme Polymorphisms on the Risk of Anti-Tuberculosis Drug-Induced Liver Injury: A Meta-Analysis</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Anti-Tuberculosis Drug-Induced Liver Injury</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cai</surname>
            <given-names>Yu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Yi</surname>
            <given-names>JiaYong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>ChaoHui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Shen</surname>
            <given-names>XiZhong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Gastroenterology, Zhongshan Hospital, Fudan Unversity, Shanghai, People’s Republic of China</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Departments of Orthopedics, Zhongshan Hospital, Fudan Unversity, Shanghai, People’s Republic of China</addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Medeiros</surname>
            <given-names>Rui</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>IPO, Inst Port Oncology, Portugal</addr-line>
      </aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">chaohuizhou001@163.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CHZ. Performed the experiments: YC JYY XZS. Analyzed the data: YC JYY. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YC JYY XZS. Wrote the paper: CHZ XZS.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e47769</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><permissions>
        
        <copyright-holder>Cai et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions><abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Three first-line antituberculosis drugs, isoniazid, rifampicin and pyrazinamide, may induce liver injury, especially isoniazid. This antituberculosis drug-induced liver injury (ATLI) ranges from a mild to severe form, and the associated mortality cases are not rare. In the past decade, many investigations have focused the association between drug-metabolising enzyme (DME) gene polymorphisms and risk for ATLI; however, these studies have yielded contradictory results.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>PubMed, EMBASE, ISI web of science and the Chinese National Knowledge Infrastructure databases were systematically searched to identify relevant studies. A meta-analysis was performed to examine the association between polymorphisms from 4 DME genes (NAT2, CYP2E1, GSTM1 and GSTT1) and susceptibility to ATLI. Odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated. Heterogeneity among articles and their publication bias were also tested.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>38 studies involving 2,225 patients and 4,906 controls were included. Overall, significantly increased ATLI risk was associated with slow NAT2 genotype and GSTM1 null genotype when all studies were pooled into the meta-analysis. Significantly increased risk was also found for CYP2E1*1A in East Asians when stratified by ethnicity. However, no significant results were observed for GSTT1.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>Our results demonstrated that slow NAT2 genotype, CYP2E1*1A and GSTM1 null have a modest effect on genetic susceptibility to ATLI.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by Shanghai Natural Science Foundation (12ZR1405300) and Shanghai Science and Technology Commission (10410709400; 10411950100). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Tuberculosis (TB) is an important infectious disease plaguing the developed and developing countries worldwide, with more than nine million new cases of active tuberculosis reported annually. Isoniazid (INH), rifampicin (RIF) and pyrazinamide (PZA) are all widely used as first-line multidrug therapy for TB. Anti-tuberculosis drug induced liver injury (ATLI), a common serious adverse drug reaction, is one of the most challenging clinical problems, cause of hospitalization and life-threatening events. ATLI can be fatal if therapy is not interrupted on time, and the subsequent adherence problem may cause treatment failure and, relapse or drug resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Tostmann1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Saukkonen1">[2]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Of the various antituberculosis regimens, isoniazid is the main drug to induce hepatotoxicity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Lee1">[3]</xref>. Metabolic intermediates of isoniazid are incriminated to be the cause of hepatotoxicity. In the liver, isoniazid is first metabolized into acetylisoniazid via N-acetyltransferase (NAT) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Mitchell1">[4]</xref>, followed by hydrolysis to acetylhydrazine. Acetylhydrazine is proposed to be oxidized into hepatotoxic intermediates by cytochrome P450 2E1 (CYP2E1) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-RungeMorris1">[5]</xref> and some hepatotoxic intermediates can be detoxified by glutathione S-transferase (GST) enzyme <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Strange1">[6]</xref>. Drug-metabolizing enzymes (DME) have critical effects on both the synthesis and detoxification of reactive metabolites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Naisbitt1">[7]</xref>. Therefore, studies on genetic predisposition for anti-TB drug-induced liver injury have focused on a few metabolizing enzymes including N-acetyltransferase 2 (NAT2), CYP2E1, GSTM1 and GSTT1.</p>
      <p>Over the past few years, considerable efforts have been devoted to exploring the relationships between the DME polymorphisms and ATLI among various populations. However, existing studies have yielded inconsistent results. These disparate findings may be due partly to insufficient power, false-positive results, and publication biases. Therefore, we performed a meta-analysis of the published studies to clarify this inconsistency and obtain summary risk estimates for the association of specific polymorphism in DME and risk of ATLI.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Literature Search Strategy</title>
        <p>Eligible literature published before the end of May 2012 were identified through a search of PubMed, EMBASE, ISI Web of Science and CNKI (Chinese National Knowledge Infrastructure) without language restriction. Search term combinations were as follows: drug-metabolising enzymes, antitubercular agents, drug-induced hepatotoxicity, drug-induced liver injury, genetic polymorphism, arylamine N-acetyltransferase, glutathione-S-transferase, cytochrome 2E1, acetylator phenotype, genetic susceptibility. All reference lists from the main reports and relevant reviews were hand searched for additional eligible studies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Eligible Studies and Data Extraction</title>
        <p>Eligible studies had to meet all of the following criteria: (i) the studies were published in peer-reviewed journals and were independent studies using original data; (ii) the studies provided genotype distribution information of polymorphism in both cases and controls or odds ratio (OR) with its 95% confidence interval and P value; (iii) the studies investigated the DME polymorphism using either case-control or cohort design; (iv) the studies described the genotyping method, equipment, and protocols used or provided reference to them and (v) the studies used TB patients without ATLI as controls.</p>
        <p>For each study, the following data were extracted independently by two authors: first author’s surname, year of publication, diagnosis criterion, age, sex, ethnicity, genotyping method, total number of cases and controls and genotype frequency in cases and controls. The results were compared, and disagreements were discussed and resolved with consensus.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Statistical Methods</title>
        <p>The proposed risk genotypes are NAT2 slow acetylator (without wild-type NAT2*4 allele), CYP2E1*1A/*1A (homozygous wild type c1/c1) and homozygous null GST genotype (GSTM1 null/null or GSTT1 null/null). Our primary analysis for measuring the overall effects of every DME was to compare the genotype distribution for ATLI patients against controls by the contrast of the above risk genotypes vs. other combined genotypes.</p>
        <p>Odds ratio (OR) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) was used to assess the strength of association between gene polymorphism and ATLI risk. Cochran’s chi-square-based Q statistic test was performed in order to assess possible heterogeneity between the individual studies and thus to ensure that each group of studies was suitable for meta-analysis. ORs were pooled according to the method of DerSimonian and Laird that takes into account the variation between studies, and 95% CI were constructed using Woolf’s method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-DerSimonian1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Woolf1">[9]</xref>. The Z test was used to determine the significance of the pooled OR. Sensitivity analyses were performed to assess the stability of the results, namely, a single study in the meta-analysis was deleted each time to reflect the influence of the individual data set to the overall OR. Publication bias was assessed using Egger’s test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Egger1">[10]</xref> and Begg’s funnel plots <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Begg1">[11]</xref>. All P values are two-sided, and P&lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant. Statistical analyses were done with Stata (version 10.0).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Characteristics of Studies</title>
        <p>The combined search yielded 412 references. Study selection process was shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047769.s001">Figure S1</xref>. A total of 38 studies were finally included with 2,225 patients and 4,906 controls <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Tang1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Vuilleumier1">[42]</xref>. For the CYP2E1, 13 studies were available, including a total of 674 cases and 1,990 controls. For the NAT2, 24 studies involved a total of 1,116 cases and 2,655 controls. For the GST M1, 11 studies involved a total of 896 cases and 1,604 controls. For the GST T1, 10 studies involved a total of 792 cases and 1,493 controls. Of the cases, 80% were East Asian, 8% were Indian, 7% were Caucasian, and 5% were of other ethnic populations. The detailed characteristics of the studies included in this meta-analysis are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0047769-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0047769-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Characteristics of the studies included in the meta-analysis.</title>
          </caption><alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0047769-t001-1" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Year</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ethnicity</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of case/control</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean age of case/control</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender component in caseand control (% male)</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Genotyping method</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Tang1">[12]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP2E1; GSTM1; GSTT1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89/356</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.7/43.6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.0/73.0</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">An <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-An1">[13]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT 2; CYP2E1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101/107</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.0/33.4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.4/70.0</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sequencing</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Rana1">[14]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Indian</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50/201</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.3/43.8</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.8/75.2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mahmoud <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-BenMahmoud1">[15]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tunisian</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14/52</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.4/42.1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.8/48.1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zhu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Zhu1">[16]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GSTM1; GSTT1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">228/300</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.8/37.5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.9/53.3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fernandez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-LeiroFernandez1">[17]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Spanish</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50/67</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34/30.5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.0/56.7</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sotsuka <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Sotsuka1">[18]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Japanese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2; CYP2E1; GSTM1; GSTT1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52/92</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.9/50.4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.3/73.9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP; PCR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sistanizad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Sistanizad1">[19]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Iranian</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14/36</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.1/49.6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.1/55.5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Huang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Huang1">[20]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119/198</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.0/44.0</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.4/64.1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sequencing</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Teixeira <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Teixeira1">[21]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Brazilian</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP2E1; GSTM1; GSTT1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26/141</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.6/43.0</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.5/52.5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sequencing; PCR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yimer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Yimer1">[22]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">European</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41/160</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sequencing</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bose <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Bose1">[23]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Indian</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2; CYP2E1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41/177</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.0/36.0</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.9/47.4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chatterjee <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Chatterjee1">[24]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Indian</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GSTM1; GSTT1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51/100</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.2/33.2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.0/63.0</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Wang1">[25]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GSTM1; CYP2E1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104/111</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.6/44.7</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.3/67.6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lee <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Lee2">[26]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2; CYP2E1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45/95</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.4/54.9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.0/66.3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Taqman</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kim <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Kim1">[27]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Korean</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GSTM1; GSTT1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57/190</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.3/42.4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.6/67.9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Wu1">[28]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155/162</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.0/60.0</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Taqman</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Guo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Guo1">[29]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">106/106</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.8/48.6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.9/68.9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Chen1">[30]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP2E1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103/236</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.0/45.7</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.6/66.1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Wang2">[31]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2009</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP2E1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104/111</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.7/45.5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.1/64.0</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Guo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Guo2">[32]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2009</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GSTM1; GSTT1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">106/106</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.8/48.6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.9/68.9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kim <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Kim2">[33]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2009</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Korean</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67/159</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.1/42.8</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.7/65.4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SNPstream</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yamada <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Yamada1">[34]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2009</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Japanese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2; CYP2E1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23/147</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.0/42.8</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sequencing, RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Wang3">[35]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2009</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36/36</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Leiro <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Leiro1">[36]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2008</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Spanish</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GSTM1; GSTT1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35/60</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.0/31.0</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.0/41.7</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bozok <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-BozokCetintas1">[37]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2008</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Turkish</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30/70</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.8/37.3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0/72.8</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Possuelo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Possuelo1">[38]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2008</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Brazilian</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14/240</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.9/36.5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0/67.9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sequencing</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Huang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Huang2">[39]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2007</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GSTM1; GSTT1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115/115</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.3/59.1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.5/63.5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cho <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Cho1">[40]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2007</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Korean</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2; CYP2E1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18/114</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.2/46.7</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.7/55.3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sequencing</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Higuchi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Higuchi1">[41]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2007</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Japanese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18/82</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.8/64.7</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0/57.3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vuilleumier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Vuilleumier1">[42]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2006</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Swiss</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP2E1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34/55</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Shimizu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Shimizu1">[43]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2006</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Japanese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10/32</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.5/64.9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.0/46.9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Roy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Roy1">[44]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2006</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Indian</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP2E1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8/101</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Wang4">[45]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32/35</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.1/45.7</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Huang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Huang3">[46]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2003</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2; CYP2E1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49/269</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.0/59.0</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.4/14.9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Huang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Huang4">[47]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2002</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33/191</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.3/63.7</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87.9/88.5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Roy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Roy2">[48]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2001</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Indian</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2; GSTM1; GSTT1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33/33</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ohno <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Ohno1">[49]</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2000</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Japanese</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14/63</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA/NA</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RFLP</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Association of CYP2E1 Gene with ATLI</title>
        <p>Meta-analysis revealed no statistically significant association between ATLI and CYP2E1 c1/c1 genotype [OR = 1.28; 95% CI: 0.97–1.69; <italic>P(Z) = </italic>0.08; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.11]. When studies were stratified for ethnicity, significant risks were found among East Asians [OR = 1.35; 95% CI: 1.01–1.81; <italic>P(Z)</italic> = 0.04; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.08]. However, no significant associations were detected among Indian, Caucasian and other ethnic populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047769-g001">Figure 1</xref>). In the subgroup analyses by sample size, the summary OR for big studies of the c1/c1 genotype was 1.36 [95% CI: 0.92–2.00; <italic>P(Z) = </italic>0.12; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.05] and for small studies was 1.17 [95% CI: 0.75–1.81; <italic>P(Z) = </italic>0.49; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.28].</p>
        <fig id="pone-0047769-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Forest plot from the meta-analysis of ATLI and <italic>CYP2E1</italic>.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Association of NAT2 Gene with ATLI</title>
        <p>Overall, there was evidence of an association between the increased risk of ATLI and the variant when all eligible studies were pooled into the meta-analysis. Using random effect model, the summary OR of the NAT2 slow acetylator genotype for ATLI was 3.18 [95% CI: 2.49–4.07; <italic>P(Z)</italic> &lt;10<sup>−5</sup>; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.03]. When stratifying for ethnicity, an OR of 3.32 [95% CI: 2.43–4.53; <italic>P(Z)</italic> &lt;10<sup>−5</sup>; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.06], 2.96 [95% CI: 1.83–4.76; <italic>P(Z)</italic> &lt;10<sup>−4</sup>; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.49], 6.64 [95% CI: 3.01–14.66; <italic>P(Z)</italic> &lt;10<sup>−4</sup>; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.36] and 5.24 [95% CI: 2.18–12.60; <italic>P(Z)</italic> &lt;10<sup>−4</sup>; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.93] resulted for the slow acetylator genotype, among East Asian, Indian, Middle Eastern and other ethnic population, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047769-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Unfortunately, we failed to detect any association to ATLI risk for Caucasians. Subsidiary analyses of control source yielded an overall OR for big studies of 2.48 [95% CI: 1.87–3.30; <italic>P(Z)</italic> &lt;10<sup>−5</sup>; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.26] and for small studies of 3.92 [95% CI: 2.75–5.58; <italic>P(Z)</italic> &lt;10<sup>−5</sup>; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.06].</p>
        <fig id="pone-0047769-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Forest plot from the meta-analysis of ATLI and <italic>NAT2</italic>.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Association of GSTM1 and GSTT1 Gene with ATLI</title>
        <p>For ATLI risk and the null genotype of GSTM1, our meta-analysis gave an overall OR of 1.43 [95% CI: 1.08–1.88; <italic>P(Z) = </italic>0.01; <italic>P(Q) = </italic>0.02] with statistically significant between-study heterogeneity. This analysis is based on pooling of data from a number of different ethnic populations. When stratifying for ethnicity, an OR of 1.55 [95% CI: 1.12–2.13; <italic>P(Z)</italic> = 0.008; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.02] resulted for null genotype among East Asians; while no significant association was found among Caucasian and Indian populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047769-g003">Figure 3</xref>). By considering sample size subgroups, the OR was 1.61 [95% CI: 1.18–2.19; <italic>P(Z) = </italic>0.003; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.005] in big studies, compared to 1.26 [95% CI: 0.54–2.95; <italic>P(Z) = </italic>0.59; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.08] in small studies.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0047769-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Forest plot from the meta-analysis of ATLI and <italic>GST M1</italic>.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The meta-analysis resulted in a statistically non-significant association between GSTT1 deficiency and ATLI. The overall OR was 1.07 [95% CI: 0.82–1.39; <italic>P(Z) = </italic>0.61; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.16]. When stratifying for ethnicity, an OR of 0.96 [95% CI: 0.78–1.18; <italic>P(Z) = </italic>0.69; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.40] and 2.92 [95% CI: 0.79–10.89; <italic>P(Z)</italic> = 0.11; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.45] resulted for null genotype, among East Asian and Indian populations, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047769-g004">Figure 4</xref>). No significant association was found in stratified analyses according to sample size. The OR was 0.97 [95% CI: 0.79–1.19; <italic>P(Z) = </italic>0.76; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.44] in big studies, 1.88 [95% CI: 0.68–5.20; <italic>P(Z)</italic> = 0.23; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.15] in small studies.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0047769-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Forest plot from the meta-analysis of ATLI and <italic>GST T1</italic>.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The effect of each genotype of GSTs was independently assessed. The data on both null genotype of GSTs among cases and controls were available in five studies, which included 460 cases and 1006 controls. The interaction between GSTM1 null and GSTT1 null, for which an OR of 1.12 [95% CI: 0.86–1.48; <italic>P(Z) = </italic>0.40; <italic>P(Q)</italic> = 0.69] for ATLI appeared in compared with individuals with the positive genotypes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Sensitivity Analyses and Publication Bias</title>
        <p>Sensitivity analyses were performed to assess the influence of each individual study on the pooled OR by sequential removal of individual studies. The results suggested that no individual study significantly affected the pooled OR, thus suggesting that the results of this meta-analysis are stable.</p>
        <p>A funnel plot of these 24 included studies concerning NAT2 and ATLI suggested a possibility of the preferential publication of positive findings in smaller studies (t = 3.72, <italic>P</italic> = 0.001; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047769.s002">Figure S2</xref>). The shape of the funnel plots was symmetrical (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047769.s003">Figures S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047769.s004">S4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047769.s005">S5</xref>) for CYP2E1, GSTM1 and GSTT1. The statistical results still did not show publication bias in these studies for CYP2E1 (t = −1.27, <italic>P</italic> = 0.23), GSTM1 (t = 0.32, <italic>P</italic> = 0.76) and GSTT1 polymorphism (t = 1.65, <italic>P</italic> = 0.14).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This is the most comprehensive meta-analysis concerning the relationship between polymorphisms of three DME genes and ATLI risk. Its strength was based on the accumulation of published data giving greater information to detect significant differences. In total, the meta-analysis involved 38 studies for ATLI that provided 2,225 patients and 4,906 controls. Our results demonstrated that the slow NAT2 genotype and GSTT1 null polymorphism is a risk factor for developing ATLI. Although no significant association between CYP2E1 *1A polymorphism and ATLI susceptibility was detected in the overall comparison, we found that the CYP2E1 *1A polymorphism was associated with increased risk of ATLI among East Asian populations when stratified by ethnicity. Ethnic differences may contribute to these different results, since the CYP2E1 c2 allele distribution of the polymorphism varies between East Asian and other ethnic populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Tang2">[50]</xref>. However, we failed to detect any positive relationship between ATLI and GSTT1 null polymorphism.</p>
      <p>As the pathogenic mechanism of ATLI is poorly understood, most studies were based on INH metabolic pathway. For predicting ATLI, the NAT2 genotype is seemingly more important than other genotypes, because this genotype possesses high susceptibility to ATLI with OR of 3.18 compared with CYP2E1 (OR = 1.28) and GSTM1 (OR = 1.43). Slow acetylators not only acetylate isoniazid more slowly but also monoacetylhydrazine, the immediate precursor of the toxic intermediates, to the harmless diacetylhydrazine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Lauterburg1">[51]</xref>. This protective acetylation is further suppressed by isoniazid. Therefore, slow acetylators may critically increase the accumulation of toxic metabolites indirectly. The action of NAT in the disposition of isoniazid is followed by CYP2E1. Earlier reports demonstrated CYP2E1 activity was less inhibited by isoniazid in subjects with CYP2E1 *1A/*1A genotype than in those with other genotypes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Huang3">[46]</xref>. Therefore, under the administration of isoniazid, subjects with CYP2E1 *1A/*1A genotype have higher CYP2E1 activity than those with other genotypes, and, hence, may produce more hepatotoxins and finally increase the risk of liver injury.</p>
      <p>GST, as an important phase II detoxification enzyme, was correlated to the susceptibility of alcoholic liver disease and many cancers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Strange1">[6]</xref>. Subjects with homozygous ‘null’ mutant genotype of GSTM1 or GSTT1 have been found to lose enzymatic activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047769-Strange1">[6]</xref>. It is speculated that people with null GSTM1 or GSTT1 genotypes could not detoxify the toxic reactive metabolites efficiently, and thus have higher risk of drug-induced liver injury and many cancers. However, failing to identify the association between GSTT1 polymorphism and ATLI may be due partly to the small sample size and low frequency of patients with ATLI; additional studies with large sample size are therefore needed to confirm our finds.</p>
      <p>In interpreting the results, some limitations of this meta-analysis should be addressed. Firstly, lack of clarification regarding the exact criteria used for the diagnosis of ATLI, and the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium status among controls in several studies may over inflate our results. Secondly, variation in the anti-TB drugs administered in the studies we analyzed limited the possibility of examining the association of DME with any specific drug. In these studies, multiple anti-TB drugs were utilized in some research, while some other adopts the single-drug therapy. Thirdly, our meta-analysis is based on unadjusted estimates, whereas a more precise analysis could be performed if individual data were available, which would allow for an adjustment estimate (by age, sex, alcohol consumption, cigarette smoking and other lifestyle). Additionally, it should be noted that the studies included patients from several different ethnic groups, with an overrepresentation of East Asian patients (e.g., Chinese, Korean, and Japanese populations) and an underrepresentation of individuals of Caucasian descent. Since allele frequencies may vary considerably between ethnic groups, careful consideration of the potential effect of population genetics on genotypic and phenotypic distribution is warranted, but the limited samples currently available have hampered this effort.</p>
      <p>As a result of the heterogeneity of medication used, the duration of illness in different samples, and the different racial groups, it is possible that we have underestimated the effect size of the gene-drug response association. Furthermore, none of the studies formally accounted for medication noncompliance, which is prevalent in patients with TB. Put simply, when a patient does not take the prescribed anti-TB drug, the measured effect size of gene-drug response association is assessed as zero, whereas the true effect of genotype on the phenotype is perhaps larger. Nevertheless, despite the potential underestimation of effect size produced by these uncontrolled factors, we were still able to detect a significant association between the NAT2, GSTM1 and CYP2E1 polymorphism and anti-TB drug response. It is suggested that patients with high-risk genotypes should have regular liver biochemical tests in the first few months following administration of anti-TB drugs. Tailoring the anti-TB regimen to patients according to individual genetic profiles is expected in the coming years.</p>
      <p>In summary, our meta-analysis indicates that CYP2E1, NAT2 and GSTM1 genetic variation is significantly associated with anti-tuberculosis drug-induced liver injury. Polymorphisms in these DME, such as NAT2*4, may be particularly important in predicting clinical response to anti-TB drug treatment. Furthermore, interaction between candidate genes and other risk factors, such as diet, alcohol consumption, smoking, existing liver disease and other comorbid diseases, should be explored to realize the modification effect of these extrinsic factors to the expression of different genotypes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047769.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>The flow chart of the included studies.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047769.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Begg’s funnel plot of </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>NAT2</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> polymorphism and ATLI risk.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047769.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Begg’s funnel plot of </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>CYP2E1</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> polymorphism and ATLI risk.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047769.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Begg’s funnel plot of </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>GST M1</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> polymorphism and ATLI risk.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047769.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.s005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Begg’s funnel plot of </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>GST T1</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> polymorphism and ATLI risk.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047769.s006" mimetype="application/msword" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047769.s006" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Checklist S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Tostmann1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tostmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boeree</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aarnoutse</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Lange</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Ven</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Antituberculosis drug-induced hepatotoxicity: concise up-to-date review</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Saukkonen1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saukkonen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jasmer</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schenker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jereb</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>An official ATS statement: hepatotoxicity of antituberculosis therapy</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source> <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>952</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Lee1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Drug-induced hepatotoxicity</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>333</volume>: <fpage>1118</fpage>–<lpage>1127</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Mitchell1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Isoniazid liver injury: clinical spectrum, pathology, and probable pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-RungeMorris1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Runge-Morris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zangar R</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novak R</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Effects of hydrazine, phenelzine, and hydralazine treatmenton rat hepatic and renal drug-metabolizing enzyme expression</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Dispos</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>734</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Strange1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strange</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fryer</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Glutathione S-transferase: genetics and role in toxicology</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Lett</source> <volume>112–113</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Naisbitt1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naisbitt</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pirmohamed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitteringham</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Reactive metabolites and their role in drug reactions</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Allergy Clin Immunol</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-DerSimonian1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DerSimonian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Control Clin Trials</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Woolf1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1955</year>) <article-title>On estimating the relation between blood group and disease</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Genet</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Egger1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Begg1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>1101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Tang1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>CYP2E1, GSTM1 and GSTT1 genetic polymorphisms and susceptibility to antituberculosis drug-induced hepatotoxicity: a nested case-control study</article-title>. <source>J Clin Pharm Ther</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>593</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-An1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>UQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>NAT 2 and CYP2E1 polymorphisms associated with antituberculosis drug-induced hepatotoxicity in Chinese patients</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Pharmacol Physiol</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>543</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Rana1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ola</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Comparison between acetylator phenotype and genotype polymorphism of n-acetyltransferase-2 in tuberculosis patients</article-title>. <source>Hepatol Int</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-BenMahmoud1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ben Mahmoud L, Ghozzi H, Kamoun A, Hakim A, Hachicha H, <etal>et al</etal>. (2011) Polymorphism of the N-acetyltransferase 2 gene as a susceptibility risk factor for antituberculosis drug-induced hepatotoxicity in Tunisian patients with tuberculosis. Pathol Biol (Paris) doi:10.1016/j.patbio.2011.07.001.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Zhu1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>[Relationship between genetic polymorphisms of GSTM1, GSTT1 and the susceptibility to antituberculosis drug-induced liver injury]</article-title>. <source>Zhongguo Kang Sheng Su Za Zhi</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>864</fpage>–<lpage>868</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-LeiroFernandez1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leiro-Fernandez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valverde</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vazquez-Gallardo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Botana-Rial</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Constenla</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>N-acetyltransferase 2 polymorphisms and risk of anti-tuberculosis drug-induced hepatotoxicity in Caucasians</article-title>. <source>Int J Tuberc Lung Dis</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1403</fpage>–<lpage>1408</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Sotsuka1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sotsuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamagishi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Association of isoniazid-metabolizing enzyme genotypes and isoniazid-induced hepatotoxicity in tuberculosis patients</article-title>. <source>In Vivo</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>803</fpage>–<lpage>812</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Sistanizad1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sistanizad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azizi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khalili</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hajiabdolbaghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gholami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Antituberculosis Drug-Induced Hepatotoxicity in Iranian Tuberculosis Patients: Role of Isoniazid Metabolic Polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Iranian Journal of Pharmaceutical Research</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>633</fpage>–<lpage>639</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Huang1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>LV</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>[Association between polymorphism of N-acetyltransferase 2 gene and development of antituberculosis drug-induced liver injury]</article-title>. <source>ZhongHua Sheng Wu Yi Xue Gong Cheng Za Zhi</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>444</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Teixeira1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morato</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabello</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muniz</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreira Ada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genetic polymorphisms of NAT2, CYP2E1 and GST enzymes and the occurrence of antituberculosis drug-induced hepatitis in Brazilian TB patients</article-title>. <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>716</fpage>–<lpage>724</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Yimer1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yimer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Habtewold</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amogne</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Pharmacogenetic &amp; pharmacokinetic biomarker for efavirenz based ARV and rifampicin based anti-TB drug induced liver injury in TB-HIV infected patients</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e27810</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Bose1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medhi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Role of polymorphic N-acetyl transferase2 and cytochrome P4502E1 gene in antituberculosis treatment-induced hepatitis</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Chatterjee1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>GSTT1 and GSTM1 gene deletions are not associated with hepatotoxicity caused by antitubercular drugs</article-title>. <source>J Clin Pharm Ther</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Wang1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genetic polymorphisms of cytochrome P450 and glutathione S-transferase associated with antituberculosis drug-induced hepatotoxicity in Chinese tuberculosis patients</article-title>. <source>J Int Med Res</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>977</fpage>–<lpage>986</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Lee2">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liou</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>NAT2 and CYP2E1 polymorphisms and susceptibility to first-line anti-tuberculosis drug-induced hepatitis</article-title>. <source>Int J Tuberc Lung Dis</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>622</fpage>–<lpage>626</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Kim1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>GSTT1 and GSTM1 null mutations and adverse reactions induced by antituberculosis drugs in Koreans</article-title>. <source>Tuberculosis (Edinb)</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Wu1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>[The association between NAT2 polymorphism and anti-tuberculosis drug-induced hepatitis]</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Gan Zang Bing Za Zhi</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>469</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Guo1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>[The relationship between polymorphisms of N-acetyltransferase 2 genes and anti-tuberculosis drug induced hepatic-injury]</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Chuan Ran Bing Za Zhi</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Chen1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>[Study of the relationship between polymorphisms of cytochrome P450 2E1 and antituberculosis drug-induced hepatic injury]</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Chuan Ran Bing Za Zhi</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>748</fpage>–<lpage>752</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Wang2">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>QQ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>[Association of P450–2E1 and GSTM1 genetic polymorphisms with susceptibility to antituberculosis drug-induced hepatotoxicity]</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Jie He He Hu Xi Za Zhi</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>587</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Guo2">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>[The effect of GST M1 and GST T1 gene mutations on anti-tuberculous drug induced hepatic injury]</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Jie He He Hu Xi Za Zhi</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Kim2">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bahn</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genetic polymorphisms of drug-metabolizing enzymes and anti-TB drug-induced hepatitis</article-title>. <source>Pharmacogenomics</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1767</fpage>–<lpage>1779</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Yamada1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halaschek-Wiener</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genetic variations of NAT2 and CYP2E1 and isoniazid hepatotoxicity in a diverse population</article-title>. <source>Pharmacogenomics</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1433</fpage>–<lpage>1445</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Wang3">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>[Prospective nested case - control study on relation between N-acetyltransferase-2 acetylator phenotype and hepatotoxicity in China] Zhongguo Gong Gong Wei Sheng</article-title>. <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>300</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Leiro1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leiro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Villar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valverde</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Constenla</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Influence of glutathione S-transferase M1 and T1 homozygous null mutations on the risk of antituberculosis drug-induced hepatotoxicity in a Caucasian population</article-title>. <source>Liver Int</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>835</fpage>–<lpage>839</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-BozokCetintas1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bozok Cetintas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erer</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kosova</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ozdemir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Topcuoglu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Determining the relation between N-acetyltransferase-2 acetylator phenotype and antituberculosis drug induced hepatitis by molecular biologic tests</article-title>. <source>Tuberk Toraks</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Possuelo1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Possuelo</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castelan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Brito</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cafrune</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Association of slow N-acetyltransferase 2 profile and anti-TB drug-induced hepatotoxicity in patients from Southern Brazil</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>673</fpage>–<lpage>681</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Huang2">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genetic polymorphisms of manganese superoxide dismutase, NAD(P)H: quinone oxidoreductase, glutathione S-transferase M1 and T1, and the susceptibility to drug-induced liver injury</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Cho1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ki</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genetic polymorphisms of NAT2 and CYP2E1 associated with antituberculosis drug-induced hepatotoxicity in Korean patients with pulmonary tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Tuberculosis (Edinb)</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>556</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Higuchi1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tahara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yanagihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukushima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suyama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>NAT2 6A, a haplotype of the N-acetyltransferase 2 gene, is an important biomarker for risk of anti-tuberculosis drug-induced hepatotoxicity in Japanese patients with tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>6003</fpage>–<lpage>6008</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Vuilleumier1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vuilleumier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rossier</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiappe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Degoumois</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dayer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>CYP2E1 genotype and isoniazid-induced hepatotoxicity in patients treated for latent tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>423</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Shimizu1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Endou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moriya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>DNA microarray genotyping of N-acetyltransferase 2 polymorphism using carbodiimide as the linker for assessment of isoniazid hepatotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Tuberculosis (Edinb)</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>374</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Roy1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sutradhar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sikdar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Predisposition of antituberculosis drug induced hepatotoxicity by cytochrome P450 2E1 genotype and haplotype in pediatric patients</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>784</fpage>–<lpage>786</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Wang4">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>[The study on the susceptible gene of isoniazid and rifampicin-induced hepatotoxicity of pulmonary tuberculosis patients]</article-title>. <source>Jun Yi Jin Xiu Xue Yuan Xue Bao</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Huang3">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chern</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Cytochrome P450 2E1 genotype and the susceptibility to antituberculosis drug-induced hepatitis</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>924</fpage>–<lpage>930</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Huang4">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chern</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Polymorphism of the N-acetyltransferase 2 gene as a susceptibility risk factor for antituberculosis drug-induced hepatitis</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>883</fpage>–<lpage>889</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Roy2">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Increased risk of antituberculosis drug-induced hepatotoxicity in individuals with glutathione S-transferase M1 ‘null’ mutation</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1033</fpage>–<lpage>1037</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Ohno1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Slow N-acetyltransferase 2 genotype affects the incidence of isoniazid and rifampicin-induced hepatotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Int J Tuberc Lung Dis</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Tang2">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genetic polymorphism analysis of cytochrome P4502E1 (CYP2E1) in Chinese Han populations from four different geographic areas of Mainland China</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047769-Lauterburg1">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauterburg</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell JR: Pharmacokinetics of the toxic hydrazine metabolites formed from isoniazid in humans. J. Pharmacol. Exp</surname><given-names>Ther</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <volume>235(3)</volume>: <fpage>566</fpage>–<lpage>570</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>