<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0154248</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-42879</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental health and psychiatry</subject><subj-group><subject>Mood disorders</subject><subj-group><subject>Depression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavior</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Engineering and technology</subject><subj-group><subject>Equipment</subject><subj-group><subject>Communication equipment</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell phones</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental health and psychiatry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care policy</subject><subj-group><subject>Screening guidelines</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Database and informatics methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Database searching</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Research assessment</subject><subj-group><subject>Systematic reviews</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Systematic Review of Cognitive Behavioral Therapy and Behavioral Activation Apps for Depression</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Systematic Review of CBT and BA Apps for Depression</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4002-8644</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Huguet</surname>
<given-names>Anna</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>Sanjay</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>McGrath</surname>
<given-names>Patrick J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff006"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wozney</surname>
<given-names>Lori</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wheaton</surname>
<given-names>Mike</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Conrod</surname>
<given-names>Jill</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Rozario</surname>
<given-names>Sharlene</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Center for Research in Family Health, IWK Health Centre, Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Department of Community Health &amp; Epidemiology, Dalhousie University, Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Annapolis Valley Health, Kentville, Nova Scotia, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Department of Psychiatry, Dalhousie University, Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff005"><label>5</label> <addr-line>Departments of Pediatrics and Science, Dalhousie University, Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff006"><label>6</label> <addr-line>Nova Scotia Health Authority, Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Choo</surname>
<given-names>Kim-Kwang Raymond</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of South Australia, AUSTRALIA</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AH SR (second author) PJM. Performed the experiments: AH SR (seventh author) MW LW JC SR (second author). Analyzed the data: AH SR (seventh author) MW LW JC SR (second author). Wrote the paper: AH.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">anna.huguet@iwk.nshealth.ca</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>2</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e0154248</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>30</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>11</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Huguet et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0154248"/>
<abstract>
<p>Depression is a common mental health condition for which many mobile apps aim to provide support. This review aims to identify self-help apps available exclusively for people with depression and evaluate those that offer cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) or behavioural activation (BA). One hundred and seventeen apps have been identified after searching both the scientific literature and the commercial market. 10.26% (n = 12) of these apps identified through our search offer support that seems to be consistent with evidence-based principles of CBT or BA. Taking into account the non existence of effectiveness/efficacy studies, and the low level of adherence to the core ingredients of the CBT/BA models, the utility of these CBT/BA apps are questionable. The usability of reviewed apps is highly variable and they rarely are accompanied by explicit privacy or safety policies. Despite the growing public demand, there is a concerning lack of appropiate CBT or BA apps, especially from a clinical and legal point of view. The application of superior scientific, technological, and legal knowledge is needed to improve the development, testing, and accessibility of apps for people with depression.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The authors have no support or funding to report.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="1"/>
<table-count count="7"/>
<page-count count="19"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Depression is one of the most common mental health disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref001">1</xref>] which often begins in adolescence and if left untreated, may persist into adulthood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref002">2</xref>]. It ranks 4th in the global burden of disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref003">3</xref>]and is of significant economic cost to society[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref004">4</xref>]. Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) and Behavioural Activation (BA) are now an accepted evidence-based first-line treatment for depression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref005">5</xref>]. Both CBT and BA have meta-analytic level of evidence in the treatment of depression[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref007">7</xref>]. Periodic face-to-face sessions between therapist and patient have been the most traditional medium to deliver CBT and BA. However, with population estimates of Major Depression at 6.7% and even higher for Non-Major Depression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref001">1</xref>], it is unlikely that this traditional approach can reach everyone.</p>
<p>More recent research indicates that depression can be treated successfully with CBT and BA based self-help interventions delivered over the Internet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref010">10</xref>]. This type of therapy is suited for digital delivery as demonstrated by the fact that there are more Internet-based studies on CBT/BA than on other evidence-based models (e.g., Interpersonal Therapy or Acceptance and Commitment Therpy). There is a strong case in healthcare for addressing access to CBT or BA through the use of technology, with mobile applications (apps) being one possible means of delivery. Apps could be especially useful in early treatment of depression in young people who report high levels of smartphone device use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref011">11</xref>].</p>
<p>Smartphone use is a growing phenomenon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref012">12</xref>] and has the advantage of being accessible, mobile, and easy to operate, with decreasing cost of use. Smartphones have been used to facilitate the delivery of healthcare interventions including treatment of mental health conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref013">13</xref>]. The number of apps intended to help people cope with depression is increasing rapidly, especially in the commercial marketplace [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref014">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref015">15</xref>]; however the development process, usability, feasibility, and efficacy of these apps developed in the commercial marketplace are rarely assessed or reported. The quality of the available apps has not been the subject of any systematic reviews, until now.</p>
<p>It is vital to perform a systematic review of apps for depression to identify what currently available apps are based on strong and recommended evidence models for depression. Evaluating the available apps can inform future development of effective smartphone delivered intervention for depression. The purpose of this systematic review was twofold: (1) To identify all currently-available native apps that provide information, support or treatment for depression; (2) To evaluate CBT or BA self-help (either guided or unguided) apps on their usefulness, usability, and integration and infrastructure, as recommended by Chan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref016">16</xref>]. Usefulness was determined by evaluating how accurately each CBT/BA app tapped into the core of the CBT and BA models, and by exploring whether the efficacy or effectiveness of the CBT/BA apps have been proven or not. Usability was evaluated by comparing each CBT/BA app to a list of heuristics, and integration and infrastructure was evaluated by looking whether the CBT/BA apps included a privacy policy and addressed safety issues.</p>
<p>The results of this review can assist care providers in choosing appropriate apps for the treatment or research of depression. The review will also identify areas for future development to effectively provide CBT or BA for depression through smartphones.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Inclusion and Exclusion criteria</title>
<p>We included in our review those apps that met the following inclusion criteria: (1) the app description stated that they provide treatment or support for depression as its exclusive goal; (2) the app was publically available for download within Canada at the time this review was performed (December, 2015), and consequently also fully available for evaluation by the research team; (3) the app was defined as a native app (i.e., developed for one particular mobile device and installed directly onto the device itself) compatible with smartphones. We excluded from the review those apps which specifically addressed depressed subpopulations (e.g., depressed people with diabetes, postpartum depression) because they have special health care needs that require different care. We also excluded those apps that were designed to support health care professionals working with depressed populations because these apps are addressed to a different audience. We excluded web-based/Internet-enabled apps only accessible via the mobile device’s Web browser because they are very challenging to identify in a systematic way. Finally, we also excluded those apps which were only available in a non-English language.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Search strategy</title>
<p>The apps included in this review were identified by searching both the scientific literature and commercial marketplace.</p>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>The search of the scientific literature</title>
<p>The following databases from health sciences and computer science were searched: IEEE, ACM Digital Library, EMBASE, PubMed (Medline), PsychINFO, and Web of Science. A library information specialist created the database-specific search strategies by combining population-specific term (i.e., depression) and terms related to technical delivery (i.e., app, smartphone, mobile phone, cell phone, text message, iphone, and android), narrowing the results to those studies related to depression and mobile apps. Search strategy in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0154248.s002">S1 Appendix</xref> displays the strategy for retrieving relevant manuscripts from PubMed. The library information specialist did the search in November 2015. During the first level of screening, two reviwers (AH, SR) independently assessed a random selection of 15% of the titles and abstracts retrieved from search (350 electronic search results) to determine inter-rater agreement on inclusion and exclusion criteria. With substantial levels of agreement (kappa = 0.69) observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref017">17</xref>], the remaining titles and abstracts were screened by only one reviewer (SR). At the second level of screening, potential relevant full- text articles were reviewed and a random selection of 30% of articles (a subset of 50 articles) were independently assessed by two reviewers (AH, SR). Articles were excluded at this stage from further consideration for a number of reasons (i.e., article did not talk about depression, article did not make mention of any native app, the app mentioned in the article was not addressed to people with depression, the manuscript was not written in English). With substantial levels of agreement observed at this second level of screening (kappa = 0.85) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref017">17</xref>], the remaining full-text articles were reviewed by only one reviewer (SR). The 53 manuscripts included at this stage mentioned a total of 253 native apps for people with depression. Two independent reviewers (SR, AH) independently evaluated whether a random selection of 50% of these 253 apps (n = 125) meet the eligibility criteria based on our inclusion/exclusion criteria. With almost perfect agreement observed at this third level of screening (kappa = 0.92) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref017">17</xref>], the remaining apps were reviewed by only one reviewer (SR). Contact was made with corresponding authors to request access to any apps described in a manuscript where there was no information provided on public access for downloading. Discrepancies at any level of screening were resolved by consensus among reviewers. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154248.g001">Fig 1</xref> for details about the screening process.</p>
<fig id="pone.0154248.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Flowchart of the screening process.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>The search of the commercial market place</title>
<p>The search was restricted to apps available through the two most popular mobile phone platforms, The Canadian Apple App Store and Android Market (Google Play). The search was made in November 2015 using ‘depression’ as the search query. One reviewer (JC) searched the stores to identify all of the available apps, and two reviewers (AH, JC) independently evaluated each identified unique app for eligibility based on our inclusion/exclusion criteria. The level of agreement between both independent reviewers using the Cohen’s Kappa was 0.89. Discrepancies were resolved through discussion. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154248.g001">Fig 1</xref> for further details.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Data extraction</title>
<p>The apps retrieved by our searches were categorized by two independent reviewers (AH, JC) according to the type(s) of support that they offered to the users. The categories, defined a priori, included: self- tracking tools, education, social support, CBT/BA treatment, state induction, diagnostic/screening tools, and miscellaneous. One app could be categorized into different types of self-help apps when the app included more than one type of support. All the apps included in the review were available in the app stores, regardless of where they were identified (i.e., scientific literature vs commercial market). The app description displayed in the stores and any available description provided in the manuscript was the only information used by the reviewers to base their decisions on which category each app fell into. The level of agreement between the two reviewers when categorizing the apps, using the Cohen’s kappa, was 0.92, indicating almost perfect agreement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref017">17</xref>]. When reviewers were in disagreement, they discussed it, and came to an agreement. When an agreement could not be reached, a third reviewer was called upon (SR). For those apps that were classified as CBT/BA the following information was extracted: accessibility (i.e., iTunes, Google Play, scientific literature), cost, and indicators of popularity (i.e., for the apps identified through the Google Play store, the number of times an app has been downloaded to an android phone; for the apps identified through the Google Play store or the iTunes store, the number of users that have rated the app on a scale of 1 to 5 as well as the average satisfaction rate provided by users; although both types of information are only available when there is a large, unspecified amount of users that have rated the app).</p>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Assessment of CBT/BA apps</title>
<p>Since our primary focus of attention was CBT or BA only those apps that offered this type of treatment were downloaded for full evaluation. When both a paid and free version of an app was available, the version requiring payment was purchased and used, while the free version was excluded. This was done to ensure that the most comprehensive version of the app was considered. In accordance with Chan et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref016">16</xref>], who have recently proposed a framework to evaluate mobile mental health apps, we evaluated each app on three dimensions using the following criteria:</p>
<p><italic>Usefulness</italic>: To determine the usefulness of the apps, the validity and accuracy (does the app actually offer CBT or BA?), and effectiveness (is the app clinically effective–with demonstrated improved outcomes- for people with depression?) criteria were used. To evaluate whether the app actually offers CBT or BA, an experienced academic CBT clinician (SR) evaluated the apps for their level of fidelity to theoretical CBT and BA principles by exploring what extent the apps included the core ingredients of these models. The evaluator has extensive experience in training CBT therapists and devising CBT clinical programmes. The core ingredients for CBT and BA were derived by consulting with two academic experts and one CBT clinician, as well as reviewing the literature for CBT and BA models in the treatment of depression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref019">19</xref>]. The following were considered as the core ingredients of a CBT approach for depression: 1) education about depression; 2) explanation of the model, 3) depression rating, 4) monitoring cognitions, 5) monitoring emotions, 6) monitoring physical sensations, 7) monitoring behaviours, 8) conceptualization, 9) behavioural techniques, and 10) cognitive techniques. The following were considered as the core ingredients of the various BA approaches: 1) education about depression, 2) explanation of the model, 3) depression rating, 4) activity monitoring, 5) giving each activity a rating for pleasure, 6) giving each activity a rating for mastery, 7) activity scheduling of pleasant behaviours, and 8) activity scheduling of avoided behaviours. The expert evaluated each app against each core ingredient on a 0–2 scale where 0 meant that the core ingredient was not integrated at all into the app, and 2 meant that the core ingredient was completely integrated. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0154248.t001">Table 1</xref> displays the scoring system devised for rating of the apps against each core ingredient. For each app, a percent total score (sum of item scores/maximum possible score * 100), representing the level of adherence of the app to the theoretical principles of CBT and BA approaches, was then calculated. To evaluate the effectiveness of the apps, we cross-referenced with apps identified in the scientific literature to see whether there was any efficacy or effectiveness study on apps included in the review.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0154248.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>System to grade the level of adherence to the theoretical principles of CBT and BA.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0154248.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Item</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">Core features</th>
<th align="left">0</th>
<th align="left">1</th>
<th align="left">2</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Behavioural activation</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Education about depression</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Clear explanation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Explanation of the model</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Clear explanation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Depression rating</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Formally rated (e.g., on a 0–10 scale)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Activity monitoring</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Formally self-monitoring (e.g., through a diary)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Activity monitoring: Pleasure rating</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Formally rated (e.g., on a 0–10 scale)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Activity monitoring: Mastery rating</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Formally rated (e.g., on a 0–10 scale)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Activity scheduling of pleasant behaviours</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Formally rated (e.g., on a 0–10 scale)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Activity scheduling of avoidancebehaviours</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Formally rated (e.g., on a 0–10 scale)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Cognitive-behavioural treatment</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Education about depression</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Clear explanation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Explanation of the model</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Clear explanation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Depression rating</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Formally rated (e.g., on a 0–10 scale)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Monitoring cognitions</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Thoughts and beliefs monitored</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Monitoring emotions</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Specific emotions monitored</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Monitoring physical sensations</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Specific physical sensations monitored</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Monitoring behaviours</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Specific behaviours monitored</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Conceptualization</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Someelements</td>
<td align="left">Adequate problem formulation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Cognitive techniques</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Systematic use of technique</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Behavioural techniques</td>
<td align="left">None</td>
<td align="left">Some</td>
<td align="left">Systematic use of technique</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p><italic>Usability</italic>: The usability of the app (can the user easily–or with minimal training- use and understand the app?) was used to evaluate this dimension. Most apps retrieved from our searches have been developed by small businesses or sole proprietors outside of academic settings, and little information is available on the app development process or evidence of formal usability testing. For this reason, a user experience designer (MW), who regulary performs expert reviews on mobile apps and websites, where he applies heuristics and professional experience to evaluate user interfaces and suggest design improvements, evaluated the usability of the apps. He evaluated the user interface of each app using a common list of usability heuristics proposed by Nielsen &amp; Mack [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref020">20</xref>]. The usability expert rated each app on a scale of 1 to 5 (1 = poor, 5 = excellent) against each usability heuristic (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0154248.t002">Table 2</xref> for the set of heuristics). A percentage total score (sum of item scores/maximum possible total score * 100) was then calculated, indicating the extent to which the user interface of the app met the usability heuristics.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0154248.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Heuristics used to assess usability of the apps.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0154248.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Heuristic</th>
<th align="left">Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Visibility of system status</td>
<td align="left">The system should always keep users informed about what is going on, through appropriate feedback within reasonable time.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Match between system and the real world</td>
<td align="left">The system should speak the users' language, with words, phrases and concepts familiar to the user, rather than system-oriented terms. Follow real-world conventions, making information appear in a natural and logical order.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">User control and freedom</td>
<td align="left">Users often choose system functions by mistake and will need a clearly marked "emergency exit" to leave the unwanted state without having to go through an extended dialogue. Support undo and redo.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Consistency and standards</td>
<td align="left">Users should not have to wonder whether different words, situations, or actions mean the same thing. Follow platform conventions.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Error prevention</td>
<td align="left">Even better than good error messages is a careful design which prevents a problem from occurring in the first place. Either eliminate error-prone conditions or check for them and present users with a confirmation option before they commit to the action.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Recognition rather than recall</td>
<td align="left">Minimize the user's memory load by making objects, actions, and options visible. The user should not have to remember information from one part of the dialogue to another. Instructions for use of the system should be visible or easily retrievable whenever appropriate.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Flexibility and efficiency of use</td>
<td align="left">Accelerators—unseen by the novice user—may often speed up the interaction for the expert user such that the system can cater to both inexperienced and experienced users. Allow users to tailor frequent actions.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Aesthetic and minimalist design</td>
<td align="left">Dialogues should not contain information which is irrelevant or rarely needed. Every extra unit of information in a dialogue competes with the relevant units of information and diminishes their relative visibility.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Help users recognize, diagnose, and recover from errors</td>
<td align="left">Error messages should be expressed in plain language (no codes), precisely indicate the problem, and constructively suggest a solution.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Help and documentation</td>
<td align="left">Even though it is better if the system can be used without documentation, it may be necessary to provide help and documentation. Any such information should be easy to search, focused on the user's task, list concrete steps to be carried out, and not be too large.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p><italic>Integration and infrastructure</italic>: Privacy and safety were the criteria used to evaluate this dimension. To evaluate privacy, an evaluator (SR) looked into whether the apps provided users with a privacy policy (within the apps themselves or on a website linked to the app). If a privacy policy was available the evaluator assessesed the scope and the level of transparency of the policy as done by Sunyaev et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref021">21</xref>]. To this end, the evaluator determined whether the policy addressed the following content categories important to users: type of information collected (e.g., operational, behavioral, sensitive), rationale for collection (i.e., app operation, personalization, secondary use), sharing of information (i.e., service provision, social interaction, third party), and users controls (i.e., supervision, notification, correction). To evaluate safety, an evaluator (SR) explored whether the apps had any mechanisms in place to handle high risk of suicidality (e.g. providing emergency contact information whenever the app detects a user is at high risk for committing suicide).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Analysis Plan</title>
<p>Basic summary statistics including counts and percentages were used to describe the characteristics of the apps. Spearman’s correlation coefficient was used to explore whether a relationship may exist between the adherence of the user interface to Nilsen’s principles of usability and adherence to the core principles underlying CBT and BA. Spearman’s correlation coefficients were also used to explore whether adherence to the core principlies underlying CBT and BA and adherence to Nilsen’s principles of usability is related with any indicator of popularity and acceptability (i.e., average rating of satisfaction, number of reviews and number of downloads).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Search</title>
<p>Our search of commercial marketplace identified a total of 310 unique apps. One hundred and four of these apps identified in the commercial marketplace meet our inclusion/exclusion criteria. The literature search yielded 2,789 abstracts, and 160 full text manuscripts were reviewed at the full-text level. Fifty-three out of 160 were relevant for our review because all them mention at least one native app addressed to people for depression. Many of these manuscripts identified as relevant for our review were reports or reviews reporting on multiple apps. For example, Shen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref014">14</xref>], has recently conducted a systematic review to identify and characterize all the apps available in the app stores to support people with depression, their families and health care professionals, based on the store description. The 53 manuscripts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref014">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref015">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref022">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref023">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref024">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref025">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref027">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref028">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref029">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref030">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref031">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref032">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref033">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref034">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref035">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref036">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref037">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref038">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref039">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref040">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref041">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref042">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref043">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref044">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref045">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref046">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref047">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref048">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref049">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref050">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref051">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref052">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref053">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref054">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref055">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref056">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref057">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref058">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref059">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref060">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref061">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref062">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref063">63</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref064">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref065">65</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref066">66</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref067">67</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref068">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref069">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref070">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref071">71</xref>] identified as relevant to the review made mention of a total of 48 unique apps that met our inclusion/exclusion criteria. Thirty-five of these 48 apps were also identified through our search of the commercial marketplace. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154248.g001">Fig 1</xref> for a flowchart of the screening process of the apps.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>App characteristics</title>
<p>Out of the total 117 apps, 36 apps (30.77%) were available on iOS only, 74 (63.25%) were available on Android only, and 7 (5.98%) were available across both platforms. The most typical type of self-help support delivered through these 117 apps was education (n = 32, 27.35%) and diagnostic/screening support (n = 30, 25.64%), followed by state induction (n = 18, 15.38%). The least typical types of self-help support delivered through these 117 apps were tracking (n = 10, 8.55%) and social support (n = 3, 2.56%). Twelve of these 117 apps (10.26%) were classified by the reviewers as delivering CBT or BA; these CBT/BA apps were identified in the description by their developers as CBT or BA apps or they seemed to offer CBT or BA based on their general description (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0154248.t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0154248.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>All apps for depression included in the review.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0154248.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Type of Self-Help App</th>
<th align="left">Screening</th>
<th align="left">Number of Apps<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
<th align="center">Total Number of apps (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
<th align="left">Name of the Apps</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="justify"><bold>Tracking</bold></td>
<td align="center">Commercial Marketplace</td>
<td align="center">6</td>
<td align="center">10 (8.55)</td>
<td align="left">Depression Test, Depression Tracker and Diary, Emotion, Life Robot- Fight Depression, Mood tracker- depression, Start</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="center">Literature</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">iDepression Tracker</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="center">Both</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Depression Inventory, Depression Journal, Depression Test &amp; Tracker</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"><bold>CBT/BA</bold></td>
<td align="center">Commercial Marketplace</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">12 (10.26)</td>
<td align="left">MoodTools- Depression Aid, Overcome the Depression pro, Anti-Depression, Activity Diary</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="center">Both</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Depression, Depression CBT Self- Help Guide, Depression Cure- The free 12 week course, iCounselor: Depression, Mood Master Anti- Depression App, Mood Sentry, Positive Activity Jackpot, eCBT Mood</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"><bold>State Induction</bold></td>
<td align="center">Commercial marketplace</td>
<td align="center">10</td>
<td align="center">18 (15.38)</td>
<td align="left">Beat Depression Hypnosis Audio, Depression Cure Hypnosis, Depression Mood Booster, Fight Depression, From Depression to Hope, MoodSpace, Vital Tones Depression, Yoga for Depression, Yoga Helps Relieve Depression, Life Robot- Fight Depression</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="center">Literature</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Depression Relief and Mood–HappyApp,Mood Elevator &amp; Support</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="center">Both</td>
<td align="center">6</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Beat Depression Hypnosis Syste, Depression Help Brainwave, Depression Inventory, Heal Depression Hypnosis, The Mindful Way Through Depression, Black Rainbow: How to Beat Depression</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"><bold>Diagnostic/ screening</bold></td>
<td align="center">Commercial Marketplace</td>
<td align="center">15</td>
<td align="center">30 (25.64)</td>
<td align="left">CESD Depression Test, Depression Diagnosis Doctor, Depression Eval Questionnaire, Depression Screening Test, Depression Test, Depression Test, Depression Test, Depression Test, Depression Test, Depression Test, Depression Test and Treatment, Depression Tracker &amp; Diary, Depression Test Pro, Depression Test, Emotion</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="center">Literature</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Am I Depressed, Do I have Depression, Happy App, Zung</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="center">Both</td>
<td align="center">11</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Are You at Risk for Depression?, Depression Calculator, Depression Screening, Depression Test, Depression Test, Learn About Depression, Major Depression Checker, Sad Scale Lite, STAT Depression Screening PHQ 9, The Depression Predictor, Depression Test &amp; Tracker</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"><bold>Education</bold></td>
<td align="center">Commercial Marketplace</td>
<td align="center">22</td>
<td align="center">32 (27.35)</td>
<td align="left">Conquering Depression, Dealing with Depression, Dealing with Depression, Depression, Depression and How to Stop it, Depression &amp; Psychology, Depression Definition, Depression Healing, Depression Information, Depression Management, Depression Symptoms, Depression Symptoms and Signs, Depression: An Overview, Depression: Natural Remedies, Fitness Against Depression, Help with Depression, How to get Over Depression, Physical Symptoms Depression, Reduce Depression, The Key to Happiness, Black Rainbow: How to Beat Depression, Emotion</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="center">Literature</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Beat Depression, Depression Treatment, Overcoming Depression</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="center">Both</td>
<td align="center">7</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Depression 101, Depression Advice, NIH Depression Information, Ten Tips to Ease Depression, The Depression Predictor, Are You at Risk for Depression?, Depression Preview</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"><bold>Social Support</bold></td>
<td align="center">Commercial Marketplace</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">3 (2.56)</td>
<td align="left">Dealing with Depression, You Are Important</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="center">Both</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Depression Test</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"><bold>Unclear/ miscellaneous</bold></td>
<td align="center">Commercial Marketplace</td>
<td align="center">22</td>
<td align="center">28 (23.93)</td>
<td align="left">A Guiding Light, Acupuncture Against Depression, Afternoon in Depression, Best Depression Quotes, Depression, dePRESSION, Depression Quotes Wallpaper, Depression Quotes Wallpaper, Depression- Acupuncture, Depressive and Sad Wallpaper, Endless Depression, Get Rid of Depression with Chinese Massage Points, Guide to Depression Self- Help, How to Beat Depression, Sad Quotes Wallpaper, Sadness and Depression Quotes, Secret of Happiness, Self-Help for Depression, MoodSpace, Life Robot- Fight Depression, Depression Management, You are Important</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="center">Literature</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Depressed, DepressPill Game for Happy, Joker</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="center">Both</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left">Anti-Depression Grocery List, Depression Fighter- A Practical Christian Guide, Surviving Depression</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p><sup>a</sup> The total sum of number of apps for each type of self-help app is not equal to the total number of apps identified through our searches (n = 117), since some apps have been categorized into multiple categories.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p><sup>b</sup> Percentage of the total 117 apps</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>CBT/BA apps characteristics</title>
<p>Five of the 12 CBT/BA apps (41.67%) were available on iOS only and 5 (41.67%) on Android only. The cost of these CBT/BA apps ranged from $0.00 to $8.99. The Depression CBT Self-Help Guide and The Mood Tools–Depression Aid were those Android apps with the highest number of downloads (i.e., between 100,000 and 500,000 downloads, and between 50,000 and 100,000, respectively) and received high user satisfaction ratings (average satisfaction rates were 4.2 and 4.3, respectively). The iPhone app that received the highest user satisfaction rating was The Depression Cure: The Free 12 Week Course app (average satisfaction rating = 4.5). However, this app was not the one that received the highest number of reviews. The iPhone apps that received the highest number of reviews were the Anti-depression and MoodTools–Depression Aid apps, both of them also available for download in the Google Play store. For further information about the characteristics of the CBT/BA apps see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0154248.t004">Table 4</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0154248.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>Currently-available CBT or BA apps for depression.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0154248.t004g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center">Name</th>
<th align="center">Author</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Commercial Market</th>
<th align="center">Scientifc Literature</th>
<th align="center">Cost</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Popularity</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Adherence with the core ingredients</th>
<th align="center">Adherencewith the heuristics</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center"/>
<th align="center"/>
<th align="center">iTunes</th>
<th align="center">Google Play</th>
<th align="center"/>
<th align="center"/>
<th align="center">ASR<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
<th align="center"># of reviews</th>
<th align="center"># of downloads</th>
<th align="center">CBT</th>
<th align="center">BA</th>
<th align="center"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depression Cure: The free 12 week course</td>
<td align="center">Archie’s Empire</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">$8.99</td>
<td align="center">4.5</td>
<td align="center">29</td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">10%</td>
<td align="center">18.75%</td>
<td align="center">92%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">iCounselor: Depression</td>
<td align="center">iCounselor</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">$1.19</td>
<td align="center">2.5</td>
<td align="center">9</td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">5%</td>
<td align="center">6.25%</td>
<td align="center">60%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Mood Master Anti depression App</td>
<td align="center">Mood Master</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">$4.59</td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">15%</td>
<td align="center">18.75%</td>
<td align="center">82%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">eCBT Mood</td>
<td align="center">MindApps LLC</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">$1.19</td>
<td align="center">2.5</td>
<td align="center">12</td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">55%</td>
<td align="center">25%</td>
<td align="center">70%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Activity Diary</td>
<td align="center">Happtic Pty. Ltd</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">$3.49</td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">0%</td>
<td align="center">18.75%</td>
<td align="center">98%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Anti-depression</td>
<td align="center">Dion LLC</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">$0</td>
<td align="center">3.7</td>
<td align="center">250</td>
<td align="center">10,000–50,000</td>
<td align="center">25%</td>
<td align="center">25%</td>
<td align="center">88%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MoodTools—Depression Aid</td>
<td align="center">MoodTools</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">$0</td>
<td align="center">4.3</td>
<td align="center">1,466</td>
<td align="center">50,000–100,000</td>
<td align="center">10%</td>
<td align="center">12.5%</td>
<td align="center">98%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Mood Sentry</td>
<td align="center">Mood Apps LLC</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">$1.97</td>
<td align="center">5.0</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">50–100</td>
<td align="center">25%</td>
<td align="center">6.25%</td>
<td align="center">42%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depression</td>
<td align="center">AppCounselor</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">$0.99</td>
<td align="center">4.0</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">500–1,000</td>
<td align="center">15%</td>
<td align="center">6.25%</td>
<td align="center">64%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depression CBT Self-Help Guide</td>
<td align="center">Excel at Life</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">$0</td>
<td align="center">4.2</td>
<td align="center">1,154</td>
<td align="center">100,000–500,000</td>
<td align="center">75%</td>
<td align="center">25%</td>
<td align="center">62%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Overcome the Depression Pro</td>
<td align="center">Zanapps</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">$0</td>
<td align="center">4.2</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">100–500</td>
<td align="center">20%</td>
<td align="center">18.75%</td>
<td align="center">84%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Positive Activity Jackpot</td>
<td align="center">T2</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">$0</td>
<td align="center">3.4</td>
<td align="center">74</td>
<td align="center">10,000–50,000</td>
<td align="center">0%</td>
<td align="center">12.5%</td>
<td align="center">84%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p><sup>a</sup> ASR- Average Satisfaction Rating</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn002"><p><sup>b</sup>Some apps do not have enough user reviews to have an average rating, stated by n/a.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Regarding the validy and accuracy of the CBT/BA apps, the median level of adherence with the CBT principles was 15% (range = 0–75%) and the median level of adherence with the BA principles was 18.75% (range = 6.25–25%). The best apps from a theoretical perspective were Depression CBT Self-Help Guide and eCBT Mood meeting 75% and 55% of the qualifying criteria for CBT, respectively. The rest of the apps presented less than 50% of adherence for both the CBT and BA principles (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0154248.t005">Table 5</xref>). The core ingredients of CBT most commonly included in these CBT/BA apps were: education about depression and depression ratings. The core ingredients included least often were: monitoring physical sensations, monitoring behaviors, and conceptualization. The core ingredients of BA most commonly included were: education about depression and depression ratings and the rest of the core ingredients were never completely integrated into the apps. Regarding the effectiveness of the apps, there were no studies reported in the scientific literature that determined the benefits of any of these CBT/BA apps.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0154248.t005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t005</object-id>
<label>Table 5</label> <caption><title>Evaluation of the usefulness dimension.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0154248.t005g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">Usefulness Dimensions</th>
<th align="center" colspan="12">Name</th>
<th align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center">Depression Cure- the Free 12 Week Course</th>
<th align="center">iCounselor: Depression</th>
<th align="center">MoodMaster- Anti Depression App</th>
<th align="center">eCBT Mood</th>
<th align="center">Activity Diary</th>
<th align="center">Anti-Depression</th>
<th align="center">MoodTools-Depression Aid</th>
<th align="center">Mood Sentry</th>
<th align="center">Depression</th>
<th align="center">Depression CBT Self-Help Guide</th>
<th align="center">Overcome the Depression Pro</th>
<th align="center">Positive Activity Jackpot</th>
<th align="center"><italic>Total</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Proven Efficacy</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Core Ingredients of CBT</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Education about depression</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Explanation of the model</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depression rating</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Monitoring cognitions</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Monitoring emotions</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Monitoring physical sensations</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Monitoring behaviors</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Conceptualization</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Cognitive techniques</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Behavioral techniques</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>Total score out of 20 (%)</italic></td>
<td align="center">2 (10)</td>
<td align="center">1 (5)</td>
<td align="center">3 (15)</td>
<td align="center">11 (55)</td>
<td align="center">0 (0)</td>
<td align="center">5 (25)</td>
<td align="center">2 (10)</td>
<td align="center">5 (25)</td>
<td align="center">3 (15)</td>
<td align="center">15 (75)</td>
<td align="center">4 (20)</td>
<td align="center">0 (0)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Core Ingredients of BA</bold></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Education about depression</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Explanation of the model</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depression rating</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Activity monitoring</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Activity monitoring: Pleasure rating</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Activity monitoring: Masteryrating</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Activity scheduling of pleasantbehaviors</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Activity scheduling of avoidance behaviors</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>Total score out of 16 (%)</italic></td>
<td align="center">3 (18.75)</td>
<td align="center">1 (6.25)</td>
<td align="center">3 (18.75)</td>
<td align="center">4 (25)</td>
<td align="center">3 (18.75)</td>
<td align="center">4 (25)</td>
<td align="center">2 (12.5)</td>
<td align="center">1 (6.25)</td>
<td align="center">1 (6.25)</td>
<td align="center">4 (25)</td>
<td align="center">3 (18.75)</td>
<td align="center">2 (12.5)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>The usability heuristic evaluation found that the median level of adherence with the heuristics was 83% (range = 42–98%). The apps associated with highest usability ratings were Mood Tools–Depression Aids, Activity Diary, and Depression on Cure–The Free 12 Week Course scoring 98%, 98%, and 92% respectively. The most frequent heuristic violations of these CBT/BA apps were: visibility of the system status, and consistency and standards. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0154248.t006">Table 6</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0154248.t006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t006</object-id>
<label>Table 6</label> <caption><title>Evaluation of the usability dimension.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0154248.t006g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t006" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Name</th>
<th align="center">Visibilityof system status</th>
<th align="center">Match between system and the real world</th>
<th align="center">User controland freedom</th>
<th align="center">Consistency and standards</th>
<th align="center">Error prevention</th>
<th align="center">Recognition rather than recall</th>
<th align="center">Flexibilityand efficiency of use</th>
<th align="center">Aestheticand minimalist design</th>
<th align="center">Help users recognize, diagnose, and recover from errors</th>
<th align="center">Help and document-ation</th>
<th align="left"><italic>Total score out of 50(%)</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depression Cure—The Free 12 Week Course</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">46 (92)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">iCounselor: Depression</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">30 (60)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MoodMaster Anti-Depression App</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">41 (82)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">eCBT Mood</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">35 (70)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Activity Diary</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">49 (98)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Anti- depression</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">44 (88)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Mood Tools–Depression Aids</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">49 (98)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Mood Sentry</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">21 (42)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depression</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">32 (64)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depression CBT Self-Help Guide</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">31 (62)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Overcome the Depression Pro</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">42 (84)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Positive Activity Jackpot</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">42 (84)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>Total</italic></td>
<td align="center">39</td>
<td align="center">57</td>
<td align="center">48</td>
<td align="center">39</td>
<td align="center">55</td>
<td align="center">43</td>
<td align="center">41</td>
<td align="center">42</td>
<td align="center">54</td>
<td align="center">44</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>Only the eCBT app and the Depression CBT Self-Help Guide app offer a privacy policy. The eCBTapp has a brief privacy policy that states that the information collected in the app is only accessed by the application on the device and they do not collect any information about the user or the use of the app. The Depression CBT Self-Help Guide app’s privacy policy applies to this app in particular, but also other products of its developer (other apps and its homepage). This policy is available on the developer’s homepage but is also available to users after they have downloaded the app. Its privacy policy indicates what information is collected and for what purpose, whether this information is shared with others but it does not address users control. Five out of the 12 apps (41.66%) provide important safety information during crisis.See <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0154248.t007">Table 7</xref> for details about what information is provided and how.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0154248.t007" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t007</object-id>
<label>Table 7</label> <caption><title>Evaluation of integration and infrastructure dimension.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0154248.t007g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.t007" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Name</th>
<th align="left">Do they have privacy policy?</th>
<th align="left">Scope of privacy policy</th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Transparency of privacy policy</th>
<th align="left">Do they deal with safety?</th>
<th align="left">How?</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">Type of information collected</th>
<th align="left">Rationale for collection</th>
<th align="left">Sharing of information</th>
<th align="left">User control</th>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depression Cure- the Free 12 Week Course</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">iCounselor: Depression</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MoodMaster- Anti Depression App</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">eCBT Mood</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">Single app</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t007fn001"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t007fn001"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">n/a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t007fn001"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="left">• If the user scores high on depression, they are encouraged to contact health care provider or crisis center (number is provided).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Activity Diary</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Anti-Depression</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MoodTools-Depression Aid</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="left">• Includes a safety plan feature, where user can input infomation about crisis warning signs, coping strategies, reasons to live, and add contacts to call.<break/>• There is also a “?” icon which gives the user the option to work with a therapist, allow user to visualize a safety plan video, and give them a direct link to call a help line.<break/>• There is a guide which goes through different stages from coping, to recovery, suicide prevention.<break/>• Static crisis tab with 4 different options; call 911, call helpline, and a map feature to either find urgent care or the nearest emergency department.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Mood Sentry</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depression</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="left">• Once user provides a high rating of depression, a safety screen with information appears.<break/>• Static tab for the same safety screen appears within the learning module.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depression CBT Self-Help Guide</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">This app plus other apps created by the developer, and the homepage</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Overcome the Depression Pro</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="left">• The user is encouraged to seek professional help if they score high on depression.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Positive Activity Jackpot</td>
<td align="center">✗</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">✓</td>
<td align="left">• In the license that user first sees upon enterting app, they make a brief statement about if user is in an emergency or life threatening situation to seek medical assistance or dial emergency number.<break/>• In the settings there is a statement that says “if at any point you feel suicidal please call crisis care hotline (number is provided).</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t007fn001"><p><sup>a</sup> All the information collected is stored on the device and can only be accessed by the user. Developer does not collect/store any information about the user or the use of the app.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>No relationship was found between the level of adherence of the app to the theoretical CBT or BA model and the level of adherence with the heuristics usability (r<sub>s</sub> = -0.45, p = 0.13 and r<sub>s</sub> = 0.30, p = 0.33, respectively). Also, no relationship was found between level of adherence of the app to the theoretical models and the indicators of popularity (range = r<sub>s</sub> = -0.02, p = 0.96 and r<sub>s</sub> = 0.57, p = 0.18), or between level of adherence of the app with the heuristic usability with the indicators of popularity (range = r<sub>s</sub> = 0.15, p = 0.68 and r<sub>s</sub> = 0.59, p = 0.07).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>While there are a large number of phone apps designed to assist those with depression available through the commercial market, few of these utilize a CBT or BA approach despite these being the gold standard of first line psychological treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref072">72</xref>]. The few apps that provide CBT or BA seem to be popular based on the number of downloads, with 4 out of 7 of the Android available apps achieving more than ten thousand downloads.</p>
<p>Chan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref016">16</xref>] have recently proposed a framework that can be used for patients and health care providers to evaluate existing mental health mobile apps and help them make informed choices about their use. Chan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref016">16</xref>] suggest evaluating apps on three broad dimensions: usefulness, usability, and integration/infrastructure. After evaluating the usefulness dimension of the CBT/BA apps taking into account the main usefulness criteria of ‘effectiveness’, we can see that there is no available information on effectiveness. The few available apps that offer CBT or BA have either not been tested or the results derived from these tests have not been reported in the scientific literature. This means that we do not have any direct evidence demonstrating the efficacy of these CBT/BA apps and consequently we do not have direct scientific proof to support their use. All the apps identified through searching the scientific literature were simply cited in reviews [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref014">14</xref>]; they were not evaluated in primary research studies. Although no data on the efficacy of these CBT/BA apps have been published, we need to acknowledge that evidence may exist outside scientific journals. Knowledge can be disseminated through grey literature. The lack of direct scientific evidence for these CBT/BA apps, however, becomes especially alarming after evaluating the validity and accuracy of the content of these apps from an expert’s point of view. Of those apps which do use CBT or BA, some apps may provide benefits by partially applying CBT or BA principles, but the majority do not come close to including the core ingredients of a CBT or BA program. The lack of fidelity to proven CBT or BA principles could hamper the efficacy of these programs.</p>
<p>When evaluating the usability dimension, we have seen that the usability of the available CBT/BA apps is highly variable and likely serves as a barrier to adoption and regular usage for those apps that violate a large number of heuristics. For instance, the Depression CBT Self-Help Guide app has the highest fidely to CBT models, but the low usability score could complicate its use. There is a danger that users of these available CBT/BA apps may interpret ineffectiveness as a treatment failure, when in fact, ineffectiveness may be the result of usability problems or the inappropriate application of the CBT or BA model.</p>
<p>On the one hand, there doesn’t appear to be a correlation between CBT/BA model adherence and usability, which means that a good application of the clinical theoretical CBT or BA knowledge when designing the app does not imply a good use of principles of usability, and/or vice versa. On the other hand, the degree to which the apps contain these core ingredients of the CBT and BA models does not appear to be correlated with the extent to which users like the app, the number of downloads, or the number of reviews for the app. Equally, the level of usability of the CBT/BA apps does not appear to be correlated with the extent to which users like the app, the number of downloads or the number of reviews for the app. This finding is not surprising; previous reviews have found no relationship between the quality of the apps and consumers reviews or ratings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref073">73</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref074">74</xref>]. Therefore, users should be careful when using the information available on the app download page to judge the app, since this information can be misleading.</p>
<p>When evaluating the integration and infrastructure dimension, we have seen that safety information is not always available in apps, and very rarely are users provided with a privacy policy. This lack of availability of privacy information seems to be an issue for mental health apps in general [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref021">21</xref>]. Research has shown that privacy is a concern for many health care professionals and patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref075">75</xref>] and this concern is a reason for them to decline the use information technology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref075">75</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref076">76</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref077">77</xref>] as part of their care.</p>
<p>We have identified through our systematic review four apps in English that offer CBT or BA treatment for depression and have been studied by researchers and published in scientific papers, the Behavioural Activation Scheduling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref050">50</xref>], the Get Happy Program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref040">40</xref>], CBT Mobilwork [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref065">65</xref>] and Mobilyze [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref045">45</xref>]. However, these four apps have not been included in our full analysis because they are not currently available for download by the public, at least from within Canada. The lack of empirically tested apps identified during this review is consistent with observations in other health fields [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref036">36</xref>] and raises concerns about relying on these tools to support treatment for depression. We therefore launch a call for scientists and/or app developers interested in the opportunities that mobile communication technology offers in terms of improving access to mental health care to test the existing best apps and determine from the outset how to best implement and sustain the apps over time given that technology is evolving rapidly. It is also important when designing new CBT/BA apps to try to integrate the core ingredients of these theoretical models, and to address the heuristics in order to optimize clinical benefits and make the app more usable. Finally, it is important that scientists and developers are more transparent about legal and regulatory aspects of the apps related to privacy issues (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref078">78</xref>]). Failure to effectively plan for sustainable dissemination of apps as well as the lack of consideration of legal aspects may present significant barriers for using apps.</p>
<p>This review is not without limitations. First, this review was limited to English downloadable apps in Canada and only looked at the two most popular platforms when exploring the commercial market. Different apps may be available on less prevalent platforms or in other languages and/or countries, and in fact we excluded apps developed and tested in the academic setting for these reasons[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref040">40</xref>]. Second, the evaluation of the CBT and BA apps was based on the opinion of one expert. Although expert opinion plays an important role when no research evidence exists, the use of an expert panel instead of only one expert could have increased the credibility of the conclusions. Finally, although it was not the primary goal of this review, the lack of common constructs, outcome measures, definitions and/or standards for tracking, state induction, diagnostic/screening, and education apps make cross-case comparison of these different types of self-help apps impossible.</p>
<p>In summary, given the prevalence of depression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref001">1</xref>] and the known effectiveness of CBT and BA in addressing this mental health condition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0154248.ref007">7</xref>], a mobile app based on clinical best practice, that meets the most basic usability standards, that is evaluated scientifically, has a privacy policy, and deals with safety matters has the potential to remove barriers to care and alleviate suffering for a large number of people with depression at a modest cost. Therefore, efforts towards achieving this are necessary.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0154248.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 PRISMA Checklist</label>
<caption>
<title>PRISMA 2009 Checklist.</title>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0154248.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0154248.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Appendix</label>
<caption>
<title>Search strategy used for Pubmed.</title>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname> <given-names>WT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Demler</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname> <given-names>EE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prevalence, severity, and comorbidity of 12-month DSM-IV disorders in the National Comorbidity Survey Replication</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>617</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15939839</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avenevoli</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merikangas</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mood disorders in children and adolescents: an epidemiologic perspective</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1002</fpage>–<lpage>1014</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11430842</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mathers C, Boerma T, Ma Fa D. The Global Burden of Disease: 2004 Update. 2008. Available:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/healthinfo/global_burden_disease/GBD_report_2004update_full.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.who.int/healthinfo/global_burden_disease/GBD_report_2004update_full.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>. <article-title>The costs of depression</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Clin North Am</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.psc.2011.11.005" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.psc.2011.11.005</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22370487</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">National Collaborating Centre for Mental Health. Depression: The treatment and management of depression in adults. 2010. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/cg90/evidence/cg90-depression-in-adults-full-guidance2" xlink:type="simple">https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/cg90/evidence/cg90-depression-in-adults-full-guidance2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuijpers</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Straten</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warmerdam</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Behavioral activation treatments of depression: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Clin Psychol Rev</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>318</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17184887</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beck</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name>. <article-title>The empirical status of cognitive-behavioral therapy: A review of meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>Clin Psychol Rev</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199119</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van't Hof</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuijpers</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Self-help and Internet-guided interventions in depression and anxiety disorders: a systematic review of meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>CNS Spectr</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ly</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Truschel</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jarl</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusson</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Windahl</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>., <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Behavioural activation versus mindfulness-based guided self-help treatment administered through a smartphone application: A randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e003440</fpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003440" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003440</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24413342</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scogin</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Napoli</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Presnell</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>A self-help behavioral activation treatment for geriatric depressive symptoms</article-title>. <source>Aging Ment Health</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/13607863.2011.651435" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/13607863.2011.651435</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22304676</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Irvine M. Report: More youth use smartphones as route to Web. 2013 March 13 [cited 6 September, 2014] The Big Story. [Internet]. Chicago: AP News-. [about 4 screens]. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bigstory.ap.org/article/report-more-youth-use-smartphones-route-web" xlink:type="simple">http://bigstory.ap.org/article/report-more-youth-use-smartphones-route-web</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">International Data Corporation. Smartphones Expected to Grow 32.7% in 2013 Fueled By Declining Prices and Strong Emerging Market Demand, According to IDC. 2013 June 4 [cited 6 September, 2014] IDC. [Internet]. Massachusetts: Business Wire-. [about 3 screens]. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.idc.com/getdoc.jsp?containerId=prUS24143513" xlink:type="simple">http://www.idc.com/getdoc.jsp?containerId=prUS24143513</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Michael S. Application of smartphone technology in the management and treatment of mental illnesses. MPH. Thesis, University of Pittsburgh. 2011. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://d-scholarship.pitt.edu/6783/" xlink:type="simple">http://d-scholarship.pitt.edu/6783/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levitan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton-Page</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>,<name name-style="western"><surname>Jadad</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Finding a depression App: A review and content analysis of the depression app marketplace</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e16</fpage></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torous</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Current research trends in the use of smartphone applications for mood disorders</article-title>. <source>Internet Interv</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torous</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hinton</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yellowlees</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Towards a framework for evaluating mobile mental health apps</article-title>. <source>Telemed J E Health</source> <year>2015</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1038</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landis</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname> <given-names>GG</given-names></name>. <article-title>The measurement of observer agreement for categorical data</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>. <year>1977</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">843571</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanter</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manos</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baruch</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Busch</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Rusch</surname> <given-names>LC</given-names></name>. <article-title>What is behavioral activation? A review of the empirical literature</article-title>. <source>Clin Psychol Rev</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>608</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20677369</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beck</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name>. <article-title>The current state of cognitive therapy: a 40-year retrospective</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>953</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16143727</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mack</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Usability inspection methods: Heuristic evaluation</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>; <year>1994</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunyaev</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dehling</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mandl</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Availability and quality of mobile mental health app privacy policies</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>e1</issue>):<fpage>e28</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/amiajnl-2013-002605" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/amiajnl-2013-002605</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25147247</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torous</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staples</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shanahan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peck</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keshavan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Utilizing a Personal Smartphone Custom App to Assess the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) Depressive Symptoms in Patients With Major Depressive Disorder</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): p. <fpage>e8</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2196/mental.3889" xlink:type="simple">10.2196/mental.3889</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Homes</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolters</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname> <given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <collab>SPIRIT (Stress in Pregnancy: Improving Results with Interative Technology) Group</collab>. <article-title>Participatory design of ehealth solutions for women from vulnerable populations with perinatal depression</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>. pii. ocv109. <year>2015</year>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jamia/ocv109" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/jamia/ocv109</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juengst</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pulantara</surname> <given-names>IW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCue</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whyte</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dicianno</surname> <given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Pilot feasibility of an mHealth system for conducting ecological momentary assessment of mood-related symptoms following traumatic brain injury</article-title>. <source>Brain Inj. 2015</source>; <volume>29</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): p. <fpage>1351</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3109/02699052.2015.1045031" xlink:type="simple">10.3109/02699052.2015.1045031</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roepke</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jafee</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riffle</surname> <given-names>OM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGonigal</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broome</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mawell</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Randomized Controlled Trial of SuperBetter, a Smartphone-Based/Internet-Based Self-Help Tool to Reduce Depressive Symptoms</article-title>. <source>Games Health J</source>. <article-title>2015</article-title>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): p. <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/g4h.2014.0046" xlink:type="simple">10.1089/g4h.2014.0046</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26182069</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horikoshi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimodera</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akechi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miki</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>.<article-title>Adding smartphone-based cognitive-behavior therapy to pharmacotherapy for major depression (FLATT project): study protocol for a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Trials</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>293</fpage>. p. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s13063-015-0805-z" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/s13063-015-0805-z</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26149441</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aboujaoude</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salame</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naim</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Telemental health: A status update</article-title>. <source>World Psychiatry</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): p. <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/wps.20218" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/wps.20218</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26043340</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ly</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Topooco</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cederlund</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bergström</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molander</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>,<etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Smartphone-Supported versus Full Behavioural Activation for Depression: A Randomised Controlled Trial</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): p. <fpage>e0126559</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0126559" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0126559</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26010890</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bitsch</surname> <given-names>JÁ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ix</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrer-Cheng</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wehrle</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>.<article-title>Psychologist in a pocket: towards depression screening on mobile phones</article-title>. <source>Stud Health Technol Inform</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>211</volume>: p. <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25980862</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiménez-Serrano</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tortajada</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>García-Gómez</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>.<article-title>A Mobile Health Application to Predict Postpartum Depression Based on Machine Learning</article-title>. <source>Telemed J E Health</source>. <volume>21</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): p. <fpage>567</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/tmj.2014.0113" xlink:type="simple">10.1089/tmj.2014.0113</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25734829</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bush</surname> <given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ouellette</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kinn</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>.<article-title>Utility of the T2 Mood Tracker mobile application among army warrior transition unit service members</article-title>. <source>Mil Med</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>179</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): p. <fpage>1453</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7205/MILMED-D-14-00271" xlink:type="simple">10.7205/MILMED-D-14-00271</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25469967</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>BinDhim</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaman</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trevena</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basyouni</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pont</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alhawassi</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>.<article-title>Depression screening via a smartphone app: cross-country user characteristics and feasibility</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): p. <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/amiajnl-2014-002840" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/amiajnl-2014-002840</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25326599</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Proudfoot</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birch</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whitton</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manicavasagar</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hadzi-Pavlovic</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of mental health self-efficacy on outcomes of a mobile phone and web intervention for mild-to-moderate depression, anxiety and stress: secondary analysis of a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>.(doi): p. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s12888-014-0272-1" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/s12888-014-0272-1</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25252853</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanrahan</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>.<article-title>Addressing Cultural Contexts in the Management of Stress via Narrative and Mobile Technology</article-title>. <source>Stud Health Technol Inform</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>199</volume>: p. <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24875715</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fogger</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGuinness</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D'Alessandro</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name>.<article-title>Mobile apps for psychiatric nurses</article-title>. <source>J Psychosoc Nurs Ment Health Serv</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>52</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): p. <fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3928/02793695-20131126-07" xlink:type="simple">10.3928/02793695-20131126-07</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24305909</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donker</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petrie</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Proudfoot</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birch</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Smartphones for smarter delivery of mental health programs: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): p. <fpage>e247</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2196/jmir.2791" xlink:type="simple">10.2196/jmir.2791</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24240579</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Proudfoot</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birch</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whitton</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manicavasagar</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>.<article-title>Impact of a mobile phone and web program on symptom and functional outcomes for people with mild-to-moderate depression, anxiety and stress: a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>312</fpage>. p. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-244X-13-312" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-244X-13-312</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24237617</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffer</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kreindler</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reis</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levitt</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Use of mental health telemetry to enhance identification and predictive value of early changes during augmentation treatment of major depression</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychopharmacol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): p. <fpage>775</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/JCP.0b013e31829e8359" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/JCP.0b013e31829e8359</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24100787</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez-Pérez</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de la Torre-Díez</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>López-Coronado</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mobile health applications for the most prevalent conditions by the World Health Organization: review and analysis</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): p. <fpage>e120</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2196/jmir.2600" xlink:type="simple">10.2196/jmir.2600</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23770578</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mackenzie</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Griskaitis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mewton</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>.<article-title>CBT for depression: a pilot RCT comparing mobile phone vs. computer</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>.(doi): p. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-244X-13-49" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-244X-13-49</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23391304</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kauer</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crooke</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khor</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hearps</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jorm</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name>,<etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Self-monitoring using mobile phones in the early stages of adolescent depression: randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): p. <fpage>e67</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2196/jmir.1858" xlink:type="simple">10.2196/jmir.1858</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22732135</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ly</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carlbring</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Behavioral activation-based guided self-help treatment administered through a smartphone application: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Trials</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>.(doi): p. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1745-6215-13-62" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1745-6215-13-62</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kauer</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hearps</surname> <given-names>SJC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crooke</surname> <given-names>AHD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khor</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanci</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A mobile phone application for the assessment and management of youth mental health problems in primary care: a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Fam Pract</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>.(doi): p. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2296-12-131" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2296-12-131</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Proudfoot</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wee</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlovic</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manicavasagar</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mobile mental health: review of the emerging field and proof of concept study</article-title>. <source>J Ment Health. 2011</source>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): p. <fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3109/09638237.2011.608746" xlink:type="simple">10.3109/09638237.2011.608746</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Begale</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duffecy</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gergle</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karr</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giangrande</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohr</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Harnessing context sensing to develop a mobile intervention for depression</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): p. <fpage>e55</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2196/jmir.1838" xlink:type="simple">10.2196/jmir.1838</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21840837</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Giridher T, Wasilewska A, Wong, JL, Rekhi KS. Global mobile applications for monitoring health. in Computer Science and Information Technology (IMCSIT), Proceedings of the 2010 International Multiconference on.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parish</surname> <given-names>C.</given-names></name><article-title>Mental Health Library apps</article-title>. <source>Nursing standard (Royal College of Nursing (Great Britain)</source>: <year>1987</year>). <volume>29</volume>(<issue>31</issue>): p. <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karasouli</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assessing the evidence for e-Resources for mental health self-management: A Systematic literature review</article-title>. <source>JMIR mental health</source>. <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): p. <fpage>e3</fpage>–e3. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2196/mental.3708" xlink:type="simple">10.2196/mental.3708</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26543903</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wan J, Hu B, Moore P, Ashford R. Intelligent mobile computing to assist in the treatment of depression. 2008 3rd International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Applications, Vols 1 and 2. 2008. 652–657.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Both F, Cuijpers P, Hoogendoorn M, Klein M. Towards fully automated psychotherapy for adults-BAS-Behavioral Activation Scheduling via web and mobile phone. Healthinf 2010: Proceedings of the Third International Conference on Health Informatics, ed. A. Fred, J. Filipe, and H. Gamboa. 375–380.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Proudfoot</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>.<article-title>The future is in our hands: The role of mobile phones in the prevention and management of mental disorders</article-title>. <source>Australian N Z J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>47</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): p. <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kauer</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hearps</surname> <given-names>SJC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crooke</surname> <given-names>AHD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khor</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanci</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patton</surname> <given-names>GC</given-names></name>. <article-title>A mobile phone application for the assessment and management of youth mental health problems in primary care: health service outcomes from a randomised controlled trial of mobiletype</article-title>. <source>BMC family practice</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>14</issue>): <fpage>84</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2296-14-84" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2296-14-84</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuen</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goetter</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herbert</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Acierno</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruggiero</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>mHealth: A Mechanism to Deliver More Accessible, More Effective Mental Health Care</article-title>. <source>Clinical Psychol &amp; Psychother</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): p. <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>436</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes-Portillo</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mufson</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenhill</surname> <given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname> <given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tarlow</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>,<name name-style="western"><surname>Rynn</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Web-based interventions for youth internalizing problems</article-title>: <source>A Systematic Review. Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>53</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): p. <fpage>1254</fpage>–<lpage>1270</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jaac.2014.09.005" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jaac.2014.09.005</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25457924</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gravenhorst</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muaremi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bardram</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grunerbl</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayora</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wurzer</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Mobile phones as medical devices in mental disorder treatment: an overview</article-title>. <source>Personal and Ubiquitous Computing</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): p. <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Zeev</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schueller</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Begale</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duffecy</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kane</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohr</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Strategies for mHealth Research: Lessons from 3 Mobile Intervention Studies</article-title>. <source>Adm Policy Ment Health</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): p. <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10488-014-0556-2" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10488-014-0556-2</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24824311</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilera</surname> <given-names>A.</given-names></name> <article-title>Digital technology and mental health interventions:Opportunities and challenges</article-title>. <source>Arbor</source>. <volume>20154191</volume>(<issue>771</issue>): <fpage>a210</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3989/arbor.2015.771n1012" xlink:type="simple">10.3989/arbor.2015.771n1012</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clough BA</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casey</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>. <article-title>The smart therapist: A look to the future of smartphones and mHealth technologies in psychotherapy</article-title>. <source>Professional Psychology-Research and Practice</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>46</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): p. <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torous</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>,<name name-style="western"><surname>Staples</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onnela</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Realizing the Potential of Mobile Mental Health: New Methods for New Data in Psychiatry</article-title>. <source>Curr Psychiatry Rep</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>602</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11920-015-0602-0" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11920-015-0602-0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26073363</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeb</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karr</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schueller</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corden</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kording</surname> <given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohr</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mobile phone sensor correlates of depressive symptom severity in daily-life behavior: An exploratory study</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e175</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2196/jmir.4273" xlink:type="simple">10.2196/jmir.4273</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26180009</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warmerdam</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riper</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van den Ven</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ricardo Henriques</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>.<article-title>Innovative ICT solutions to improve treatment outcomes for depression: The ICT4Depression project</article-title>. <source>Stud Health Technol Inform</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>181</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22954884</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rozbroj</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyons</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pitts</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>.<article-title>Assessing the applicability of e-therapies for depression, anxiety, and other mood disorders among lesbians and gay men: Analysis of 24 web- and mobile phone-based self-help interventions</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>16</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): p. <fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Zeev</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scherer</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Next-generation psychiatric assessment: Using smartphone sensors to monitor behavior and mental health</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Rehabil J</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): p. <fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/prj0000130" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/prj0000130</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25844912</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kauer</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crooke</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khor</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patton</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jorm</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Emotional self-awareness: Preliminary analyses of a RCT using a cellular phone self-monitoring program (mobiletype) to decrease early symptoms of depression</article-title>. <source>Journal of Adolescent Health</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>48</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): p. <fpage>S91</fpage>–<lpage>S92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Callan</surname> <given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>., <article-title>CBT mobilework: A technological solution to improve depression outcomes</article-title>. <source>Clinical and Translational Science</source>. <volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): p. <fpage>120</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murugan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mobile phone based supportive patient care</article-title>. <source>Indian Journal of Psychiatry</source>. <volume>55</volume>: p. <fpage>S72</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijk</surname> <given-names>SV</given-names></name>,<name name-style="western"><surname>Voshaar</surname> <given-names>RO</given-names></name>. <article-title>Black-Box: Snapshots of daily life time series analysis in a depressed elderly patient</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Geriatric Psychiatry</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): p. <fpage>S57</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmi</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zohar</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Secondary prevention in depression, bipolar and addiction via mobile phone</article-title>. <source>European Neuropsychopharmacology</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>24</volume>: p. <fpage>S734</fpage>–<lpage>S735</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowman</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neale</surname> <given-names>NV</given-names></name>. <article-title>Focus on clinical practice: Improving the quality of care</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Board of Family Medicine</source>. <volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): p. <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>265</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3122/jabfm.2012.03.120068" xlink:type="simple">10.3122/jabfm.2012.03.120068</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22570385</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javelot</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spadazzi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gentili</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kosel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertschy</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Telemonitoring with respect to mood disorders and information and communication technologies: Overview and presentation of the PSYCHE project</article-title>. <source>BioMed Research International</source> Article ID <volume>104658</volume>, 12 pages <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2014/104658" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2014/104658</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ly</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janni</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wrede</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sedem</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donker</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carlbring</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Experiences of a guided smartphone-based behavioral activation therapy for depression: A qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Internet Interventions</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): p. <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab>National Institute for Clinical Excellence</collab>. <article-title>Depression: management of depression in primary and secondary care</article-title>. <source>Clinical Guideline</source> <volume>23</volume>. <year>2004</year>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scamfyc.org/documentos/depresion%20NICE.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.scamfyc.org/documentos/depresion%20NICE.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 16 June 2015)</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>BinDhim</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name>. <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkey</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <name name-style="western"><surname>Trevena</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>A systematic review of quality assessment methods for smartphone health apps</article-title>. <year>2015</year> <month>Feb</month>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/tmj.2014.0088" xlink:type="simple">10.1089/tmj.2014.0088</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25469795</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kuehnhausen M, Frost VS. Trusting smartphone apps? To install or not to install, that is the question. Cognitive Methods in Situation Awareness and Decision Support; IEEE International Multi-Disciplinary Conference; 2013 Feb 25–28; San Diego, CA, USA. IEEE; 2013. pp. 30–37.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitropoulos</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffler</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Posnack</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Public attitudes in health information exchange: Perceived benefits and concerns</article-title>. <source>Am J Manag Care</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>12</issue> Spec No.):<fpage>SP111</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22216769</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunnebeil</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sunyaev</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blohm</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leimeister</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kromar</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Determinants of physicians technology acceptance for e-health in ambulatory care</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Inform</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>81</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>746</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2012.02.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2012.02.002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22397989</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agaku</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adisa</surname> <given-names>AO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayo-Yusuf</surname> <given-names>OA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly</surname> <given-names>GN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Concern about security and privacy, and perceived control over collection and use of health information are related to withholding of health information from healthcare providers</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>.<year>2014</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>374</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/amiajnl-2013-002079" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/amiajnl-2013-002079</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23975624</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0154248.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">U.S. Food and Drug Administration. Guidance for industry and food and drug administration staff- mobile medical applications. 2013. Available:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/downloads/MedicalDevices/…/UCM263366.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.fda.gov/downloads/MedicalDevices/…/UCM263366.pdf</ext-link> on.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>