<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136667</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-14593</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Comparing Visually Assessed BI-RADS Breast Density and Automated Volumetric Breast Density Software: A Cross-Sectional Study in a Breast Cancer Screening Setting</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Comparing BI-RADS Breast Density and Volumetric Density</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>van der Waal</surname>
<given-names>Daniëlle</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>den Heeten</surname>
<given-names>Gerard J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Pijnappel</surname>
<given-names>Ruud M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff004" ref-type="aff"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Schuur</surname>
<given-names>Klaas H.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Timmers</surname>
<given-names>Johanna M. H.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Verbeek</surname>
<given-names>André L. M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Broeders</surname>
<given-names>Mireille J. M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Radboud university medical center, Radboud Institute for Health Sciences, Nijmegen, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Dutch Reference Centre for Screening, Nijmegen, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Radiology, Academic Medical Centre, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Department of Radiology, University Medical Center Utrecht, Utrecht, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Paci</surname>
<given-names>Eugenio</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>ISPO, ITALY</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>GJ den Heeten is a former member of the medical advisory board of Mātakina, founder of sigmascreening (spin-off company Academic Medical Centre Amsterdam), and consultant of Philips ICT. This does not alter the authors' adherence to PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials. No other authors have any competing interests.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: DW MB JT GH AV. Performed the experiments: DW JT GH KS RP. Analyzed the data: DW MB GH AV. Wrote the paper: DW MB AV JT GH KS RP.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">Danielle.vanderWaal@radboudumc.nl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>3</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<elocation-id>e0136667</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>17</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>6</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>van der Waal et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The objective of this study is to compare different methods for measuring breast density, both visual assessments and automated volumetric density, in a breast cancer screening setting. These measures could potentially be implemented in future screening programmes, in the context of personalised screening or screening evaluation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>Digital mammographic exams (N = 992) of women participating in the Dutch breast cancer screening programme (age 50–75y) in 2013 were included. Breast density was measured in three different ways: BI-RADS density (5<sup>th</sup> edition) and with two commercially available automated software programs (Quantra and Volpara volumetric density). BI-RADS density (ordinal scale) was assessed by three radiologists. Quantra (v1.3) and Volpara (v1.5.0) provide continuous estimates. Different comparison methods were used, including Bland-Altman plots and correlation coefficients (e.g., intraclass correlation coefficient [ICC]).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Based on the BI-RADS classification, 40.8% of the women had ‘heterogeneously or extremely dense’ breasts. The median volumetric percent density was 12.1% (IQR: 9.6–16.5) for Quantra, which was higher than the Volpara estimate (median 6.6%, IQR: 4.4–10.9). The mean difference between Quantra and Volpara was 5.19% (95% CI: 5.04–5.34) (ICC: 0.64). There was a clear increase in volumetric percent dense volume as BI-RADS density increased. The highest accuracy for predicting the presence of BI-RADS c+d (heterogeneously or extremely dense) was observed with a cut-off value of 8.0% for Volpara and 13.8% for Quantra.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Although there was no perfect agreement, there appeared to be a strong association between all three measures. Both volumetric density measures seem to be usable in breast cancer screening programmes, provided that the required data flow can be realized.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="1"/>
<table-count count="5"/>
<page-count count="15"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>Due to ethical and legal restrictions, data are available upon request. Interested researchers may submit request for data to the Corresponding Author, Daniëlle van der Waal, <email xlink:type="simple">Danielle.vanderWaal@radboudumc.nl</email>.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Fibroglandular breast tissue, which is referred to as dense tissue, is known to mask breast carcinomas on mammograms [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0136667.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In addition to being a very strong independent breast cancer risk factor [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], high mammographic density is thus also associated with a decreased sensitivity of mammographic screening [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0136667.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Based on these associations, breast density could potentially be an important factor in breast cancer risk prediction and evaluation of breast cancer screening programmes. It might even become more important if considered for personalised screening [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Evidence on alternative screening regimens for population-based organized screening programmes is still limited, but additional screening modalities for women with a high breast density are extensively studied. Mammographic density can, however, only be used for evaluation or risk-stratified screening when it is assessed in an objective and reproducible manner.</p>
<p>Wolfe proposed a breast pattern scale in 1976 [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. This led to the introduction of many other classifications in the following years, such as the Tabár scale [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and the Breast Imaging Reporting and Data System (BI-RADS) density scale [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The latter is still used in breast cancer screening in the USA. A major drawback of these methods is the intra- and inter-rater variability [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. More quantitative measures were therefore developed, with the area-based threshold software Cumulus ultimately becoming the standard method for breast density assessment in scientific research. Cumulus density values are, however, still subject to some measurement variability, and the use of the software within nationwide screening programmes is too time-consuming [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Furthermore, the introduction of digital mammography opened up a range of possibilities regarding automated methods that no longer assess dense area but dense volume. Dense volume, which takes breast thickness into account, is expected to be a more ‘biologically relevant’ measure [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0136667.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The commercial software programs Quantra and Volpara are now both commonly used, yet data on associations between these different methods is still scarce [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p>
<p>Breast density is not structurally assessed at screening examinations in the Netherlands. BI-RADS density is only recorded in the clinical setting. The Breast Density Inform Law in the USA [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] did lead to parliamentary questions in the Netherlands on the potential introduction of breast density measurements. With this increasing interest in breast density, it is important to find ways to obtain and report information on breast density of women participating in screening [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. We thus have to learn more about the available methods. There is currently no consensus on what method to use for measuring breast density in the context of a screening programme. The objective of this study was therefore to compare different methods to measure breast density in the Dutch screening setting. The methods included here are BI-RADS density (visually assessed) and two volumetric software programs (Quantra and Volpara).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Setting</title>
<p>In the Netherlands, women ages 50–75 years are invited to participate in breast cancer screening every two years. We included 1000 mammographic examinations of participants who were screened at the Nijmegen screening unit in 2013. The dataset consists of multiple small sets of consecutive exams. The dates of retrieval were chosen at random, and we therefore believe that the dataset as a whole can be seen as a random sample of the Nijmegen screening population. Both a mediolateral oblique (MLO) and a craniocaudal (CC) view were obtained per breast. In five participants, only the left (N = 3) or the right (N = 2) views were available. Five examinations were excluded because the women had breast prostheses, which would distort the automated breast density measurements. In addition, three exams could not be read by the volumetric breast density software. This resulted in a dataset of 992 mammograms.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Ethics statement</title>
<p>According to the Dutch law, medical ethics approval is not needed for this type of study, with no extra burden for participants and anonymized data. Written informed consent was not required for this study because the data were obtained in the context of an agreement between the regional screening organisations and the Dutch Reference Centre for Screening. Women automatically consent to the use of their data for scientific purposes by participating in screening. The screening organisations are responsible for data delivery in accordance with privacy regulations, particularly regarding anonymizing data and potentially removing data of participants who objected to the exchange of personal data with specific organisations (opt-out procedure).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Breast density measurements</title>
<p>The Dutch screening programme uses Full-Field Digital Mammography (FFDM). All exams in this study were performed on the same Hologic Selenia system (Bedford, USA). Breast density was measured in three different ways: BI-RADS density (visually assessed by radiologists), Quantra volumetric density (automated software), and Volpara volumetric density (automated software). The R2 Quantra Volumetric Assessment software (version 1.3) was integrated in the Cenova DICOM server (version 2.1; Hologic, Bedford, USA). Version 1.5.0 of the Volpara Algorithm (Volpara Imaging Software 1.5.11; Mātakina, Wellington, New Zealand) was used.</p>
<p>BI-RADS breast density was assessed by three experienced screening radiologists. An initial pilot was performed where the radiologists scored the first 250 mammograms (from the original dataset of 1000 mammograms), which was concluded with a consensus meeting to ensure that the radiologists were applying the scale in a similar way. The ACR guidelines were discussed during the meeting, and discrepancies in the pilot scores were addressed. The consensus meeting had a favourable effect on the agreement between the radiologists. The scores before the consensus meeting were not included in our main analyses. Instead, the mammograms were scored again by the radiologists (individually) several weeks after the consensus meeting.</p>
<p>The overall scores were based on the agreement between at least two of the three radiologists. In the rare cases that all three radiologists disagreed (n = 9), the middle score was used. The mammograms were scored according to the newest (5<sup>th</sup> edition, American College of Radiology) BI-RADS density classification [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In contrast to previous versions of the BI-RADS density classification, the qualitative categories are not matched to area-based density percentages in the new edition. The BI-RADS density categories in the 5<sup>th</sup> edition are: (a) fatty, (b) scattered density, (c) heterogeneously dense, and (d) extremely dense [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. A subset of 250 mammograms was scored twice by each radiologist to assess intra-observer variability. This was a different subset (mammogram 251–500) than the subset that was used in the pilot session. All assessments were performed on processed images at a review workstation. The radiologists were blinded to their previous scores and scores of others.</p>
<p>Quantra and Volpara are fully automated software programs that both assess the volumetric breast density on ‘for processing’ (raw) image data [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0136667.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0136667.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The X-rays are attenuated, as a result of photon absorption and scattering, in varying degrees as they pass through the different tissues. Estimates of fibroglandular tissue volume (absolute dense volume, in cm<sup>3</sup>) are based on the measured X-ray attenuation per pixel. Dividing the fibroglandular tissue volume by the total breast volume gives an estimate of the percentage volumetric breast density (percent dense volume). Volpara has developed an additional measure of breast density, namely the Volpara Density Grade (VDG). The VDG is based on percent dense volume, which is divided as follows: 0.0–4.5% (VDG1), 4.5–7.5% (VDG2), 7.5–15.5% (VDG3), and ≥15.5% (VDG4). The categories are based on agreement with the BI-RADS density scale.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p>We present different agreement and reliability measurements to compare the density measurements [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Reliability refers to the ability to differentiate between women with a different density level [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Agreement, on the other hand, refers to the degree of similarity between two measurements. When two raters, for example, give different density values, the agreement between these measurements will be poor. Reliability can, however, still be substantial when the raters give the same women relatively low or high density scores. Agreement depends on measurement error, whereas with reliability measures the measurement error is related to the between-subject variability [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p>
<p>Weighted kappa scores (κ<sub>w</sub>; Fleiss-Cohen, quadratic weights) with corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CI) were used to assess the intra- and inter-rater reliability of the BI-RADS density scores [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The kappa scores were also compared to the categories originally defined by Landis and Koch [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and slightly reworded by Altman [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]: poor (&lt;0.20), fair (0.21–0.40), moderate (0.41–0.60), good (0.61–0.80), and very good (&gt;0.80) reliability. In addition, we present the overall proportions of agreement (absolute agreement). This is the proportion of the scores that were exactly the same for two ratings.</p>
<p>The volumetric breast density estimates were compared to the BI-RADS classification by determining the median and the inter-quartile ranges (IQR) according to BI-RADS category for each volumetric density measure. We did not define a golden standard for breast density in our study. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analyses were, however, used to assess the ability of both volumetric software programs to differentiate between women with a high breast density (BI-RADS c+d) and women with a low breast density (BI-RADS a+b) based on the visual BI-RADS classification. This was done to enable comparisons with the literature. Chosen cut-off values were based on the highest accuracy, which we calculated using the following formula:
<disp-formula id="pone.0136667.e001">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0136667.e001g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.e001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M1" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
</disp-formula>
In this study, ‘true-positives’ are women with a breast density of BI-RADS c+d who are classified as having a high breast density based on the volumetric estimates. ‘True-negatives’, on the other hand, refers to women with a BI-RADS a+b density who also have a low volumetric density.</p>
<p>The volumetric breast density measures were also compared to each other. Both Pearson’s correlation coefficients (r), based on log-transformed values (ln[x+1]), and two-way mixed intraclass correlation coefficients (ICC) were calculated for comparison of the different volumetric density measures. The following formula was used to calculate the ICC [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]:
<disp-formula id="pone.0136667.e002">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0136667.e002g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.e002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M2" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
</disp-formula></p>
<p><inline-formula id="pone.0136667.e003"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0136667.e003g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.e003" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> Variance as a result of differences between participants</p>
<p><inline-formula id="pone.0136667.e004"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0136667.e004g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.e004" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M4" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> Variance as a result of differences between software programs</p>
<p><inline-formula id="pone.0136667.e005"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0136667.e005g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.e005" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>res</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> Residual variance</p>
<p>An ICC of +1.0 indicates that the measures give perfectly matching scores, with ICC values &gt;0.7 often being considered as ‘good’ [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0136667.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. However, this cut-off point is rather arbitrary, and some have argued that the ICC should be at least 0.9 when measures have to be used interchangeably in clinical practice [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Confidence intervals were obtained by bootstrapping.</p>
<p>Finally, Bland-Altman plots are presented as agreement measures. The Bland-Altman plot consists of differences between two measurements on the y-axis and the mean of the two methods on the x-axis. Limits of agreement can be calculated by multiplying the standard deviation (σ) of the differences with 1.96 (+/-1.96σ). This is based on the assumptions that: (a) the variation in differences is similar across the range of values for the mean, and (b) the differences follow a normal distribution. The original (untransformed) differences were used for the Bland-Altman analyses. The observed difference between Quantra and Volpara is expected to be in between the limits of agreement in 95% of (future) measurements. Bias is defined as the mean difference between the two methods. The standard error of the bias is calculated as:
<disp-formula id="pone.0136667.e006">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0136667.e006g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.e006" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M6" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
</disp-formula>
Age was the only other breast cancer risk factor available in this study population. As a descriptive analysis, the association between age and breast density was assessed by calculating proportions (BI-RADS density) and medians (Quantra and Volpara estimates) for each age group.</p>
<p>All statistical analyses were performed using SAS (version 9.2, SAS Institute), apart from the ICC calculations that were performed with SPSS (version 20, SPSS). Figures were made with GraphPad Prism (version 5.03, GraphPad Software). Two-sided p-values smaller than 0.05 were considered to be statistically significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>BI-RADS</title>
<p><xref rid="pone.0136667.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the BI-RADS density scores, as assessed by the three radiologists. Overall, 11.2% (n = 111) of the women were categorized as having ‘extremely dense’ breasts and 29.6% (n = 294) had a ‘heterogeneously dense’ breast pattern. Measures of intra-rater agreement and reliability for the BI-RADS density scores are presented in <xref rid="pone.0136667.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> as well. The κ<sub>w</sub> ranged from 0.82 (95% CI: 0.79–0.86) to 0.87 (95% CI: 0.83–0.91). Based on the Landis and Koch guidelines (reworded by Altman), the intra-rater reliability could thus be seen as ‘very good’. The intra-rater agreement ranged from 62.8% (n = 157) to 84.8% (n = 212) (<xref rid="pone.0136667.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), with a mean agreement of 75.3%. When the BI-RADS scale was dichotomized (a+b vs. c+d), the proportions of agreement were larger (range %: 86.4–95.6, range n: 216–239). Only the first observer had paired scores that differed more than one category (n = 1).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0136667.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>BI-RADS density scores: intra-rater agreement and reliability (n = 992).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0136667.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% (N)<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BI-RADS density</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rater 1</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rater 2</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rater 3</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5 (203)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1 (130)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0 (218)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8 (177)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.0 (377)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.9 (485)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6 (323)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3 (410)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.3 (291)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5 (322)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5 (273)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.6 (294)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2 (121)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (55)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9 (178)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 (111)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Intra-rater statistics</bold><xref rid="t001fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% agreement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.4 (196)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.8 (212)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.8 (157)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% agreement (a+b vs. c+d)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.4 (221)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.6 (239)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.4 (216)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ᴋ<sub>w</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.83–0.91)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.80–0.89)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.79–0.86)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>ᴋ<sub>w</sub> = weighted kappa scores (Fleiss-Cohen, quadratic weights)</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> With the exception of the last row, which consists of kappa values with 95% confidence intervals.</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn003"><p><sup>b</sup> The overall classification is based on the agreement between all three radiologists. The three radiologists all agreed in 570 of the cases. The other values were based on at least two radiologists agreeing (n = 413) or the middle value (n = 9).</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn004"><p><sup>c</sup> The % agreement and the κ<sub>w</sub> values were based on a subset (n = 250) that was scored twice by each radiologist.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>All three radiologists agreed in 570 out of 992 (57.5%) assessments. <xref rid="pone.0136667.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the inter-rater agreement and reliability for the BI-RADS density scores. The mean proportion of agreement for the pair-wise comparisons was 71.3% (range %: 67.6–74.3, range n: 671–737). The proportions were even higher when the measure was dichotomized (range %: 89.0–90.2, range n: 883–895). The κ<sub>w</sub> of the inter-rater comparisons ranged from 0.80 to 0.84, which corresponds to ‘good’ or ‘very good’ reliability. In nine cases, the radiologists all scored differently. The number of discordant pairs with a difference of more than one category was limited (n = 8 for rater 1 vs. 2, n = 8 for rater 1 vs. 3, and n = 2 for rater 2 vs. 3).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0136667.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>BI-RADS density scores: inter-rater agreement and reliability (n = 992).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0136667.t002g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% (N)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ᴋ<sub>w</sub> (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% agreement</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% agreement (a+b vs. c+d)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rater 1 vs. 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.78–0.83)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.3 (737)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.2 (895)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rater 1 vs. 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.82–0.86)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.1 (715)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.0 (883)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rater 2 vs. 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.78–0.82)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.6 (671)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.9 (892)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rater 1 vs. majority</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.91–0.94)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.0 (883)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.7 (939)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rater 2 vs. majority</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.87–0.91)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.8 (841)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.6 (948)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rater 3 vs. majority</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.89–0.92)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.8 (821)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.4 (936)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>ᴋ<sub>w</sub> = weighted kappa scores (Fleiss-Cohen, quadratic weights), CI = confidence interval</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Volumetric density</title>
<p>The volumetric breast density measures are presented in <xref rid="pone.0136667.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The median volumetric breast density was 12.1% (IQR: 9.6–16.5) based on Quantra measurements, which was higher than the Volpara estimate (median: 6.6%, IQR: 4.4–10.9). Quantra also gave a higher median estimate of dense volume: 70 cm<sup>3</sup> (IQR: 49–101) with Quantra compared to 50 cm<sup>3</sup> (IQR: 39–70) with Volpara. Total breast volume, on the other hand, was higher for Volpara: 774 cm<sup>3</sup> (IQR: 509–1119) compared to 577 cm<sup>3</sup> (IQR: 368–842) for Volpara and Quantra, respectively. Based on the VDG, 12.3% and 30.7% of the women had ‘extremely dense’ (VDG 4) and ‘heterogeneously dense’ breasts (VDG 3), respectively.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0136667.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Volumetric breast density estimates in overall population (n = 992).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0136667.t003g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (IQR)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Percent dense volume (in %)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volpara</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6 (4.4–10.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantra</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 (9.6–16.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dense volume (in cm</bold><sup><bold>3</bold></sup><bold>)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volpara</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (39–70)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantra</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (49–101)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">403</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total volume (in cm</bold><sup><bold>3</bold></sup><bold>)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volpara</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">774 (509–1119)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3179</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantra</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">577 (368–842)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>% (N)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>VDG</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3 (261)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.6 (304)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.7 (305)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3 (122)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p>IQR = inter-quartile range</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref rid="pone.0136667.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref> shows the agreement between the volumetric measures in Bland-Altman plots. Volpara consistently gave lower percent dense volume and absolute dense volume estimates than Quantra. The mean difference (bias) between the methods (Quantra-Volpara) was 5.19% (95% CI: 5.04–5.34) for percent dense volume and 24.1 cm<sup>3</sup> (95% CI: 22.0–26.3) for dense volume. Compared with the Volpara measurement, the Quantra estimate of percent dense volume is expected to range between +0.5% and +9.9% in 95% of the measurements (limits of agreement). The Pearson’s r and the ICC were 0.91 (95% CI: 0.90–0.92) and 0.64 (95% CI: -0.07–0.88), respectively. The limits of agreement of absolute dense volume were -43.6 cm<sup>3</sup> and +91.9 cm<sup>3</sup>, with a Pearson’s r of 0.82 (95% CI: 0.80–0.84) and an ICC of 0.55 (95% CI: 0.24–0.72).</p>
<fig id="pone.0136667.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Bland-Altman plots comparing Quantra and Volpara absolute dense volume (a) and percent dense volume (b).</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>BI-RADS and volumetric breast density</title>
<p><xref rid="pone.0136667.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> shows the volumetric breast density according to BI-RADS density category. For both measures, there was a clear increase in volumetric breast density as BI-RADS density increased: median estimates increased from 3.6% (IQR 3.1–4.4) to 19.3% (IQR 15.1–23.5) with Volpara and from 8.5% (IQR 7.6–9.9) to 23.1% (IQR 19.6–26.8) with Quantra. In addition, the VDG distribution was comparable to the BI-RADS density distribution (κ<sub>w</sub>: 0.80, 95% CI: 0.77–0.82; proportion agreement: 65.4%) (<xref rid="pone.0136667.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). Volpara and Quantra did not agree on the association between BI-RADS density and absolute dense volume: a positive association was observed with Volpara, whereas Quantra estimates of absolute dense volume did not appear to be associated with the BI-RADS classification.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0136667.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>Percent dense volume and absolute dense volume by BI-RADS density category and by age group.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0136667.t004g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/>
<th colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Percent dense volume</th>
<th colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Absolute dense volume</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Volpara</th>
<th colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Quantra</th>
<th colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Volpara</th>
<th colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Quantra</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (IQR)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (IQR)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (IQR)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (IQR)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BI-RADS</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (3.1–4.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (7.6–9.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (37–52)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (56–112)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">403</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 (4.3–6.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6 (9.4–12.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (35–57)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (44–89)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">294</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2 (8.1–13.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1 (14.0–19.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (50–88)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (55–110)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">364</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3 (15.1–23.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1 (19.6–26.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (50–102)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (44–97)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">290</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age group</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49–58</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">491</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 (4.9–13.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6 (10.3–19.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (42–78)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (50–105)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">364</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59–68</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 (4.2–9.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 (9.1–15.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (37–66)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (49–98)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">403</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69+</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 (4.1–7.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6 (8.8–12.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (35–57)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (44–104)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">272</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BI-RADS c+d</bold></td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>BI-RADS d</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>VDG 3+4</bold></td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>VDG4</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age group</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>% (N)</bold></td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49–58</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">491</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.1 (246)</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">14.9 (73)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.4 (262)</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">18.7 (92)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59–68</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.0 (139)</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">8.8 (34)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.8 (138)</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">7.0 (27)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69+</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4 (20)</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">3.5 (4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5 (27)</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2.6 (3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p>IQR = inter-quartile range</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The ROC analyses on predicting the presence of BIRADS c+d (high density) with percent dense volume resulted in the following area under the curve (AUC) values: 0.948 (95% CI: 0.935–0.960) with Volpara and 0.948 (95% CI: 0.935–0.961) with Quantra (<xref rid="pone.0136667.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). The highest accuracy was observed with a cut-off value of 8.0% for Volpara (sensitivity = 84%, specificity = 91%) and 13.8% for Quantra (sensitivity = 82%, specificity = 92%).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Age</title>
<p>The median age at examination was 59 years (IQR: 54–64). The median percent dense volume, Volpara and Quantra estimates, appeared to decrease with age (<xref rid="pone.0136667.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The association between age and absolute dense volume was less pronounced in this population, with no clear pattern for the Quantra measurements and a slight decrease with Volpara. The percentage of women with ‘heterogeneously’ or ‘extremely’ dense breasts according to the BI-RADS density classification was lower for women in the highest age group (≥69y) compared to women in lowest age group (49–58y) (17.4% vs. 50.1%). A similar association between age and VDG was observed (23.5% vs. 53.4%).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>We studied three different methods to assess breast density, namely the BI-RADS density scale and two software programs (Quantra and Volpara). Quantra gave higher estimates of percent dense volume and absolute dense volume than Volpara. There was a positive association between percent dense volume and the BI-RADS density scale for both programs. In addition, the VDG (Volpara measure) seemed to be a good approximation of BI-RADS density in our study. Absolute dense volume only appeared to be associated with BI-RADS density when using the Volpara estimates. These density measures may potentially be used in the evaluation of screening performance and to identify risk groups.</p>
<p>Although other studies used older editions of the BI-RADS classification, the intra- and inter-observer reliability estimates in our study appeared to be similar to previous findings [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0136667.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The κ<sub>w</sub> tends to suggest ‘good’ to ‘very good’ reliability based on the Landis and Koch guidelines, even though these categories may be somewhat arbitrary. The proportions of agreement improved after the consensus meeting (data not shown), but there are still relatively large discrepancies between the radiologists (up to 32.4% for observer 2 vs. 3). For this reason, density assessment by individual radiologists is not useful for selecting women for future alternative screening regimens in population-based organised breast cancer screening programmes or risk management. Furthermore, the intra- and inter-rater variability may differ between radiologists, for example based on experience level [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p>
<p>The use of automated volumetric density measures has been advocated [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0136667.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Volumetric density would have several advantages over qualitative scales and area-based density measures. Volumetric software programs calculate breast density based on 3D instead of 2D information, thus also including thickness of the tissue. An estimate of the actual volume of the tissue rather than the 2D projection of the tissue is expected to have a stronger biological association [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0136667.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In addition, the calculations incorporate imaging settings (e.g., X-ray dose). Furthermore, with both software programs there is perfect agreement between two assessments of the same mammogram, which we also observed in our data. This is in contrast to the qualitative and semi-automated measurements, in which some degree of intra- and inter-rater variation appears to be inevitable. Finally, the volumetric measurements would be easier to implement in screening programmes as the automated software tends to be less time-consuming and labour-intensive than the rather variable visual assessment with BI-RADS breast density, which in dual reading set-up will cause many discrepancies.</p>
<p>Several studies have compared the volumetric estimates to the BI-RADS scale (<xref rid="pone.0136667.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. An important difference between radiologists’ scores and automated methods is that radiologists tend to give the maximum value (as suggested by the ACR), whereas volumetric density estimates are based on the average of multiple views. The results from all these studies do, however, suggest a clear positive association between percent dense volume and BI-RADS density. The median estimates of percent dense volume we obtained with Volpara for each BI-RADS category appeared to be at the lower end of the range. Our Quantra estimates were lower than the available literature values as well. This may be explained by differences in setting and risk factor distribution (e.g., age range, use of hormone therapy, clinic versus screening). Using area-based measures, the highest BI-RADS density category was previously linked to density percentages greater than 75% (4<sup>th</sup> BI-RADS edition). All our volumetric estimates for percent dense volume were below 40%, which clearly illustrates a difference in range between area-based and volumetric methods. Similar to our findings, Gweon <italic>et al</italic>. and Jeffreys <italic>et al</italic>. both found an increase in absolute dense volume with increasing BI-RADS density [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0136667.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. We observed a distinct difference in Volpara absolute dense volume between the two lowest and the two highest BI-RADS density categories. There was no clear association between Quantra absolute dense volume and BI-RADS density. In line with these results, Eng <italic>et al</italic>. found that Quantra absolute dense volume, in contrast to Volpara dense volume or Cumulus dense area, was not associated with an increased breast cancer risk (Q5 vs. Q1: OR 1.08) [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0136667.t005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.t005</object-id>
<label>Table 5</label> <caption><title>Association between BI-RADS density measures and volumetric density in other studies.<xref rid="t005fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0136667.t005g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BI-RADS 1/a</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BI-RADS 2/b</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BI-RADS 3/c</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BI-RADS 4/d</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association measures</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Volpara: percent dense volume</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mean (SD)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gweon [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">778</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (0.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (2.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1 (5.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1 (5.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% density vs. BI-RADS (Spearman’s ρ) = 0.765; VDG vs. BI-RADS (κ<sub>w</sub>) = 0.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Median (IQR)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">992</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (3.1–4.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 (4.3–6.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2 (8.1–13.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3 (15.1–23.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jeffreys [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">324</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 <italic>(3–5)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>6 (4–8)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>11 (8–16)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9 <italic>(15–22)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seo [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>5 (4–8)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>9 (7–11)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>14 (12–17)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>21 (18–25)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% density vs. BI-RADS (Spearman’s ρ) = 0.754; VDG vs. BI-RADS (ICC) = 0.757</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gubern-Mérida [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.66 <italic>(5–6)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>9 (8–11)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>21 (18–24)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.69 <italic>(24–29)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% density vs. BI-RADS (Spearman’s ρ) = 0.79; VDG vs. BI-RADS (κ<sub>w</sub>) = 0.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ko [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1129</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VDG vs. BI-RADS (κ) = 0.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Volpara: dense volume</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mean (SD)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gweon [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">778</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7 (7.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.7 (13.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.7 (23.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.8 (35.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Median (IQR)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">992</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (37–52)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (35–57)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (50–88)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (50–102)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jeffreys<xref rid="t005fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">324</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 <italic>(30–50)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>50 (40–60)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>60 (50–80)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 <italic>(60–120)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Quantra: percent dense volume</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mean (SD)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regini [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4 (3.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8 (4.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5 (7.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8 (8.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% density vs. BI-RADS (Pearson’s r) = 0.99; Cut-off value BI-RADS3+4 = 21%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Median (IQR)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">992</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (7.6–9.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 (9.4–12.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1 (14.0–19.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1 (19.6–26.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Median (range)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciatto<xref rid="t005fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref> [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">418</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 (7.0–19.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5 (10.0–32.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5 (16.0–47.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.0 (24.5–50.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cut-off value BI-RADS3+4 = 22%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Quantra: dense volume</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Median (IQR)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current study</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">992</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (56–112)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (44–89)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (55–110)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (44–97)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t005fn001"><p>SD = standard deviation, IQR = inter-quartile range</p></fn>
<fn id="t005fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> The results in italics were not published, but were based on estimates from the published boxplots.</p></fn>
<fn id="t005fn003"><p><sup>b</sup> Values were rounded off.</p></fn>
<fn id="t005fn004"><p><sup>c</sup> Also presented means, which were: 12.2 for BI-RADS 1, 18.0 for BI-RADS 2, 28.5 for BI-RADS 3, and 34.5 for BI-RADS 4.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>There was a relatively strong correlation in percent dense volume between the two automated volumetric methods (Pearson’s r: 0.91, ICC: 0.64). The correlation for absolute dense volume, on the other hand, appeared to be somewhat weaker, with lower correlation coefficients (Pearson’s r: 0.82, ICC: 0.55). The first results from validation studies, comparing volumetric density to MRI results, are now appearing in the literature. Gubern-Mérida <italic>et al</italic>. indicated that Volpara may slightly underestimate the true density (as measured with MRI) [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Wang <italic>et al</italic>. is, to our knowledge, the first study to include both Volpara and Quantra. They observed a strong correlation between the two measures, as well as a strong correlation of both with MRI [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However, absolute dense volume was not included in either of these studies. Morrish <italic>et al</italic>. did report on absolute dense volume in their comparison study of Quantra and Volpara [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Although they observed a weaker correlation for percent dense volume, the results on absolute dense volume appear to be in line with our findings. It should be noted that this study was performed in a slightly different setting (e.g., country, age range, participant selection) and used different software versions, which may explain differences in volume estimates and observed correlations.</p>
<p>The effect of breast density on breast cancer risk is relevant for personalised (primary and secondary) prevention, where it can potentially be used as a risk stratification factor. Little evidence has yet been published on the association between volumetric density and breast cancer risk to date, although previous studies have suggested that volumetric density may be more strongly associated with breast cancer risk due to its predicted biological association [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0136667.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. According to the meta-analysis of McCormack <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], women with extremely dense breasts based on the BI-RADS classification have a 4.08 (95% CI: 2.96–5.63) times higher breast cancer risk compared with women with fatty breasts. In our study, the highest BI-RADS category corresponded to a median percent dense volume of 19.3% (Volpara) or 23.1% (Quantra). However, with overlapping ranges of volumetric density for different BI-RADS categories, it is difficult to directly relate these findings to the previously determined risks based on the BI-RADS scale. Park and colleagues reported an adjusted OR of 3.07 for women with more than 15.1% Volpara percent dense volume compared to women with less than 4.7% in a Korean population [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. A study by Brand <italic>et al</italic>. showed that the highest Volpara density quartile was associated with a 2.93 (percent dense volume) or 1.63 (absolute dense volume) higher risk than the lowest quartile [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Finally, Eng <italic>et al</italic>. studied several breast density measures: both Volpara (Q5 vs. Q1: OR 8.26) and Quantra (Q5 vs. Q1: OR 3.94) estimates of percent dense volume were associated with an increased breast cancer risk [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p>
<p>The associations between volumetric density and other established breast cancer risk factors may provide some insight into the etiological role of volumetric density. We studied the association with age, where we observed a similar inverse association as has previously been determined using other density measures. Studies have shown that most risk factors have a similar association with Volpara volumetric breast density as they do with area-based measures [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Only limited evidence is available on the association between established risk factors and Quantra volumetric density [<xref rid="pone.0136667.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].</p>
<p>One of the limitations of our study is that we did not have any information on breast cancer risk, which would ultimately be needed to validate both breast density measures and potentially implement them in a breast cancer screening setting if they are to be used for risk stratification. More research is needed as well on the association between volumetric density and sensitivity of digital mammography. This information is required to identify a clinically relevant breast density cut-off value above which additional screening (e.g., with MRI or ultrasound) may be cost effective. Studies are also needed on the potential inclusion of volumetric density in risk models. Strengths of the current study include the use of both Volpara and Quantra, which we were able to study in relation to the newest BI-RADS density classification. In addition, we included both percent dense volume and absolute dense volume. Finally, our study sample was relatively large compared to previous studies (<xref rid="pone.0136667.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p>
<p>Before volumetric density measurements can be implemented in breast cancer screening, the infrastructure on storing unprocessed mammogram data has to be developed further. This would involve large amounts of data. However, the advantage of this data storage is that multiple automated tools can easily be compared over time. Furthermore, if at any time an algorithm would be introduced that performs considerably better, it could also be applied to historical data. This is especially important for monitoring density changes, for example between geographic areas and within women. Due to the lack of intra- and inter-observer variability, in contrast to the BI-RADS density classification, changes in density can be more readily detected if random measurement error is small.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Volpara and Quantra clearly differed from each other. However, there appeared to be a strong association of these measures with each other and with the BI-RADS density scale. Further research on the differences between the measures is needed before they can be implemented in breast cancer screening programmes. This applies both to the logistics surrounding breast density measurements and the role of breast density in screening programmes. If studies indeed show that breast density is important for evaluating performance or could be useful for risk stratification, then both Quantra and Volpara may be considered.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0136667.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>ROC analyses on predicting high density (BI-RADS c+d) with percent dense volume (a) and dense volume (b).</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0136667.s002" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0136667.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Comparison of VDG and BI-RADS density classification (N, %).</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors thank the screening organisation (Foundation of Population Screening East) for providing the data.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Gils</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otten</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verbeek</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendriks</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mammographic breast density and risk of breast cancer: masking bias or causality?</article-title> <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9690746</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fishell</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Mammographic density and the risk and detection of breast cancer</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>356</volume>:<fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17229950</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCormack</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos Silva</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Breast density and parenchymal patterns as markers of breast cancer risk: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1159</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16775176</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerlikowske</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>The mammogram that cried Wolfe</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>356</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17229958</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carney</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miglioretti</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yankaskas</surname> <given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerlikowske</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rutter</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Individual and combined effects of age, breast density, and hormone replacement therapy use on the accuracy of screening mammography</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>138</volume>:<fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12558355</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schousboe</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerlikowske</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loh</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Personalizing mammography by breast density and other risk factors for breast cancer: analysis of health benefits and cost-effectiveness</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7326/0003-4819-155-1-201107050-00003" xlink:type="simple">10.7326/0003-4819-155-1-201107050-00003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21727289</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname> <given-names>JN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Breast patterns as an index of risk for developing breast cancer</article-title>. <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source> <year>1976</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>1130</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">179369</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gram</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Funkhouser</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tabár</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Tabár classification of mammographic parenchymal patterns</article-title>. <source>Eur J Radiol</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9097055</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sickles</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D’Orsi</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bassett</surname> <given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <chapter-title>ACR BI-RADS Mammography</chapter-title>. In: <source>ACR BI-RADS Atlas, Breast Imaging Reporting and Data System</source>. <publisher-name>American College of Radiology</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Reston</publisher-loc></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciatto</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Houssami</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Apruzzese</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bassetti</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brancato</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carozzi</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Categorizing breast mammographic density: intra- and interobserver reproducibility of BI-RADS density categories</article-title>. <source>Breast</source> <year>2005</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16085233</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Assi</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warwick</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuzick</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Clinical and epidemiological issues in mammographic density</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Clin Oncol</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaffe</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mammographic density. Measurement of mammographic density</article-title>. <source>Breast Cancer Res</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/bcr2102" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/bcr2102</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18598375</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vachon</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Gils</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sellers</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pruthi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Mammographic density, breast cancer risk and risk prediction</article-title>. <source>Breast Cancer Res</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/bcr1829" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/bcr1829</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18190724</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azziz</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malkov</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klifa</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newitt</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Agreement of mammographic measures of volumetric breast density to MRI</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e81653</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0081653" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0081653</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24324712</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrish</surname> <given-names>OW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willsher</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mammographic Breast Density: Comparison of Methods for Quantitative Evaluation</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source> <year>2015</year>:<fpage>141508</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmachtenberg</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammann-Kloss</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bick</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engelken</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intraindividual Comparison of Two Methods of Volumetric Breast Composition Assessment</article-title>. <source>Acad Radiol Epub</source> <year>2015</year> <month>Jan</month> <day>10</day>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartman</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Highnam</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Volumetric Assessment of Breast Tissue Composition from FFDM Images</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Krupinski</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Lecture Notes in Computer Science: 9<sup>th</sup> International Workshop on Digital Mammography; 2008 Jul 20–23</source>; <publisher-loc>Tucson, AZ, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>. p. <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joe</surname> <given-names>BN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Breast density legislation: mandatory disclosure to patients, alternative screening, billing, reimbursement</article-title>. <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source> <year>2015</year>;<volume>204</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2214/AJR.14.13558" xlink:type="simple">10.2214/AJR.14.13558</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25615746</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yip</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taib</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Standardisation of clinical breast-density measurement</article-title>. <source>Lancet Oncol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>334</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(12)70093-1" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S1470-2045(12)70093-1</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22469115</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Engeland</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snoeren</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huisman</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boetes</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karssemeijer</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Volumetric breast density estimation from full-field digital mammograms</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Med Imaging</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16524084</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Highnam</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brady</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yaffe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karssemeijer</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Robust breast composition measures—Volpara</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Martí</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freixenet</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martí</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Lecture Notes in Computer Science: 10<sup>th</sup> International Workshop on Digital Mammography; 2010 Jun 16–18</source>; <publisher-loc>Girona, Spain</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>. p. <fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kottner</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Audige</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brorson</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donner</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gajewski</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hrobjartsson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Guidelines for Reporting Reliability and Agreement Studies (GRRAS) were proposed</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.03.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.03.002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21130355</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Vet</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terwee</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knol</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouter</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>. <article-title>When to use agreement versus reliability measures</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>1033</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16980142</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleiss</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paik</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The Measurement of Interrater Agreement</chapter-title>. In: <source>Statistical methods for rates and proportions</source>. <edition>Third edition</edition>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken (NJ)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>; <year>2003</year>. p. <fpage>598</fpage>–<lpage>626</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landis</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname> <given-names>GG</given-names></name>. <article-title>The measurement of observer agreement for categorical data</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <year>1977</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">843571</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Some common problems in medical research</chapter-title>. In: <source>Practical statistics in medical research</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>; <year>1991</year>. p. <fpage>404</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunnally</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname> <given-names>IH</given-names></name>. <source>Psychometric theory</source>. <edition>Third edition</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York, McGraw Hill</publisher-name>; <year>1994</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Redondo</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Comas</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macia</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrer</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murta-Nascimento</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maristany</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Inter- and intraradiologist variability in the BI-RADS assessment and breast density categories for screening mammograms</article-title>. <source>Br J Radiol</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>1465</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1259/bjr/21256379" xlink:type="simple">10.1259/bjr/21256379</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22993385</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardi</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pellegrini</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Michele</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tuttobene</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fanto</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valentini</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Interobserver agreement in breast radiological density attribution according to BI-RADS quantitative classification</article-title>. <source>Radiol Med</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11547-011-0777-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11547-011-0777-3</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22228132</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrido-Estepa</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Perales</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miranda</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ascunce</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Roman</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Contador</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Evaluation of mammographic density patterns: reproducibility and concordance among scales</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>485</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20836850</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ooms</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zonderland</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eijkemans</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kriege</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahdavian Delavary</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burger</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Mammography: interobserver variability in breast density assessment</article-title>. <source>Breast</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18035541</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname> <given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campassi</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langenberg</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sexton</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Breast Imaging Reporting and Data System: inter- and intraobserver variability in feature analysis and final assessment</article-title>. <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source> <year>2000</year>;<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>1769</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10845521</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciatto</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Houssami</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Apruzzese</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bassetti</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brancato</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carozzi</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Reader variability in reporting breast imaging according to BI-RADS assessment categories (the Florence experience)</article-title>. <source>Breast</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16076556</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopans</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Basic physics and doubts about relationship between mammographically determined tissue density and breast cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>246</volume>:<fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1148/radiol.2461070309" xlink:type="simple">10.1148/radiol.2461070309</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18227535</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gweon</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Youk</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Radiologist assessment of breast density by BI-RADS categories versus fully automated volumetric assessment</article-title>. <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>201</volume>:<fpage>692</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2214/AJR.12.10197" xlink:type="simple">10.2214/AJR.12.10197</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23971465</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeffreys</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Highnam</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Comparing a New Volumetric Breast Density Method (Volpara) to Cumulus</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Martí</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freixenet</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martí</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Lecture Notes in Computer Science: 10<sup>th</sup> International Workshop on Digital Mammography; 2010 Jun 16–18</source>; <publisher-loc>Girona, Spain</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>. p. <fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname> <given-names>EY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname> <given-names>SY</given-names></name>. <article-title>Automated volumetric breast density estimation: a comparison with visual assessment</article-title>. <source>Clin Radiol</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>690</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.crad.2013.01.011" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.crad.2013.01.011</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23434202</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gubern-Merida</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kallenberg</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Platel</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marti</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karssemeijer</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Volumetric breast density estimation from full-field digital mammograms: a validation study</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e85952</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0085952" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0085952</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24465808</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname> <given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mammographic density estimation with automated volumetric breast density measurement</article-title>. <source>Korean journal of radiology</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3348/kjr.2014.15.3.313" xlink:type="simple">10.3348/kjr.2014.15.3.313</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24843235</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Regini</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mariscotti</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durando</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghione</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luparia</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campanino</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Radiological assessment of breast density by visual classification (BI-RADS) compared to automated volumetric digital software (Quantra): implications for clinical practice</article-title>. <source>Radiol Med</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>741</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11547-014-0390-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11547-014-0390-3</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24610166</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciatto</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardi</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calabrese</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durando</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gentilini</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mariscotti</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A first evaluation of breast radiological density assessment by QUANTRA software as compared to visual classification</article-title>. <source>Breast</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.breast.2012.01.005" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.breast.2012.01.005</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22285387</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eng</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallant</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shepherd</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCormack</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dowsett</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Digital mammographic density and breast cancer risk: a case-control study of six alternative density assessment methods</article-title>. <source>Breast Cancer Res</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>439</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s13058-014-0439-1" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/s13058-014-0439-1</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25239205</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>IH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joo</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname> <given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>High Volumetric Breast Density Predicts Risk for Breast Cancer in Postmenopausal, but not Premenopausal, Korean Women</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg Oncol</source> <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Czene</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shepherd</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leifland</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heddson</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sundbom</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Automated measurement of volumetric mammographic density: a tool for widespread breast cancer risk assessment</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1764</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-13-1219" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-13-1219</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25012995</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lokate</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kallenberg</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karssemeijer</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van den Bosch</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peeters</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Gils</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Volumetric breast density from full-field digital mammograms and its association with breast cancer risk factors: a comparison with a threshold method</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>3096</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-10-0703" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-10-0703</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20921336</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schetter</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartman</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richie</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prokopczyk</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DuBrock</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Differential impact of body mass index on absolute and percent breast density: implications regarding their use as breast cancer risk biomarkers</article-title>. <source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>146</volume>:<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10549-014-3031-6" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10549-014-3031-6</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24951269</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0136667.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skippage</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roche</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dowsett</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>A'Hern</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Correlation of age and HRT use with breast density as assessed by Quantra</article-title>. <source>Breast J</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/tbj.12046" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/tbj.12046</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23230974</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>