<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">pcbi</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="allenpress-id">plcb</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07-PLCB-RA-0401R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="sici">plcb-03-11-16</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Developmental Biology</subject><subject>Mathematics</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Drosophila</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Self-organizing Mechanism for Development of Space-filling Neuronal Dendrites</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Neurite Branching by RD System</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimura</surname><given-names>Kaoru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>
            <sup>1</sup>
          </sup>
          </xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="n103">
            <sup>¤</sup>
          </xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimono</surname><given-names>Kohei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>
            <sup>2</sup>
          </sup>
          </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>Tadashi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>
            <sup>1</sup>
          </sup>
          </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>Atsushi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>
            <sup>3</sup>
          </sup>
          </xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>
				 Graduate School of Biostudies, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan
			</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>
				 Department of Science, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan
			</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>
				 Division of Theoretical Biology, National Institute for Basic Biology, Okazaki, Japan
			</addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>Karl J</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University College London, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">ksugimura@brain.riken.jp</email> (KS); <email xlink:type="simple">mochi@nibb.ac.jp</email> (AM)</corresp><fn fn-type="con" id="ack1"><p> K. Sugimura and A. Mochizuki designed the work. K. Sugimura and K. Shimono performed simulation and analyzed the data. K. Sugimura, A. Mochizuki, and T. Uemura wrote the paper.</p></fn><fn fn-type="current-aff" id="n103"><p>¤ Current address: Laboratory for Cell Function Dynamics, Advanced Technology Development Group, RIKEN Brain Science Institute, Wako, Japan</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict" id="ack3"><p> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e212</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></date></history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><copyright-holder> Sugimura et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Neurons develop distinctive dendritic morphologies to receive and process information. Previous experiments showed that competitive dendro-dendritic interactions play critical roles in shaping dendrites of the space-filling type, which uniformly cover their receptive field. We incorporated this finding in constructing a new mathematical model, in which reaction dynamics of two chemicals (activator and suppressor) are coupled to neuronal dendrite growth. Our numerical analysis determined the conditions for dendritic branching and suggested that the self-organizing property of the proposed system can underlie dendritogenesis. Furthermore, we found a clear correlation between dendrite shape and the distribution of the activator, thus providing a morphological criterion to predict the in vivo distribution of the hypothetical molecular complexes responsible for dendrite elongation and branching.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><sec id="st1"><title/><p>Neurons elaborate two types of neuronal extensions. One is axon, which sends outputs to other neurons. Another is dendrite, which is specialized for receiving and processing synaptic or sensory inputs. Like elaborated branches of trees, the shape of dendrites is quite variable from one type to another, and different dendritic geometry contributes to differential informational processing and computation. For instance, neurons of the space-filling type (e.g., retinal ganglion cells) fill in an open space to pick up spatial information from every corner of their receptive field. Therefore, dendrite development is one of the representative examples of the emergence of function through morphogenesis. Previous experiments including ours showed that competitive dendro-dendritic interactions play critical roles in shaping dendrites of the space-filling type. In the present study, we incorporated this finding in constructing a new mathematical model, in which reaction dynamics of chemicals are coupled to neuronal dendrite growth. Our numerical analysis suggested that self-organizing property of the proposed system underlies formation of space-filling dendrites. Furthermore, we provided a morphological criterion to predict the in vivo distribution of the hypothetical molecular complexes responsible for dendrite elongation and branching. We have now found a substantial number of molecules involved in dendrite development, thus it is timely to discuss the prediction from this work.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement> This work was supported by grants from the programs Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research on Priority Areas-Molecular Brain Science of the MEXT of Japan (17024025 to TU) and Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research on Priority Areas -Systems Genomics from the MEXT of Japan (17017019 to AM). KS was supported by a JSPS Research Fellowship for Young Scientists, and is a RIKEN special postdoctoral fellow.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts><!--===== Restructure custom-meta-wrap to custom-meta-group =====--><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>citation</meta-name><meta-value>Sugimura K, Shimono K, Uemura T, Mochizuki A (2007) Self-organizing mechanism for development of space-filling neuronal dendrites. PLoS Comput Biol 3(11): e212. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212</ext-link></meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>One of the primary interests in developmental biology is the emergence of function through morphogenesis. Morphological diversity of dendrites and its impact on neuronal computation perfectly represents the importance of this problem: shapes of dendrites are highly variable from one neuronal type to another, and it has been suggested that this diversity supports differential processing of information in each type of neuron [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b001">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b003">3</xref>]. Therefore, patterning of neuronal class-specific dendrites is a process to produce shapes that realizes the physiological functions of neurons. Recent advances in genetic manipulation at the single-cell level enabled us to identify genes whose loss of function affects neuronal morphology (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b004">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b006">6</xref>]); however, we are far from formulating an overall picture of the underlying mechanism of pattern formation.</p><p>Among various classes of dendrites is the “space-filling” type, which uniformly covers its receptive field. The concept of space-filling was introduced by Fiala and Harris [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b007">7</xref>], and we use this term with a slightly different meaning here. Neurons elaborating space-filling dendrites are found in various parts of nervous system, including retinal ganglion cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b008">8</xref>], trigeminal ganglion cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b009">9</xref>], Purkinje cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">Figure 8</xref>B) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b010">10</xref>], and <italic>Drosophila</italic> class IV dendritic arborization (da) neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g001">Figure 1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b011">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b014">14</xref>]. The space-filling type looks very complex morphologically, but can be regarded as being simple in their isotropic features and in their two-dimensionality. Most importantly, it shows distinctive spatial regulation of pattern formation: for instance, dendritic branches of <italic>Drosophila</italic> class IV da neurons avoid dendrites of the same cell and those of neighboring class IV cells, which allows complete, but minimal overlapping, innervation of the body wall (designated as isoneuronal avoidance and tiling) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g001">Figure 1</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g001">1</xref>B) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b013">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b015">15</xref>]. Our previous experiment together with studies by others demonstrated that competitive dendro-dendritic interaction underlies tiling, as shown by the fact that the da neurons reaccomplish tiling in response to ablation of adjacent neurons of the same class or to severing of their branches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g001">Figure 1</xref>C) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b014">14</xref>]. It should be noted that the qualitatively same inhibitory dendro-dendritic interaction is working between the adjacent neurons of the same type as well as between dendrites of the same neurons.</p><fig id="pcbi-0030212-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Competitive Interactions between Dendrites Mediate Isoneuronal Avoidance and Tiling</title><p>(A) An image of <italic>Drosophila</italic> larva of <italic>NP7028 UAS-mCD8::GFP</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b011">11</xref>]. Class IV da neurons ddaC (arrows) were visualized with GFP. Dendrites of class IV da neurons almost completely cover the body wall.</p><p>(B) A high-power image of class IV da neurons at single dendrite resolution (left). Dendrites from the left segment are colored purple; and those from the right segment, green (right). Dendrites of the same class IV da neuron come very close, but hardly overlap each other (isoneuronal avoidance); in addition, minimal overlap was seen between dendrites of neighboring neurons (heteroneuronal avoidance or tiling).</p><p>(C) Schematic drawing of a filling-in response (adapted from 12). Left: Branches enclosed by the dotted line were severed by laser irradiation (arrow). Right: Neighboring dendrites filled in the open space that had been covered by the detached branches and space-filling pattern was regenerated. Black: dendrites of the operated cell. Gray: dendrites of the neighboring cell. This experiment clarifies an essential role of inhibitory dendro-dendritic interactions in isoneuronal avoidance and tiling. Bar, 50 μm for “A” and 20 μm for “B.”</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><p>There are two types of the proposed mechanisms that support this repulsive behavior of dendrites: one is contact-dependent retraction of dendrites and the other is repulsion of dendrites via diffusive suppressors. The contact-dependent mechanism seems insufficient to a clear field splitting, because as far as dendrites do not make contacts (by passing under other dendrites, for example) they can invade neighboring territories. Moreover, time-lapse analysis showed that dendrites make a turn before they are about to cross nearby branches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b016">16</xref>]. So we prefer diffusive signaling to a contact-dependent one. Similar mechanisms have been suggested to work in other model systems as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b017">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b018">18</xref>]. With all available information taken together, we considered the space-filling dendrite to be an ideally suited one for us to start modeling, due to the simplicity of its patterning and the experimentally verified mechanism of the pattern formation.</p><p>A number of mathematical models for neurite formation were previously proposed; and most of them assumed that dendrite development is a consequence of stochastic sprouting and subsequent growth arrest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b019">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b022">22</xref>]. Different forms of branching functions were postulated and modified so that calculated dendrograms would fit dendritic arbors of real neurons in a quantitative manner. Those studies were descriptive and did not provide a comprehensive mechanism of pattern formation. In this study, we developed a new class of mathematical model for neurite formation to approach a principle of development of the space-filling dendrites. In our neurite growth model that is based on the aforementioned inhibitory dendro-dendritic interaction, various aspects of pattern formation, e.g., extension, orientation of growth, and branching of dendrites, are represented in a single framework. Computer simulation showed that our model develops dendritic extension and branching autonomously; furthermore, numerical analysis determined the conditions for dendritic growth.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Cell Compartment Model for Dendritic Growth</title><p>As mentioned above, two-dimensionality is a characteristic of space-filling dendrites; thus we built our model in the 2D space, dividing the 2D space into two distinct compartments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g002">Figure 2</xref>A), i.e., the compartment occupied by neurons (designated as the cell compartment or the cell region hereafter) and the extracellular compartment. This model is referred to as the “cell compartment model.” We assumed that growth of the cell region, which shapes the dendritic trees, is regulated by a hypothetical intracellular chemical, i.e., the activator (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g002">Figure 2</xref>A). We set a restriction in terms of the movement of the activator so that it diffuses only the inside of cells. The activator promotes the growth of the cell compartment when its concentration is higher than threshold (<italic>Tr</italic> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g002">Figure 2</xref>D). To account for the inhibitory dendro-dendritic interaction, we hypothesized another chemical, the suppressor. The suppressor is produced when the concentration of activator is high, i.e., it is produced at the actively growing region of dendrites. The suppressor acts to decrease the concentration of activator, but the concentration of activator can increase by its autocatalytic production where the activator is locally concentrated. The reaction between activator and suppressor is the so-called “activator-inhibitor type” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b023">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b024">24</xref>] (“1” in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g002">Figure 2</xref>A). The activator-induced production of the suppressor can be realized by either local translation of suppressor-encoding mRNA in dendrites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b025">25</xref>] or secretion of suppressor proteins from intracellular organelles. The suppressor is secreted from the cell, diffuses throughout the extracellular space, and then binding of the suppressor to its receptor drives intracellular signaling to repress the production of the activator (“2” in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g002">Figure 2</xref>A). So, the suppressor mediates long-range inhibitory interactions between dendrites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g002">Figure 2</xref>B). These settings endow the system with feedback-loop regulation at two different levels: one is between the two chemicals and the other is between the dynamics of these chemicals and the expansion of the cell compartment. The latter consists of the following reciprocal interactions: the activator controls growth of the cell region and growth of the cell region determines where the activator can diffuse further.</p><fig id="pcbi-0030212-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Schematic Representation of the Cell Compartment Model</title><p>(A,B) An activator–suppressor system. Intracellular activator promotes growth of dendrite and produces the suppressor or accelerates secretion of the suppressor from intracellular organelles (“1” in (A)). On the other hand, the suppressor is secreted from the cell and diffuses in extracellular compartments. Binding of its receptor on the plasma membrane triggers signaling to inhibit synthesis of the activator (“2” in (A)). These reactions underlie inhibitory dendro-dendritic interactions (B).</p><p>(C) Black: core of the cell; dark gray: cell boundary. The cell compartment is represented by collective circular domains around the core with radius <italic>R</italic> (gray circles).</p><p>(D) Dynamics of core of the cell (<italic>c</italic>). The activator promotes cell growth when its concentration is higher than threshold (<italic>Tr</italic>). <italic>a</italic>(<italic>u</italic>) = 0.49 (<italic>u</italic> ≤ <italic>Tr</italic>) or <italic>a</italic>(<italic>u</italic>) = 0.49 − 2.5(<italic>u</italic> – <italic>Tr</italic>) (<italic>u</italic> &gt; <italic>Tr</italic>). Upper graph: Both <italic>c</italic> = 0 and <italic>c</italic> = 1 are stable equilibrium points. Lower graph: When <italic>a</italic>(<italic>u</italic>) &lt; 0, <italic>c</italic> = <italic>a</italic>(<italic>u</italic>) and <italic>c</italic> = 1 are stable equilibrium points and <italic>c</italic> = 0 becomes an unstable equilibrium point. Very small positive noise was added to <italic>c</italic>, so <italic>c</italic> → 1 quickly. These settings make it possible to store the history of growth of <italic>c</italic>, because <italic>c</italic> = 1 is a stable equilibrium point all the time.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Model Formulation</title><p>Our model can be written as the following equations:
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ea001"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ea001" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&Delta;</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>&plus;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&gamma;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>&Omega;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-eb001"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.eb001" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>&Delta;</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>&plus;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&gamma;</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:mi>&Omega;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ec001"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ec001" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&gamma;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:mi>&Omega;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>where <italic>u</italic> and <italic>v</italic> are concentrations of the activator and the suppressor, respectively. Note that these equations are already non-dimensionalized, so <italic>d</italic> is the ratio of the diffusion coefficient between the two substances (see the section “Original equations”). As we hypothesize that diffusion of the suppressor is faster than that of the activator, <italic>d</italic> is larger than 1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b026">26</xref>]. <italic>c</italic>(<bold>x</bold>, <italic>t</italic>) is a symbolic variable to indicate the “core” of the cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g002">Figure 2</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g002">2</xref>D). The biological correlates of <italic>c</italic> could be microtubules that support structural integrity of the cell. The right-hand side of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ec001">Equation 1</xref>c indicates that the dynamics of the cell state is bi-stable and that the two steady states are 1 and 0, indicating “core” and “not core,” respectively, and <italic>a</italic>(<italic>u</italic>) is the switching point at which the growth behavior of <italic>c</italic> is flipped. <italic>c</italic> quickly reaches 1 when <italic>u</italic> is higher than threshold (<italic>Tr</italic>). The symbol Ω is the 2D real space, and <bold>x</bold><italic><sub>c</sub></italic> denotes a point in Ω, where <italic>c</italic> is larger than 0.5. Ω<italic>c</italic>, which is the region of the cell in Ω, and is defined by using <bold>x</bold><italic><sub>c</sub></italic> as follows: <inline-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ex001"><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ex001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
					 (<italic>γ</italic> is a rate constant to rescale time and space) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b026">26</xref>]. <italic>R</italic> is the distance between core and the plasma membrane, and the cell compartment is represented by collective circular domains around the core with radius <italic>R</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g002">Figure 2</xref>C). We found that <italic>R</italic> = 0.004 realized the finest resolution of patterns, so we used this value of <italic>R</italic> throughout this study (see the section “<italic>R</italic> value” for details). Describing the cell growth as a rapid transition between bistable states is reminiscent of a way to solve moving boundary problems in phase-field models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b027">27</xref>]. A difference between these models and ours is whether diffusion of the phase field is incorporated or not; a diffusion term does not appear in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ec001">Equation 1</xref>c, because diffusion of the cell state is biologically unrealistic in this case.
				</p><p><italic>f</italic>(<italic>u</italic>,<italic>v</italic>) and <italic>g</italic>(<italic>u</italic>,<italic>v</italic>) represent chemical reaction terms, where the partial derivatives satisfy the following conditions: <inline-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ex002"><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ex002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
					 &gt; 0 (autocatalytic production of the activator), <inline-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ex003"><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ex003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
					 &lt; 0 (inhibition of synthesis of the activator by the suppressor), <inline-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ex004"><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ex004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
					 &gt; 0 (production of the suppressor by the activator) and <inline-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ex005"><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ex005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
					 &lt; 0 (concentration-dependent degradation of the suppressor). We used the following formulas for <italic>f</italic> and <italic>g</italic>:
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ea002"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ea002" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>&plus;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-eb002"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.eb002" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
				</p><p>We assumed that the receptor is uniformly distributed over the dendritic surface and that the strength of the signaling follows the local concentration of the suppressor. We adopted the 0-fixed boundary condition for the activator at the cell boundary:
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ec002"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ec002" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant='bold' mathsize='normal'><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&emsp; for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:mstyle mathvariant='bold' mathsize='normal'><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>&isin;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width=".5pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>&Omega;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
				</p><p>We used the periodic boundary for the other variables <italic>v</italic> and <italic>c</italic> at the boundary of the 2D square space to model the real 2D space Ω in numerical simulation.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Autonomous Formation of Dendritic Patterns</title><p>We numerically calculated the model given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ea001">Equations 1</xref>a–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ec001">1</xref>c with reaction terms of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ea002">Equations 2</xref>a and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-eb002">2</xref>b (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). Computer simulation showed that the cell compartment model could autonomously generate quite distinct dendritic patterns depending on the set of parameters employed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>). In each case where the model produced dendritic patterns, they were generated through repeated cycles of elongation and branching of dendrites (two examples are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi-0030212-sv001">Videos S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi-0030212-sv003">S3</xref>). With one set of parameters, smooth branches were formed, where neighboring branches aligned themselves nearly parallel to each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>A). In such a cell, the distribution of the activator is continuous and mostly uniform, except for every branch terminal, where the density of the activator is relatively high (arrows in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>B; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi-0030212-sv002">Video S2</xref>). With a different set of parameters, the dendritic branches showed a more rugged morphology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>D). Stubby and non-aligned branches were formed, and the activator was distributed in a punctate manner in that cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>E; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi-0030212-sv004">Video S4</xref>). We call each punctum, where the activator was highly concentrated, a “spot.” Dendrites elongated by generating new spots (arrows in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>E) and bifurcated when spots fissioned (arrowheads in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>E). The suppressor was concentrated where the density of the activator was high, and it was distributed more broadly than the activator (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">3</xref>F). This distribution underlies long-range inhibitory interactions between neighboring dendrites. The interactions appeared to control whether or not dendrites would branch and in which direction dendrites would elongate. As a result, the branching frequency considerably varied among branchlets (compare yellow and blue arbors in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">3</xref>D), whereas the branch density was kept almost constant throughout the dendritic trees.</p><fig id="pcbi-0030212-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Distinctive Dendritic Patterns Obtained from the Computer Simulation of the Cell Compartment Model</title><p>(A–C) and (D–F) Two distinct patterns obtained by using different parameter values in the activator–suppressor model. Whole images of dendritic trees (A,D), magnified images of the activator (B,E) and those of the suppressor (C,F). Examples of branch-poor arbors and branch-rich arbors were indicated in yellow and blue, respectively, (A) and (D). Density of the activator is relatively high at the terminal of each branch (arrows in “B”). Alternatively, dendrites elongate as new spots are generated (arrows in “E”) and bifurcate as spots undergo fission (arrowheads in “E”). Parameter values were <italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic> = 0.9 and <italic>p<sub>e</sub></italic> = 6.5 (A–C) and <italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic> = 0.5 and <italic>p<sub>e</sub></italic> = 2.6 (D–F). Other parameters were <italic>p<sub>b</sub></italic> = 0.8, <italic>d</italic> = 30.0, <italic>p<sub>h</sub></italic> = 1.0, <italic>T<sub>r</sub></italic> = 1.0, A<sub>max</sub> = 30.0, <italic>R</italic> = 0.004, and <italic>γ</italic> = 625. The grid size is 800 × 800, <italic>dx</italic> = 0.02, and <italic>dt</italic> = 1 × 10<sup>−6</sup>.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g003" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><p>In a separately prepared manuscript, we addressed more biological issues such as tiling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g001">Figure 1</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g001">1</xref>B) and regeneration in response to branch severing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g001">Figure 1</xref>C). Branches of multiple neurons in our computer simulation, when they appeared in the same 2D space, avoided each other and accomplished tiling and isoneuronal avoidance. The neurons in our computer simulation were even able to reaccomplish tiling after local destruction of dendritic arbors exactly as <italic>Drosophila</italic> class IV da neurons do. Furthermore, modifications of our model enabled reproduction of a wide range of space-filling dendritic trees and even a non–space-filling type. Taken together, our model succeeded in qualitatively recapturing development of space-filling dendrites.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Typical Behaviors of <italic>u</italic> and <italic>v</italic> at the Branch Terminals</title><p>In the all cells examined, <italic>u</italic> and <italic>v</italic> exhibited a linear relationship at the growing tip of dendrite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g004">Figure 4</xref>A for smooth branches and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g004">Figure 4</xref>B for rugged ones). Starting from <italic>u</italic> = 0 at the distal margin of dendrite, <italic>u</italic> should increase with time and it is observed as spatial change in <italic>u</italic> from distal to more-proximal parts of dendritic terminals. In contrast, the spatial change in <italic>v</italic> cannot be explained by reaction dynamics: for instance, in a case of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g004">Figure 4</xref>A, <italic>u</italic> and <italic>v</italic> should increase and decrease, respectively, according to vector field. Nevertheless, the supply of the suppressor from proximal dendrites via its diffusion seems to counteract actions of reaction functions, resulting in the increase of <italic>v</italic> in the proximal direction. Thus, most likely diffusion plays an essential role in determining the dynamics of the suppressor at dendritic tips.</p><fig id="pcbi-0030212-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Typical Changes of <italic>u</italic> and <italic>v</italic> at the Tips of Branches</title><p>(A,B) Representative data of the values of <italic>u</italic> and <italic>v</italic> were indicated on the phase plane, where direction of dynamics and null-cline of <italic>u</italic> and <italic>v</italic> are also shown (“A” for the cell of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>A and “B” for that of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>D). The data is sampled in every grid from the branch terminals. <italic>v</italic> increases linearly with <italic>u</italic> from the cell boundary to the interior of the cell. Solid lines and dashed lines represent <italic>f</italic>(<italic>u</italic>,<italic>v</italic>) = 0 and <italic>g</italic>(<italic>u</italic>,<italic>v</italic>) = 0, respectively. We have found that an elongation speed is about twice slower in rugged dendrites than in well-aligned ones (compare <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi-0030212-sv001">Videos S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi-0030212-sv003">S3</xref>). The difference in the positioning of the <italic>u</italic> − <italic>v</italic> values relative to the isoclines may potentially explain the difference in a velocity of pattern formation (our unpublished data).</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g004" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Classical Turing Condition and Distinctive Dendritic Patterns</title><p>As described below, we conducted numerical analysis to examine the generality of our cell compartment model and to determine the conditions for growth of dendrites that could be common to various types of neurons.</p><p>We calculated the cell compartment model by using different parameter sets of reactions between the activator and the suppressor, and searched for those by which dendritic patterns were successfully generated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>A). We defined a dendritic pattern by the following two conditions: first, cellular extensions bifurcated. Second, the density of dendrites was less than a criteria value. Typical examples of patterns violating either of these conditions are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>B–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">5</xref>D. This analysis clearly shows that dendritic patterns could be generated in a large parameter region (closed circles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>A), and so formation of dendritic patterns in our model does not appear to depend on particular parameter sets.</p><fig id="pcbi-0030212-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Parameter-Dependency of the Pattern Formation</title><p>(A–D) Searches for parameter values for dendritic branch formation on a (<italic>p<sub>e</sub></italic> − <italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic>)-plane. The fixed parameters were <italic>p<sub>b</sub></italic> = 0.8, <italic>d</italic> = 30.0, <italic>p<sub>h</sub></italic> = 1.0, <italic>Tr</italic> = 1.0, <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> = 30.0, <italic>R</italic> = 0.004, and <italic>γ</italic> = 625. Total calculation time was 4 × 10<sup>5</sup> steps.</p><p>(A) Closed circle: dendritic pattern; square: wide branches; triangle: no second-order branching; and star: no growth. Examples of non-dendritic patterns of square, triangle, and star are shown in (B) (<italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic> = 2.1 and <italic>p<sub>e</sub></italic> = 8.0), (C) <italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic> = 0.5 and <italic>p<sub>e</sub></italic> = 4.0), and (D) (D (<italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic> = 0.7 and <italic>p<sub>e</sub></italic> = 6.5), respectively. Region I satisfies conditions of Turing diffusion-induced instability described by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ea006">Equations 6</xref>a–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ed006">6</xref>d, whereas region II satisfies <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ea006">Equations 6</xref>a–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ec006">6</xref>c, but not <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ed006">Equation 6</xref>d and region 0 satisfies <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-eb006">Equations 6</xref>b–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ed006">6</xref>d, but not <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ea006">Equation 6</xref>a. In region I, spatially periodic patterns appear in a conventional RD model, whereas homogenous patterns are stable in region II.</p><p>(E1–E4) Distributions of the activator that were obtained at different coordinates in the phase diagram (A). <italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic> = 0.7 for all panels; and <italic>p<sub>e</sub></italic> = 3.0 (E1), 3.5 (E2), 4.0 (E3), and 4.5 (E4). The distribution of the activator changes from a punctate pattern (E1) to a more continuous pattern (E4).</p><p>(E2) A punctate distribution of the activator in a branch-rich region (enclosed area at right) and a more continuous one in a branch-less region (enclosed area at left).</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g005" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><p>As explained before, our model produced two different types of patterns: the well-aligned smooth pattern, in which the activator is continuously distributed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>A) and the poorly aligned rugged pattern, in which punctate distribution of the activator is seen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>D). Those patterns shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref> are two extreme examples; and intermediate patterns could be generated, depending on parameters employed. Interestingly, our numerical analysis revealed a correlation between Turing instability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b023">23</xref>] and the distinctive shape of dendritic patterns. Turing instability, a widely applied theory of pattern formation, indicates an ability of chemical (in this case, activator–suppressor) interactions to develop spatially periodic patterns. The condition of chemical reaction dynamics for Turing instability was addressed by considering the two-variable (<italic>u</italic> and <italic>v</italic>) dynamics in the uncompartmentalized 2D space (designated as no compartment model, that is, a conventional RD model), and then by numerically calculating a parameter region for potential Turing instability in the no-compartment model (see Equations A3a–A3d in the section “Conditions for Turing diffusion-induced instability” and region I in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>A) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b026">26</xref>]. We used typical values for other parameters such as <italic>p<sub>b</sub></italic> because changing the <italic>p<sub>b</sub></italic> value did not significantly alter the shape or the size of region I (unpublished data). The results of this analysis clearly showed that relatively rugged patterns were obtained by using the condition that satisfied Turing instability (region I in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>A); on the other hand, better-aligned patterns were obtained by using the condition that did not satisfy it (region II in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>A). Therefore, it is suggested that the difference in two typical dendritic patterns obtained in our computer simulation stems from whether chemical dynamics in themselves are able to develop spatially periodic patterns or not.</p><p>Furthermore, we noticed that the shape of dendrites reflected the intracellular distribution of the activator. From bottom-left to top-right of the (<italic>p<sub>e</sub></italic> − <italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic>) space (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>A), the dendrite morphology became smoother; and distribution of the activator changed from punctate in nature to more continuous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>E1-5E4). Continuity in the activator distribution seems to strongly depend on the shape of local branches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>E2). Even within the same cell, the local distribution of the activator was punctate in branch-rich regions (e.g., right-enclosed branches in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>E2), whereas it was more continuous in branchless regions (e.g., left-enclosed branch in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>E2). Co-existence of two distinctive types of distributions, punctuate and continuous, in a single cell suggests that these two types of distributions are locally stable structures.</p><p>The above-mentioned analysis also indicated that the condition for developing dendritic patterns did not entirely cover region I. In addition, it is of particular interest that spatially non-homogeneous dendritic patterns were generated in region II, in which homogeneous distribution at the steady state should be stable in the two-variable (<italic>u</italic> and <italic>v</italic>) dynamics (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Discussion</xref> for details). Most likely this discrepancy of conditions for pattern formation in the cell compartment model and the no compartment one originates from the structure of cell and the feedback between the chemical reaction and cell growth in the model.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Conditions for Dendritic Patterning and those for Dot Pattern Generation</title><p>We further examined the relationship between our model and the Turing system. In general, the Turing system develops dot, stripe, or reverse-dot patterns in the 2D space, depending on parameters (e.g., the distance from the equilibrium point to the upper limitation of activator [<italic>A<sub>max</sub></italic>]) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b028">28</xref>]. So we explored whether or not the conditions for dendritic pattern formation were related to the property of the Turing system to generate either a dot, stripe, or reverse-dot pattern.</p><p>By changing the upper limitation of activator (<italic>A<sub>max</sub></italic>) in the no-compartment model, we drew a phase diagram, in which each dot, stripe, and reverse-dot pattern was mapped to a different parameter region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g006">Figure 6</xref>A). Subsequently we searched for parameter sets that developed dendritic patterns in the cell compartment model (circles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g006">Figure 6</xref>A); and the results of this analysis indicated that dendritic patterns were obtained mostly in the dot domain (D in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g006">Figure 6</xref>A). Therefore the punctate distribution of the activator in rugged dendrites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>E) can be interpreted as the typical dot pattern of the conventional RD system being generated inside of the cell compartment. Dendritic patterns were not obtained in most of the stripe or reverse-dot domains (S or R in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g006">Figure 6</xref>A). Computer simulation with parameter settings in the stripe or reverse-dot domains generated patterns, which did not resemble the shape of dendritic arbors of real neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g006">Figure 6</xref>B–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g006">6</xref>E). If conditions for Turing instability were not satisfied, dendritic pattern was produced in a parameter region adjacent to the dot domain. These results are consistent with an intuitive understanding of the process of dendritic pattern formation; that is, dendrites grow in pursuit of a track of locally activated molecular complexes for branching. In this sense, a punctate or terminally dense distribution of activator is favored, whereas the stripe or reverse-dot one is not.</p><fig id="pcbi-0030212-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Comparative Analysis of Conditions for Dendritic Pattern Formation and Those for Dot, Stripe, and Reverse-Dot Pattern Generation</title><p>(A) Condition of parameters for neuronal branching and Turing condition on a (<italic>p<sub>e</sub></italic> − <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub>)-plane. Simulations of the no-compartment model showed that dot, stripe, and reverse-dot domains are mapped to different parameter regions (D, S, and R, respectively); and dotted lines roughly represent boundaries between the domains. Closed circles: dendritic patterns obtained by our cell-compartment model. The fixed parameters were <italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic> = 0.7, <italic>p<sub>b</sub></italic> = 0.8, <italic>d</italic> = 30.0, <italic>p<sub>h</sub></italic> = 1.0, <italic>R</italic> = 0.004, and <italic>γ</italic> = 625. We used <italic>Tr</italic> = 0.95 (when <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> = 1.0), <italic>Tr</italic> = 0.85 (when <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> = 0.9), and <italic>Tr</italic> = 1.0 (otherwise). Total calculation time was 4 × 10<sup>5</sup> steps.</p><p>(B–E) Typical examples in the stripe domain (B,C): <italic>p<sub>e</sub></italic> = 4.0, <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> = 1.1, and <italic>Tr</italic> = 1.0, and in the reverse-dot domain (D,E): <italic>p<sub>e</sub></italic> = 3.6 and <italic>Tr</italic> = 0.95. Dendrites (B,D) and the distribution of the activator (C,E) are shown.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g006" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>An Analysis of Other Dynamics</title><p>It is worth evaluating whether the results of this study are specific to a particular dynamics or if they represent more general properties of the RD system. For that purpose, we tested several different forms of reaction terms and one of them was as given below:
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ea003"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ea003" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>&plus;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-eb003"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.eb003" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
				</p><p>Parameter settings for potential Turing instability in the linear dynamics described by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ea003">Equations 3</xref>a and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-eb003">3</xref>b were determined and plotted (region I in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g007">Figure 7</xref>A) as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>A.</p><fig id="pcbi-0030212-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Patterns Generated by the Linear Dynamics</title><p>(A) Region I indicates a parameter region on a (<italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic> − <italic>p<sub>b</sub></italic>)-plane that satisfies the classical Turing condition. <italic>p<sub>c</sub></italic> does not appear in the Turing condition. Region II is as described in the legend of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>.</p><p>(B,C) and (D,E) Examples of patterns generated in region II and region I, respectively. Magnified images of dendrites (B,D) and those of activator distributions (C,E). Parameter values were <italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic> = 0.5, <italic>p<sub>b</sub></italic> = 2.5, and <italic>p<sub>c</sub></italic> = 0.16 (B,C) and <italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic> = 0.6, <italic>p<sub>b</sub></italic> = 2.9, and <italic>p<sub>c</sub></italic> = 0.2 (D,E). Other parameters were the same as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>A, except for <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> = 10.0 and <italic>Tr</italic> = 0.75. Conditions of simulation were as described in the legend of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g007" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pcbi-0030212-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Two Distinctive Branching Patterns of Real Neurons</title><p>(A,B) Smooth and well-aligned type. A neuron in thalamic nuclei in monkey (A) and Purkinje cell at postnatal day 25 (B).</p><p>(C,D) Rugged and less-aligned type. A neuron of inferior olivary complex of monkey (C) and a remodeled class I da neuron at a pupal stage, which was visualized with <italic>ppk</italic>-<italic>GAL4 UAS-mCD8::GFP</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b049">49</xref>] (D). Images in (A and C) were taken from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b050">50</xref>].</p><p>(E) Quantification of DOB in the generated patterns in our computer simulation. Data are presented as the means ± SD. A single asterisk indicates <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 (<italic>t</italic>-test), and double asterisks indicate <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 (<italic>t</italic>-test).</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g008" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><p>Parameter dependency of dendritic pattern formation was examined, and we found that dendritic patterns were generated in both outside and inside of region I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g007">Figure 7</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g007">7</xref>D, respectively). Therefore, classical Turing conditions were not necessary or sufficient for dendritic pattern formation in this linear dynamics, either. Furthermore, whether the function was linear or non-linear, the activator distribution well-correlated with the shape of branches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g007">Figure 7</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g007">7</xref>E; compare them to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>E); and dendritic patterns were generated preferentially in the dot domain, but not in the stripe or reverse-dot domain (unpublished data). Collectively, all of the results suggest that a wide range of parameter settings and different dynamics of chemical reactants allow development of dendritic patterns in the cell compartment model.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Morphological Measures for Predicting In Vivo Distribution of the Activator</title><p>Finally we found that our cell compartment model provides a prediction for future experiments. As described before, the numerical simulation of the model unraveled a strong correlation between shapes of dendrite and distributions of the activator (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g005">Figure 5</xref>E and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g007">Figure 7</xref>E). We noticed that dendritic trees of some real neurons were reminiscent of those of the smooth type in our computer simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">Figure 8</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">8</xref>B) and that terminal branches of some other real neurons were less aligned (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">Figure 8</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">8</xref>D). Accordingly, if the developmental machinery proposed by this study is actually functioning in vivo, the intracellular distribution of the hypothetical activator could be predicted on the basis of the morphological features of dendrites. More specifically, the distribution of the activator may be terminally dense in neurons of the smooth type and punctate in the rugged type (for instance, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">Figure 8</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">8</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">Figure 8</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">8</xref>D, respectively).</p><p>To support the validity of our prediction, we set a quantitative measure called a “dispersion of orientation of branches” (DOB) to characterize dendrite morphology. DOB is the coefficient of variation of directions of branch segments in each local region of dendritic trees (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g009">Figure 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>); hence the smaller is the DOB, the better-aligned are the local branches. Quantification of the DOB for the smooth and rugged types of the obtained patterns in our computer simulation confirmed that it was significantly smaller in the former type (double asterisks in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">Figure 8</xref>E). We next quantified the DOB for real neurons and found that values for the smooth type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">Figure 8</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">8</xref>B) were significantly smaller than those for the less-aligned type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">Figure 8</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">8</xref>D; asterisks in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">Figure 8</xref>E). These results suggest that geometry of real neurons may also be characterized by DOB and that we can use DOB as a morphological measure for predicting the intracellular distribution of the activator in vivo.</p><fig id="pcbi-0030212-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Procedures for Quantification of DOB</title><p>Step 1: Skeletonize images with ImageJ. Step 2: Crop four pairs of squares. Step 3: Approximate each dendritic segment between the two branching points by a line segment connecting those points. Measure the angle of a branch segment with respect to the horizontal direction. Repeat measurement for all segments in each local area and calculate the coefficient of variation, DOB.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.g009" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Self-organizing Mechanism in Dendrite Pattern Formation</title><p>In this study, we developed the first mathematical model that sheds light on autonomous pattern formation of neuronal dendrites. The cell compartment model, which is based on the experimentally verified dendro-dendritic interaction, autonomously develops dendritic elongation and branching. It should be noted that dendritic patterns are defined not only by the numerical parameters such as the terminal number, but also by other properties such as mutual avoidance. Our model places emphasis on the latter aspects of the space-filling dendrites, which are difficult to characterize by quantitative measures, and indeed qualitatively recaptures developmental regulation of the space-filling dendritic patterns. Collectively, we believe that this study offers a new concept in developmental biology, a self-organizing mechanism in neuronal dendrite pattern formation.</p><p>Many of the previous models assumed that elongation and branching of dendrites are controlled by probability functions, in which each parameter separately codes individual growth rules such as degree- or segment length- dependent rate of elongation and/or branching [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b019">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b020">20</xref>]. In contrast, dendritic patterns are autonomously generated without embedding different parameters to control each branching frequency, branch angle, and self-avoidance of dendrites in our model. Considering that we are presently far from understanding the entirety of the molecular mechanisms of chemical reactions occurring in vivo, the high performance of the proposed system obtained with diverse forms of reaction function takes on significance, because it may support a future application of the model to the dendritogenesis of a whole variety of real neurons.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Instability of Chemical Dynamics and That of Cell Boundary Contribute to Dendritic Pattern Formation</title><p>Our numerical analysis showed that generation of dot patterns of the activator in rugged dendrites could be attributed to a property of chemical dynamics, which is supported by Turing instability. On the other hand, classical Turing diffusion-induced instability alone cannot give us a comprehensive explanation of the pattern formation in our model, because dendritic patterns were successfully developed even when the spatially homogeneous pattern at the steady state of chemical reaction dynamics was stable. We think that the compartmentalized structure in our model may increase instability of the dynamics of the cell growth. Actually, it was shown both in experiments and in computer simulation that a straight interface could become unstable to make complex spatial patterns in certain bistable dynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b027">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b029">29</xref>]. Hence, analyzing the model based on the idea of front instability may be one way to understand the behavior of our model. From a viewpoint of experimental biology, these results suggest that simultaneous, high-resolution imaging analyses on molecular interactions and plasma membrane dynamics would be informative.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Distribution of the Activator In Vivo</title><p>We introduced new criteria to categorize patterns of dendrites in real neurons and to predict the intracellular distribution of potential molecular complexes for dendrite growth. Two distinctive dendritic patterns were found in both computer-simulated and real neurons, and it is suggested that the distribution of the activator is characteristic of the shape of branches. Further advances in our understanding of the molecular mechanisms involved in dendrite development are required to address whether the prediction from our cell compartment model is valid or not. Yet, there are a couple of interesting observations that may indicate periodicity in dendrites of real neurons. For instance, Golgi apparatus is distributed in a punctate manner in da neurons and pyramidal neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b030">30</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b032">32</xref>]; and its localizations at branch points are important for branch formation. In addition, staining for microtubule-associated protein 2 in the absence of detergents reveals that regions of high signal intensity are found in a spatially periodic manner along dendrites and that dendritic branch points are preferentially associated with these regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b033">33</xref>]. It would be interesting to review these observations in the perspective of our model.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Enlarged Editions of the Cell Compartment Model</title><p>Our cell compartment model is a simplified version of dendrite growth in vivo, and new elements can be installed depending on needs or researchers' interests. For instance, although generated patterns in the present model are highly homogeneous, less homogeneous patterns could be obtained if stochastic aspects or noise are strengthened (for example, by fluctuating <italic>Tr</italic> along dendritic branches). It is also interesting to extend our model to include activity-dependent processes, such as synaptotropic dendrite growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b034">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b035">35</xref>] and refinement of pre-existing branches during late stages of development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b036">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b037">37</xref>]. Furthermore, we are now trying to reproduce development of non–space-filling type dendrites, which are anisotropic in terms of the direction of elongation and inhomogeneous in terms of coverage of a field, by incorporating a guidance mechanism and/or an RD system of intracellular activator and suppressor. Although we should bear in mind that overlaying these additional features could modify the properties of the system, we hope that combination of biochemical experiments with enlarged editions of this mathematical model may clarify the comprehensive logic underlying neuronal dendrite development.</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Insights to Other Types of Branching Morphogenesis</title><p>Colony formation by <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus subtilis</named-content> is a well-known example of dendritic patterning in biology. <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus subtilis</named-content> generates distinctive colony patterns depending on the substrate softness and nutrient concentration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b038">38</xref>], and formation of most of the colony patterns was well-reproduced by RD models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b039">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b040">40</xref>] and a cell automaton model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b041">41</xref>]. Similarity between neuronal dendrites and bacteria colonies is found not only in terms of their morphology, but also with respect to repulsive behaviors; i.e., when two colonies are in close proximity, they avoid each other just as do space-filling neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b042">42</xref>]. In addition, interesting parallels can be also found between dendrite development and other branching morphogenesis such as coral [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b043">43</xref>], vertebrate lung [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b044">44</xref>], and trachea of <italic>Drosophila</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b045">45</xref>]. These systems accomplish physiological functions that can be regarded as similar to space-filling dendrites. For instance, trachea must elaborate its branches to deliver oxygen to the whole body. Mathematical models for these pattern formations have been proposed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b043">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b044">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b046">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b047">47</xref>], and it is suggested that branching morphogenesis in general can be understood as the following: a part of the structure that happens to sprout due to some fluctuation locally speeds up its growth and eventually develops a visible branch. We observed a similar behavior of dendrites in our computer simulation. Furthermore, recent works revealed the molecular basis of lateral inhibition between the neighboring lung epithelium and between growing tips of trachea that may correspond to long-range inhibitory dendro-dendritic interactions in the development of space-filling dendrites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b044">44</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b046">46</xref>]. Therefore, our model on neurite formation would be potentially informative in understanding the above-mentioned branching morphogenesis.</p><p>Despite the afore-mentioned similarities, there is one big difference between bacteria colony models and ours. The former relies on non-linearity in diffusion and reaction function for pattern formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b039">39</xref>]. On the other hands, dendritc growth in our model does not require such non-linearity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g007">Figure 7</xref>). It might be that unambiguous boundary of the cell in our model plays an equivalent role to non-linear diffusion terms in bacteria colony models. Taking advantage of the fewer constraints in chemical dynamics in our model, we addressed the relationship between Turing instability and biological branching morphogenesis. Other branching morphogenesis might obey the conditions that were clarified in this study. Again, generality of the proposed mechanism would be significant for testing this possibility in other systems of interest.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Numerical analysis.</title><p>To calculate the model, we used the finite difference method, a simple explicit scheme. The simulation starts from a small cell body. The initial value of the activator is 0.5± small random deviations in each position inside of the cell body and 0 in other places, whereas the value of the suppressor is 0.1± small random deviations in the cell body and 0 otherwise. Changes in initial conditions of the activator or the suppressor affected the results only slightly. Small noise was added to the diffusion coefficient of the activator in every calculation step to cancel the anisotropy of the grid in numerical simulation.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Quantification of dispersion of orientation of branches.</title><p>Image processing and measurement were done with ImageJ. First, we superimposed a square on individual dendritic trees (those in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">3</xref>D and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">Figure 8</xref>A–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">8</xref>D; see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g009">Figure 9</xref>). The size of each square was normalized to that of the entire dendritic tree (the size of the tree was defined as that of a polygon connecting dendritic tips). As for the obtained patterns in computer simulation (those in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">3</xref>D), we skeletonized them and sampled four pairs of squares that were located at the same coordinates (“1” and “2” in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g009">Figure 9</xref>). Each branch segment was approximated by a line segment connecting two edges of the branch segment (“3” in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g009">Figure 9</xref>). We measured the angle of the line segment with respect to the horizontal direction, repeated measurement for all segments in each small square, and calculated the coefficient of variation, which we called the DOB. Average values of DOB for each dendritic tree are shown with means ± SD in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g008">Figure 8</xref>E.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Imaging collection of Dendritic trees.</title><p>Imaging and single cell labeling of <italic>Drosophila</italic> sensory neurons were done as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b013">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b048">48</xref>]. Strains used were <italic>NP7028 UAS-mCD8::GFP</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b011">11</xref>], <italic>ppk</italic>-<italic>GAL4 UAS-mCD8::GFP</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b049">49</xref>], <italic>elav-GAL4 UAS-mCD8::GFP hsFLP</italic>, <italic>tub-Gal80 FRT40A</italic>, and <italic>FRT40A</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b013">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Original equations.</title><p>Original equations of the activator-suppressor model were as follows:
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ea004"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ea004" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>&Delta;</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>&plus;</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>&Omega;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-eb004"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.eb004" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>&Delta;</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>&plus;</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:mi>&Omega;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ec004"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ec004" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="3pt"/><mml:mi>&Omega;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>where <italic>u</italic> and <italic>v</italic> are the concentration of the activator and that of the suppressor, respectively. <italic>d<sub>u</sub></italic> and <italic>d<sub>v</sub></italic> are diffusion coefficients. Original chemical reaction terms were:
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ea005"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ea005" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>&plus;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-eb005"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.eb005" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&equals;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
				</p><p>We non-dimensionalized <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ea004">Equations 4</xref>a–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ec004">4</xref>c and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ea005">Equations 5</xref>a–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-eb005">5</xref>b to obtain <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ea001">Equations 1</xref>a–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ec001">1</xref>c and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ea002">Equations 2</xref>a–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-eb002">2</xref>b.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><italic>R</italic> value.</title><p>The value of <italic>R</italic> determines the thickness of the branches as expected. Smaller <italic>R</italic> resulted in thinner branches, thus finer patterns. However, there seems to be a minimum value of <italic>R</italic> to support dendrite growth. The minimum value may be necessary to produce a new spot of the activator, which is separated from the pre-existing spot, in the vicinity of the cell boundary. We confirmed that the minimum value of <italic>R</italic> was independent of the spatial grid size in numerical simulation, and thus the above results are not an artifact of numerical simulation. So we used <italic>R</italic> = 0.004, which gave the finest dendritic patterns (<italic>R</italic> = 0.0041 yielded nearly equal results to those obtained with <italic>R</italic> = 0.004).</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Conditions for Turing diffusion-induced instability.</title><p>Conditions for Turing diffusion-induced instability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b023">23</xref>] are the following:
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ea006"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ea006" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&plus;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-eb006"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.eb006" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ec006"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ec006" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&plus;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>
					<disp-formula id="pcbi-0030212-ed006"><graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.ed006" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <mml:math display='block'><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&plus;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&minus;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&part;</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math> --></disp-formula>where the partial derivatives of <italic>f</italic> and <italic>g</italic> are evaluated at the steady state (<italic>u</italic><sub>0</sub>,<italic>v</italic><sub>0</sub>) which satisfies f(<italic>u</italic><sub>0</sub>,<italic>v</italic><sub>0</sub>) = 0 and g(<italic>u</italic><sub>0</sub>,<italic>v</italic><sub>0</sub>) = 0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0030212-b026">26</xref>]. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ea006">Equations 6</xref>a and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-eb006">6</xref>b describe conditions for a stable equilibrium point in the absence of diffusion. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ec006">Equations 6</xref>c and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi-0030212-ed006">6</xref>d describe conditions for an unstable periodic solution in the presence of diffusion.
				</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material id="pcbi-0030212-sv001" mimetype="video/quicktime" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.sv001" xlink:type="simple"><label>Video S1</label><caption><title>Formation of a Well-Aligned Dendritic Pattern</title><p>One frame of this movie is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>A.</p><p>(84 KB MOV)</p></caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi-0030212-sv002" mimetype="video/quicktime" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.sv002" xlink:type="simple"><label>Video S2</label><caption><title>Continuous, but Terminally Enriched Distribution of the Activator During Dendritic Growth Shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi-0030212-sv001">Video S1</xref></title><p>Five frames of this movie are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>B.</p><p>(24 KB MOV)</p></caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi-0030212-sv003" mimetype="video/quicktime" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.sv003" xlink:type="simple"><label>Video S3</label><caption><title>Formation of a Rugged Dendritic Pattern</title><p>One frame of this movie is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>D.</p><p>(189 KB MOV)</p></caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi-0030212-sv004" mimetype="video/quicktime" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030212.sv004" xlink:type="simple"><label>Video S4</label><caption><title>Punctate Distribution of the Activator During Dendritic Growth Shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi-0030212-sv003">Video S3</xref></title><p>Five frames of this movie are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-0030212-g003">Figure 3</xref>E.</p><p>(71 KB MOV)</p></caption></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Mineko Kengaku (RIKEN BSI, Japan) for generously providing the image of a Purkinje cell and to Azusa Fujimoto for the image of a pupal sensory neuron. We thank Shuji Ishihara for comments on the manuscript, and Kei Ito, Takashi Shimada and Hisao Honda for encouraging discussion at initial phases of this project.</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>da</term><def><p>dendritic arborization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DOB</term><def><p>dispersion of orientation of branches</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Häusser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2003</year>
					<article-title>Dendrites: bug or feature?</article-title>
					<source>Curr Opin Neurobiol</source>
					<volume>13</volume>
					<fpage>372</fpage>
					<lpage>383</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2003</year>
					<article-title>The control of dendrite development.</article-title>
					<source>Neuron</source>
					<volume>40</volume>
					<fpage>229</fpage>
					<lpage>242</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>London</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Häusser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Dendritic computation.</article-title>
					<source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>
					<volume>28</volume>
					<fpage>503</fpage>
					<lpage>532</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2001</year>
					<article-title>How do dendrites take their shape?</article-title>
					<source>Nat Neurosci</source>
					<volume>4</volume>
					<fpage>359</fpage>
					<lpage>365</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitford</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkhuizen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polleux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2002</year>
					<article-title>Molecular control of cortical dendrite development.</article-title>
					<source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>
					<volume>25</volume>
					<fpage>127</fpage>
					<lpage>149</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landgraf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evers</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Control of dendritic diversity.</article-title>
					<source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source>
					<volume>17</volume>
					<fpage>690</fpage>
					<lpage>696</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiala</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1999</year>
					<article-title>Dendrite structure.</article-title>
					<comment>In:</comment>
					<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spruston</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Häusser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
					<source>Dendrites</source>
					<publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
					<fpage>1</fpage>
					<lpage>34</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masland</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2001</year>
					<article-title>The fundamental plan of the retina.</article-title>
					<source>Nat Neurosci</source>
					<volume>4</volume>
					<fpage>877</fpage>
					<lpage>886</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sagasti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guido</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raible</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schier</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Repulsive interactions shape the morphologies and functional arrangement of zebrafish peripheral sensory arbors.</article-title>
					<source>Curr Biol</source>
					<volume>15</volume>
					<fpage>804</fpage>
					<lpage>814</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapfhammer</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>Cellular and molecular control of dendritic growth and development of cerebellar Purkinje cells.</article-title>
					<source>Prog Histochem Cytochem</source>
					<volume>39</volume>
					<fpage>131</fpage>
					<lpage>182</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2003</year>
					<article-title>Distinct developmental modes and lesion-induced reactions of dendrites of two classes of Drosophila sensory neurons.</article-title>
					<source>J Neurosci</source>
					<volume>23</volume>
					<fpage>3752</fpage>
					<lpage>3760</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>Development of morphological diversity of dendrites in Drosophila by the BTB-zinc finger protein abrupt.</article-title>
					<source>Neuron</source>
					<volume>43</volume>
					<fpage>809</fpage>
					<lpage>822</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grueber</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2002</year>
					<article-title>Tiling of the Drosophila epidermis by multidendritic sensory neurons.</article-title>
					<source>Development</source>
					<volume>129</volume>
					<fpage>2867</fpage>
					<lpage>2878</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grueber</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2003</year>
					<article-title>Dendrites of distinct classes of Drosophila sensory neurons show different capacities for homotypic repulsion.</article-title>
					<source>Curr Biol</source>
					<volume>13</volume>
					<fpage>618</fpage>
					<lpage>626</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wässle</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peichl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boycott</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1981</year>
					<article-title>Dendritic territories of cat retinal ganglion cells.</article-title>
					<source>Nature</source>
					<volume>292</volume>
					<fpage>344</fpage>
					<lpage>345</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grueber</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>Control of dendritic branching and tiling by the Tricornered-kinase/Furry signaling pathway in Drosophila sensory neurons.</article-title>
					<source>Cell</source>
					<volume>119</volume>
					<fpage>245</fpage>
					<lpage>256</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1982</year>
					<article-title>Evidence for dendritic competition in the developing retina.</article-title>
					<source>Nature</source>
					<volume>297</volume>
					<fpage>683</fpage>
					<lpage>685</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macagno</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1995</year>
					<article-title>Interactions between segmental homologs and between isoneuronal branches guide the formation of sensory terminal fields.</article-title>
					<source>J Neurosci</source>
					<volume>15</volume>
					<fpage>3243</fpage>
					<lpage>3253</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowakowski</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1992</year>
					<article-title>Competitive interactions during dendritic growth: a simple stochastic growth algorithm.</article-title>
					<source>Brain Res</source>
					<volume>576</volume>
					<fpage>152</fpage>
					<lpage>156</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b020"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Pelt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dityatev</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uylings</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1997</year>
					<article-title>Natural variability in the number of dendritic segments: model-based inferences about branching during neurite outgrowth.</article-title>
					<source>J Comp Neurol</source>
					<volume>387</volume>
					<fpage>325</fpage>
					<lpage>340</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b021"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Pelt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>JBP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uylings</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2003</year>
					<article-title>Formation of dendritic branching patterns.</article-title>
					<comment>In:</comment>
					<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Ooyen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
					<source>Modeling Neural Development</source>
					<publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>
					<fpage>75</fpage>
					<lpage>94</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b022"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samsonovich</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ascoli</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Statistical determinants of dendritic morphology in hippocampal pyramidal neurons: A hidden Markov model.</article-title>
					<source>Hippocampus</source>
					<volume>15</volume>
					<fpage>166</fpage>
					<lpage>183</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b023"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turing</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1952</year>
					<article-title>The chemical basis of morphogenesis.</article-title>
					<source>Phil Trans R Soc Lond B</source>
					<volume>237</volume>
					<fpage>37</fpage>
					<lpage>72</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b024"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gierer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinhardt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1972</year>
					<article-title>A theory of biological pattern formation.</article-title>
					<source>Kybernetik</source>
					<volume>12</volume>
					<fpage>30</fpage>
					<lpage>39</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b025"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steward</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2003</year>
					<article-title>Compartmentalized synthesis and degradation of proteins in neurons.</article-title>
					<source>Neuron</source>
					<volume>40</volume>
					<fpage>347</fpage>
					<lpage>359</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b026"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1989</year>
					<source>Mathematical biology</source>
					<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>Springer–Verlag</publisher-name>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b027"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1993</year>
					<article-title>Modeling and numerical simulations of dendritic crystal-growth.</article-title>
					<source>Physica D</source>
					<volume>63</volume>
					<fpage>410</fpage>
					<lpage>423</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b028"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2003</year>
					<article-title>Stripes, spots, or reversed spots in two-dimensional Turing systems.</article-title>
					<source>J Theor Biol</source>
					<volume>224</volume>
					<fpage>339</fpage>
					<lpage>350</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b029"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mccormick</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swinney</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1993</year>
					<article-title>Pattern-formation by interacting chemical fronts.</article-title>
					<source>Science</source>
					<volume>261</volume>
					<fpage>192</fpage>
					<lpage>194</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b030"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2007</year>
					<article-title>The secretory pathway and neuron polarization.</article-title>
					<source>J Neurosci</source>
					<volume>26</volume>
					<fpage>10631</fpage>
					<lpage>10632</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b031"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>Secretory trafficking in neuronal dendrites.</article-title>
					<source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
					<volume>6</volume>
					<fpage>585</fpage>
					<lpage>591</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b032"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Racz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monson</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Polarized secretory trafficking directs cargo for asymmetric dendrite growth and morphogenesis.</article-title>
					<source>Neuron</source>
					<volume>48</volume>
					<fpage>757</fpage>
					<lpage>771</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b033"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fallon</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Dendrites contain a spacing pattern.</article-title>
					<source>J Neurosci</source>
					<volume>26</volume>
					<fpage>1154</fpage>
					<lpage>1163</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b034"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>In vivo imaging of synapse formation on a growing dendritic arbor.</article-title>
					<source>Nat Neurosci</source>
					<volume>7</volume>
					<fpage>254</fpage>
					<lpage>260</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b035"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Theoretical analysis of a synaptotropic dendrite growth mechanism.</article-title>
					<source>J Theor Biol</source>
					<volume>241</volume>
					<fpage>39</fpage>
					<lpage>48</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b036"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Regulation of dendritic development by neuronal activity.</article-title>
					<source>J Neurobiol</source>
					<volume>64</volume>
					<fpage>4</fpage>
					<lpage>10</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b037"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Ooyen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Pelt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corner</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kater</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2003</year>
					<article-title>Activity-dependent neurite outgrowth: Implications for network development and neuronal morphology.</article-title>
					<comment>In:</comment>
					<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Ooyen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
					<source>Modeling neural development</source>
					<publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>
					<fpage>111</fpage>
					<lpage>132</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b038"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakahara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsushita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1994</year>
					<article-title>Experimental investigation on the validity of population-dynamics approach to bacterial colony formation.</article-title>
					<source>J Phys Soc Japan</source>
					<volume>63</volume>
					<fpage>1205</fpage>
					<lpage>1211</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b039"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsushita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Umeda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shigesada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1997</year>
					<article-title>Modeling spatio-temporal patterns generated by Bacillus subtilis.</article-title>
					<source>J Theor Biol</source>
					<volume>188</volume>
					<fpage>177</fpage>
					<lpage>185</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b040"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsushita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2000</year>
					<article-title>Reaction-diffusion modelling of bacterial colony patterns.</article-title>
					<source>Physica a-Stat Mech Appl</source>
					<volume>282</volume>
					<fpage>283</fpage>
					<lpage>303</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b041"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Jacob</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schochet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tenenbaum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czirók</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>1994</year>
					<article-title>Generic modelling of cooperative growth patterns in bacterial colonies.</article-title>
					<source>Nature</source>
					<volume>368</volume>
					<fpage>46</fpage>
					<lpage>49</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b042"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsushita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1991</year>
					<article-title>Bacterial fractal growth in the concentration field of nutrient.</article-title>
					<source>J Phys Soc Japan</source>
					<volume>60</volume>
					<fpage>88</fpage>
					<lpage>94</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b043"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaandorp</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuebler</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2001</year>
					<source>The algorithmic beauty of seaweeds, sponges and corals</source>
					<publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b044"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiota</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2002</year>
					<article-title>Depletion of FGF acts as a lateral inhibitory factor in lung branching morphogenesis in vitro.</article-title>
					<source>Mech Dev</source>
					<volume>116</volume>
					<fpage>29</fpage>
					<lpage>38</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b045"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikeya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1999</year>
					<article-title>Interplay of Notch and FGF signaling restricts cell fate and MAPK activation in the Drosophila trachea.</article-title>
					<source>Development</source>
					<volume>126</volume>
					<fpage>4455</fpage>
					<lpage>4463</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b046"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Modelling in vitro lung branching morphogenesis during development.</article-title>
					<source>J Theor Biol</source>
					<volume>242</volume>
					<fpage>862</fpage>
					<lpage>872</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b047"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Epithelial morphogenesis: Branching.</article-title>
					<comment>In:</comment>
					<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
					<source>Mechanisms of morphogenesis</source>
					<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>Elsevier Academic Press</publisher-name>
					<fpage>259</fpage>
					<lpage>287</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b048"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Truman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>Mechanisms of dendritic elaboration of sensory neurons in Drosophila: Insights from in vivo time lapse.</article-title>
					<source>J Neurosci</source>
					<volume>24</volume>
					<fpage>1541</fpage>
					<lpage>1550</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b049"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Usui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsubouchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Potential dual molecular interaction of the Drosophila 7-pass transmembrane cadherin Flamingo in dendritic morphogenesis.</article-title>
					<source>J Cell Sci</source>
					<volume>119</volume>
					<fpage>1118</fpage>
					<lpage>1129</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0030212-b050"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1983</year>
					<source>Human neuroanatomy</source>
					<publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>Lippincott Williams and Wilkins</publisher-name>
				</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>