<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-10-01304</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015953</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anatomy and physiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Musculoskeletal system</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Biomechanics</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Bone and joint mechanics</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Muscle</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Muscle functions</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Exertion</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biophysics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biomechanics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anatomy and physiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Musculoskeletal system</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Biomechanics</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Bone and joint mechanics</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Muscle</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Muscle functions</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Exertion</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Physiological processes</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Aging</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Sports and exercise medicine</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Physiology</subject>
          <subject>Biophysics</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Contractile and Elastic Ankle Joint Muscular Properties in Young and Older Adults</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Ankle Muscular Properties and Aging</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hasson</surname>
            <given-names>Christopher J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
            <sup>¤</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            <given-names>Ross H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Caldwell</surname>
            <given-names>Graham E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">          <addr-line>Biomechanics Laboratory, Department of Kinesiology, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Amherst, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Nogales-Gadea</surname>
            <given-names>Gisela</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University Hospital Vall d'Hebron, Spain</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">cjhasson@neu.edu</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CJH RHM GEC. Performed the experiments: CJH RHM. Analyzed the data: CJH RHM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: GEC. Wrote the paper: CJH RHM GEC.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="fn1">
          <label>¤</label>
          <p>Current address: Department of Biology, Northeastern University, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e15953</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hasson et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>The purpose of this study was to investigate age-related differences in contractile and elastic properties of both dorsi- (DF) and plantarflexor (PF) muscles controlling the ankle joint in young and older adults. Experimental data were collected while twelve young and twelve older male and female participants performed maximal effort isometric and isovelocity contractions on a dynamometer. Equations were fit to the data to give torque-angle (<italic>Tθ</italic>) and torque-angular velocity (<italic>Tω</italic>) relations. Muscle series-elasticity was measured during ramped dynamometer contractions using ultrasonography to measure aponeurosis extension as a function of torque; second order polynomials were used to characterize the torque-extension (<italic>TΔL</italic>) relation. The results showed no age differences in DF maximal torque and none for female PF; however, older males had smaller maximal PF torques compared to young males. In both muscle groups and genders, older adults had decreased concentric force capabilities. Both DF and PF <italic>TΔL</italic> relations were more nonlinear in the older adults. Older PF, but not DF muscles, were stiffer compared to young. A simple antagonism model suggested age-related differences in <italic>Tθ</italic> and <italic>Tω</italic> relations would be magnified if antagonistic torque contributions were included. This assessment of static, dynamic, and elastic joint properties affords a comprehensive view of age-related modifications in muscle function. Although many clinical studies use maximal isometric strength as a marker of functional ability, the results demonstrate that there are also significant age-related modifications in ankle muscle dynamic and elastic properties.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Funded by National Institutes of Health Grant R03AG026281. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The functional capabilities of the dorsi- (DF) and plantarflexor (PF) muscles controlling the ankle joint are important in many activities of daily living. Age-related degradations of muscular properties such as a decline in maximal isometric ankle torque can impact these activities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Vandervoort1">[1]</xref>. However, maximal isometric torque capability is only one of several joint properties that may change with advancing age. Ankle torque production also depends on the joint position or angle (the torque-angle relation; <italic>Tθ</italic>), the joint angular velocity (the torque-angular velocity relation; <italic>Tω</italic>), and the series elasticity (the torque-extension relation; <italic>TΔL</italic>) of the muscles crossing the joint. Together, these three relations reflect the active contractile and elastic properties of the muscles controlling the ankle joint.</p>
      <p>To date, studies investigating age-related changes in DF and PF joint <italic>Tθ</italic> relations have produced equivocal results. Lanza et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Lanza1">[2]</xref> have reported an angle-dependent decrease in torque for older adults; however, this might simply be due to their decreased range of motion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Lanza1">[2]</xref>. Other studies have found no <italic>Tθ</italic> changes for DF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-vanSchaik1">[3]</xref> or PF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Winegard1">[4]</xref>. Studies on the <italic>Tω</italic> relation have generally shown reduced torque capability for concentric velocities for older DF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Lanza1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Thelen1">[5]</xref> and PF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Thelen1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Thom1">[6]</xref> muscles, but some have found that eccentric torque production is preserved in older adults <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Porter1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Porter2">[8]</xref>. Technical aspects of <italic>Tω</italic> determination may play a role in variations between studies. Many studies select the peak torque values generated at a range of joint angular velocities, and scale the data to the maximal value of the isometric <italic>Tθ</italic> curve <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Thelen1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Klass1">[9]</xref>. However, these peak torque data points may occur at different joint angles, therefore appropriate adjustments should be made to account for the shape of the underlying <italic>Tθ</italic> relation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Caldwell1">[10]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Although the <italic>Tθ</italic> and <italic>Tω</italic> relations reflect the force-length <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Gordon1">[11]</xref> and force-velocity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Hill1">[12]</xref> relations of human muscle, the exact relation between joint and muscle properties also depends on the stiffness of the muscular series elastic elements, which are characterized by the <italic>TΔL</italic> relation. Studies on DF stiffness are scarce, while PF stiffness findings are equivocal. Quick-release studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Ochala1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Ochala2">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Blanpied1">[15]</xref> suggest an increase in PF stiffness with age, but an ultrasonography study showed a decrease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Onambele1">[16]</xref>. This inconsistency may be due to measurement methods; the quick-release technique measures total muscle-tendon stiffness (<italic>K<sub>MT</sub></italic>, including external tendon, aponeurosis, and within sarcomeres), while the ultrasonography study measured the stiffness of the external tendon <italic>K<sub>ET</sub></italic>. Animal studies have indicated that <italic>K<sub>ET</sub></italic> is greater than stiffness of the aponeurosis <italic>K<sub>AP</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Lieber1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-DelgadoLezama1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Ettema1">[19]</xref>; although see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Scott1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Muramatsu1">[21]</xref>), so greater <italic>K<sub>MT</sub></italic> in older adults could result from an increase in <italic>K<sub>AP</sub></italic>, which can be measured in humans using ultrasonography.</p>
      <p>It is important to recognize that the joint <italic>Tθ</italic>, <italic>Tω</italic>, and <italic>TΔL</italic> relations are closely intertwined, and that age-related changes in series elasticity may occur in tandem with <italic>Tθ</italic> and <italic>Tω</italic> modifications, thereby complicating interpretations based on <italic>Tθ</italic> and/or <italic>Tω</italic> measurements alone. The <italic>Tθ</italic> relation affects the shape of the <italic>Tω</italic> relation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Bobbert1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Taylor1">[23]</xref>, and series elastic stiffness (<italic>TΔL</italic>) influences muscle fiber length and velocity, altering the shapes of the <italic>Tθ</italic> and <italic>Tω</italic> relations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Kawakami1">[24]</xref>. Therefore, measuring <italic>Tθ</italic> and <italic>Tω</italic> characteristics in parallel with the <italic>TΔL</italic> relation may offer additional insight into age-related differences in functional capability.</p>
      <p>Accordingly, the purpose of this study was to investigate age-related differences in static (<italic>Tθ</italic>), dynamic (<italic>Tω</italic>), and elastic (<italic>TΔL</italic>) characteristics of both dorsi- (DF) and plantarflexor (PF) muscles controlling the ankle joint in young and older adults. Based on evidence from previous studies, we anticipated that active community dwelling older adults would have smaller isometric torque capacities, slower concentric muscular properties (i.e. less torque at a given velocity on the <italic>Tω</italic> relation), and stiffer series elasticity in the aponeurosis <italic>TΔL</italic> relation when compared to active young adults. We also expected to find greater age-related differences for the PF muscle group than in the DF, based on more atrophy of Type II fibers in the gastrocnemius <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Coggan1">[25]</xref>. Measuring all three <italic>Tθ</italic>, <italic>Tω</italic>, and <italic>TΔL</italic> properties in the DF and PF antagonist muscle groups provided a comprehensive snapshot of age-related differences in ankle joint function.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p>Twelve young and twelve older independent community-dwelling adults without musculoskeletal or neurological impairments participated in the study (balanced for gender, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015953-t001">Table 1</xref>). Physician's clearance was obtained for all older subjects. Prior to participating, subjects read and signed an informed consent document approved by the University of Massachusetts Amherst Institutional Review Board. Subjects performed two experimental protocols, with all measurements taken on the left leg.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0015953-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
          <title>Subject characteristics.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0015953-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Subject Group</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Age (yrs)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Height (m)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mass (kg)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean±SD</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean±SD</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean±SD</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range</td>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Young Male</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27±3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21–30</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.81±0.06</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.70–1.85</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.9±8.2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.3–87.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Young Female</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26±3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21–31</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.65±0.08</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.52–1.74</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.2±6.6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.9–65.8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Older Male</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73±5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67–79</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.77±0.08</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.68–1.88</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91.7±10.3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.0–102</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Older Female</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70±5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66–78</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.66±0.09</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.60–1.70</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.6 ±17.0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.3–77.4</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label/>
            <p>N =  number of subjects; SD =  between-subjects standard deviation.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Torque-Angle (<italic>Tθ</italic>) and Torque-Angular Velocity (<italic>Tω</italic>) Measurements</title>
        <sec id="s2a1">
          <title>Experimental Setup</title>
          <p>To measure the <italic>Tθ</italic> and <italic>Tω</italic> relations, a series of isometric and isovelocity muscular efforts were performed on a Biodex System 3 dynamometer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Drouin1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Taylor2">[27]</xref> (Biodex Medical Systems, Shirley, NY). Ankle torque and angular displacement were sampled from the dynamometer at 1000 Hz and 16-bit resolution with software written in Visual Basic 6.0 (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2a2">
          <title>Protocol</title>
          <p>Subjects sat upright with their trunk inclined backwards 45° from the vertical and arms crossed in front of their chest. After sub-maximal warm-up efforts, passive joint torque was measured by having the dynamometer slowly (20°/s) move the ankle joint through its range of motion without active subject resistance. Isometric (<italic>Tθ</italic>) and isovelocity (<italic>Tω</italic>) dynamometer trials were done on separate days to minimize fatigue. Two trials were performed at each joint angle (<italic>θ</italic>) and angular velocity (<italic>ω</italic>), with trial order randomized and a one-minute rest between trials. The knee remained fixed at 100° for DF and 90° for PF. For isometric trials the ankle position was varied at five different angles evenly spaced throughout each subject's full range of motion. Concentric isovelocity trials were performed at 20°/s, and from 30 to 240°/s in 30°/s increments. Eccentric trials were performed at −150, −60, and −30°/s. In all trials, passive elastic, gravitational, and inertial torque contributions were assessed to calculate the active muscular torque <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Herzog1">[28]</xref>. The passive torque-angle data were averaged across dorsi/plantarflexion trials (typically three per subject); a third-order polynomial was fit to these mean data to generate a passive torque-angle relationship. In the active trials, the polynomial was evaluated at the each instantaneous joint angle and subtracted from the measured torque. Torque contributions due to the weight and inertia of the foot, estimated from de Leva <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-DeLeva1">[29]</xref>, and dynamometer arm, measured experimentally, were also subtracted. We did not account for joint viscosity and friction, as these make negligible contributions to the net joint torque compared with passive elastic, gravitational, and inertial effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Johns1">[30]</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2a3">
          <title>Data Processing – Torque Angle (Tθ)</title>
          <p>For each subject, the larger of the two maximal isometric joint torque measurements at each ankle angle (<italic>T<sub>IM</sub></italic>) was used to construct a <italic>Tθ</italic> relationship. The <italic>Tθ</italic> relationship for each subject was expressed as a second order polynomial fit to the DF and PF <italic>T<sub>IM</sub></italic> vs. <italic>θ</italic> data using a least squares approach. The maximum of the polynomial within the measured range of motion was used to define the maximum isometric torque <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> and the optimal angle <italic>θ</italic><sub>0</sub>.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Data Processing – Torque Angular Velocity (Tω)</title>
        <p>The peak torque <italic>T<sub>IV</sub></italic> and corresponding <italic>ω</italic> from each isovelocity trial were used to construct a <italic>Tω</italic> relation. At peak torque all shortening/lengthening occurs via the contractile component, i.e. elastic component velocity is momentarily zero. Measured <italic>Tω</italic> data were also adjusted to account for <italic>Tθ</italic> effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Lanza1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Caldwell1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Chapman1">[31]</xref>. For each subject, the relation between <italic>θ</italic> and <italic>ω</italic> coinciding with the <italic>T<sub>IV</sub></italic> data points was established using linear regression, and used with the <italic>Tθ</italic> relation to predict the isometric torque capability corresponding to each <italic>T<sub>IV</sub></italic> value. Each original <italic>Tω</italic> data point was divided by its angle-specific isometric torque capability to give scaled isovelocity peak torque (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.) values (if <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.<italic> = 1</italic> then <italic>T<sub>IV</sub></italic> was equal to the isometric torque at that angle). A rectangular hyperbola was fit to these scaled <italic>Tω</italic> data. Based on Hill <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Hill2">[32]</xref>, if <italic>ω</italic> (rad/s) is positive (concentric), then<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <italic>A<sub>Tω</sub></italic> and <italic>B<sub>Tω</sub></italic> are coefficients describing the shape of the scaled <italic>Tω</italic> relation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g001">Figure 1</xref>). For eccentric conditions, when <italic>ω</italic> is negative, based on FitzHugh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-FitzHugh1">[33]</xref><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>and <italic>T<sub>ECC</sub></italic> defines the eccentric plateau.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0015953-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of changing the coefficients describing the torque-angular velocity relation (<italic>Tω</italic>).</title>
            <p>Left: effect of varying <italic>A<sub>Tω</sub></italic> from 0.02 to 0.62 while keeping <italic>B<sub>Tω</sub></italic> =  2.25. Right: effect of varying <italic>B<sub>Tω</sub></italic> from 0.2 to 5.0 while keeping <italic>A<sub>Tω</sub></italic> = 0.1. The eccentric plateau (<italic>T<sub>ECC</sub></italic>) was set to 1.5 <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>. Dashed and thick solid lines indicate small and large values for each coefficient, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Torque-Extension (<italic>TΔL</italic>) Measurements</title>
        <sec id="s2c1">
          <title>Experimental Setup</title>
          <p>To estimate DF and PF <italic>TΔL</italic> relationships, ankle torque was measured as subjects performed a series of ramped maximal isometric efforts on the dynamometer. The tibialis anterior, lateral head of the gastrocnemius, and soleus muscles were imaged using an Acuson 128XP real-time ultrasonic scanner with a linear-array probe (7.5 MHz, 50 mm scanning length, B-mode). The ultrasound probe was orientated along the mid-sagittal axis of each muscle, with transmission gel used for improved acoustic coupling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Maganaris1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Maganaris2">[35]</xref>. Ultrasound images (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g002">Figure 2A</xref>) were sampled at 30 Hz and saved to magnetic tape. With the knee extended, the ankle was positioned at 90° where passive contributions are minimal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Siegler1">[36]</xref>. The torque data were sampled at 900 Hz with 16-bit resolution, using a 5V analog pulse for synchronization with the ultrasound data.</p>
          <fig id="pone-0015953-g002" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g002</object-id>
            <label>Figure 2</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Methodology for measuring musculotendon series elasticity.</title>
              <p>A: Ultrasound stills from the start (left) and end (right, at MVC) of a dorsi- (top) and plantarflexion (bottom) ramped trial. The white dots indicate points of interest, including a set of reference points near the skin, and a set of points on the aponeurosis of each muscle. The motion of the points was tracked using an automated cross-correlation algorithm. B: Example of the horizontal displacements of the reference points (top) and aponeurosis points for a dorsiflexion trial (thick line = average). C: The visual torque-time template (left) and the actual dorsiflexion torque produced (right). D: The resulting torque vs. extension plot. A second order polynomial was fit to the torque up to 60% MVC, and then extended up to MVC (dashed line).</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2c2">
          <title>Protocol</title>
          <p>Subjects performed two blocks of trials (DF, PF), with block order balanced across subjects. Within each block, two maximal voluntary contractions (MVCs) were performed to establish maximal isometric ankle torque, followed by five trials with torque and ultrasound measurements. In each 30-second trial, subjects were asked to match their ankle torque to a predefined green target force template that increased exponentially from 0 to 30% MVC, and linearly from 30 to 100% MVC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g002">Figure 2C</xref>, solid line). The initial exponential increase was to ensure a slow rate of extension to facilitate subsequent image analysis. Red lines defined acceptable torque variation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g002">Figure 2C</xref>, broken lines). During each trial, the subject's actual ankle torque appeared in real time. Subjects were instructed to follow the green line as closely as possible. Trials were separated by two-minute rest periods.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2c3">
          <title>Video Capture and Preprocessing</title>
          <p>The ultrasound video was parsed into individual trials and converted to digital format (AVI, 720×480 pixels) using a video capture system (Studio MovieBox USB, Pinnacle Systems). Subsequent processing was done using M<sc>atlab</sc>™ (Version 7, The MathWorks, Natick MA). The 900 Hz torque data were downsampled to 30 Hz and synchronized with the ultrasound video using the rising edge of the analog pulse.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2c4">
          <title>Tracking of Aponeurosis Extension</title>
          <p>To measure extension, multiple points on the ultrasound images were identified: one set of eight superficial reference points evenly spaced near the skin, and a cluster of eight points along the aponeurosis (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). The movement of all points was automatically tracked using a two-dimensional cross-correlation tracking algorithm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Loram1">[37]</xref>. The tibialis anterior aponeurosis extension was assumed to represent the DF muscles (including the tibialis anterior, extensor hallucis longus, extensor digitorum longus, and peroneus tertius), while the extension of the combined gastrocnemuis and soleus aponeuroses represented the PF muscles.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2c5">
          <title>Data Processing</title>
          <p>Horizontal and vertical point displacements and the torque data were smoothed using a Butterworth digital filter with optimal cut-off frequencies determined through residual and power spectral analyses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Winter1">[38]</xref>. The multiple reference and aponeurosis point displacements were averaged to give a single reference and aponeurosis time-series (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). After subtraction of reference point motion to account for possible probe movement relative to the skin, the magnitude of the aponeurosis displacement vector was expressed as extension (<italic>ΔL</italic>) from the rest position. Highly variable data above 60% MVC torque were excluded from the subsequent fitting of a second order polynomial <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Onambele1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Magnusson1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Magnusson2">[40]</xref> to the ankle torque (<italic>T</italic>) vs. <italic>ΔL</italic> data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g002">Figure 2D</xref>):<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <italic>α<sub>TΔL</sub></italic> and <italic>β<sub>TΔL</sub></italic> are shape coefficients. The linear stiffness (<italic>K</italic>) was calculated as the slope of the fitted polynomials (i.e. <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.) at three different torque levels (<italic>K<sub>Low</sub></italic> = 5 Nm [DF], 15 Nm [PF]; <italic>K<sub>Med</sub></italic> = 15 Nm [DF], 30 Nm [PF]; <italic>K<sub>High</sub></italic> = 30 Nm [DF], 60 Nm [PF]). The maximum extension of the series elastic components (<italic>ΔL<sub>MAX</sub></italic>) was assessed by evaluating the polynomial equation at MVC.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Statistics</title>
        <p>Due to technical issues affecting torque measurement, one of the young male subjects was excluded from the <italic>Tθ</italic> and <italic>Tω</italic> analysis. Separate three-way ANOVAs (age [Y,O] x gender [M,F] x muscle [PF,DF]) were performed on each dependent variable. The dependent variables included two <italic>Tθ</italic> variables (<italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>θ</italic><sub>0</sub>) and three <italic>Tω</italic> variables (<italic>A<sub>Tω</sub></italic>, <italic>B<sub>Tω</sub></italic>, and <italic>T<sub>ECC</sub></italic>). For the <italic>TΔL</italic> relations, the three dependent variables were <italic>α<sub>TΔL</sub></italic><sub>,</sub> <italic>β<sub>TΔL</sub></italic> and <italic>ΔL<sub>MAX</sub></italic>. Separate two-way ANOVAs (age x gender) were performed for DF and PF linear stiffness measures (<italic>K<sub>Low</sub></italic>, <italic>K<sub>Med</sub></italic>, <italic>K<sub>High</sub></italic>); an additional one-way ANOVA was performed to test for muscle group difference at the same absolute torque level (15 Nm). Outliers were defined as data points that exceeded the mean by more than three times the inter-quartile range. Statistical significance for all tests was set at <italic>p≤</italic>.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Torque-Angle (<italic>Tθ</italic>)</title>
        <p>Individual subject <italic>Tθ</italic> and <italic>Tω</italic> relations are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g003">Figure 3</xref>; summary statistics are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015953-t002">Table 2</xref>, with age group mean curves shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g004">Figure 4</xref>. For maximal isometric torque <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>, there was a main effect of age, with <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> greater in the young compared to old (<italic>p</italic> = .028), and a main effect of muscle, with PF greater then DF (<italic>p</italic>&lt;.001). There was also a three-way interaction between age, gender, and muscle (<italic>p</italic> = .034) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g005">Figure 5</xref>). No age-related differences were found in females for DF <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> (<italic>p</italic> = .794) or PF <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> (<italic>p</italic> = .161), or for DF <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> in males (<italic>p</italic> = .587), but older males had significantly weaker PF compared to younger males (<italic>p</italic>&lt;.001). There was a main effect of muscle for optimal angle <italic>θ</italic><sub>0</sub> (<italic>p</italic>&lt;.001), with <italic>θ</italic><sub>0</sub> occurring at a more plantarflexed position for DF (at +14° of plantarflexion) than for PF (at −14° of dorsiflexion), but there were no <italic>θ</italic><sub>0</sub> effects for age (<italic>p</italic> = .834) or gender (<italic>p</italic> = .201).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0015953-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Equations representing the best fit between the experimental data and second order polynomials (torque-angle relation; isometric) and rectangular hyperbolas (torque-angular velocity relation; isovelocity) for young (solid black lines) and older (dashed gray lines).</title>
            <p>The solid circles positioned on the isometric curves represent the peak isometric torque. For some subjects, the peak did not occur within the subject's range of motion, in these cases the solid circle is positioned at the end of the range of motion. The isovelocity fits are scaled to the peak isometric torques.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0015953-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Average young (black solid lines) and older (gray dashed lines) torque-angle (left) and torque-angular velocity (right) curves.</title>
            <p>Both measured (thick lines) and co-activation adjusted (thin lines; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Discussion</xref>) data fits are shown.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0015953-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Interaction plots for maximal isometric torque (<italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0015953-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title>Parameters characterizing torque-angle (<italic>Tθ</italic>) and torque-angular velocity (<italic>Tω</italic>) data (mean±between-subjects standard deviation).</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0015953-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Muscle Group</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Tθ</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Tω</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> (Nm)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>θ</italic><sub>0</sub> (°)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>A<sub>Tω</sub></italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>B<sub>Tω</sub></italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>T<sub>ECC</sub></italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Young Male <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.1±8.70</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.3±5.28</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.030±0.078</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.12±0.43</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.48±0.31</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114±28.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−12.7±2.48</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.350±0.585</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.19±3.04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.37±0.35</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Young Female</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.9±7.40</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.6±8.25</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.241±0.358</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.81±1.27</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.43±0.20</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.9±22.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−14.3±7.65</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.240±0.535</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.15±1.58</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.35±0.41</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Young Average</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.5±8.10</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.9±6.77</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.136±0.218</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.47±0.85</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.46±0.26</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.5±25.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−13.5±5.07</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.295±0.560</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.67±2.31</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.36±0.38</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Older Male</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.2±7.20</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.0±6.15</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.029±0.044</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.31±0.28</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.30±0.12</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.4±9.72</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−12.8±7.74</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.034±0.068</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.53±0.82</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.21±0.20</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Older Female</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.1±11.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.4±6.74</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.008±0.014</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.59±0.29</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.39±0.27</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.5±34.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−13.8±8.94</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.050±0.123</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41±1.05</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.35±0.33</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Older Average</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.7±9.35</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.2±6.45</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.019±0.029</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.45±0.29</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.35±0.20</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.9±22.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−13.3±8.34</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.042±0.096</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.47±0.94</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28±0.27</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Main Effects<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A, M</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interactions<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A X G X M</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G X M</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>One outlier is excluded.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>Significant main effects and interactions for age (A), gender (G), and muscle (M).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label/>
              <p>DF, PF: dorsiflexors, plantarflexors.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label/>
              <p><italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>: maximal isometric joint torque.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt106">
              <label/>
              <p><italic>θ</italic><sub>0</sub>: ankle angle at <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> (DF =  Negative; PF =  Positive).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt107">
              <label/>
              <p><italic>A<sub>Tω</sub></italic>, <italic>B<sub>Tω</sub></italic>: shape coefficients for <italic>Tω</italic> relation; units for <italic>B<sub>Tω</sub></italic> are rad/s.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt108">
              <label/>
              <p><italic>T<sub>ECC</sub></italic>: eccentric plateau of <italic>Tω</italic> relation (relative to <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Torque-Angular Velocity (<italic>Tω</italic>)</title>
        <p>Compared to the younger individuals, older adults produced less torque relative to <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> for concentric velocities, as indicated by the smaller <italic>Tω</italic> shape coefficient <italic>B<sub>Tω</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015953-t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g004">4</xref>; age main effect <italic>p</italic> = .003). There were no main effects of gender (<italic>p</italic> = .935) or muscle (<italic>p</italic>  = .977). There were no effects of age, gender, or muscle on the <italic>Tω</italic> parameters <italic>A<sub>T</sub></italic><sub>ω</sub> (<italic>p</italic>&gt;.110 for all tests) or <italic>T<sub>ECC</sub></italic> (<italic>p</italic>&gt;.192 for all tests).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Torque-Extension (<italic>TΔL</italic>)</title>
        <p>Individual subject <italic>TΔL</italic> relations are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g006">Figure 6</xref>. For these second order polynomial relations, older subjects had larger <italic>α<sub>TΔL</sub></italic> coefficients (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015953-t003">Table 3</xref>; <italic>p</italic> = .009), but no differences for <italic>β<sub>TΔL</sub></italic> (<italic>p</italic> = .457). Both coefficients were larger for PF compared to DF (<italic>α<sub>TΔL</sub></italic>; <italic>p</italic> = .002; <italic>β<sub>TΔL</sub></italic>; <italic>p</italic>&lt;.001). There were no gender differences for either coefficient (<italic>α<sub>TΔL</sub></italic>; <italic>p</italic> = .706; <italic>β<sub>TΔL</sub></italic>; <italic>p</italic>&lt;.343). There were no age effects for DF at any linear stiffness level (<italic>K<sub>Low</sub></italic>, <italic>K<sub>Med</sub></italic>, <italic>K<sub>High</sub></italic>) (p&gt;.691), and none for PF at <italic>K<sub>Low</sub></italic> (<italic>p</italic>  = .143) and <italic>K<sub>Med</sub></italic> (p = .058). However, <italic>K<sub>High</sub></italic> was greater for the older subjects (<italic>p</italic>  = .031). There were no gender differences at any <italic>K</italic> for DF (<italic>p</italic>&gt;.538) or PF (<italic>p</italic>&gt;.231). When comparing <italic>K</italic> at the same absolute torque level (15 Nm), the PF muscles were stiffer than the DF (<italic>p</italic>&lt;.001). Older adults had smaller maximal aponeurosis extensions (5.7 mm) than the younger subjects (8.8 mm) (<italic>ΔL<sub>MAX</sub></italic>; <italic>p</italic>&lt;.001). There was an age by muscle interaction for maximal extension (<italic>p</italic> = .015), with PF <italic>ΔL<sub>MAX</sub></italic> smaller than DF (<italic>p</italic> = .017) for the older subjects, but not for the young (<italic>p</italic> = .388).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0015953-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Second order polynomial fits to the young (solid black lines) and older (broken gray lines) torque-extension data from the ultrasound experiments.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0015953-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
            <title>Parameters describing the torque-extension (<italic>TΔL</italic>) data (mean±between-subjects standard deviation).</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0015953-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mus.</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>ΔL<sub>MAX</sub></italic> (mm)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>α<sub>TΔL</sub></italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>β<sub>TΔL</sub></italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>K<sub>Low</sub></italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>K<sub>Med</sub></italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>K<sub>High</sub></italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Young Male</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.4±1.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.491±0.221</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.570±0.643</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.51±0.64</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.62±0.92</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.75±1.42</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11±3.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.835±0.697</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.22±3.55</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.61±2.25</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.1±2.75</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.6±4.31</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Young Female</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.0±1.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.386±0.194</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.577±0.550</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.83±0.59</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.77±1.09</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.69±1.57</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.8±3.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.809±0.733</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.64±4.17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.59±3.61</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.8±4.48</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.1±6.22</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Young Average</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2±1.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.439±0.208</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.574±0.597</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.17±0.62</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.20±1.01</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.22±1.50</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.4±3.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.822±0.715</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.43±3.86</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.60±2.93</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.0±3.62</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.4±5.27</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Older Male<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">a</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.5±4.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.578±0.617</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.893±0.816</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.22±1.75</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.34±3.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.45±4.28</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5±1.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.10±5.11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.42±1.35</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.3±1.41</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.9±1.96</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.5±15.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Older Female</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0±1.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.809±0.678</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.197±0.403</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.81±1.48</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.57±2.59</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.27±3.67</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.7±2.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.64±1.73</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.52±5.59</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.55±2.67</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.9±3.40</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.1±10.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Older Average</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3±3.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.694±0.648</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.545±0.610</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.52±1.62</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.96±2.81</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.36±3.98</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PF</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.1±1.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.87±3.42</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.47±3.47</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.93±2.04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.9±2.68</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.8±12.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Main Effects<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">b</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A, M</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A (PF)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interactions<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">b</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A×M</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt109">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>One outlier is excluded.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt110">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>Significant main effects and interactions for age (A) and muscle (M).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt111">
              <label/>
              <p>DF, PF: dorsiflexors, plantarflexors.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt112">
              <label/>
              <p><italic>ΔL<sub>MAX</sub></italic>: maximum extension of aponeurosis.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt113">
              <label/>
              <p><italic>α<sub>TΔL</sub></italic>, <italic>β<sub>TΔL</sub></italic>: shape coefficients for the <italic>TΔL</italic> relation.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt114">
              <label/>
              <p><italic>K</italic>: Linear stiffness coefficients at different absolute torque levels; for DF: [<italic>K<sub>Low</sub></italic>, <italic>K<sub>Med</sub></italic>, <italic>K<sub>High</sub></italic>] = [5, 15, 30 Nm]; For PF: [<italic>K<sub>Low</sub></italic>, <italic>K<sub>Med</sub></italic>, <italic>K<sub>High</sub></italic>] = [15, 30, 60 Nm]. Stiffness units are Nm/mm.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The hypothesis of lower maximal isometric torques (<italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>) in the older adults was supported partially; only the older male subjects had lower <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>, and only in the PF muscle group. There was stronger support for the hypotheses of decreased concentric force capabilities and increased series elastic stiffness in the older adults; however, the latter was observed only for PF. We also expected to find greater age-related differences for PF compared to DF due to previous reports of Type II fiber atrophy in the gastrocnemius in older adults. This was observed for the male PF <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> as well as the PF stiffness; however, age-related reductions in concentric force capabilities were found for both DF and PF. No differences were found between age groups in the optimal joint angle of the <italic>Tθ</italic> relation, or in eccentric torque capabilities.</p>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Torque-Angle</title>
        <p>As in prior studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Vandervoort1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Lanza1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Simoneau1">[41]</xref>, we found age-related deficits in maximal isometric joint strength (<italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>), but only for PF in male subjects; females showed no age-related differences. Kent-Braun and Ng <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-KentBraun1">[42]</xref> reported a similar interaction for DF, with <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> greater in young men than older, but not in the females. Other support for an age and gender interaction is provided by Winegard et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Winegard1">[4]</xref>, in which older female subjects had larger PF <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> values than older males, and did not show significant age-related deficits in strength. These findings could be related to age-related decreases in male testosterone concentrations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Harman1">[43]</xref>, which is associated with decreased muscle mass and strength <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Abbasi1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Baumgartner1">[45]</xref>. We saw no age-related differences for the angle of peak torque (<italic>θ</italic><sub>0</sub>), consistent with Simoneau and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Simoneau2">[46]</xref>, who found no variations with age in the DF and PF <italic>Tθ</italic> relations. We also observed that the angle at maximum torque (<italic>θ</italic><sub>0</sub>) was not different between the age/gender groups. Relative to neutral (0°), both DF <italic>θ</italic><sub>0</sub> (+14° of plantarflexion) and PF <italic>θ</italic><sub>0</sub> (−14° of dorsiflexion) were similar to other studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Lanza1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Bobbert1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Belanger1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Ferri1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Marsh1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Sale1">[50]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Our estimates of <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> were based on a second order polynomial that represented the <italic>Tθ</italic> relation. Average DF <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> values were ∼37 Nm for the younger subjects and ∼35 Nm for the older subjects. These data agree with literature values that range from ∼22 to 44 Nm for both young and older adults <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Vandervoort1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Lanza1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Thelen1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Simoneau2">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Anderson1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Fukunaga1">[52]</xref>. For PF <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>, values averaged 93 Nm for young and 70 Nm for older males, while literature values range from 104 to 232 Nm for young males and from 100 to 125 Nm for older males <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Vandervoort1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Winegard1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Thelen1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Simoneau2">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Anderson1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Karamanidis1">[53]</xref>. Our relatively low results could be due to several factors, including the use of a knee angle of 90°, at which the gastrocnemius is shorter than optimum length <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Sale1">[50]</xref>, reducing the net plantarflexor torque. We also report active torque after subtracting for passive torque contributions, and were stringent concerning proper joint alignment and/or upper body fixation during the experimental trials <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Oberg1">[54]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Torque-Angular Velocity</title>
        <p>The <italic>Tω</italic> relation was characterized by the shape parameters <italic>A<sub>Tω</sub></italic> and <italic>B<sub>Tω</sub>,</italic> akin to the dynamic constants of the Hill force-velocity equation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Hill1">[12]</xref> and independent of <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g001">Figure 1</xref> illustrates that independently increasing <italic>A<sub>Tω</sub></italic> produces lower torque at any given concentric velocity, while increasing <italic>B<sub>Tω</sub></italic> leads to greater concentric, but decreased eccentric force capability.</p>
        <p>The shape of the <italic>Tω</italic> relation differed between age groups, with weaker/slower concentric force capabilities (lower <italic>B<sub>Tω</sub></italic>) in older DF and PF, but without a concomitant deficit in eccentric strength as indicated by the eccentric torque plateau (<italic>T<sub>ECC</sub></italic>). These data are consistent with other reports that concentric capability is reduced with aging <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Lanza1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Thelen1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Thom1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Harries1">[55]</xref>, but that eccentric torque production is preserved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Porter1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Porter2">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Klass1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Hortobagyi1">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Poulin1">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Vandervoort2">[58]</xref>. Because we accounted for individual subject differences in strength, muscle moment arms, and muscle torque-angle relations, our <italic>Tω</italic> findings represent a difference in the intrinsic force-velocity properties of the ankle muscles. This may be related to an age-related decrease in the size and/or number of fast-twitch Type II muscle fibers in the dorsiflexor tibialis anterior and the plantarflexor gastrocnemius <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Lexell1">[59]</xref>. With aging the percentage of Type IIa fibers decreases by about 9% in the tibialis anterior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Jakobsson1">[60]</xref>. Although gastrocnemius Type IIa and Type IIb fiber number remains stable with increased age, these fibers shrink by about 13–31% in comparison with sedentary young adults <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Coggan1">[25]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Series Elasticity</title>
        <p>The change in series elastic component length as a function of joint torque (i.e. the <italic>TΔL</italic> relation) was represented by a second order polynomial with shape coefficients <italic>α<sub>TΔL</sub></italic> and <italic>β<sub>TΔL</sub></italic>. The squared coefficient <italic>α<sub>TΔL</sub></italic> has a large influence on the rate of torque increase with increasing extension, and this coefficient was larger for the older subjects, indicating greater non-linearity in the <italic>TΔL</italic> relation. There were no age differences in the <italic>β<sub>TΔL</sub></italic> coefficient, which has a smaller role in determining the shape of the <italic>TΔL</italic> relation. To determine linear stiffness, we computed the slope of the non-linear <italic>TΔL</italic> relation at three different relative torque levels (<italic>K<sub>Low</sub>, K<sub>Med</sub>, K<sub>High</sub></italic>). Although we found no age differences among DF linear stiffness values at any torque level, older PF muscles had greater stiffness when evaluated at the high torque level (<italic>K<sub>High</sub></italic>). Greater PF stiffness in older adults agrees with other studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Ochala1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Ochala2">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Blanpied2">[61]</xref>, and may offset the age-related decrement in velocity-dependent force capabilities, as force can rise faster if the contractile component is attached to a stiffer series elastic component rather than a more compliant one <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Caldwell2">[62]</xref>.</p>
        <p>This study also found <italic>TΔL</italic> differences between the muscle groups. Compared to DF, both <italic>α<sub>TΔL</sub></italic> and <italic>β<sub>TΔL</sub></italic> polynomial coefficients and the linear stiffness measure at 15 Nm were greater for PF. This is supported by literature reports of aponeurosis stiffness and Young's modulus (<italic>E</italic>) (at maximal torque) <italic>in vivo</italic>, with lower values (stiffness = 32 N/mm; <italic>E</italic> = 0.563 Gpa) reported for DF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Ito1">[63]</xref> than for the PF muscles (stiffness = 467 N/mm; <italic>E</italic> = 1.474 GPa)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Magnusson1">[39]</xref>. We did not compute <italic>E</italic>, since it requires explicit measures of series elastic component length and cross-sectional area <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Maganaris3">[64]</xref>. Our findings of increased PF stiffness are also supported by evidence that muscle elastic characteristics are influenced by physiological function <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Shadwick1">[65]</xref>; PF would be expected to have a higher stiffness to support much higher static and dynamic loads compared to DF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Roy1">[66]</xref>. This is one of the first reports on DF stiffness in older adults, as most studies focus on PF because they are purported to make a larger contribution to activities of daily living <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Judge1">[67]</xref>. On the other hand, DF can generate significant torque and contribute to ankle joint stiffness that is important for postural stabilization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Winter2">[68]</xref>.</p>
        <p>It is important to note the limitations associated with these interpretations of series-elastic stiffness. Although we only measured aponeurosis extension in the longitudinal direction, the aponeurosis stretches bi-axially in the longitudinal and transverse planes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Scott1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-VanDonkelaar1">[69]</xref>. This complex behavior results in a variable aponeurosis stiffness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Azizi1">[70]</xref>, which we characterized with a second-order polynomial, and made linear approximations of the stiffness (<italic>K</italic>) at different torque values to facilitate group comparisons. Although we assumed that the aponeurosis acts in series with the muscle fibers and external tendon, the force expressed across these structures may differ due to the complex geometry of the musculotendon unit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Epstein1">[71]</xref>. We did not normalize the stiffness measures by the cross-sectional area and rest length of the elastic structures. Additionally, the gastrocnemius and soleus aponeuroses are separate structures linked by transverse collagen fibers, which can move independently during PF torque production, i.e. there is inter-aponeurosis shear <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-BojsenMoller1">[72]</xref>. Our ultrasound machine had insufficient resolution to make this subtle distinction. Thus, our PF aponeurosis extension values represent an average for the gastrocnemius and soleus (the tracking points spanned both aponeuroses).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Antagonist Co-Activation</title>
        <p>In measuring resultant joint torque to assess muscle function, we made the common assumption of no antagonist co-activation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Lanza1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Thelen1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Ochala2">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Bobbert1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Anderson1">[51]</xref>. This assumption is likely false in maximal joint torque efforts, and could cause agonist torque capabilities to be underestimated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Simoneau3">[73]</xref>, which in turn would lead to inaccurate muscular properties. To assess possible influences of antagonistic co-activation, we estimated the percentage of antagonistic co-activation (<italic>%CoAct</italic>) from the isometric data of Simoneau et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Simoneau1">[41]</xref><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <italic>T<sub>DF</sub></italic> and <italic>T<sub>PF</sub></italic> are the agonist DF and PF torques (Nm). For each muscle group the antagonistic torque contribution (<italic>T<sup>Antag</sup>,</italic> Nm) was computed as<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015953.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></p>
        <p>We found that including antagonistic contributions increased agonist DF <italic>T<sub>0</sub></italic> by 35% in young and 26% in older subjects, and increased agonist PF <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> by 16% in young and 12% in older subjects. The most pronounced change was for isometric DF, in which the small differences between the young and old subjects became much greater with the inclusion of antagonism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015953-g004">Figure 4</xref>). This was because the younger subjects had stronger PF muscles and therefore greater antagonistic torque during the isometric DF trials.</p>
        <p>Including antagonistic contributions may also influence stiffness measurements. Agonist muscles produce more torque than the dynamometer measures when antagonist muscles produce opposing torques. Magnusson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Magnusson1">[39]</xref> demonstrated that antagonistic influences are small but significant for PF in male adults (average age: 37 yrs), such that Achilles tendon force was underestimated by ∼2.6% when antagonist coactivation was ignored. Lower torques for a given tendinous extension would cause stiffness to be underestimated. However, in the present study the degree of underestimation would be smaller for the older subjects and the DF muscles, since in both cases the magnitudes of the joint torques were smaller than those measured by Magnusson and colleagues.</p>
        <p>Our simple antagonism model assumed that antagonist co-activation is dictated by agonist torque level alone, is independent of joint angular velocity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Bazzucchi1">[74]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-HubleyKozey1">[75]</xref>, and that the torque/co-activation relation was the same for both age groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Simoneau1">[41]</xref>. However, the degree of antagonistic co-contraction is likely task-specific, and may be influenced by joint angle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Simoneau2">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Billot1">[76]</xref>, angular velocity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Behm1">[77]</xref>, and whether the muscular effort is isometric, concentric, or eccentric <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Aagaard1">[78]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Kellis1">[79]</xref>. One possibility is to use electromyography to estimate co-activation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Maganaris4">[80]</xref>, but some have questioned the reliability of antagonist torque estimated in this manner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Billot1">[76]</xref>. Therefore, the exact magnitude of the co-activation adjusted results should be viewed with caution, but the simple model used here demonstrates the importance of including antagonism when predicting muscular properties.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p>Many clinical studies use maximal isometric strength as a marker of functional ability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Carmeli1">[81]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015953-Hyatt1">[82]</xref>. However, the present study has shown additional age-related differences in the dynamic properties of the ankle muscles, with slower concentric force capabilities and stiffer series elasticity in the older adults. This assessment of static, dynamic, and elastic joint properties affords a comprehensive view of age-related modifications in muscle function. Future work should further investigate links between age-related differences in these properties, which together may represent adaptations to physiological and lifestyle changes in older adults. Since the subjects in the present study were all healthy and active members of the community, we speculate that these differences represent a normal aging process.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We would like to thank the subjects who participated in the study, Brigid McKenna for assistance with data collection, and Ian Loram for suggesting the use of spatial cross-correlation in our ultrasound data tracking.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Vandervoort1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandervoort</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McComas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1986</year>             <article-title>Contractile changes in opposing muscles of the human ankle joint with aging.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>61</volume>             <fpage>361</fpage>             <lpage>367</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Lanza1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanza</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Towse</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wigmore</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kent-Braun</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Effects of age on human muscle torque, velocity, and power in two muscle groups.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>95</volume>             <fpage>2361</fpage>             <lpage>2369</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-vanSchaik1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Schaik</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCartney</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>An evaluation of the length-tension relationship in elderly human ankle dorsiflexors.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol</source>             <volume>49</volume>             <fpage>B121</fpage>             <lpage>127</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Winegard1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winegard</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandervoort</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>An evaluation of the length-tension relationship in elderly human plantarflexor muscles.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source>             <volume>52</volume>             <fpage>B337</fpage>             <lpage>343</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Thelen1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thelen</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashton-Miller</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Effects of age on rapid ankle torque development.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>M226</fpage>             <lpage>232</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Thom1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thom</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narici</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Influence of muscle architecture on the torque and power-velocity characteristics of young and elderly men.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>100</volume>             <fpage>613</fpage>             <lpage>619</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Porter1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myint</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandervoort</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Concentric and eccentric knee extension strength in older and younger men and women.</article-title>             <source>Can J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>20</volume>             <fpage>429</fpage>             <lpage>439</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Porter2">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandervoort</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Eccentric peak torque of the plantar and dorsiflexors is maintained in older women.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source>             <volume>52</volume>             <fpage>B125</fpage>             <lpage>131</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Klass1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klass</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baudry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duchateau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Aging does not affect voluntary activation of the ankle dorsiflexors during isometric, concentric, and eccentric contractions.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>99</volume>             <fpage>31</fpage>             <lpage>38</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Caldwell1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whetstone</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Torque/velocity properties of human knee muscles: peak and angle-specific estimates.</article-title>             <source>Can J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>274</fpage>             <lpage>290</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Gordon1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huxley</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Julian</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1966</year>             <article-title>The variation in isometric tension with sarcomere length in vertebrate muscle fibres.</article-title>             <source>J Physiol</source>             <volume>184</volume>             <fpage>170</fpage>             <lpage>192</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Hill1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1938</year>             <article-title>The heat of shortening and the dynamic constants of muscle.</article-title>             <source>Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>             <volume>126B</volume>             <fpage>136</fpage>             <lpage>195</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Ochala1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochala</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambertz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Hoecke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pousson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Effect of strength training on musculotendinous stiffness in elderly individuals.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>94</volume>             <fpage>126</fpage>             <lpage>133</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Ochala2">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochala</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambertz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pousson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goubel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoecke</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Changes in mechanical properties of human plantar flexor muscles in ageing.</article-title>             <source>Exp Gerontol</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>349</fpage>             <lpage>358</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Blanpied1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanpied</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smidt</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>The difference in stiffness of the active plantarflexors between young and elderly human females.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>M58</fpage>             <lpage>63</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Onambele1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onambele</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narici</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maganaris</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Calf muscle-tendon properties and postural balance in old age.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>100</volume>             <fpage>2048</fpage>             <lpage>2056</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Lieber1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieber</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trestik</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Frog semitendinosis tendon load-strain and stress-strain properties during passive loading.</article-title>             <source>Am J Physiol</source>             <volume>261</volume>             <fpage>C86</fpage>             <lpage>92</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-DelgadoLezama1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delgado-Lezama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raya</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munoz-Martinez</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Methods to find aponeurosis and tendon stiffness and the onset of muscle contraction.</article-title>             <source>J Neurosci Methods</source>             <volume>78</volume>             <fpage>125</fpage>             <lpage>132</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Ettema1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ettema</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huijing</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Properties of the tendinous structures and series elastic component of EDL muscle-tendon complex of the rat.</article-title>             <source>J Biomech</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>1209</fpage>             <lpage>1215</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Scott1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Mechanical properties of aponeurosis and tendon of the cat soleus muscle during whole muscle isometric contractions.</article-title>             <source>J Morphol</source>             <volume>224</volume>             <fpage>73</fpage>             <lpage>86</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Muramatsu1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muramatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muraoka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeshita</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Mechanical properties of tendon and aponeurosis of human gastrocnemius muscle in vivo.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>90</volume>             <fpage>1671</fpage>             <lpage>1678</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Bobbert1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bobbert</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Ingen Schenau</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Isokinetic plantar flexion: experimental results and model calculations.</article-title>             <source>J Biomech</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>105</fpage>             <lpage>119</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Taylor1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Functional torque-velocity and power-velocity characteristics of elite athletes.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol</source>             <volume>62</volume>             <fpage>116</fpage>             <lpage>121</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Kawakami1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukunaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Effect of series elasticity on isokinetic torque-angle relationship in humans.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>87</volume>             <fpage>381</fpage>             <lpage>387</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Coggan1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coggan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spina</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1992</year>             <article-title>Histochemical and enzymatic comparison of the gastrocnemius muscle of young and elderly men and women.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol</source>             <volume>47</volume>             <fpage>B71</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Drouin1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drouin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valovich-mcLeod</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shultz</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gansneder</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Reliability and validity of the Biodex system 3 pro isokinetic dynamometer velocity, torque and position measurements.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>91</volume>             <fpage>22</fpage>             <lpage>29</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Taylor2">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howick</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Static and dynamic assessment of the Biodex dynamometer.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol</source>             <volume>62</volume>             <fpage>180</fpage>             <lpage>188</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Herzog1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>The relation between the resultant moments at a joint and the moments measured by an isokinetic dynamometer.</article-title>             <source>J Biomech</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>5</fpage>             <lpage>12</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-DeLeva1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Leva</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Adjustments to Zatsiorsky-Seluyanov's segment inertia parameters.</article-title>             <source>J Biomech</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>1223</fpage>             <lpage>1230</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Johns1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1962</year>             <article-title>Relative importance of various tissues in joint stiffness.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>824</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Chapman1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selbie</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1985</year>             <article-title>Mechanical output following muscle stretch in forearm supination against inertial loads.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>59</volume>             <fpage>78</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Hill2">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1970</year>             <article-title>First and last experiments in muscle mechanics.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Cambridge Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-FitzHugh1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>FitzHugh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1977</year>             <article-title>A model of optimal voluntary muscular control.</article-title>             <source>J Math Biol</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>203</fpage>             <lpage>236</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Maganaris1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maganaris</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baltzopoulos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sargeant</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>In vivo measurements of the triceps surae complex architecture in man: implications for muscle function.</article-title>             <source>J Physiol</source>             <volume>512</volume>             <issue>Pt 2</issue>             <fpage>603</fpage>             <lpage>614</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Maganaris2">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maganaris</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Force-length characteristics of in vivo human skeletal muscle.</article-title>             <source>Acta Physiol Scand</source>             <volume>172</volume>             <fpage>279</fpage>             <lpage>285</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Siegler1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moskowitz</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1984</year>             <article-title>Passive and active components of the internal moment developed about the ankle joint during human ambulation.</article-title>             <source>J Biomech</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>647</fpage>             <lpage>652</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Loram1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loram</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maganaris</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Paradoxical muscle movement in human standing.</article-title>             <source>J Physiol</source>             <volume>556</volume>             <fpage>683</fpage>             <lpage>689</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Winter1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Biomechanics and Motor Control of Human Movement: John Wiley &amp; Sons</article-title>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Magnusson1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aagaard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyhre-Poulsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjaer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Load-displacement properties of the human triceps surae aponeurosis in vivo.</article-title>             <source>J Physiol</source>             <volume>531</volume>             <fpage>277</fpage>             <lpage>288</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Magnusson2">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aagaard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brond</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyhre-Poulsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Differential strain patterns of the human gastrocnemius aponeurosis and free tendon, in vivo.</article-title>             <source>Acta Physiol Scand</source>             <volume>177</volume>             <fpage>185</fpage>             <lpage>195</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Simoneau1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simoneau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Hoecke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Muscular performances at the ankle joint in young and elderly men.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source>             <volume>60</volume>             <fpage>439</fpage>             <lpage>447</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-KentBraun1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kent-Braun</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Specific strength and voluntary muscle activation in young and elderly women and men.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>87</volume>             <fpage>22</fpage>             <lpage>29</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Harman1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metter</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Longitudinal effects of aging on serum total and free testosterone levels in healthy men. Baltimore Longitudinal Study of Aging.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>             <volume>86</volume>             <fpage>724</fpage>             <lpage>731</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Abbasi1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DuthieJr</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheldahl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Predictors of lean body mass and total adipose mass in community-dwelling elderly men and women.</article-title>             <source>Am J Med Sci</source>             <volume>315</volume>             <fpage>188</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Baumgartner1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Predictors of skeletal muscle mass in elderly men and women.</article-title>             <source>Mech Ageing Dev</source>             <volume>107</volume>             <fpage>123</fpage>             <lpage>136</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Simoneau2">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simoneau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Hoecke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Effects of joint angle and age on ankle dorsi- and plantar-flexor strength.</article-title>             <source>J Electromyogr Kinesiol</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>307</fpage>             <lpage>316</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Belanger1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belanger</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McComas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elder</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1983</year>             <article-title>Physiological properties of two antagonist human muscle groups.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>381</fpage>             <lpage>393</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Ferri1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scaglioni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capodaglio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Hoecke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Strength and power changes of the human plantarflexors and knee extensors in response to resistance training in old age.</article-title>             <source>Acta Physiol Scand</source>             <volume>177</volume>             <fpage>69</fpage>             <lpage>78</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Marsh1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McComas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>Influence of joint position on ankle dorsiflexion in humans.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>160</fpage>             <lpage>167</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Sale1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McComas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belanger</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1982</year>             <article-title>Influence of joint position on ankle plantarflexion in humans.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>52</volume>             <fpage>1636</fpage>             <lpage>1642</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Anderson1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madigan</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nussbaum</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Maximum voluntary joint torque as a function of joint angle and angular velocity: model development and application to the lower limb.</article-title>             <source>J Biomech</source>             <volume>40</volume>             <fpage>3105</fpage>             <lpage>3113</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Fukunaga1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukunaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ichinose</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Tendinous movement of a human muscle during voluntary contractions determined by real-time ultrasonography.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>81</volume>             <fpage>1430</fpage>             <lpage>1433</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Karamanidis1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karamanidis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arampatzis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Mechanical and morphological properties of human quadriceps femoris and triceps surae muscle-tendon unit in relation to aging and running.</article-title>             <source>J Biomech</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>406</fpage>             <lpage>417</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Oberg1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tropp</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>Testing of isokinetic muscle strength in the ankle.</article-title>             <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>318</fpage>             <lpage>322</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Harries1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harries</surname><given-names>UJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassey</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Torque-velocity relationships for the knee extensors in women in their 3rd and 7th decades.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol</source>             <volume>60</volume>             <fpage>187</fpage>             <lpage>190</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Hortobagyi1">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hortobagyi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weidner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westbrook</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>The influence of aging on muscle strength and muscle fiber characteristics with special reference to eccentric strength.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source>             <volume>50</volume>             <fpage>B399</fpage>             <lpage>406</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Poulin1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandervoort</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1992</year>             <article-title>Eccentric and concentric torques of knee and elbow extension in young and older men.</article-title>             <source>Can J Sport Sci</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>3</fpage>             <lpage>7</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Vandervoort2">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandervoort</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wharram</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Eccentric knee strength of elderly females.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol</source>             <volume>45</volume>             <fpage>B125</fpage>             <lpage>128</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Lexell1">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lexell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sjostrom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>What is the cause of the ageing atrophy? Total number, size and proportion of different fiber types studied in whole vastus lateralis muscle from 15- to 83-year-old men.</article-title>             <source>J Neurol Sci</source>             <volume>84</volume>             <fpage>275</fpage>             <lpage>294</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Jakobsson1">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakobsson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edström</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimby</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>Use of motor units in relation to muscle fiber type and size in man.</article-title>             <source>Muscle Nerve</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>1211</fpage>             <lpage>1218</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Blanpied2">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanpied</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smidt</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>The difference in stiffness of the active plantar flexors between young and elderly human females.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>58</fpage>             <lpage>63</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Caldwell2">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Tendon elasticity and relative length: Effects on the Hill two-component muscle model.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Biomech</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>24</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Ito1">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ichinose</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukashiro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukunaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Nonisometric behavior of fascicle during isometric contractions of a human muscle.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>80</volume>             <fpage>1235</fpage>             <lpage>1235</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Maganaris3">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maganaris</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>In vivo human tendon mechanical properties.</article-title>             <source>J Physiol</source>             <volume>521</volume>             <issue>Pt 1</issue>             <fpage>307</fpage>             <lpage>313</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Shadwick1">
        <label>65</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shadwick</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Elastic energy storage in tendons: mechanical differences related to function and age.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>68</volume>             <fpage>1033</fpage>             <lpage>1040</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Roy1">
        <label>66</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bever</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forrester</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Robot-aided neurorehabilitation: a novel robot for ankle rehabilitation.</article-title>             <source>IEEE Trans Robot</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>569</fpage>             <lpage>582</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Judge1">
        <label>67</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Judge</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RB</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ounpuu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Step length reductions in advanced age: the role of ankle and hip kinetics.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>M303</fpage>             <lpage>312</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Winter2">
        <label>68</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patla</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gielo-Perczak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Stiffness control of balance in quiet standing.</article-title>             <source>J Neurophysiol</source>             <volume>80</volume>             <fpage>1211</fpage>             <lpage>1221</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-VanDonkelaar1">
        <label>69</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Donkelaar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muijtjens</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drost</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Skeletal muscle transverse strain during isometric contraction at different lengths.</article-title>             <source>J Biomech</source>             <volume>32</volume>             <fpage>755</fpage>             <lpage>762</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Azizi1">
        <label>70</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azizi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Biaxial strain and variable stiffness in aponeuroses.</article-title>             <source>J Physiol</source>             <volume>587</volume>             <fpage>4309</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Epstein1">
        <label>71</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Should tendon and aponeurosis be considered in series?</article-title>             <source>J Biomech</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>2020</fpage>             <lpage>2025</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-BojsenMoller1">
        <label>72</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bojsen-Moller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aagaard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Svantesson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjaer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Differential displacement of the human soleus and medial gastrocnemius aponeuroses during isometric plantar flexor contractions in vivo.</article-title>             <source>J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>97</volume>             <fpage>1908</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Simoneau3">
        <label>73</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simoneau</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Billot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Hoecke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Antagonist mechanical contribution to resultant maximal torque at the ankle joint in young and older men.</article-title>             <source>J Electromyogr Kinesiol</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>e123</fpage>             <lpage>131</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Bazzucchi1">
        <label>74</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bazzucchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sbriccoli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marzattinocci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felici</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Coactivation of the elbow antagonist muscles is not affected by the speed of movement in isokinetic exercise.</article-title>             <source>Muscle Nerve</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>191</fpage>             <lpage>199</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-HubleyKozey1">
        <label>75</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hubley-Kozey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Earl</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Coactivation of the ankle musculature during maximal isokinetic dorsiflexion at different angular velocities.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>82</volume>             <fpage>289</fpage>             <lpage>296</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Billot1">
        <label>76</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Billot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simoneau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Hoecke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Coactivation at the ankle joint is not sufficient to estimate agonist and antagonist mechanical contribution.</article-title>             <source>Muscle Nerve</source>             <volume>41</volume>             <fpage>511</fpage>             <lpage>518</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Behm1">
        <label>77</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Behm</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sale</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Influence of velocity on agonist and antagonist activation in concentric dorsiflexion muscle actions.</article-title>             <source>Can J Appl Physiol</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>403</fpage>             <lpage>416</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Aagaard1">
        <label>78</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aagaard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simonsen</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bojsen-Moller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Antagonist muscle coactivation during isokinetic knee extension.</article-title>             <source>Scand J Med Sci Sports</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>58</fpage>             <lpage>67</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Kellis1">
        <label>79</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kellis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Quantification of quadriceps and hamstring antagonist activity.</article-title>             <source>Sports Med</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>37</fpage>             <lpage>62</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Maganaris4">
        <label>80</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maganaris</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baltzopoulos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sargeant</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Differences in human antagonistic ankle dorsiflexor coactivation between legs; can they explain the moment deficit in the weaker plantarflexor leg?</article-title>             <source>Exp Physiol</source>             <volume>83</volume>             <fpage>843</fpage>             <lpage>855</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Carmeli1">
        <label>81</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmeli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reznick</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmeli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Muscle strength and mass of lower extremities in relation to functional abilities in elderly adults.</article-title>             <source>Gerontology</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>249</fpage>             <lpage>257</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015953-Hyatt1">
        <label>82</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitelaw</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Association of muscle strength with functional status of elderly people.</article-title>             <source>Age Ageing</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>330</fpage>             <lpage>336</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>