<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-11051</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043955</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Developmental biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Stem cells</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Stem cell lines</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genomics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genome analysis tools</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Transcriptomes</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genome expression analysis</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Molecular cell biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Signal transduction</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Signaling cascades</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Wnt signaling cascade</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Oncology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Basic cancer research</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Oncology</subject>
          <subject>Developmental Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Establishment of Mouse Teratocarcinomas Stem Cells Line and Screening Genes Responsible for Malignancy</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Teratocarcinomas Stem Cells Line from mESCs</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Tao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Ying</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Peng</surname>
            <given-names>Xinrong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Liqing</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cheng</surname>
            <given-names>Jingbo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Jin</surname>
            <given-names>Huajun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Mengchao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Qian</surname>
            <given-names>Qijun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Laboratory of Viral and Gene Therapy, Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgical Hospital, The Second Military Medical University, Shanghai, China</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Xinyuan Institute of Medicine and Biotechnology, College of Life Science, Zhejiang Sci-Tech University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China</addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sarkar</surname>
            <given-names>Fazlul H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Wayne State University School of Medicine, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">qianqj@sino-gene.cn</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: TL QJQ. Performed the experiments: TL XRP LQZ HJJ JBC. Wrote the paper: YW TL. Carried out the bioinformatics analysis: YW. Performed the microarray data analysis: YW. Supervised the research group: QJQ MCW. Helped critically revise the entire manuscript: QJQ MCW. Read and approved the final manuscript: TL YW XRP LQZ JBC HJJ MCW QJQ.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e43955</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><permissions>
        
        <copyright-holder>Liu et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions><abstract>
        <p>The sequential transplantation of embryonal carcinoma cells <italic>in vivo</italic> can accelerate the growth and malignancy of teratocarcinomas. However, the possible molecular mechanisms in this process that reflect cancer formation in the early stage are largely unknown and. To identify which genes are associated with the changes of malignancy of teratocarcinomas, we established a tumorigenesis model in which teratocarcinoma were induced via injecting embryonic stem cells into immuno-deficiency mice, isolating teratocarcinoma stem cell from a teratocarcinoma in serum-free culture medium and injecting teratocarcinoma stem cells into immune-deficient mice continuously. By using high-throughput deep sequence technology, we identified 26 differentially expressed genes related to the changes of characteristics of teratocarcinoma stem cell in which 18 out of 26 genes were down-regulated and 8 genes were up-regulated. Among these genes, several tumor-related genes such as <italic>Gata3</italic>, <italic>Arnt</italic> and <italic>Tdgf1</italic>, epigenetic associated genes such as <italic>PHC1</italic> and <italic>Uty</italic> were identified. Pathway enrichment analysis result revealed that Wnt signaling pathway, primary immunodeficiency pathway, antigen processing and presentation pathway and allograft rejection pathway were involved in the teratocarcinoma tumorigenesis (corrected <italic>p</italic> value&lt;0.05). In summary, our study established a tumorigenesis model and proposed some candidate genes and signaling pathways that may play a key role in the early stage of cancer occurrence.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Science Funds for Distinguished Young Scholar (No. 30925037), the Science Fund for Creative Research Group of NSFC (No. 30921006) and the National Significant Science and Technology Special Projects of New Drugs Creation (No. 2011ZX09102-010-02). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Teratomas are benign germ cell tumors with somatic tissue or organ components of all three embryonic germ layers. Teratocarcinomas is a kind of malignant teratomas with low spontaneous rate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Fawcett1">[1]</xref> in which malignant stem cells called embryonal carcinoma cells (ECCs) are regarded as equivalent to germ cells or early embryonic cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Damjanov1">[2]</xref>. In previous studies, a teratocarcinomas model was established via extrauterine transplantation of pregastrulation stage embryos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Stevens1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Solter1">[4]</xref>, and then Evans et al achieved the establishment of in vitro culture methods of mouse ECCs by co-cultured with fibroblasts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Evans1">[5]</xref>. On this basis, isolating mouse embryonic stem cells (ESCs) from blastocysts was achieved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Evans1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Martin1">[6]</xref>. Additionally, homologous mouse or Immuno-deficiency mouse injected with ESCs can also generate teratomas or teratocarcinomas, which became one of a common method to detect the pluripotent of ESCs. However, it also became a security barrier for cell replacement therapy of ESCs.</p>
      <p>The study of teratocarcinomas makes cancer “stem cell” or embryonal origin become one of the most widely accepted theory in the process of cancer occurrence. The embryonal rest theory proposed that cancers arose from displacement of embryonic cells and the stem cell theory suggested that tumor arose from dedifferentiation of mature cells or from maturation arrest of immature stem cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Sell1">[7]</xref>. Several researches revealed that ECCs and ESCs give rise to teratocarcinomas in the adult milieu. Also, it can develop into normal individuals when injecting them into blastocysts, indicating that the environmental factors can control the malignant of cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Brinster1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Papaioannou1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Mintz1">[10]</xref>. Another study showed that the sequential transplantation of ECCs in vivo can accelerate the growth and malignancy of teratocarcinomas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Damjanov2">[11]</xref>, suggesting that the molecular mechanisms in this process may reflect cancer formation in the early stage.</p>
      <p>In our study, we established a tumorigenesis model in which teratocarcinomas were developed via injecting embryonic stem cells into immuno-deficiency mice. We used serum-free and feeder-free 2i culture system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Ying1">[12]</xref> to establish ECCs cell lines and sequential transplantation in vivo to obtain higher malignancy level of ECCs cell lines. Furthermore, we performed high-throughput deep sequence technology to identify some malignancy-related genes via comparing the gene expression level between ESCs and series of ECCs which may play a key role in the early stage of cancer occurrence.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Tumor Induction and Teratocarcinoma Stem Cells Isolation</title>
        <p>The Oct4-GFP (Oct-4 promoter driving a green fluorescent protein reporter) ES cell line was present by Professor Qilong Ying <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Ying2">[13]</xref>. BALB/c athymic mice were purchased from Shanghai Experimental Animal Center, Chinese Academy of Sciences. All animal experiments were carried out in adherence with the National Institutes of Health Guidelines on the Use of Laboratory Animals and approved by the Second Military Medical University Committee on Animal Care (EC11–055). The ES cells were dissociated into a single-cell by trypsin/EDTA and resuspended in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). About 5×10<sup>6</sup> ES cells (in 100 microlitres) was injected subcutaneously into inbred BALB/c athymic nude mice. When the diameter of tumor was up to 1.5 cm, the tumor was removed from sacrificed nude mice, washed each three times in PBS and cut into 1cubic millimeter pieces. After digesting by collagenase IV for 30 min at 37°C, the cell suspension was filtered through an 200-mesh sieve and centrifuged for 3 minutes at 100 g. Then the cells were plated in culture flask. The composition of culture medium contained N2B27+2i (Neurobasal 50 ml, DMEM/F12 50 ml, 100×N2 1 ml, 50×B27 2 ml, 100×L-Glutamine 1ml, CHIR99021 3 µM, PD0325901 1 µM). We have successfully established a stable cell line named G1 (Generation I). According to the same method, G1 was inoculated subcutaneously into nude mice, and then teratocarcinomas stem cell named G2 (Generation II) was isolated from the outgrowth tumor. Again, we subsequently repeated the above procedure to obtain cell line named G3 (Generation III). In each generation, a representative teratocarcinomas was took and fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 36 hr. After that, teratocarcinomas were embedded in paraffin, then sectioned and stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Limiting Dilution Analysis and Proliferation</title>
        <p>For limiting dilution analysis, G1 cells were cultured in 96-well plates in 2i DMEM. Wells with single cell were marked and observed after 6 days. Different generations of teratocarcinoma stem cells and Oct4-GFP ES cells were cultured in 6-well plates at 3×10<sup>5</sup> cells per well. We passage cells every 3 days, counted cell number, and then calculated doubling time.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Immunostaining</title>
        <p>Cells were prepared for immunostaining via being fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 15 min and subsequent permeabilized for 10 min with 0.3% Triton-X in PBS. Cells were then blocked for non-specific binding with 10% normal goat or donkey serum (Abcam) in PBS for 1–2 hr at room temperature. Primary antibodies were diluted in blocking solution and incubated with the samples overnight at 4°C. Samples were rinsed with PBS and incubated with the PE labeled Rabbit Anti-Goat IgG (Invitrogen, 1∶500) for 1 hr at room temperature. Primary antibodies were listed as follows: goat polyclonal IgG Sox2 (sc-54517; Santa Cruz, 1∶100) and goat polyclonal IgG Nanog (sc-30329; Santa Cruz, 1∶100).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Reverse Transcription PCR</title>
        <p>Total RNA was prepared using the RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen) with DNaseI treatment. First-strand cDNA was synthesised using Superscript III reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen). The primers for PCR amplification of interested genes were listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043955.s004">Table S2</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Comparison of Tumorigenicity</title>
        <p>G1, G2, and G3 cells of pair-wise combination were injected subcutaneously into both sides of the nude mice with 5×10<sup>6</sup> cells. All 12 nude mice in the experiment were killed after 3 weeks. We removed tumor and weighted immediately. Moreover, each representative generation of teratocarcinoma was chosed and fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 36 hr. And then fixed teratocarcinoma were embedded in paraffin, sectioned and stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Raw Sequence Reads Preprocessing of Deep Sequence Dataset</title>
        <p>RNA sequence was produced by BGI Company via Illumina HiSeq™ 2000 platform. The original image data is transferred into sequence data by base calling, which is named as raw sequence reads and saved as fastq files. Before bioinformatics analysis, data filtering was performed to get the clean reads including three steps: removed reads with adaptors sequence, removed reads in which unknown bases are more than 10% and removed low quality reads which the percentage of the low quality bases of quality value ≤5 is more than 50% in a read. And then the clean reads were mapped to reference sequences using soap2 software <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Li1">[14]</xref>. After the preprocessing steps, the gene expression level is calculated by RPKM method (Reads Per kb per Million reads) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Mortazavi1">[15]</xref>. The formula of RPKM algorithms is shown as follows:<disp-formula id="pone.0043955.e001"><graphic orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></p>
        <p>Given RPKM to be the expression of gene A, C represented the number of reads that uniquely aligned to gene A, N represented the total number of reads that uniquely aligned to all genes, and L represented the number of bases on gene A. The RPKM method is able to eliminate the influence of different gene length and sequencing discrepancy when calculating the expression of genes. Therefore, the calculated value can be directly used for comparing the difference of gene expression among experimental samples.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Bioinformatics Analysis of the Dataset</title>
        <p>We performed Fold Change method to identify the genes differed in expression level between three generation samples of teratocarcinoma and ES sample respectively which we called Group1 genes and also identify significant genes among G1, G2 and G3 samples which was named as Group2 genes. Moreover, two-way hierarchical global clustering was performed to all genes using Cluster 3.0 software. We chose centered correlation for array measurement, Euclidean distance for gene measurement and average linkage algorithms.</p>
        <p>Functional analysis was performed to map differentially expressed genes in Gene Ontology (GO) database, which is an international standardized gene functional classification system including three ontologies: molecular function, cellular component and biological process. We mapped several interested genes to GO database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneontology.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.geneontology.org/</ext-link>), and then used hypergeometric test to evaluate significantly enriched GO terms. The p-value calculating formula is:<disp-formula id="pone.0043955.e002"><graphic orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></p>
        <p>We define N as the number of all genes with GO annotation; n is the number of interested genes in N; M is the number of all genes that are annotated to the certain GO terms; m is the number of interested genes in M.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, pathway enrichment analysis was performed to map significant genes in KEGG pathway database via Pathway-Express software. The calculation method of p-value is the same as that of functional analysis. Here N is the number of all genes that with KEGG annotation, n is the number of interested genes in N, M is the number of all genes annotated to specific pathways, and m is number of interested genes in M. A p-value was calculated to each candidate pathway and went through FDR correction. We took corrected p-value ≤0.05 as a threshold. Chromosome analysis was also performed on identified differentially expressed genes. The Gene database in NCBI was used to query the exact chromosome location of interested genes. Chromosome maps were displayed by Endemble.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>2i Culture Medium is Suitable for the Growth of Teratocarcinoma Stem Cells</title>
        <p>To induce teratocarcinoma, Oct4-GFP ES cells were subcutaneously injected into immuno-deficiency nude mice. Three weeks later teratocarcinoma cells obtained from the tumor were cultured in 2i medium. After 3 days, the compact clones were composed of small cell emerged with ES cell-like phenotype including dome shape, little cytoplasm and high nuclear-cytoplasmic ratio (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). The isolated cells were named as G1(Generation I) which can long-term passage in 2i culture condition, maintain ES cells-like phenotype, have rapid proliferation feature and colony formation ability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g001">Figure 1B</xref>) and express pluripotent markers of ES cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). To obtain a second generation of teratocarcinoma, G1 cells were inoculated into nude mice again. We isolated G2 cells using 2i culture system and subsequently obtained G3 cells in the same manner. The characteristics of G2 and G3 cells were the same as those of G1 cells, maintaining ES cell-like phenotype, rapid proliferation and expressing pluripotent markers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g002">Figure 2B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0043955-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The feature of teratocarcinoma stem cells.</title>
            <p>A. the phenotype of clones was same as that of ES cells. B. the clones formed by 6-day-cultured single cell. C: expressing pluripotency-related genes including Oct4, Sox2 and Nanog with alkaline phosphatase-positive.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0043955-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Changes of characteristics of teratocarcinoma stem cells after sequential transplantation.</title>
            <p>A. the growth curve of teratocarcinoma stem cell marked doubling time. B Decreasing or disappearing expression of pluripotency-related genes of G3 cell cultured by DMEM +10% FBS.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Changes of Characteristics of Teratocarcinoma Stem Cells after Sequential Transplantation</title>
        <p>First, we compared the proliferation rate among different transplant generation of teratocarcinoma stem cells, identifying that the doubling time of these cells was about the same as those of embryonic stem cells (17 h VS 17.3 h) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). When cultured in DMEM +10% FBS medium, G1 and G2 cells cannot be passage (data not shown). However, G3 cells can grow in a monolayer (denominated G3-DF) and long-term passage (more than 100 passages) but unfortunately lose the majority pluripotent markers of ES cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043955.s001">Figure S1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g002">Figure 2B</xref>), in which only a few cells showed weakly alkaline phosphatase activity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043955.s001">Figure S1B</xref>). Furthermore, when we subcutaneously injected long-term cultured G3-DF cells into immuno-deficiency nude mice, teratocarcinoma outgrew still. It is interesting that if we cultured G3-DF cells long-term cultured with DMEM +10% FBS medium in 2i condition, these cells acquired ES cells-like characteristics again (data not show).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Increasing Malignant Degree of Teratocarcinoma after Sequential Transplantation</title>
        <p>We wonder whether the degree of malignancy increased in vivo correspondingly, for which we compared the growth rate and malignant degree of teratocarcinoma via subcutaneously inoculating different generations of teratocarcinoma stem cells into nude mice on both sides of the body. It showed that after sequential transplantation the tumor formation rate of teratocarcinoma stem cells accelerated in immuno-deficient mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Teratocarcinoma formed by ES cells mainly composed by a variety of adult tissues containing a small amount of malignant tissue. However, teratocarcinomas formed by sequential transplantation of teratocarcinoma stem cells mainly composed by poorly differentiated adenocarcinoma, carcinomatous nerve tissue and squamous cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Therefore, we suggested that sequential heterotopic transplantation could accelerate malignant degree of teratocarcinoma stem cells.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0043955-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The malignant degree of teratocarcinoma increased after sequential transplantation.</title>
            <p>A. Different generation of teratocarcinoma stem cells and ES cells were injected subcutaneously into nude mice on both sides of the body; the teratocarcinoma growth of G3 cells was significantly faster than that of ES cells. B. With the increasing of transplantation generation, it accelerated the tumor formation of teratocarcinoma stem cells.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0043955-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>H &amp; E stained tissue sections of teratocarcinoma.</title>
            <p>A. H &amp; E stained tissue sections of teratocarcinoma formed after inoculating ES cells in nude mice. A1 muscle, A2 cartilage, A3 glands, A4 bone, A5 nerve, A6 hair follicle; B H &amp; E stained tissue sections of teratocarcinoma formed after injecting G3 cells in nude mice. B1 malignant neural tube, B2 squamous cell carcinoma with keratin pearls, B3 adenocarcinoma.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Bioinformatics Analysis of Mouse Teratocarcinoma Deep Sequence Dataset</title>
        <p>In <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0043955-t001">Table 1</xref>, it summarized the detail sample information of RNA sequence dataset via high-throughput deep sequence technology. To evaluate the quality of the sequence raw data, we performed the distribution statistics analysis of all reads (See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043955.s002">Figure S2</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g005">Figure 5A</xref> showed the scatterplots comparing the gene-specific deviation of three generation teratocarcinoma cell line with ES cell lines respectively, in which several pluripotent genes such as Oct4, Sox2, Nanog were marked. Genes with similar expression patterns usually mean functional correlation. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g005">Figure 5B</xref> described the global cluster analysis of all genes among four samples. When thinking about the differences between ES cell and three teratocarcinoma cell, the 1673 genes whose fold change &gt;2 were up or down regulated consistently among G1 vs. ES, G2 vs. ES and G3 vs. ES samples. These genes were named as Group1 interested genes. Moreover, to investigate the difference among three generations teratocarcinoma samples, we performed the same analysis manner in G1 vs. G2 and G2 vs. G3 samples, 331 genes were satisfied with fold change &gt;2 which we called group2 interested genes. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g005">Figure 5C</xref> showed the overlapping gene number between group1 and group2, in which 26 of the 38 overlapped genes were up/down expressed consistently among G1 vs. ES, G2 vs. G1 and G3 vs. G2 samples. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g005">Figure 5D</xref> showed the gene clustering result of these 26 indentified genes. Then, in order to identify the functional classification of these 26 genes, we performed functional enrichment analysis in GeneOntology database. The detail result was listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043955.s003">Table S1</xref>. Furthermore, chromosome enrichment analysis was also performed to these 26 interested genes. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g005">Figure 5E</xref>, it showed that chromosome 12 and 3 was enriched by our interested genes which contained four and three genes, respectively. Chromosomes 2,8,11 and 17 enriched two genes. These six chromosomes occupied a total number of 57.7%. In addition, to identify differential genes of Group1/Group2 enriched in which kind of biological pathways, pathway enrichment analysis was performed in KEGG database. The analysis result revealed that wnt signaling pathway, primary immunodeficiency pathway, antigen processing and presentation pathway and allograft rejection pathway were involved in the teratocarcinoma tumorigenesis (corrected p value&lt;0.05). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043955-g006">Figure 6</xref> showed the map of Wnt signaling pathway and 17 significant genes were marked on the map in which wnt3a, wnt9a and wnt16 were mapped to the same object (Wnt protein) and Ppp2cb and Ppp2r5 were mapped to PP2A protein.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0043955-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Bioinformatics analysis of mouse teratocarcinoma microarray dataset.</title>
            <p>A. Scatter plots of global gene expression patterns between teratocarcinoma sample(y axis) and ES sample (x axis). Red, gray and blue represent gene expression levels up, equivalent and down between the samples. The positions of pluripotent genes such as Oct4, Sox2, Nanog were marked by green spot. B. Two-way hierarchical global clustering of microarray dataset C. Overlapping analysis of two groups of genes. D. Two-way hierarchical clustering of 26 identified genes. E. the result of chromosome enrichment analysis of 26 interested genes.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0043955-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>the map of Wnt signaling pathway.</title>
            <p>The map of wnt signaling pathway included at least three different Wnt pathways: the canonical pathway, the planar cell polarity (PCP) pathway and the Wnt/Ca2+ pathway. Most of the interested genes enriched in canonical pathway. The highly-expressed genes identified from dataset are represented with red color, and the down-regulated genes are represented with green color. The key genes of wnt signaling pathway such as wnt and beta-catenin were identified and marked in the map.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0043955-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>The information of mouse RNA sequence dataset.</title>
          </caption><alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0043955-t001-1" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample ID</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ES</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mouse embryonic stem cell</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mouse teratocarcinoma generation I</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mouse teratocarcinoma generation II</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mouse teratocarcinoma generation III</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives></table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Based on the hypothesis that tumor originated in the early stage of remaining embryonic pluripotent cells and the fact that ECCs sequential transplantation in vivo could accelerate the growth and malignancy of teratocarcinomas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Damjanov2">[11]</xref>, we obtained teratocarcinoma via injecting ICM origin pluripotent stem cells subcutaneously into immune-deficient mice, and then isolated teratocarcinoma stem cells and used sequential transplantation to simulate early stage of tumor development and progression. Furthermore, we performed microarray analysis to identify candidate genes which may play a key role in the changes of malignancy of teratocarcinoma stem cell.</p>
      <p>Teratocarcinoma stem cells have self-renewal and unlimited proliferation feature as same as those of mES cells. Self-renewal is an intrinsic property of mES cells which is not depend on extracellular factors and inhibition of differentiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Ying1">[12]</xref>. Similarly, using small molecule inhibitors (2i) to inhibit the differentiation of teratocarcinoma stem cells can maintain their self-renewal and unlimited proliferation, and with the increasing times of migration, the expression of pluripotency-related genes in teratocarcinoma stem cells and ES cells are considerable which indicated that teratocarcinoma stem cells and mES cells may use the same molecular mechanism to maintain their self-renewal.</p>
      <p>Our research is similar to the previous study of using the ECCs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Damjanov2">[11]</xref>, after sequential transplantation in vivo the growth and malignancy degree of teratocarcinoma stem cells increased and showed a trend to the neuroectodermal differentiation. And the accelerated formation rate of teratocarcinoma is not due to the increasing growth rate of teratocarcinoma stem cells. The teratocarcinoma stem cell via sequential transplantation can be long-term cultured in DMEM +10% FBS like many other tumor cell lines. In this culture condition, the expression of majority pluripotency-related genes greatly down-regulated or disappear. However, it is also worth to note that the expression of Oct4 is still weak. Several studies indicated that Oct4 played a key role in the generation and maintenance of teratocarcinoma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Chambers1">[16]</xref>. Other researchers found that Oct4 also expressed in some tumor cells and they speculated that it may be cancer stem cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Chiou1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Peng1">[18]</xref>. In conclusion, these results suggested that the internal changes of teratocarcinoma stem cell are result from sequential transplantation which may reflect the early process of tumor development.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, microarray analysis result showed that 26 differentially expressed genes related to the changes of characteristics of teratocarcinoma stem cell in which 18 out of 26 genes were down-regulated and 8 genes were up-regulated. Among these genes, Gata3 and Arnt were well-known tumor-associated genes. Gata3 regulates tumor differentiation, suppresses tumor metastasis in breast cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-KourosMehr1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Yan1">[20]</xref> and increased Arnt (HIF-1) activity promotes tumor progression. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Semenza1">[21]</xref> Other genes such as PHC1 and Uty were reported as epigenetic related genes. PHC1 is a component of the Polycomb group (PcG) multiprotein PRC1 complex, a complex required to maintain the transcriptionally repressive state of many genes throughout development including Hox genes. PcG PRC1 complex acts via chromatin remodeling and modification of histones. Uty is a gene that encodes a demethylase. This result is consistent with previous study that indicated epigenetic change played a crucial role in the development of teratoma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-BulicJakus1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Bonner1">[23]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Additionally, WNT signaling plays a pivotal role in the tissue lineage differentiation during embryogenesis and the maintenance and self renewal of embryo-derived stem cells in vitro <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Tanaka1">[24]</xref>. A lot of researches have proven that tumor stem cell involved many of the same signaling pathways that are found in normal stem cells including Wnt signaling pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Takebe1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Espada1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Vermeulen1">[27]</xref>, which was thought to play a central role in transformation normal stem cells into cancer stem cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Lu1">[28]</xref>. In this study, pathway enrichment analysis also showed that wnt signaling pathway may play an important function in the process of characteristics changes of teratocarcinoma.</p>
      <p>Also, we performed overlapping analysis between our study and Bonner’s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Bonner1">[23]</xref> study. Among the 53 genes identified by Bonner et al, seven genes, Cxcl1, Gata6, Pdlim4, Rasd1, Tdgf1, Bcat1 and Fst, were overlapped with our analysis. Among these significant candidate genes, the mouse Bcat1 gene has shown to be amplified and over-expressed in a teratocarcinoma cell line <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-deBont1">[29]</xref>. Ben-Yosef’s study indicated that the expression level of Bcat1 is induced during proliferation, the cytosolic BCAT1 activity was detected during fetal development and only in some adult tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-BenYosef1">[30]</xref>. Previous study also demonstrated that the Gata6 gene regulated Wnt signaling pathway which played a core role in epithelial stem cell development and airway regeneration, and in pancreatic cancer GATA6 activates Wnt signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Zhong1">[31]</xref>. Tdgf1, teratocarcinoma-derived growth factor-1, is also a well-known gene played an essential role in tumor growth and metastasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043955-Miyoshi1">[32]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In summary, we established a tumorigenesis model in which teratocarcinomas were induced via injecting ES cells into immuno-deficiency mice, then isolated teratocarcinoma stem cells from a teratocarcinoma and injected teratocarcinoma stem cells into immune-deficient mice continuously. Through microarray analysis of teratocarcinoma stem cells, we identified several tumor-related genes, epigenetic associated genes and several significant pathways such as wnt signaling pathway, which may be associated with early onset of tumor development.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0043955.s001" mimetype="image/jpeg" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Changes of G3 cells cultured in DMEM +10% FBS.</bold> A Monolayer phenotype of G3 cell cultured in DMEM +10% FBS; B Only part of G3 cells keep weakly alkaline phosphatase activity cultured in DMEM +10% FBS.</p>
          <p>(JPG)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0043955.s002" mimetype="image/jpeg" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>the distribution statistics of all reads.</bold> Each figure represented the classification of raw reads in each sample. “Only Adaptor (N1, P1%)” means the number of reads containing adaptor is N1 and the proportion is P1% of total reads. “Cotaining N (N2, P2%)” means the number of reads containing N is N2 and the proportion is P2% of the total reads. “Low Quality (N3, P3%)” means the number of low quality reads is N3 and the proportion is P3% of the total reads. “Clean Reads (N4, P4%)” means the number of clean reads is N4 and the proportion is P4% of the total reads.</p>
          <p>(JPG)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0043955.s003" mimetype="application/msword" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>the result of GO enrichment analysis of 26 interested genes.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0043955.s004" mimetype="application/msword" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043955.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>the primers for reverse transcription PCR.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Fawcett1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fawcett</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name> (<year>1950</year>) <article-title>Bilateral ovarian teratomas in a mouse</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>705</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Damjanov1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Damjanov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Teratocarcinoma: neoplastic lessons about normal embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Int J Dev Biol</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Stevens1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name> (<year>1970</year>) <article-title>The development of transplantable teratocarcinomas from intratesticular grafts of pre- and postimplantation mouse embryos</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>364</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Solter1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Solter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skreb</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Damjanov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1970</year>) <article-title>Extrauterine growth of mouse egg-cylinders results in malignant teratoma</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>227</volume>: <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Evans1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Establishment in culture of pluripotential cells from mouse embryos</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>292</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Martin1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Isolation of a pluripotent cell line from early mouse embryos cultured in medium conditioned by teratocarcinoma stem cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>7634</fpage>–<lpage>7638</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Sell1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Cellular origin of cancer: dedifferentiation or stem cell maturation arrest</article-title>? <source>Environ Health Perspect</source> <volume>101</volume> <supplement>Suppl 5</supplement>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Brinster1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brinster</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>The effect of cells transferred into the mouse blastocyst on subsequent development</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source> <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>1049</fpage>–<lpage>1056</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Papaioannou1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Papaioannou</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McBurney</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Fate of teratocarcinoma cells injected into early mouse embryos</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>258</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Mintz1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mintz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Illmensee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Normal genetically mosaic mice produced from malignant teratocarcinoma cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>3585</fpage>–<lpage>3589</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Damjanov2">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Damjanov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Teratocarcinoma with the capacity for differentiation restricted to neuro-ectodermal tissue</article-title>. <source>Virchows Arch B Cell Pathol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Ying1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Batlle-Morera</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doble</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The ground state of embryonic stem cell self-renewal</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>453</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>523</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Ying2">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Changing potency by spontaneous fusion</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>416</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Li1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yiu</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>SOAP2: an improved ultrafast tool for short read alignment</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1966</fpage>–<lpage>1967</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Mortazavi1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>621</fpage>–<lpage>628</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Chambers1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Self-renewal of teratocarcinoma and embryonic stem cells</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>7150</fpage>–<lpage>7160</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Chiou1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiou</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Coexpression of Oct4 and Nanog enhances malignancy in lung adenocarcinoma by inducing cancer stem cell-like properties and epithelial-mesenchymal transdifferentiation</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>10433</fpage>–<lpage>10444</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Peng1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maihle</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Pluripotency factors Lin28 and Oct4 identify a sub-population of stem cell-like cells in ovarian cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>2153</fpage>–<lpage>2159</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-KourosMehr1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kouros-Mehr</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bechis</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slorach</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Littlepage</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egeblad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>GATA-3 links tumor differentiation and dissemination in a luminal breast cancer model</article-title>. <source>Cancer Cell</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Yan1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arenas</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>GATA3 inhibits breast cancer metastasis through the reversal of epithelial-mesenchymal transition</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>14042</fpage>–<lpage>14051</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Semenza1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semenza</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>HIF-1 and tumor progression: pathophysiology and therapeutics</article-title>. <source>Trends Mol Med</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>S62</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-BulicJakus1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bulic-Jakus</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ulamec</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlahovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sincic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katusic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Of mice and men: teratomas and teratocarcinomas</article-title>. <source>Coll Antropol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>921</fpage>–<lpage>924</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Bonner1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonner</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Gene expression profiling of mouse teratocarcinomas uncovers epigenetic changes associated with the transformation of mouse embryonic stem cells</article-title>. <source>Neoplasia</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>490</fpage>–<lpage>502</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Tanaka1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishinakamura</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Impact of WNT signaling on tissue lineage differentiation in the early mouse embryo</article-title>. <source>Dev Growth Differ</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>856</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Takebe1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takebe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>RQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ivy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Targeting cancer stem cells by inhibiting Wnt, Notch, and Hedgehog pathways</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Clin Oncol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Espada1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Espada</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz-Prado</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Wnt signalling and cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Clin Transl Oncol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Vermeulen1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeulen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Sousa</surname><given-names>EMF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Heijden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Wnt activity defines colon cancer stem cells and is regulated by the microenvironment</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>468</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Lu1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of Wnt signaling and cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>587</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-deBont1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Bont</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kros</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Passier</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reddingius</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sillevis Smitt</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Differential expression and prognostic significance of SOX genes in pediatric medulloblastoma and ependymoma identified by microarray analysis</article-title>. <source>Neuro Oncol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>648</fpage>–<lpage>660</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-BenYosef1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Yosef</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benvenisty</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Characterization of murine BCAT genes: Bcat1, a c-Myc target, and its homolog, Bcat2</article-title>. <source>Mamm Genome</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>595</fpage>–<lpage>597</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Zhong1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yachida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>GATA6 activates Wnt signaling in pancreatic cancer by negatively regulating the Wnt antagonist Dickkopf-1</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e22129</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043955-Miyoshi1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mimori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sekimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>TDGF1 is a novel predictive marker for metachronous metastasis of colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Int J Oncol</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>563</fpage>–<lpage>568</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>