<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-10405</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075278</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Egg-Laying “Intermorphs” in the Ant <italic>Crematogaster smithi</italic> neither Affect Sexual Production nor Male Parentage</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Intermorphs in <italic>Crematogaster smithi</italic></alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oettler</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkstra</surname><given-names>Michiel B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>Jürgen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Biologie I, Universität Regensburg, Regensburg, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Ecology and Evolution, University of Lausanne, Lausanne, Switzerland</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>Deborah M.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Stanford University, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">jan.oettler@biologie.uni-regensburg.de</email> (JO); <email xlink:type="simple">michiel.b.dijkstra@gmail.com</email> (MBD)</corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JO JH. Performed the experiments: JO MBD. Analyzed the data: JO MBD. Wrote the paper: JO MBD JH.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<elocation-id>e75278</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Oettler et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We study male parentage and between-colony variation in sex allocation and sexual production in the desert ant <italic>Crematogaster smithi</italic>, which usually has only one singly-mated queen per nest. Colonies of this species are known to temporarily store nutrients in the large fat body of intermorphs, a specialized female caste intermediate in morphology between queens and workers. Intermorphs repackage at least part of this fat into consumable but viable male-destined eggs. If these eggs sometimes develop instead of being eaten, intermorphs will be reproductive competitors of the queen but—due to relatedness asymmetries—allies of their sister worker. Using genetic markers we found a considerable proportion of non-queen sons in some, but not all, colonies. Even though intermorphs produce ∼1.7× more eggs than workers, their share in the parentage of adult males is estimated to be negligible due to their small number compared to workers. Furthermore, neither colony-level sex allocation nor overall sexual production was correlated with intermorph occurrence or number. We conclude that intermorph-laid eggs typically do not survive and that the storage of nutrients and their redistribution as eggs by intermorphs is effectively altruistic.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by two grants to JO from the German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD) and a Marie Curie grant 41343-INVICTA2 to MBD. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>As in non-social organisms, resource availability constrains how much colonies of wasps, bees, and ants (order Hymenoptera, with haplodiploid sex determination) can allocate to reproduction: the greater the number and size of dispersing virgin queens and males raised per reproductive season, the less workers can be raised to sustain colony growth. It is thus imperative that workers, who nurse the brood, raise only those sexuals that yield the highest fitness return on investment.</p>
<p>The discrimination by workers in favor of some brood categories is the expression of two potential queen-worker conflicts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Foster1">[1]</xref>. The first conflict, over which males should be raised, occurs because all females (e.g. workers, mother queens, mature virgin queens) can lay unfertilized, haploid, male eggs and thus compete over the production of males (for exceptions see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Dijkstra1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Khila1">[3]</xref>). It has been shown that workers and queens of many ants, bees, and wasps selectively eat those eggs to which they are least related (“worker policing”, “selfish policing”, or “queen policing”, depending on whether the egg-eater is a non-reproductive or reproductive worker or a queen: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Ratnieks1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Wenseleers1">[5]</xref>).</p>
<p>The second conflict is over the sex ratio: queens are equally related to daughters and sons, so that an average colony sex allocation ratio of 0.5 (i.e. 50% energy invested in virgin queens and 50% in males) is typically optimal for queens (for exceptions see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Pamilo1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Chapuisat1">[7]</xref>). But due to haplodiploidy, workers are more related to sisters than to brothers, so that the workers' optimum for the average colony sex allocation ratio is always more virgin queen-biased than the queen's optimum <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Pamilo1">[6]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Kmmerli1">[10]</xref>. A colony's final sex ratio is constrained by the queen's output of female (fertilized) and male (unfertilized) eggs, and other females' output of exclusively male eggs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Chapuisat1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Mehdiabadi1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Helanter1">[16]</xref>, but nurse workers are known to influence the final sex ratio by preferential cannibalization of larvae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Chapuisat2">[17]</xref>. The queen-worker conflict over the sex ratio has been “won” by the workers in many taxa (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Bourke1">[18]</xref>), but there are exceptions to this general pattern <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Beekman1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-DeMenten1">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Helanter1">[16]</xref>.</p>
<p>Queen and worker optima can predict not only the average colony sex allocation ratio, but also the between-colony variation in sex ratio. A non-unimodal distribution of colony sex ratios may indicate that workers follow a conditional behavioral strategy for sex allocation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Sundstrm1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Herbers1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Dijkstra2">[21]</xref>. For example, workers of many species have been shown to increase their inclusive fitness by preferentially raising virgin queens or males, depending on whether the colony-specific ratio of the relatedness of workers to sisters versus brothers is smaller versus greater, respectively, than the population average (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Meunier1">[22]</xref>).</p>
<p>Another well-documented conditional strategy of eusocial Hymenoptera is to raise preferentially virgin queens in large, well-fed colonies and preferentially males in small, poorly fed colonies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Nonacs1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Deslippe1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Smith2">[31]</xref>. Food-dependent sex ratios are an example of the Trivers-Willard theory of sex allocation, which predicts that females (or colonies in eusocial taxa) with few resources should preferentially produce offspring of the sex whose reproductive success is least sensitive to variation in maternal investment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Trivers2">[32]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Bosch1">[35]</xref>; reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Sheldon1">[36]</xref>). Furthermore, the cost ratio hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Nonacs1">[20]</xref>, but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Boomsma1">[37]</xref>), the constant male hypothesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Frank1">[38]</xref> and the multifaceted parental investment theory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Rosenheim1">[39]</xref> predict sex allocation based on resource availability. In eusocial Hymenoptera, food limitation is thought to impinge most on the virgin queens' future reproductive success because: (1) males are smaller, live considerably shorter, and have smaller fat reserves than queens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Dijkstra1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Nonacs1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Brown1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Boomsma2">[40]</xref>; (2) males of ants exclusively produce sperm as pupae, so their fecundity and fertility is hardly affected by food availability after eclosion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Boomsma2">[40]</xref>; (3) males do not fight and hence should benefit less from a larger body size than queens, who are known to fight over nest sites during the colony founding stage in many taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Boomsma2">[40]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Suefuji1">[44]</xref>; for exceptions to points 2–3 see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze1">[45]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Schrempf2">[47]</xref>).</p>
<p>Here we study an unusual extension of the typical queen-worker conflict over sex allocation and male parentage in the ant <italic>Crematogaster smithi</italic> from Arizona. In addition to workers and queens, colonies may contain one or several “intermorphs,” which are intermediate between queens and workers in body size, morphology, and ovarian morphology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze2">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze3">[49]</xref>. As such they have to be considered different from major worker castes with specialized morphological adaptations to distinct tasks. Major worker castes occur in many ant lineages. The functions of major workers are as diverse as food processing in <italic>Pheidole</italic>, nest entrance blocking in turtle ants, soldier behavior in army ants or leaf carrying in leafcutter ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Hlldobler1">[50]</xref>. Intermorphs are widespread in the subgenus <italic>Crematogaster</italic> (<italic>Orthocrema</italic>) (e. g., <italic>C.</italic> cf. <italic>baduvi</italic>, <italic>C. curvispinosa</italic>, <italic>C. bryophilia</italic>, <italic>C. nigropilosa</italic>, <italic>C. rasoherinae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Buschinger1">[51]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Peeters1">[54]</xref>). In <italic>C. smithi</italic>, intermorphs lack a spermatheca for the storage of sperm but have developed ovaries with numerous developing oocytes. The behavior of <italic>C. smithi</italic> intermorphs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze2">[48]</xref> shows that they are clearly not a soldier caste in spite of having been described as one recently <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Peeters1">[54]</xref>. Most of the eggs laid by intermorphs are eaten by the larvae and by the queen, though a previous, small-scale genetic study indicated that at least some survive and develop into adult males <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze4">[55]</xref>.</p>
<p>The aim of the present study was to determine who benefits from the intermorphs' presence: the whole colony, the queen, the collective of the workers, or only the intermorphs themselves. Like “fat body repletes” (<italic>cf.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Brgensen1">[56]</xref>) known from other ants, intermorphs might serve as sinks for food gathered by workers and store energy and nutrients as fat, which they can redistribute to colony mates in the form of consumable eggs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze2">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze3">[49]</xref>. As the availability of food strongly affects sex allocation ratios, the presence of intermorphs might be associated with the production of more sexuals and a more female-biased sex allocation ratio. Alternatively, intermorphs might be reproductive allies of their worker sisters. <italic>C. smithi</italic> queens are singly mated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze4">[55]</xref> and workers therefore are more closely related to intermorph sons than to queen sons. To increase relatedness to the male brood while avoiding the expected colony-level productivity costs of having numerous reproductively inefficient egg-laying workers in the colony (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Dijkstra3">[57]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Wenseleers2">[59]</xref>), workers could thus benefit from raising a few fecund, reproductively efficient intermorph sisters whose sons will replace queen sons (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Tsuneoka1">[60]</xref> for male-producing intermorphs in <italic>Polyergus samurai</italic>).</p>
<p>We estimated sexual production, relative sex ratio bias towards costly virgin queens, and male parentage (and thus the average relatedness of intermorphs, queens, and workers to the males) in field and laboratory colonies of <italic>C. smithi</italic> with varying numbers of intermorphs. We also collected life history data (colony composition, egg laying rates, worker-worker relatedness and effective queen mating frequency estimated with genetic markers) from a considerably larger number of colonies compared to previous studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze2">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze3">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze4">[55]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Study species</title>
<p><italic>Crematogaster smithi</italic> (Creighton 1950) occurs in mixed forests in the arid mountains of Arizona, USA, and Sonora, Mexico, and lives in underground nests consisting of a single tunnel (up to 40 cm deep) with up to 10 nest chambers. Between July and early August, multiple synchronized mating flights occur during the evenings of rainy days. Queens found new colonies independently and claustrally, i.e. they start a new nest without the help from workers and raise the first brood without foraging. Sexuals develop from eggs laid in late summer, overwinter as larvae, pupate around March and reach maturity around June. During the cool evenings and nights, forager workers hunt for small insects and consume these outside the nest (J.O. &amp; C.R. Smith, personal field observations).</p>
<p>In queenright colonies, queens, workers, and intermorphs lay viable “large” eggs (∼0.5 mm long) and in addition also flaccid “small” eggs (&lt;0.4 mm long) that fail to develop. Queens produce proportionally more (∼19% of queen-laid eggs) small eggs than intermorphs (∼2%) and workers (∼3) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze2">[48]</xref> Queens and larvae exclusively feed on these “large” and “small” eggs, but it is unknown whether they discriminate between worker-, intermorph-, and queen-laid eggs.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Collection and maintenance of colonies</title>
<p>In July 2005 and 2006 we excavated complete colonies of <italic>C. smithi</italic> near the Southwestern Research Station (SWRS) in the Chiricahua Mountains, Arizona. A permit was obtained from the SWRS to work on Forest Service property. Immediately after collection, we counted all workers, intermorphs, mother queens, virgin queens, and males, and preserved all virgin females and males and a sample of workers in &gt;99% ethanol for genotyping. Adult sexuals, worker larvae and pupae, and callow (i.e. recently emerged from the pupa) and mature workers, but no sexual larvae or pupae were present at the time of collection. Colonies were transported to Germany and maintained in the laboratory (24°C and 60% relative humidity, with a day/night cycle that was twice a month adjusted to Arizona's latitude), where they were fed three times weekly with chopped cockroaches and diluted honey. In June 2006, we collected newly produced adult males from five of these 2005 laboratory colonies containing intermorphs – all of which had retained their queen – and stored them in &gt;99% ethanol for additional genotyping. In February 2009, we sampled additional males from four colonies that had been maintained in the laboratory since 2005 and which did not contain any intermorphs. We also analyzed caste composition data from additional 74 colonies collected between 1992 and 1998 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze2">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze3">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze4">[55]</xref> from the same population for which no sex allocation data were available. For an overview of the data used see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0075278-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0075278-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Summary table of samples.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0075278-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collection years</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nr colonies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used for: Caste composition</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used for: Sex allocation (field)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used for: Male parentage (field)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used for: Male parentage (lab)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1992–1998</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 colonies with intermorph (45 males [median 10.5, range 7–17], 46 workers); re-analyzed from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze4">[55]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2005</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 colonies (149 workers, 156 males, colonies with intermorph), Different colonies than for Male parentage in lab colonies</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2006</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 colonies with intermorph (60 males [median 13, range 6–14]). 4 colonies without intermorph (38 males [median 11.5, range 8–15], 40 workers)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Microsatellite genotyping of workers and males</title>
<p>To estimate (1) the proportion of non-queen sons (i.e. sons of workers or intermorphs) and (2) the average mating frequency of queens, we genotyped a total of 149 workers (range 12–19 per colony) and 156 males (range 3–28 per colony) from nine “queenright” (i.e. containing a mother queen) field colonies collected in 2005 containing (1–6) intermorphs. Between 2006–2009, we genotyped 60 males from five queenright laboratory colonies containing (1–7) intermorphs and 38 males and 40 workers from four colonies without intermorphs. We also included data on 45 males and 46 workers from four colonies from an earlier study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze4">[55]</xref>. We extracted genomic DNA with the Gentra Puregene Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) and amplified the two microsatellite loci C20 (GenBank accession number AF 167066) and C9 (AF 167064) with the protocols in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Hlldobler1">[50]</xref>. We ran PCR products on an ABI 310 (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) and manually scored peaks. Both loci were variable (C20: 4 alleles, expected heterozygosity <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic> = 0.62; C9: 10 alleles, <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic> = 0.82) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze4">[55]</xref>. We estimated the population-wide allele frequencies and the mean within-colony relatedness with the program Relatedness (version 4.2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Queller1">[61]</xref>). We deduced the most likely genotype of the single queen per colony and her mate(s) with the program Matesoft Silver (version 1.0; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Moilanen1">[62]</xref>). We estimated the effective mating frequency of queens <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0075278.e022">equation 2</xref> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Pamilo2">[63]</xref>, which corrects for unequal contributions of multiple fathers to the female offspring.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Correction for imperfect genetic detection of non-queen sons</title>
<p>“Non-queen sons”, i.e. sons of intermorphs or workers, can only be “detected”, that is genetically distinguished from queen sons if they have inherited an allele from their maternal grandfather that their maternal grandmother did not carry. We estimated the probability <italic>P<sub>d,i</sub></italic> of detecting a non-queen son in each colony <italic>i</italic> with the standard formula 2 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Foster2">[64]</xref>, which assumes that both of our microsatellite loci are unlinked. We were interested in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the true number of non-queen sons in each colony <italic>i</italic>. To estimate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, two sources of binomially distributed errors must be taken into account: (1) the numbers of non-queen sons in the sample of genotyped males that are detectable versus non-detectable, assuming fair meiosis and no effect of microsatellite genotype on survival of males; and (2) the numbers of queen and non-queen sons that we haphazardly sampled for genotyping from among all the males produced by the colony. To estimate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and its statistical uncertainty, we wrote a script (available upon request from the second author) in the “R” language (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cran.r-project.org" xlink:type="simple">http://cran.r-project.org</ext-link>).</p>
<p>Our script returns a vector of likelihoods <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, calculated with (Eqn. 1):<disp-formula id="pone.0075278.e007"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>in which <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the known number of genotyped males from colony <italic>i</italic>; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the known total number of males produced by colony <italic>i</italic>; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the number of detectable non-queen sons in the genotyped sample from colony <italic>i</italic>; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is any theoretically possible value for the unknown true value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see above) and gets sequentially set at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is any theoretically possible value for the unknown true value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (the total number of non-queen sons in the genotyped sample from colony <italic>i</italic>, both detectable and non-detectable) and gets sequentially set at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The vector <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> has a unimodal shape, similar to a binomial density function but with a higher kurtosis. The value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for which <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is maximal is the maximum likelihood estimate for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The lower 95% confidence limit of this estimate is the smallest value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for which the following inequality is true:<disp-formula id="pone.0075278.e022"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e022" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>in which <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>is the cumulative distribution function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the maximum likelihood estimate for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Analogously, the upper 95% confidence limit for the estimate for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the highest value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for which the following inequality is true:<disp-formula id="pone.0075278.e029"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e029" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>To verify that our script returns accurate values for the maximum likelihood estimate of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and its 95% confidence limits, we used a large simulated data set of 18450 colonies, with ranges of possible values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <italic>P<sub>d,i</sub></italic> and drawing values from the stochastic variables <italic>n<sub>s,j</sub></italic> and <italic>d<sub>i</sub></italic> from an uniform distribution. Indeed, we found that the accuracy (i.e. the estimated value <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> divided by the <italic>a priori</italic> known true value <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) of the maximum likelihood estimate was 1.04±0.004 (mean ± SE; N = 18450 simulated colonies), which is close to the expected value of 1 for perfect accuracy. Similarly, the proportion of <italic>a priori</italic> known true values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that lay between the obtained 95% confidence limits was 0.93, which is close to the expected value of 0.95 for perfect accuracy. Equations 1–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0075278.e029">3</xref> and our script thus give reliable results.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Reproductive success of workers and intermorphs</title>
<p>Our microsatellite markers could distinguish between queen and non-queen sons, but not between intermorph and worker sons. We therefore estimated the relative contributions of intermorphs and workers as follows. If intermorphs have sons that are raised at the expense of queen sons, the proportion of non-queen sons among all the males in the colony (<italic>n</italic><sub>c,i</sub>, for which <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the maximum likelihood estimate should increase with increasing numbers of intermorphs per colony. We tested this prediction by fitting a generalized linear model (GLM) with a “logit” link function and pseudo-binomial errors (i.e. correcting for overdispersion of the response with an empirical scale factor) with the proportions <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as response variable, “Laboratory or field colony?” (N = 12 and N = 7, respectively) as fixed factors, “Square root of number of intermorphs per colony” (median after transformation: 1.2; range: 0–2.6) as covariate, and the total number of males per colony as weights. The vertical intercept thus yields an estimate for the workers' joint contribution to the adult males in the absence of intermorphs, while the slope estimates the average reproductive success per intermorph. The covariate had been square-root-transformed to avoid giving excessive weight to the colonies with the largest number of intermorphs in the genotyped sample. “Colony” could not be made a random factor, because each data point consisted of a single unique colony. We sequentially removed the least significant term in each step, until only significant terms remained (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Dijkstra2">[21]</xref> for details).</p>
<p>As an independent estimate of the relative contributions of intermorphs and workers to the production of non-queen sons, in 2006 we compared the egg laying rates of intermorphs and workers in a bioassay described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze2">[48]</xref>. Briefly, we isolated broodless colony fragments from laboratory colonies consisting either of ten workers and one intermorph (3.3 ± SD 1.5 replicates for each of seven colonies), or 11 nest mate workers (2.1 ± SD 1.4 replicates for each of 18 colonies). For comparison with queen fecundity we also included colonies consisting of one queen and 10 workers (one replicate for each of 15 colonies). We counted the number of eggs present at 6, 12, and 18 d after the females' separation from the colony, without distinguishing between “small” (∼3%) and “large” (∼97%) eggs. From these egg-laying data we estimated the proportion of males that workers and intermorphs could theoretically produce based on the estimate for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Do intermorphs affect sexual production and sex ratio?</title>
<p>To determine whether colonies with intermorphs are more productive than colonies without intermorphs, we estimated sexual productivity in field colonies (July 2005 &amp; 2006; see above) with (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Dijkstra2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Boomsma3">[65]</xref>):<disp-formula id="pone.0075278.e040"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>in which S<sub>i</sub> is the “Sexual production” of colony i (a relative measure of energy allocated to sexuals, expressed in male equivalents), c (the “cost ratio”) is a correction factor for the greater colony-level productivity and maintenance cost of virgin queens compared to males, and F<sub>i</sub> and M<sub>i</sub> are the number of virgin queens and males (only mature sexuals were present in the colonies) in colony i on the day of excavation, respectively.</p>
<p>We estimated c with (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Dijkstra2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Boomsma1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Foster3">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Boomsma4">[67]</xref>):<disp-formula id="pone.0075278.e041"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>in which <italic>f</italic> and <italic>m</italic> are the average dry masses of mature virgin queens and males, respectively, and <italic>k</italic> is the “metabolic parameter” that corrects for the lower respiration rate and higher fat content of ant virgin queens compared to males <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Boomsma4">[67]</xref>. We used the across-species average value <italic>k</italic> = 0.7 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Foster3">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Boomsma4">[67]</xref> that is typically used in sex ratio studies on ants. To estimate <italic>f</italic> and <italic>m</italic>, we dried flight-ready sexuals from the field in 2005 that had been preserved in &gt;99% ethanol for ≥72 h at 50–55°C, and weighed them to the nearest 0.01 mg.</p>
<p>To determine whether the number of intermorphs affects sexual production or biases the sex ratio towards virgin queens (the sex for which average fitness is thought to increase fastest with increasing nutrition), we performed a GLM on the colony-level numerical sex ratios (i.e. the proportion of virgin queens among all the sexuals in the colony) with quasi-binomial errors. We tested the covariates “Square root of number of intermorphs per colony,” “Number of workers” and their second order interaction term, the covariate “Sexual production <italic>S<sub>i</sub></italic>”, and the factor “Year”, and stepwise removed the least significant term.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Information about the caste composition (38 colonies from 2005 and 18 colonies from 2006) and genetic structure of the colonies is summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0075278-t002">Table 2</xref>, which also contains data from 74 colonies that had been collected between 1992 and 1998 at the same site <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze2">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze3">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze4">[55]</xref>. Sex ratio data for the latter colonies were unavailable because they had been collected outside the mating season. There was a significant positive association between the intermorph number and worker number across all colonies (Spearman correlation coefficient <italic>r<sub>s</sub></italic> = 0.384, n = 115, p&lt;0.007).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0075278-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Summary of colony parameters are given as mean ± SE (range) [number of colonies].</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0075278-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All field colonies (1992–2006)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reproductive field colonies (2005/2006)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry mass (mg) of mature virgin queens <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41±0.07 [7]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry mass (mg) of mature males <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09±0.003 [107<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">1</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Virgin queen-to-male energy cost ratio (<italic>c</italic>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.97±0.81 (SD<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">2</xref>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Queens per colony</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1±0.012 (1–2) [130]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [31]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of colonies with two queens</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5% [130]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% [31]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermorphs per colony</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8±0.22 (0–16) [130]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97±0.68 (0–16) [31]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of colonies without intermorphs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29% [130]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.26% [31]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workers per colony</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">305±22 (4–1370) [130]</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">538±56 (117–1370) [31]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effective queen mating frequency <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14±0.12 (1–2) [9]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probability of detecting non-queen sons <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40±0.05 (0–0.50) [13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">3</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regression relatedness among workers</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73±0.06 [9]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regression relatedness among males</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52±0.12 [9]</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>1</label><p>Collected from a mating flight in 2005.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>2</label><p>Only a single estimate is available for this parameter because it has been derived from other parameters.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>3</label><p>Also includes four reproductive laboratory colonies.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>The relatedness among nest mate workers in reproductive field colonies was r = 0.73±0.06, which does not significantly differ from the value of 0.75 expected for colonies with a single, singly mated queen (t<sub>8</sub> = 0.33, p = 0.75). However, the average effective queen mating frequency was slightly above 1 (<italic>q<sub>e</sub></italic> = 1.14±0.12) because a second queen's mate was detected in two (22%) of the nine genotyped sexual-producing field colonies. In another two colonies the queen and her mate did not have informative alleles at both loci and thus the probability <italic>P<sub>d</sub></italic> of detecting a non-queen son was zero. These two colonies were discarded from the subsequent analysis because a maximum likelihood estimate could not be calculated.</p>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Male parentage</title>
<p>None of the males were heterozygous at either microsatellite locus, which is consistent with all of them being haploid rather than diploid males (typically infertile) such as are occasionally produced in Hymenoptera with single- or multi-locus complementary sex determination. The “Square root of number of intermorphs per colony”” was not significant (df = 18, F = 0.33, p = 0.57) in the logistic regression on the maximum likelihood estimate of the proportion of non-queen sons, indicating that the proportion of non-queen sons does not change with intermorph number when there are 1–7 intermorphs in the colony. The overall median proportion of non-queen sons among all the adult males in the genotyped colonies was 0%, but varied considerably (1<sup>st</sup> quartile, 3<sup>rd</sup> quartile, range; 0%, 19%, 0–46.2%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0075278-g001">Fig. 1a</xref>). The proportion of non-queen sons did not differ between laboratory colonies from 1998 (reanalyzed from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze4">[55]</xref>), laboratory colonies from 2006/2009, and field colonies from 2005 (df = 16, F<sub>1, 16</sub> = 0.232, p = 0.80) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0075278-g001">Fig. 1b</xref>). The total number of eggs produced after six days was significantly higher for colony fragments consisting of 10 workers and one intermorph (Median, 1<sup>st</sup> quartile, 3<sup>rd</sup> quartile, range; 6, 4, 18, 0–42) than for 11 workers alone (3.5, 2, 6, 0–20) (W = 269.5, p = 0.013), and significantly higher for colonies consisting of one queen and 10 workers (35, 22.5, 63, 0–75) than for colonies with intermorphs (W = 57, p&lt;0.001), and reached a maximum after 12 days (data not shown).</p>
<fig id="pone-0075278-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>The maximum likelihood (ML) estimate of proportions of non-queen sons (i.e. intermorph and/or worker sons) among the adult males in the colony, corrected for non-detection.</title>
<p>Laboratory samples from 2000 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Sundstrm1">[11]</xref> were reanalyzed from the original data; all other data are from the present study. Error bars denote 95% confidence intervals. 1a) Individual results for the 19 genotyped colonies, sample sizes are given as number of genotyped males : numbers of intermorphs per nest. 1b) Boxplot of the ML estimates for samples from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze4">[55]</xref>, field colonies collected in 2005 and lab colonies. Depicted are medians, 3<sup>rd</sup> quartiles and maxima. Numbers above whiskers denote the number of genotyped colonies.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Colony fragments with one intermorph and 10 workers produced ∼1.7 more eggs within 6 days than groups of 11 workers. However, the overall contribution of intermorphs to the production of non-queen sons is considered small because the colonies collected during the mating season in 2005 and 2006 with intermorphs (n = 20) had ∼130 times more workers (median, 1<sup>st</sup> quartile, 3<sup>rd</sup> quartile, range; 524.5, 343.5, 733.25, 117–1370) than intermorphs (4, 1.75, 6, 1–16). A negligible contribution of intermorphs to the production of adult males implies that the number of non-queen sons does not differ significantly between colonies with and without intermorphs.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Sex ratio and sexual production is independent of intermorph number</title>
<p>Like in many other eusocial Hymenoptera <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Meunier1">[22]</xref>, the colony-level numerical sex ratios were strongly split, meaning that colonies tended to specialize in producing mostly mature virgin queens or mostly mature males (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0075278-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). Colonies with intermorphs did not have a significantly higher “Sexual production” than colonies without intermorphs (Wilcoxon rank sum test: W = 101.5, p = 0.73). “Sexual production” increased significantly with the number of workers per colony (GLM, df = 29, F = 5.01, p = 0.033), while “Square root of number of intermorphs per colony” did not. The analysis of the colony numerical sex ratio showed that the covariates “Number of workers per colony” and “Square root of number of intermorphs per colony” were not significant. The covariate “Sexual production” was also not significant, indicating that the colony sex ratio was independent of the total investment into sexuals.</p>
<fig id="pone-0075278-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Biplot of numerical sex ratio (i.e. the proportion of virgin queens among all sexuals in the colony) and total sexual production <italic>S<sub>i</sub></italic> (including the correction for higher investment in females) across colonies.</title>
<p>These data show a tendency for split sex ratio strategy regardless of investment.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0075278.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Aim of our study was to determine the effect of intermorphs on the sexual production of colonies of the ant <italic>Crematogaster smithi</italic>. As shown previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze3">[49]</xref>, the number of intermorphs increased with colony size. Surprisingly, however, we did not detect any direct effect of intermorphs on colony reproduction.</p>
<p>Even though intermorphs have a higher direct fitness compared to workers their direct fitness was estimated to be surprisingly low. Even in colonies with a significant proportion of non-queen sons, workers outnumber the intermorphs by two orders of magnitude. Thus, only an estimated negligible proportion of adult males were intermorph sons, while the majority were offspring of the queen and the rest were offspring of normal workers. Hence, it is unlikely that intermorphs are a selfish caste (comparable to the “dwarf” queens in some stingless bees, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Wenseleers3">[68]</xref>) that does not give any benefit to the colony. Assuming a conservative estimate of 1% intermorph sons, the life-for-life relatedness coefficient of workers to males would be only 0.5% higher in colonies with one or more intermorphs than in colonies without intermorphs (0.265 vs. 0.264, respectively). Similarly, the life-for-life relatedness of queens to males would be only 0.5% lower in colonies with than in colonies without intermorphs (0.470 vs. 0.473). At least for our sampling years we therefore have to reject the earlier hypothesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze3">[49]</xref> that intermorphs are an “extended phenotype” of their worker sisters that helps the latter to replace brothers with more related nephews while avoiding the colony-level cost of inefficient worker reproduction.</p>
<p>In contrast to a previous assumption <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze3">[49]</xref>, feeding larvae and queens with eggs laid by intermorphs neither affected total sexual production nor sex ratio. Instead, sexual production was correlated with colony size, but resources were not necessarily allocated towards the more costly virgin queens. Most colonies produced a numerical sex ratio that was considerably more or considerably less queen-biased than the 1∶1 queen optimum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0075278-g002">Fig. 2</xref>), strongly suggesting that workers and/or queens follow a conditional strategy for sex allocation. Numerical sex ratio was not associated with the number of intermorphs and total sexual production did not differ between colonies with and without intermorphs. This indicates that at least during the sampling years, colonies did not rely on the eggs laid by intermorphs to produce costly virgin queens or to increase the total sexual output.</p>
<p>Finally, we can reject a trivial proximate explanation for the occurrence of intermorphs, namely that intermorphs arise from queen-destined larvae whose development was somehow impaired (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze5">[69]</xref>). First, the number of intermorphs was not correlated with the number of virgin females. Second, the production of intermorphs and virgin queens is temporally decoupled: colonies collected in 2005 produced new intermorphs at irregular intervals throughout the year in the laboratory, but they produced sexuals from overwintering larvae one year after collection, approximately synchronously with other colonies.</p>
<p>Overall, our study does not give a clear explanation for the tight correlation of colony size and intermorph number. The recently documented widespread existence of intermorphic females in species of the subgenus <italic>Orthocrema</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Buschinger1">[51]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Peeters1">[54]</xref> prevents us from simply dismissing intermorphs as a non-adaptive idiosyncrasy of <italic>C. smithi</italic>. Intermorphic females have now been described for species living in such diverse habitats as in the soil in dry juniper-oak–pinyon forests (<italic>C. smithi</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Heinze3">[49]</xref>), under epiphyte mats in the canopies of montane wet forests (<italic>C. bryophilia</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Longino1">[52]</xref>), and branches on trees or on the ground in rainforests, dry forests, and spiny forests (<italic>C. rasoherinae</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Blaimer1">[53]</xref>). Intermorphs and the provisioning of the queen and larvae with viable eggs might be an ancestral state in this taxon that originally served to overcome food shortage under the most diverse ecological conditions and now is retained even where it has only small fitness effects.</p>
<p>Previous studies in polymorphic social insects have shown that it is often difficult to reconcile empirical findings with theoretical predictions about adaptive demography <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-SchmidHempel1">[70]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0075278-Gould1">[76]</xref>. More information on the occurrence, ontogeny and behavior of intermorphs in other species of <italic>Crematogaster</italic> might be helpful to determine the proximate and ultimate causes of their existence.</p>
</sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>Many thanks to Christopher R. Smith for sharing thoughts, to Kojun Kanda for help finding ant nests and to the Southwestern Research Station for their hospitality. We also like to thank two anonymous reviewers for their comments. The experiments and fieldwork comply with the current laws of the USA and Germany.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Foster1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnieks</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The effect of sex-allocation biasing on the evolution of worker policing in hymenopteran societies</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>158</volume>: <fpage>615</fpage>–<lpage>622</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Dijkstra1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkstra</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boomsma</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The economy of worker reproduction in <italic>Acromyrmex</italic> leafcutter ants</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>529</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Khila1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khila</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abouheif</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Reproductive constraint is a developmental mechanism that maintains social harmony in advanced ant societies</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>17884</fpage>–<lpage>17889</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Ratnieks1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnieks</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Reproductive harmony via mutual policing by workers in eusocial Hymenoptera</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Wenseleers1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenseleers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnieks</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Comparative analysis of worker policing and reproduction in eusocial Hymenoptera supports relatedness theory</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>168</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Pamilo1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pamilo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Evolution of colony characteristics in social insects. I. Sex allocation</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Chapuisat1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapuisat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Testing kin selection with sex allocation data in eusocial hymenoptera</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Trivers1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivers</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hare</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Haplodipoidy and the evolution of the social insects</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>191</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Mehdiabadi1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehdiabadi</surname><given-names>NJH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reeve</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>UG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Queens versus workers: sex-ratio conflict in eusocial Hymenoptera</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Kmmerli1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kümmerli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Patterns of split sex ratio in ants have multiple evolutionary causes based on different within-colony conflicts</article-title>. <source>Biol Lett</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>713</fpage>–<lpage>716</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Sundstrm1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundström</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Sex ratio bias, relatedness asymmetry and queen mating frequency in ants</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>367</volume>: <fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Passera1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Passera</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vargo</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Queen control of sex ratio in fire ants</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>293</volume>: <fpage>1308</fpage>–<lpage>1310</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Beekman1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beekman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Komdeur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnieks</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Reproductive conflicts in social animals: who has power?</article-title> <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-DeMenten1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Menten</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Primary sex ratio adjustment by ant queens in response to local mate competition</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1031</fpage>–<lpage>1035</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Rosset1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosset</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapuisat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Sex allocation conflict in ants: when the queen rules</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>328</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Helanter1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Helanterä</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnieks</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Sex allocation conflict in insect societies: who wins?</article-title> <source>Biol Lett</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>700</fpage>–<lpage>704</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Chapuisat2"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapuisat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sundström</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Sex-ratio regulation: the economics of fratricide in ants</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B</source> <volume>264</volume>: <fpage>1255</fpage>–<lpage>1260</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Bourke1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bourke AFG (2005) Genetics, relatedness and social behaviour in insect societies. In: Fellowes, MDE, Holloway GJ, Rolff J (eds) Insect Evolutionary Ecology pp 1–30</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Herbers1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herbers</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Reproductive investment and allocation ratios for the ant <italic>Leptothorax longispinosus</italic>: Sorting out the variation</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Nonacs1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nonacs</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Ant reproductive strategies and sex allocation theory</article-title>. <source>Quart Rev Biol</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Dijkstra2"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkstra</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boomsma</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Sex allocation in fungus-growing ants: worker or queen control without symbiont-induced female bias</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>1892</fpage>–<lpage>1906</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Meunier1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meunier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapuisat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Split sex ratios in the social hymenoptera: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>382</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Deslippe1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deslippe</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Sex investment in a social insect: The proximate role of food</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Kim1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Influence of resource level on maternal investment in a leaf-cutter bee (Hymenoptera: Megachilidae)</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>556</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Aron1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Passera</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Role of resource availability on sex, caste and reproductive allocation ratios in the Argentine ant <italic>Linepithema humile</italic></article-title>. <source>J Anim Ecol</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>831</fpage>–<lpage>839</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Bono1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bono</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heithaus</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Sex ratios and the distribution of elaiosomes in colonies of the ant, <italic>Aphaenogaster rudis</italic></article-title>. <source>Insectes Soc</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Bono2"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bono</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herbers</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Proximate and ultimate control of sex ratios in <italic>Myrmica brevispinosa</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B</source> <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>811</fpage>–<lpage>817</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Foitzik1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foitzik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Backus</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trindl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herbers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Ecology of <italic>Leptothorax</italic> ants: impact of food, nest sites, and social parasites</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>484</fpage>–<lpage>493</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Brown1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Resource supplements cause a change in colony sex-ratio specialization in the mound-building ant, <italic>Formica exsecta</italic></article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>612</fpage>–<lpage>618</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Smith1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tschinkel</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The sociometry and sociogenesis of reproduction in the Florida harvester ant (<italic>Pogonomyrmex badius</italic>)</article-title>. <source>J Insect Sci</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Smith2"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Energy use and allocation in the Florida harvester ant <italic>Pogonomyrmex badius</italic>: Are stored seeds a buffer?</article-title> <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1479</fpage>–<lpage>1487</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Trivers2"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivers</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willard</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Natural selection of parental ability to vary the sex ratio of offspring</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>179</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Strohm1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strohm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linsenmair</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Low resource availability causes extremely male-biased investment ratios in the European beewolf, <italic>Philanthus triangulum</italic> F. (Hymenoptera, Sphecidae)</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B</source> <volume>264</volume>: <fpage>423</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Desfor1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Desfor</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boomsma</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sunde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Tawny owls <italic>Strix aluco</italic> with reliable food supply produce male-biased broods</article-title>. <source>Ibis</source> <volume>149</volume>: <fpage>98</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Bosch1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Production of undersized offspring in a solitary bee</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>809</fpage>–<lpage>816</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Sheldon1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Maternal dominance, maternal condition and offspring sex ratio in ungulate mammals</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>163</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Boomsma1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boomsma</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Sex investment ratios in ants: has female bias been systematically overestimated?</article-title> <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>517</fpage>–<lpage>532</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Frank1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Variable sex ratios among colonies of ants</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Rosenheim1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenheim</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nonacs</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mangel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Sex ratios and multi-facetted parental investment</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>535</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Boomsma2"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boomsma</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The evolution of male traits in social insects</article-title>. <source>An Rev Entomol</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>420</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Bartz1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartz</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hölldobler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Colony founding in <italic>Myrmecocystus mimicus</italic> Wheeler (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) and the evolution of foundress associations</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Cahan1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cahan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Julian</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Fitness consequences of cooperative colony founding in the desert leaf-cutter ant <italic>Acromyrmex versicolor</italic></article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>591</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Yamauchi1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hashim</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Queen-queen competition by precocious male production in multiqueen ant colonies</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>2424</fpage>–<lpage>2427</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Suefuji1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suefuji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oettler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Queen number influences the timing of the sexual production in colonies of <italic>Cardiocondyl</italic>a ants</article-title>. <source>Biol Lett</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>670</fpage>–<lpage>673</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Heinze1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hölldobler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Fighting for a harem of queens: Physiology of reproduction in <italic>Cardiocondyla</italic> male ants</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>8412</fpage>–<lpage>8414</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Schrempf1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrempf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Sexual cooperation: Mating increases longevity in ant queens</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Schrempf2"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrempf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mating with stressed males increases the fitness of ant queens</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>3</volume> (<issue>(7)</issue>) <fpage>e2592</fpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0002592" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0002592</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Heinze2"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cover</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hölldobler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Neither worker nor queen: an ant caste specialized on the production of male eggs</article-title>. <source>Psyche</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Heinze3"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foitzik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oberstadt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rüppell</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hölldobler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>A female caste specialized for the production of unfertilized eggs in the ant <italic>Crematogaster smithi</italic></article-title>. <source>Naturwissenschaften</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Hlldobler1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hölldobler B, Wilson EO (1990) The ants. Springer Verlag Berlin Heidelberg</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Buschinger1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buschinger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maschwitz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Kein Kühlschrank? No problem! Wie <italic>Cremastogaster</italic>-Ameisen in den Feuchttropen das Problem der Vorratshaltung lösen</article-title>. <source>Ameisenschutz aktuell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Longino1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Longino</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Crematogaster</italic> (Hymenoptera, Formicidae, Myrmicinae) of Costa Rica</article-title>. <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>151</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Blaimer1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blaimer</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Taxonomy and species-groups of the subgenus <italic>Crematogaster</italic> (<italic>Orthocrema</italic>) in the Malagasy region (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)</article-title>. <source>Zookeys</source> <volume>199</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Peeters1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quinet</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Segundo</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Evolution of a soldier caste specialized to lay unfertilized eggs in the ant genus <italic>Crematogaster</italic> (subgenus Orthocrema)</article-title>. <source>Arth Struct Dev</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Heinze4"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strätz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haberl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Microsatellite analysis suggests occasional worker reproduction in the monogynous ant <italic>Crematogaster smithi</italic></article-title>. <source>Insectes Soc</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Brgensen1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Børgensen</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Nutritional function of replete workers in the pharaoh's ant, <italic>Monomorium pharaonis</italic> (L.)</article-title>. <source>Insectes Soc</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Dijkstra3"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkstra</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boomsma</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The economy of worker reproduction in <italic>Acromyrmex</italic> leafcutter ants</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>529</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Ratnieks2"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnieks</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Reproductive harmony via mutual policing by workers in eusocial Hymenoptera</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Wenseleers2"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenseleers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helanterä</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnieks</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Worker reproduction and policing in insect societies: an ESS analysis</article-title>. <source>J Evol Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1035</fpage>–<lpage>1047</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Tsuneoka1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuneoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Wingless reproductives in the slave-making ant <italic>Polyergus samurai</italic>: specialized producers of males (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)</article-title>. <source>Entomol Sci</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Queller1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Queller</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goodnight</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Estimating relatedness using genetic markers</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Moilanen1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moilanen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sundström</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>MateSoft: a program for deducing parental genotypes and estimating mating system statistics in haplodiploid species</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Notes</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>795</fpage>–<lpage>797</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Pamilo2"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pamilo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Polyandry and allele frequency differences between the sexes in the ant <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic></article-title>. <source>Heredity</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>472</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Foster2"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnieks</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raybould</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Do hornets have zombie workers?</article-title> <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Boomsma3"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Boomsma JJ, Nachman G (2002) Analysis of sex ratios in social insects. In: Hardy ICW, editor. Sex ratios. Concepts and research methods. Cambridge, Cambridge University Press. pp. 93–111.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Foster3"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnieks</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raybould</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Do hornets have zombie workers?</article-title> <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Boomsma4"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boomsma</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>A comparative analysis of sex ratio investment parameters in ants</article-title>. <source>Funct Ecol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>743</fpage>–<lpage>753</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Wenseleers3"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenseleers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnieks</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>Mde F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>Dde A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imperatriz-Fonseca</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Working-class royalty: bees beat the caste system</article-title>. <source>Biol Lett</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Heinze5"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Intercastes, intermorphs, and ergatoid queens: who is who in ant reproduction?</article-title> <source>Ins Soc</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-SchmidHempel1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Worker castes and adaptive demography</article-title>. <source>J Evol Biol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Kaspari1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaspari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Caste allocation in litter <italic>Pheidole</italic>: lessons from plant defense theory</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Yang1"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nijhout</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Geographic variation of caste structure among ant populations</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>514</fpage>–<lpage>519</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Heinze6"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rüppell</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Sex allocation ratios in the facultatively polygynous ant, <italic>Leptothorax acervorum</italic></article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>270</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Herbers2"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herbers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>The evolution of sex-ratio strategies in hymenopteran societies</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>818</fpage>–<lpage>834</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Crozier1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Crozier RH, Pamillo P (1996). Evolution of social insect colonies. Sex allocation and kin-selection. Oxford University Press, Oxford, UK.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0075278-Gould1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewontin</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>The spandrels of San Marco and the Panglossian Paradigm: A critique of the adaptationist programme</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>205</volume>: <fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>598</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>