<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146706</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-40845</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Genetic Diversity Affects the Daily Transcriptional Oscillations of Marine Microbial Populations</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Differential Daily Gene Transcription in Marine Microbes</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Shilova</surname>
<given-names>Irina N.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Robidart</surname>
<given-names>Julie C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="currentaff001"><sup>¤</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>DeLong</surname>
<given-names>Edward F.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zehr</surname>
<given-names>Jonathan P.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Ocean Sciences, University of California Santa Cruz, Santa Cruz, California, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>School of Ocean and Earth Science and Technology, University of Hawai’i at Manoa, Honolulu, Hawaii, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lovejoy</surname>
<given-names>Connie</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Laval University, CANADA</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: IS JZ. Performed the experiments: IS. Analyzed the data: IS JR. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: IS JR ED JZ. Wrote the paper: IS JR ED JZ. Chief scientist on the BioLINCS cruise and responsible for ESP deployment: JR. Designed the bioinformatic approach: IS.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff001">
<label>¤</label><p>Current address: National Oceanography Centre, Southampton, United Kingdom</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">zehrj@ucsc.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>11</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<elocation-id>e0146706</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>15</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>21</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Shilova et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706"/>
<abstract>
<p>Marine microbial communities are genetically diverse but have robust synchronized daily transcriptional patterns at the genus level that are similar across a wide variety of oceanic regions. We developed a microarray-inspired gene-centric approach to resolve transcription of closely-related but distinct strains/ecotypes in high-throughput sequence data. Applying this approach to the existing metatranscriptomics datasets collected from two different oceanic regions, we found unique and variable patterns of transcription by individual taxa within the abundant picocyanobacteria <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> and <italic>Synechococcus</italic>, the alpha Proteobacterium <italic>Pelagibacter</italic> and the eukaryotic picophytoplankton <italic>Ostreococcus</italic>. The results demonstrate that marine microbial taxa respond differentially to variability in space and time in the ocean. These intra-genus individual transcriptional patterns underlie whole microbial community responses, and the approach developed here facilitates deeper insights into microbial population dynamics.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This work was funded by the National Science Foundation Center for Microbial Oceanography: Research and Education (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cmore.soest.hawaii.edu/" xlink:type="simple">http://cmore.soest.hawaii.edu/</ext-link>, EF0424599), the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.moore.org/" xlink:type="simple">https://www.moore.org/</ext-link>, JZ and ED), the Simons Collaboration on Ocean Processes and Ecology (SCOPE, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.simonsfoundation.org/life-sciences/simons-collaboration-on-ocean-processes-and-ecology/" xlink:type="simple">https://www.simonsfoundation.org/life-sciences/simons-collaboration-on-ocean-processes-and-ecology/</ext-link>) and National Science Foundation Dimensions in Biodiversity (1241221, JZ). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="5"/>
<table-count count="2"/>
<page-count count="17"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Marine microbial communities play critical roles in the cycling of organic matter and nutrients and in food webs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref001">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref002">2</xref>]. These complex communities are composed of diverse, poorly-characterized taxa, including many uncultivated lineages and strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref003">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref006">6</xref>]. Much has been learned about marine microbial communities using cultivation-independent methods, in particular, metagenomics and metatranscriptomics approaches enabled by high-throughput and next-generation nucleic acid sequencing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref005">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref006">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref010">10</xref>]. One recent discovery is that individual populations of phototrophic and heterotrophic plankton have complex but coordinated rhythmic daily transcription patterns that are highly conserved throughout oceanic microbial communities worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref013">13</xref>]. This was particularly surprising, since genome comparisons of closely-related cultivated and uncultivated taxa, such as the abundant phototrophs <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> and <italic>Synechococcus</italic>, show that strains or ecotypes are diverse and variable in nucleotide sequence and gene content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref010">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref014">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref018">18</xref>]. Studies with cultured isolates showed that genotypic diversity among bacterial strains is reflected in gene regulation at the transcription and expression levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref019">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref020">20</xref>], and gene regulation has been recognized as an important factor driving evolution and adaption in microbes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref021">21</xref>]. It is currently not clear how the potentially great physiological diversity implied by high genomic variability in marine microbial populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref005">5</xref>] could result in consistent, robust and synchronized daily gene transcription patterns in the environment.</p>
<p>The whole genome population binning (WGPB) approaches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref013">13</xref>] for analysis of the high-throughput sequence data have the advantage of examining transcriptional responses across the whole genome, but without appropriate reference genomes, cannot usually resolve populations at the species or sub-species taxonomic levels. This high resolution is only possible when genome sequences are known and metagenomic/metatranscriptomic datasets have high coverage for these genomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref009">9</xref>]. At the current depth of sequencing, assigning short reads to individual taxa is only possible for taxonomically identifiable signature regions and for genes/transcripts present in high abundance (for example, the &lt;200 nucleotide long region of the proteorhodopsin gene has been examined in detail in order to evaluate <italic>Pelagibacter</italic> subtaxa contributions in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>]). Oligotyping [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref022">22</xref>] and minimum entropy decomposition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref023">23</xref>] are powerful approaches that uncover finer community changes based on a marker gene, but both require that sequences cover the same region of the gene (for example, the V4-V5 hypervariable region of the 16S-rRNA gene). We developed a microarray-inspired gene centric (MAGC) approach that links sequences originated from different regions of a gene/transcript and resolves transcription of closely-related taxa. We applied MAGC to examine the contribution of individual microbial taxa to synchronized transcription patterns observed previously at the genus level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>] and examined transcription of specific functional genes by individual taxa within the cyanobacteria <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> and <italic>Synechococcus</italic>, the proteorhodopsin-containing alpha proteobacterium <italic>Pelagibacter ubique</italic> (SAR11) and the eukaryotic picophytoplankton <italic>Ostreococcus</italic>. The results showed that closely related microbial taxa (defined as taxa that have greater than 95% nucleotide identity to the target gene sequence) have distinct and differential transcription patterns for ecologically-relevant functional genes, and these individual patterns may reflect the differences in microbial responses to environmental conditions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<p>The MAGC approach described in this study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g001">Fig 1</xref>) is an in silico nucleotide sequence-query based method that uses 60-nucleotide (nt) long sequences (probes) previously designed for the MicroTOOLs environmental microarray [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref024">24</xref>]. The probes are specific for known marker genes for metabolic and cellular processes important for microbes living in pelagic oligotrophic environments. These processes include energy, carbon and nitrogen metabolisms, phosphonate and dimethylsulfoniopropionate utilization, nutrient transport, stress responses, DNA replication and cell division [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref025">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref030">30</xref>]. The ortholog sequences for each marker gene were collected from marine metagenomic and metatranscriptomic sequence datasets and marine microbial genome sequences. These sequences were clustered at 95% nucleotide identity, and a total of six probes were designed for each representative target sequence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref024">24</xref>]. Thus, the ~99,000 probes that are specific for 16,800 orthologs of 145 different functional genes target a diverse set of representative organisms and genes from pelagic microbial communities. In the MAGC approach, this MicroTOOLs probe set was used as a query set against metatranscriptomic sequence data to discriminate gene transcription at a high phylogenetic resolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g001">Fig 1</xref>). In this paper, we define a group of gene sequences or transcripts that shares 95% nt identity as a gene-Operational Taxonomic Unit (OTU) or transcript-OTU, respectively. Because six probes target the same individual transcript-OTU, and transcript abundance is estimated as the average of all probe hits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g001">Fig 1</xref>), the MAGC approach links several reads over the length of the transcript to one transcript-OTU and shows OTU-specific patterns in gene transcription.</p>
<fig id="pone.0146706.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Principle of the MAGC approach for analysis of nucleotide sequences obtained from high-throughput sequencing.</title>
<p>(A) Each of the16,806 gene-OTU has six highly specific probes, and all of the 98,632 probe sequences are used as queries in BLASTN searches against the database of nucleotide sequences obtained from environmental samples (metagenomes or metatranscriptomes). The transcript-OTU abundances are estimated as the averages of reads with ≥95% nucleotide identity (nt) across the entire length of each probe. (B) Distribution of probes specific for the <italic>Synechococcus</italic> KORDI-49 <italic>rbcL</italic> gene shown with reads identified with these probes in a California Current System diel study. Three probes (indicated with shaded area) for <italic>Synechococcus</italic> KORDI-49 <italic>rbcL</italic> had ≥95% nt sequence identity to reads from this sample. The read ID and probe start position are shown above each read and probe, respectively.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>We used the MAGC approach to analyze previously published metatranscriptomic datasets that were obtained from a three-day duration, two-hour interval sampling in the North Pacific Subtropical Gyre (NPSG) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>] and a two-day duration, four-hour interval sampling in the California Current System (CCS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>]. Both studies collected microbial biomass in the 0.2–5.0 μm size fraction from 23 m depth using the free-drifting robotic Environmental Sample Processor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>]. The CCS study consisted of 13 samples that were sequenced with a 454 GS FLX Titanium DNA sequencer (19 runs of 4.4 Gbp total, 450 bp long single reads), and the NPSG study consisted of 30 samples sequenced with an Illumina MiSeq sequencer (119 runs of 18.8 Gbp total, 150 bp long paired-end reads). The goal of this study was to investigate the transcriptional patterns of individual gene-OTUs within the cyanobacteria <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> and <italic>Synechococcus</italic>, the alpha proteobacterium <italic>Pelagibacter</italic> and the eukaryote <italic>Ostreococcus</italic> during the diel cycle. The probes identified 0.68M (0.55% of total) and 0.38M (0.38% of total) sequence reads at 95% sequence identity in metatranscriptome data from the NPSG and CCS, respectively (Table A in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s001">S1 File</xref>). The number of identified reads per gene identified with MAGC were highly correlated (Pearson’s r 0.92±0.07, n = 3) with read counts identified by the WGPB approach in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>]. A large fraction of the reads per gene were identified by MAGC, with the median of 53% of reads per gene per sample identified by MAGC to reads identified by WGPB (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0146706.t001">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0146706.t002">2</xref>). Interestingly, the probes used in MAGC were originally designed for sequences that were available publically before 2010 and obtained from samples collected from different regions of the oceans before 2008 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref024">24</xref>]. A large portion of the sequences came from the metagenomic dataset from Station ALOHA in the NPSG collected in 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref007">7</xref>], the Global Ocean Sampling expedition collected during 2004–2006 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref031">31</xref>], and metatranscriptomic datasets from the North Pacific, Southwest Pacific and Equatorial Atlantic Oceans collected during 2005–2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref032">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref034">34</xref>]. The CCS and NPSG datasets were obtained in 2009 (CCS) and 2011, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>]. The fact that the probes captured a significant fraction of the targeted transcripts from the CCS and NPSG datasets and the high correlation between the MAGC and WGPB methods imply that, perhaps, we have now largely characterized the diversity of sequences in the environment, at least at the current depth of sequencing, making it feasible to use more targeted approaches, such as MAGC, to address hypothesis-driven ecological questions.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0146706.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Genes With Differential Transcription Patterns Among <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> and <italic>Pelagibacter</italic> OTUs in the NPSG diel study.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0146706.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" rowspan="2">Gene</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="2">Annotation</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="2">KEGG Pathway</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Number of reads detected by MAGC</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="2">Pearson's r</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="2">OTU-transcripts detected</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center">Total reads</th>
<th align="center">% of WGPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>]</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="7"><bold><italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> in NPSG</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>phoH</italic></td>
<td align="left">phosphate starvation-inducible protein</td>
<td align="left">[Phosphorus stress response]</td>
<td align="right">2322</td>
<td align="right">129</td>
<td align="right">0.82</td>
<td align="right">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>sbtA</italic></td>
<td align="left">sodium-dependent bicarbonate transporter</td>
<td align="left">[Transporters (carbon fixation)]</td>
<td align="right">481</td>
<td align="right">46</td>
<td align="right">0.91</td>
<td align="right">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>metC</italic></td>
<td align="left">cystathionine beta-lyase family protein (aluminum resistance)</td>
<td align="left">Amino acid metabolism</td>
<td align="right">340</td>
<td align="right">84</td>
<td align="right">0.65</td>
<td align="right">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>dxs</italic></td>
<td align="left">1-deoxy-D-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase</td>
<td align="left">Carbohydrate and lipid metabolism</td>
<td align="right">1522</td>
<td align="right">48</td>
<td align="right">0.96</td>
<td align="right">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>ppc</italic></td>
<td align="left">phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase</td>
<td align="left">Carbon metabolism (carbon fixation)</td>
<td align="right">1264</td>
<td align="right">37</td>
<td align="right">0.94</td>
<td align="right">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>icd</italic></td>
<td align="left">isocitrate dehydrogenase</td>
<td align="left">Carbon metabolism (citrate cycle)</td>
<td align="right">601</td>
<td align="right">51</td>
<td align="right">0.93</td>
<td align="right">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>pyk</italic></td>
<td align="left">pyruvate kinase</td>
<td align="left">Carbon metabolism (glycolysis)</td>
<td align="right">783</td>
<td align="right">46</td>
<td align="right">0.92</td>
<td align="right">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>prsA</italic></td>
<td align="left">ribose-phosphate pyrophosphokinase</td>
<td align="left">Carbon metabolism (pentose phosphate pathway)</td>
<td align="right">1950</td>
<td align="right">43</td>
<td align="right">0.95</td>
<td align="right">19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>zwf</italic></td>
<td align="left">glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase</td>
<td align="left">Carbon metabolism (pentose phosphate pathway)</td>
<td align="right">590</td>
<td align="right">56</td>
<td align="right">0.97</td>
<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>ftsZ</italic></td>
<td align="left">cell division protein FtsZ</td>
<td align="left">Cellular processes</td>
<td align="right">502</td>
<td align="right">12</td>
<td align="right">0.94</td>
<td align="right">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>ndhI</italic></td>
<td align="left">NADH dehydrogenase subunit I</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (oxidative phosphorylation)</td>
<td align="right">1589</td>
<td align="right">121</td>
<td align="right">0.97</td>
<td align="right">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>petF</italic></td>
<td align="left">ferredoxin</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (photosynthesis)</td>
<td align="right">2099</td>
<td align="right">91</td>
<td align="right">0.91</td>
<td align="right">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>psaA</italic></td>
<td align="left">photosystem I P700 chlorophyll a apoprotein A1</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (photosynthesis)</td>
<td align="right">19081</td>
<td align="right">76</td>
<td align="right">0.95</td>
<td align="right">43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>psbB</italic></td>
<td align="left">photosystem II PsbB protein (CP47)</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (photosynthesis)</td>
<td align="right">11960</td>
<td align="right">66</td>
<td align="right">0.97</td>
<td align="right">47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>dnaA</italic></td>
<td align="left">chromosomal replication initiator protein DnaA</td>
<td align="left">Replication and repair</td>
<td align="right">390</td>
<td align="right">38</td>
<td align="right">0.95</td>
<td align="right">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>dnaE</italic></td>
<td align="left">DNA polymerase III subunit alpha</td>
<td align="left">Replication and repair</td>
<td align="right">139</td>
<td align="right">7</td>
<td align="right">0.76</td>
<td align="right">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>recA</italic></td>
<td align="left">recombinase A</td>
<td align="left">Replication and repair</td>
<td align="right">5004</td>
<td align="right">68</td>
<td align="right">0.99</td>
<td align="right">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>rpoD</italic></td>
<td align="left">RNA polymerase primary sigma factor</td>
<td align="left">Transcriptional machinery</td>
<td align="right">1027</td>
<td align="right">29</td>
<td align="right">0.99</td>
<td align="right">21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>sigAII</italic></td>
<td align="left">type II alternative sigma-70 family RNA polymerase sigma factor</td>
<td align="left">Transcriptional machinery</td>
<td align="right">1181</td>
<td align="right">50</td>
<td align="right">0.97</td>
<td align="right">29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>pstS</italic></td>
<td align="left">phosphate-binding transporter protein PstS</td>
<td align="left">Transporters [Phosphorus stress response]</td>
<td align="right">1479</td>
<td align="right">32</td>
<td align="right">0.97</td>
<td align="right">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>gidA</italic></td>
<td align="left">glucose inhibited division protein A</td>
<td align="left">tRNA modification factors</td>
<td align="right">501</td>
<td align="right">45</td>
<td align="right">0.93</td>
<td align="right">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>AVERAGE</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="right"/>
<td align="right"><bold>56±31</bold></td>
<td align="right"><bold>0.92±0.08</bold></td>
<td align="right"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>SUM</bold></td>
<td align="right"><bold>21 genes</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="right"/>
<td align="right"/>
<td align="right"/>
<td align="right"><bold>280</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="7"><bold><italic>Pelagibacter</italic> in NPSG</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>bop</italic></td>
<td align="left">proteorhodopsin</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="right">2699</td>
<td align="right">7.3</td>
<td align="right">0.94</td>
<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>For each gene, number of reads identified using MAGC for all samples and as a percent relative to the number of reads identified by WGPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>], correlation (the Pearson correlation coefficient) between results obtained by the two approaches and number of transcript-OTUs identified in all samples are shown. In the KEGG pathway column, the square brackets indicate pathways/metabolisms/processes that do not have KEGG assignment.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0146706.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Genes With Differential Transcription Patterns Among <italic>Synechococcus</italic>, <italic>Pelagibacter</italic> and <italic>Ostreococcus</italic> OTUs in the CCS diel study.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0146706.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" rowspan="2">Gene</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="2">Annotation</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="2">KEGG Pathway</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Number of reads detected by MAGC</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="2">Pearson's r</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="2">OTU-transcripts detected</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center">Total reads</th>
<th align="center">% of reads by WGPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>]</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="7"><bold><italic>Synechococcus</italic> in the CCS</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>sodN</italic></td>
<td align="left">putative nickel-containing superoxide dismutase</td>
<td align="left">[Oxidative stress response]</td>
<td align="right">47</td>
<td align="right">55</td>
<td align="right">0.88</td>
<td align="right">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>ppc</italic></td>
<td align="left">phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase</td>
<td align="left">Carbon metabolism (carbon fixation)</td>
<td align="right">30</td>
<td align="right">48</td>
<td align="right">0.79</td>
<td align="right">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>rbcL</italic></td>
<td align="left">ribulose-bisphosphate carboxylase large chain</td>
<td align="left">Carbon metabolism (carbon fixation)</td>
<td align="right">617</td>
<td align="right">82</td>
<td align="right">0.97</td>
<td align="right">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>prsA</italic></td>
<td align="left">ribose-phosphate pyrophosphokinase</td>
<td align="left">Carbon metabolism (pentose phosphate pathway)</td>
<td align="right">28</td>
<td align="right">48</td>
<td align="right">0.91</td>
<td align="right">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>coxA</italic></td>
<td align="left">cytochrome c oxidase subunit I</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (oxidative phosphorylation)</td>
<td align="right">91</td>
<td align="right">56</td>
<td align="right">0.96</td>
<td align="right">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>ndhI</italic></td>
<td align="left">NADH dehydrogenase subunit I</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (oxidative phosphorylation)</td>
<td align="right">73</td>
<td align="right">135</td>
<td align="right">0.89</td>
<td align="right">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>cpaB1</italic></td>
<td align="left">phycocyanin, beta subunit</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (photosynthesis)</td>
<td align="right">592</td>
<td align="right">94</td>
<td align="right">0.99</td>
<td align="right">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>cpc</italic></td>
<td align="left">phycocyanin, beta subunit</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (photosynthesis)</td>
<td align="right">54</td>
<td align="right">9</td>
<td align="right">0.82</td>
<td align="right">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>petF</italic></td>
<td align="left">ferredoxin</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (photosynthesis)</td>
<td align="right">74</td>
<td align="right">128</td>
<td align="right">0.96</td>
<td align="right">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>psaA</italic></td>
<td align="left">photosystem I P700 chlorophyll a apoprotein A1</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (photosynthesis)</td>
<td align="right">370</td>
<td align="right">27</td>
<td align="right">0.92</td>
<td align="right">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>psaB</italic></td>
<td align="left">photosystem I P700 chlorophyll a apoprotein A10</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (photosynthesis)</td>
<td align="right">352</td>
<td align="right">51</td>
<td align="right">0.95</td>
<td align="right">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>psbA</italic></td>
<td align="left">photosystem II PsbA protein (D1)</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (photosynthesis)</td>
<td align="right">189</td>
<td align="right">47</td>
<td align="right">0.97</td>
<td align="right">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>psbB</italic></td>
<td align="left">photosystem II PsbB protein (CP47)</td>
<td align="left">Energy metabolism (photosynthesis)</td>
<td align="right">115</td>
<td align="right">25</td>
<td align="right">0.81</td>
<td align="right">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>recA</italic></td>
<td align="left">recombinase A</td>
<td align="left">Replication and repair</td>
<td align="right">49</td>
<td align="right">41</td>
<td align="right">0.9</td>
<td align="right">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>rpoD</italic></td>
<td align="left">RNA polymerase primary sigma factor</td>
<td align="left">Transcriptional machinery</td>
<td align="right">14</td>
<td align="right">26</td>
<td align="right">0.85</td>
<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>sigAII</italic></td>
<td align="left">type II alternative sigma-70 family RNA polymerase sigma factor</td>
<td align="left">Transcriptional machinery</td>
<td align="right">118</td>
<td align="right">32</td>
<td align="right">0.98</td>
<td align="right">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>AVERAGE</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="right"/>
<td align="right"><bold>57±36</bold></td>
<td align="right"><bold>0.91±0.07</bold></td>
<td align="right"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>SUM</bold></td>
<td align="right"><bold>16 genes</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="right"><bold>85</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="7"><bold><italic>Pelagibacter</italic> in CCS</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>bop</italic></td>
<td align="left">proteorhodopsin</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="right">950</td>
<td align="right">32.1</td>
<td align="right">0.90</td>
<td align="right">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>idiA</italic></td>
<td align="left">iron deficiency induced protein A, ferric iron transporter</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="right">183</td>
<td align="right">27.0</td>
<td align="right">0.93</td>
<td align="right">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="7"><bold><italic>Ostreococcus</italic> in CCS</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>rbcL</italic></td>
<td align="left">RuBisCO, large subunit</td>
<td align="left">Carbon metabolism (carbon fixation)</td>
<td align="right">3649</td>
<td align="right">29.0</td>
<td align="right">0.96</td>
<td align="right">2</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>For each gene, number of reads identified using MAGC for all samples and as a percent relative to the number of reads identified by WGPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>], correlation (the Pearson correlation coefficient) between results obtained by the two approaches and number of transcript-OTUs identified in all samples are shown. In the KEGG pathway column, the square brackets indicate pathways/metabolisms/processes that do not have KEGG assignment.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The MAGC approach revealed that oscillating patterns of gene transcription in <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> in the NPSG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>] were composed of distinct OTU-specific patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g002">Fig 2</xref>). Seven hundred ninety-one unique <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> transcript-OTUs were detected which represented 54 different genes (Table A in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s001">S1 File</xref>), and 55.6% of <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> transcript-OTUs representing 42 genes had significant diel periodicity in their abundance. From the 42 periodically expressed genes, orthologs of 21 genes (63.5% of the periodic transcript-OTUs) had differential transcriptional patterns among <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> taxa and included genes for DNA replication and repair and carbohydrate metabolism (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0146706.t001">Table 1</xref>). For example, the time of maximum transcription of the genes for the DNA replication initiation protein <italic>dnaA</italic> and for the key cell division protein <italic>ftsZ</italic> was distinct even among closely related high-light <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> OTUs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g002">Fig 2</xref>). This diversity in gene expression patterns was not resolved within binned <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> populations using the WGPB approach, where transcription of both <italic>dnaA</italic> and <italic>ftsZ</italic> had periodic patterns with peaks at ~17 h and 16 h, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>]. In contrast to genes with different patterns of transcription among gene-OTUs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0146706.t001">Table 1</xref>), 16 genes had the same transcriptional patterns for all detected <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> gene-OTUs (Table B in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s001">S1 File</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s002">S1 Fig</xref>). <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> populations are comprised of genetically different strains that vary substantially in gene content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref010">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref035">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref036">36</xref>]. Variations in the transcriptional patterns of genes such as DNA replication and cell division may reflect the differences in physiology, growth and cell division among these <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> strains. Additionally, the fact that many genes with periodic transcription patters had differential transcription at the OTU level suggests differences in global regulatory mechanisms among the <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> OTUs.</p>
<fig id="pone.0146706.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>OTU-Specific <italic>Prochloroccus</italic> Daily Gene Transcription Patterns in the NPSG.</title>
<p>Periodic transcription of the DNA replication initiation protein <italic>dnaA</italic> (A) and cell division protein <italic>ftsZ</italic> (B) genes varied among <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> OTUs. Top panels: Transcriptional composition detected based on the MAGC approach, where transcription was normalized to the total <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> hits in each sample, over time of day (X-axis in hours). OTUs are color-coded according to the heatmap. The transcript-OTU name (for example, 119098 AS9601 98%) shows ID of the target sequence (119098) for which probes were designed and percent nucleotide identity of the OTU to the most similar genome sequence (AS9601 98%). Transcription for all OTUs shown was estimated based on at least three probes with the exception of the two OTUs indicated with *. Middle panels: Hierarchical clustering of transcription patterns (by Pearson correlation). Each row in the heatmap shows transcription pattern of a unique OTU, and each column is a time point within the time-series. Bottom panels: Temporal patterns of total transcript abundances detected by MAGC (open circle) in this study and by WGPB (closed circle) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>] shows that the results of the two approaches are consistent.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Daily transcription patterns also varied among <italic>Synechococcus</italic> gene-OTUs in coastal California Current waters. Among 98 unique transcript-OTUs for 37 different genes in <italic>Synechococcus</italic> (Table A in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s001">S1 File</xref>), 63.6% of the transcript-OTUs had differential patterns over the diel cycle (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0146706.t002">Table 2</xref>). Eighteen transcript-OTUs from ten different genes had significant periodic patterns, and two genes had significantly different periodic transcriptional patterns among the <italic>Synechococcus</italic> OTUs. Interestingly, transcription of the <italic>cpc</italic> gene encoding the pigment phycocyanin and the <italic>cpaB1</italic> gene encoding the type 1 phycoerythrin pigment had significant periodicity in the <italic>Synechococcus</italic> CC9902-like OTUs (e.g. <italic>cpaB1</italic> sequence is within 95% nucleotide identity to <italic>cpaB1</italic> sequence in cultured <italic>Synechococcus</italic> CC9902), but not in the co-existing <italic>Synechococcus</italic> CC9311-like OTU. The timing of maximum abundance of transcripts of the <italic>cpc</italic> and <italic>cpaB1</italic> genes was distinct for each OTU (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g003">Fig 3A</xref>). The <italic>Synechococcus</italic> OTUs also varied in time of peak transcript abundances for other genes including the key enzyme for carbon fixation, ribulose-bisphosphate carboxylase large subunit gene (RuBisCO) (<italic>rbcL</italic>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s003">S2A Fig</xref>) and the photosystem I subunit gene <italic>psaA</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s003">S2B Fig</xref>). The <italic>Synechococcus</italic> CC9311, CC9902 and BL107-like strains detected in the CCS diel study ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>] and here) are members of two abundant and dynamically co-existing clades of <italic>Synechococcus</italic>, Clade I (CC9311) and Clade IV (CC9902 and BL107), and both clades chromatically adapt by changing their pigment content to optimize light utilization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref037">37</xref>]. The different daily transcription patterns for genes encoding pigments, RuBisCO and photosystem I indicate that the two <italic>Synechococcus</italic> clades were responding differentially to temporal and spatial variability of environmental factors such as light and nutrient availability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref037">37</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref039">39</xref>]. In addition, distinctions in <italic>cpaB-1</italic> and <italic>cpc</italic> transcription patterns among <italic>Synechococcus</italic> strains explains the lack of significant periodic patterns observed for these genes when clustered at the genus level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>].</p>
<fig id="pone.0146706.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>OTU-Specific Daily Gene Transcription Patterns by <italic>Synechococcus</italic> and SAR11 in the CCS.</title>
<p>Periodic transcription of phycoerythrin type I <italic>cpaB1</italic> gene (A) varied among <italic>Synechococcus</italic> OTUs. Transcription of the <italic>bop</italic> gene varied among the SAR11 OTUs (B). Top panels: Transcriptional composition detected based on the MAGC approach, where transcription was normalized to the total <italic>Synechococcus</italic> (A) and SAR11 (B) hits in each sample, over time of day (X-axis in hours). OTUs are color-coded according to the heatmap. Middle panels: Hierarchical clustering of transcription patterns (by Pearson correlation). The heatmap for <italic>Synechococcus</italic> gene-OTUs (A) also shows transcriptional patterns for phycoerythrin type II <italic>pcaB2</italic> and phycocyanin <italic>cpc</italic> genes. Each row in the heatmap shows transcription pattern of a unique OTU, and each column is a time point within the time-series. Bottom panels: Temporal patterns of total transcript abundances detected by MAGC (open circle) in this study and by WGPB (closed circle) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>] shows that the results of the two approaches are consistent.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The alpha proteobacteria SAR11 proteorhodopsin gene (<italic>bop</italic>) had a predominantly oscillating transcriptional pattern (with some variation) at the genus level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>], and the MAGC approach showed that these patterns varied substantially among different SAR11 OTUs in both the CCS and NPSG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g003">Fig 3B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s004">S3 Fig</xref>). In the NPSG, individual <italic>bop</italic> transcript-OTUs peaked at 3AM, 9AM and 11AM. Out of a total of eight <italic>bop</italic> transcript-OTUs, one had a weak periodic diel pattern (false discovery rate FDR = 0.23); however, patterns of most of the <italic>bop</italic> transcript-OTUs were dissimilar (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s004">S3 Fig</xref>), with Pearson correlation coefficients ranging from -0.19 to 0.60 (median of 0.35; n = 28). In the CCS, the <italic>bop</italic> pattern observed for the combined SAR11 populations was driven largely by the dominant transcript-OTU (40–60% of detected <italic>bop</italic> transcripts) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g003">Fig 3B</xref>). The less abundant <italic>bop</italic> transcript-OTUs, comprising the remaining 40–60% of the transcripts, had oscillating peak transcript abundances. Thus, OTU-specific transcription demonstrates that one dominant OTU can mask detection of variability in individual patterns. The variable proteorhodopsin gene transcriptional patterns among OTUs suggest that genetic diversity among SAR11 strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref040">40</xref>] sometimes results in different daily gene transcription patterns. Proteorhodopsin is a light-driven proton motive pump, and while the effect of light on the transcription of the <italic>bop</italic> gene is debatable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref041">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref042">42</xref>], proteorhodopsin is involved in SAR11 cell survival under carbon-limited conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref043">43</xref>]. Thus, variation in <italic>bop</italic> transcript abundances among OTUs may reflect the differences in the metabolic status of the cells and reflect variability in environmental conditions (e.g. organic carbon concentration and chemical composition).</p>
<p>Transcripts recovered in the CCS were dominated by the eukaryotic phytoplankter <italic>Ostreococcus</italic>, which displayed significant transcriptional periodicity across many genes, including the <italic>rbcL</italic> gene encoding the large subunit of RuBisCo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>]. OTU-specific transcriptional patterns showed that there was a change in the relative composition of the picoeukaryote <italic>Ostreococcus</italic> populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g004">Fig 4</xref>). We detected two different <italic>Ostreococcus rbcL</italic> OTUs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g004">Fig 4C and 4D</xref>), with 87% and 90% similarity to the chloroplast of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>tauri</italic> RCC1561, and both transcript-OTUs had similar patterns of abundances during the CCS study (Pearson 0.74). However, while transcripts from one <italic>Ostreococcus rbcL</italic>-OTU were very abundant over the two days sampled, transcripts from another OTU-<italic>rbcL</italic> increased by more than a factor of two in relative abundance by the end of sampling period. Transcription of <italic>rbcL</italic> by other eukaryotic phytoplankton also shifted, with the relative abundances of haptophyte and stramenopile transcripts decreasing significantly on the second day (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g004">Fig 4D</xref>). These transcript shifts coincided with a change in water masses by the end of the diel sampling in the CCS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>] (also in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g004">Fig 4B</xref>). Thus, the shift in <italic>rbcL</italic> transcript abundances indicate OTU-specific responses to changed conditions (for example, nutrient availability) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref044">44</xref>] and the advection of new populations with different water masses.</p>
<fig id="pone.0146706.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Eukaryotic Phytoplankton RuBisCO Gene (<italic>rbcL</italic>) Transcription Patterns in the CCS Associated with the Change in Water Masses.</title>
<p>(A) Location and transect of the CCS diel study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>]. CTD cast stations that followed the drifting sampler are shown. (B) Chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> as a function of salinity during the period of the CCS transect showing that samples were taken from different water masses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>]. (C) Transcript composition and (D) transcriptional patterns of the <italic>rbcL</italic> gene by eukaryotic phytoplankton. Arrow indicates the direction of the drifting sampler.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Lagrangian sampling efforts, designed to sample the same water mass, are becoming more feasible to implement at sea using advanced robotic approaches, but deconvoluting the effects of spatial and temporal variability is still difficult. The metatranscriptomic samples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>] were collected with a robotic drifting sampler to approximate Lagrangian sampling, but the path of each drifter migrated between submesoscale features, with corresponding changes in salinity and other environmental conditions such as nutrient concentrations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref045">45</xref>]. Differences in <italic>pstS</italic> (the gene encoding the high-affinity phosphate-binding protein that is a marker for phosphorus stress) transcript abundances along the NPSG sampling transect were particularly striking, with <italic>Prochlorococcus pstS</italic>-OTUs within 95% identity to sequences from MIT9215 and MIT9515 having highest transcript abundances in low-phosphate waters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g005">Fig 5</xref>). Phosphorus is an important nutrient that can limit primary productivity in the ocean (Table D in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s001">S1 File</xref>, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref045">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref046">46</xref>]), and these <italic>pstS</italic> OTU-specific patterns indicate that MIT9215 and MIT9515-like OTUs may be particularly sensitive to low phosphorus concentrations, relative to other high-light <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> strains. Such OTU or strain-level differences are indicative of the specific niches occupied by different populations that lead to differences in growth rates as a function of phosphate concentration. Thus, the OTU-specific transcriptional patterns observed here reveal the differences in physiological statuses of co-existing members of the microbial community and their individual responses to environmental variability.</p>
<fig id="pone.0146706.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title>Transcription of the Phosphate Transporter Gene <italic>pstS</italic> by Specific <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> OTUs Associated with Inorganic Phosphate Concentrations in the NPSG Study.</title>
<p>(A) Location and transect of the NPSG diel study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref045">45</xref>]. CTD cast stations following the drifting sampler are shown. (B) Phosphate concentrations measured from seawater collected from a CTD Niskin bottle following the drifting sampler are shown for the NPSG transect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref045">45</xref>]. Eight depths were sampled at each of the five sampling locations, and the stars indicate 25 m depth. The boxes indicate the midday time of depth profile sampling for phosphate. (C) Normalized <italic>pstS</italic> transcript abundances among <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> OTUs during the 72h NPSG study. (D) Temporal patterns of total <italic>Prochlorococcus pstS</italic> transcript abundances detected by MAGC (open circle) here and by WGPB (closed circle) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>].</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The variability in transcription at the OTU or strain-level resolution helps explain how such genetically diverse, sympatric microbial communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref005">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref010">10</xref>] still retain robust daily patterns in gene transcription [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref013">13</xref>]. The OTU-specific patterns of gene transcription reported here show that closely-related but genetically distinct taxa indeed have unique transcription patterns, that reflect the temporal (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g002">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g003">3</xref>) and spatial (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g004">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g005">5</xref>) variability in the environment. The results also support the hypothesis that genetic diversity among microbial strains/ecotypes is reflected in gene expression patterns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref019">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref020">20</xref>]. The MAGC method provides a powerful complementary approach to the WGPB approach to resolve individual gene transcription at the higher taxonomic level, and thereby reveal differential responses that would otherwise be undetectable. The dynamics at the species and sub-species levels underpins a vast array of microbial population genetic diversity. To better understand the fundamental factors that shape marine microbial community composition relative to environmental variability, more highly resolved taxon-specific information is extremely important. Higher resolution approaches may also provide deeper insights into microbiome variability and dynamics in a variety of different environmental contexts.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Metatranscriptome sequence data, analyzed in this study, was obtained from NCBI Short Read Archive database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/sra/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/sra/</ext-link>) from projects under accession numbers SRA: SRP017469 (the two-day study in the California Current System, CCS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>] and SRA: SRP041215 (three-day study in the North Pacific Subtropical Gyre, NPSG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>]. The probes from the MicroTOOLs microarray [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref024">24</xref>] were obtained from NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" xlink:type="simple">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) under accession number GPL16706. The probes were further filtered to target sequences that are at least 330-nt long, and the final query database consisted of total 98,632 probes targeting 16,806 gene-OTUs of 145 unique functional genes, where each gene-OTU was targeted by six probes. The probes were designed by Roche NimbleGen (Madison, WI) and quality-checked as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref024">24</xref>]. Each set of six 60-nt long probes is specific to one gene-out; one probe could potentially show cross-specificity to another gene-OTU, but not all six probes. It is important to note that probes can be designed for any genes of interest using several approaches, e.g. using eArray (Agilent, earray.chem.agilent.com/earray/). In order to assign each read to a target probe, the probe sequences were used as queries in BLASTN search against the metatranscriptomic sequence databases on a local server with the following parameters: 20,000 hits per query and E value of at least 0.0001. The BLASTN results were sorted to leave only the hits with alignment length of 60 nucleotides and nucleotide identity at least 95% for all probes, except probes for <italic>Prochlorococcus psbA</italic>, for which at least 98% nucleotide identity was selected. Because paired-end Illumina MiSeq sequencing was done in SRP041215, and both pair reads target the same transcript region, only one Illumina read from a pair was selected for further processing. The abundance of a transcript-OTU was calculated as average hit count for all probes (example in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146706.g001">Fig 1</xref>). Rarely (three instances total, all for the <italic>Prochlorococcus psaA</italic> gene), a read would hit with equal similarity to several probes from different gene-OTUs, and the read was assigned to all these probes. Reads with incorrect assignments showed high variability between the probes and were manually evaluated. Detected transcripts were determined if at least two probes for this transcript had hits in at least one sample, and the minimum total transcription values were at least 3 or 6 (which is equal to 6–36 reads per transcript) in the CCS and NPSG, respectively. Next, gene transcription within each genus was normalized to total read count for this genus in each sample and multiplied by 10<sup>6</sup>.</p>
<p>Transcriptional patterns were defined as the difference in transcript abundance in samples relative to the mean transcript abundance in all samples, and periodic (following a cosine curve over a 24-hour period) transcriptional patterns were identified using the Fourier score (R package ‘cycle’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref047">47</xref>]). The significance of Fourier score was assessed with the false discovery rate (FDR) using a total of 10,000 background models generated with the autoregressive processes of order (AR1) model. The AR1 model allows generating background models with the same distribution as the original dataset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref048">48</xref>]. Due to the nature of environmental data, the chosen FDR threshold was higher than it would be for a dataset obtained from cultures, and the significantly periodic transcripts were defined as those that had FDR &lt; 0.25.</p>
<p>Transcriptional patterns were clustered using hierarchical clustering (Pearson correlation for distance measure and complete agglomeration method for clustering), and the significance of cluster assignment was estimated using Approximately Unbiased (AU) P-values of &gt;0.95 (AU P-values range from 0 to 1 and show how strong the cluster is supported by data), where the AU P-values were calculated from at least 1,000 mutliscale bootstrap resampling (pvclust R package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref049">49</xref>]). The identified genes, periodicity and cluster assignment for both NPSG and CCS studies are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s005">S1 Table</xref>. All reads found with the probes for <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic>, <italic>Synechococcus</italic>, SAR11 and <italic>Ostreococcus</italic> are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s006">S2 Table</xref>.</p>
<p>All data processing and analysis were done using RStudio and BioConductor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref050">50</xref>] with the additional packages ggplot2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref051">51</xref>], seqinr [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref052">52</xref>] and ShortRead [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref053">53</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0146706.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 File</label>
<caption>
<title>Supporting Tables.</title>
<p>Summary of Results Obtained with the MAGC Approach in Comparison to the WGPB Approach for Metatranscriptomes from the Two Oceanic Regions (<bold>Table A</bold>). Genes with Similar Transcriptional Patterns among <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> OTUs during the 72-h Study in the NPSG (<bold>Table B</bold>). Genes with Similar Transcriptional Patterns among <italic>Synechococcus</italic> OTUs during the 48-h Study in the CCS (<bold>Table C</bold>). Phosphate Concentrations and Primary Production during the NPSG Cruise (<bold>Table D</bold>).</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0146706.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>OTU-specific <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> Daily Gene Transcription Patterns in the NPSG.</title>
<p><italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> high-light OTUs had similar patterns of transcription for the gene encoding the ammonium transporter (A) <italic>amt</italic> and (B) the <italic>psbA</italic> gene encoding photosystem II core protein. Top panels: Transcriptional composition detected by the MAGC approach, where transcription was normalized to the total <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> hits in each sample, over time of day (X-axis in hours). OTUs are color-coded according to the heat map coloration below. Middle panels: Hierarchical clustering of transcriptional patterns (by Pearson correlation) for <italic>amt</italic> and <italic>coxA</italic> transcripts. Each row in the heatmap shows transcription of a unique OTU transcript, and each column is a time point within the 72 hour time-series. The OTU transcript ID are only shown, and affiliation for each transcript can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146706.s005">S1 Table</xref>. Bottom panels: Temporal patterns of total transcript abundances detected by MAGC (open circle) in this study and by WGPB (closed circle) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>] shows that the results of the two approaches are consistent.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0146706.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.s003" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>OTU-Specific Daily <italic>Synechococcus</italic> Gene Transcription in the CCS.</title>
<p>(A) Periodic transcription of the RuBisCO <italic>rbcL</italic> gene and (B) the photosystem I <italic>psbA</italic> genes varied among <italic>Synechococcus</italic> OTUs. Top Panels in each section: Transcriptional composition detected by MAGC, where transcription was normalized to the total <italic>Synechococcus</italic> hits in each sample, over time of day (X-axis in hours). OTUs are color-coded according to the OTU coloration in the heatmap below. Middle panels: Hierarchical clustering of transcriptional patterns (by Pearson correlation) for <italic>rbcL</italic> and <italic>psaA</italic> transcripts. Each row in the heatmap shows transcription of a unique OTU transcript, and each column is a time point within the 48 hour time-series. Bottom panels: Temporal patterns of total transcript abundances detected by MAGC (open circle) in this study and by WGPB (closed circle) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref011">11</xref>] shows that the results of the two approaches are consistent.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0146706.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.s004" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>OTU-Specific SAR11 Daily Gene Transcription in the NPSG.</title>
<p>Top Panel: Transcriptional composition detected by MAGC, where transcription was normalized to the total SAR11 hits in each sample, over time of day (X-axis in hours). OTUs are color-coded according to the OTU coloration in the heatmap below. Middle panels: Hierarchical clustering of transcriptional patterns (by Pearson correlation) for <italic>bop</italic> transcripts. Each row in the heatmap shows transcription of a unique OTU transcript, and each column is a time point within the 72 hour time-series. Bottom panels: Temporal patterns of total transcript abundances detected by MAGC (open circle) in this study and by WGPB (closed circle) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0146706.ref012">12</xref>] shows that the results of the two approaches are consistent.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0146706.s005" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.s005" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Gene Transcription by OTU in the Diel Metatranscriptomes from the NPSG and CCS.</title>
<p>Transcription is shown for <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic>, <italic>Synechococcus</italic> and SAR11 genes and for the eukaryotic <italic>rbcL</italic> gene.</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0146706.s006" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0146706.s006" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Sequence Read IDs Identified by the MAGC Approach from the NPSG and CCS Metatranscriptomes.</title>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Kendra Turk-Kubo for her critical comments on an earlier draft of the manuscript. We thank the ESP Team and Chris Scholin (MBARI) for ESP deployments, Francisco Chavez (MBARI) and the Lucile and David Packard Foundation for providing the CTD data from the CANON-2010 cruise, the Captain and crew of the R/V Western Flyer and R/V Kilo Moana, and personnel of the Hawaiian Ocean Time-series program and the NSF Science and Technology Center for Microbial Oceanography: Research and Education for nutrient data from the BioLINCS cruise.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zehr</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kudela</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nitrogen cycle of the open ocean: from genes to ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Mar Sci</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21329204</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karl</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Church</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dore</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Letelier</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahaffey</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Predictable and efficient carbon sequestration in the North Pacific Ocean supported by symbiotic nitrogen fixation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>109</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1842</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1120312109" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1120312109</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22308450</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahlgren</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocap</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Diversity and distribution of marine <italic>Synechococcus</italic>: multiple gene phylogenies for consensus classification and development of qPCR assays for sensitive measurement of clades in the ocean</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2012.00213" xlink:type="simple">10.3389/fmicb.2012.00213</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22723796</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vergin</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beszteri</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monier</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thrash</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Temperton</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Treusch</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>High-resolution SAR11 ecotype dynamics at the Bermuda Atlantic Time-series Study site by phylogenetic placement of pyrosequences</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1322</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.32" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ismej.2013.32</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23466704</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunagawa</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coelho</surname> <given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaffron</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kultima</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labadie</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salazar</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Structure and function of the global ocean microbiome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>348</volume>(<issue>6237</issue>): <fpage>1261359</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1261359" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1261359</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25999513</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Vargas</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Audic</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Decelle</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahé</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Logares</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Eukaryotic plankton diversity in the sunlit ocean</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>348</volume>(<issue>6237</issue>): <fpage>1261605</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1261605" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1261605</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25999516</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname> <given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Preston</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mincer</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rich</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hallam</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frigaard</surname> <given-names>N-U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Community genomics among stratified microbial assemblages in the ocean's interior</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>311</volume>(<issue>5760</issue>): <fpage>496</fpage>–<lpage>503</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16439655</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rusch</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halpern</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heidelberg</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yooseph</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The Sorcerer II global ocean sampling expedition: northwest Atlantic through eastern tropical Pacific</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>e77</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17355176</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Satinsky</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crump</surname> <given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zielinski</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doherty</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Microspatial gene expression patterns in the Amazon River Plume</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>30</issue>): <fpage>11085</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1402782111" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1402782111</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25024226</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kashtan</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roggensack</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigue</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biller</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coe</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Single-cell genomics reveals hundreds of coexisting subpopulations in wild <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>344</volume>(<issue>6182</issue>): <fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1248575" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1248575</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24763590</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ottesen</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eppley</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chavez</surname> <given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scholin</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Pattern and synchrony of gene expression among sympatric marine microbial populations</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>E488</fpage>–<lpage>E97</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1222099110" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1222099110</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23345438</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ottesen</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gifford</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eppley</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marin</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Multispecies diel transcriptional oscillations in open ocean heterotrophic bacterial assemblages</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>345</volume>(<issue>6193</issue>): <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1252476" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1252476</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25013074</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aylward</surname> <given-names>FO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eppley</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chavez</surname> <given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scholin</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname> <given-names>EF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Microbial community transcriptional networks are conserved in three domains at ocean basin scales</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2015</year>: <fpage>201502883</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocap</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larimer</surname> <given-names>FW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamerdin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malfatti</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chain</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahlgren</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Genome divergence in two <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> ecotypes reflects oceanic niche differentiation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>424</volume>(<issue>6952</issue>): <fpage>1042</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12917642</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palenik</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dupont</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname> <given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heidelberg</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Badger</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Genome sequence of <italic>Synechococcus</italic> CC9311: insights into adaptation to a coastal environment</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>36</issue>): <fpage>13555</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16938853</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martiny</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kathuria</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berube</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Widespread metabolic potential for nitrite and nitrate assimilation among <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> ecotypes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>26</issue>): <fpage>10787</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0902532106" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0902532106</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19549842</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malmstrom</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigue</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kern</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Ecology of uncultured <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> clades revealed through single-cell genomics and biogeographic analysis</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2012.89" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ismej.2012.89</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22895163</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Konstantinidis</surname> <given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname> <given-names>EF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genomic patterns of recombination, clonal divergence and environment in marine microbial populations</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1052</fpage>–<lpage>1065</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2008.62" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ismej.2008.62</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18580971</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Konstantinidis</surname> <given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serres</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romine</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname> <given-names>JLM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Auchtung</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCue</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Comparative systems biology across an evolutionary gradient within the <italic>Shewanella</italic> genus</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>37</issue>): <fpage>15909</fpage>–<lpage>15914</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0902000106" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0902000106</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805231</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vital</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Østman</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Konstantinidis</surname> <given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tiedje</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gene expression analysis of <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> strains provides insights into the role of gene regulation in diversification</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1130</fpage>–<lpage>1140</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2014.204" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ismej.2014.204</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25343512</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Philippe</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crozat</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenski</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of global regulatory networks during a long-term experiment with <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>BioAssays</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>846</fpage>–<lpage>860</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eren</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maignien</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sul</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grim</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sogin</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oligotyping: Differentiating between closely related microbial taxa using 16S rRNA gene data</article-title>. <source>Methods Ecol Evol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1111</fpage>–<lpage>1119</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eren</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lescault</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reveillaud</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vineis</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sogin</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>Minimum entropy decomposition: Unsupervised oligotyping for sensitive partitioning of highthroughput marker gene sequences</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>968</fpage>–<lpage>979</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2014.195" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ismej.2014.195</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25325381</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shilova</surname> <given-names>IN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robidart</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tripp</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turk-Kubo</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wawrik</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A microarray for assessing transcription from pelagic marine microbial taxa</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1476</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2014.1" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ismej.2014.1</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24477198</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindell</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ecological aspects of <italic>ntcA</italic> gene expression and its use as an indicator of the nitrogen status of marine <italic>Synechococcus</italic> spp</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>67</volume>: <fpage>3340</fpage>–<lpage>3349</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11472902</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holtzendorff</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marie</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Partensky</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rivlin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname> <given-names>WR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Synchronized expression of ftsZ in natural <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> populations of the Red Sea</article-title>. <source>Environ. Microbiol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>653</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12460272</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kan</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bachoon</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Phylogenetic diversity of Synechococcus in the Chesapeake Bay revealed by ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase-oxygenase (RuBisCO) large subunit gene (rbcL) sequences</article-title>. <source>Aquat Microb Ecol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zehr</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montoya</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewson</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mondragon</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Short</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name> <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Experiments linking nitrogenase gene expression to nitrogen fixation in the North Pacific subtropical gyre</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varaljay</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gifford</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karl</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>.<article-title>Bacterial dimethylsulfoniopropionate degradation genes in the oligotrophic north pacific subtropical gyre</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>2775</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/AEM.07559-11" xlink:type="simple">10.1128/AEM.07559-11</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22327587</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casciotti</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>BB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dissimilatory nitrite reductase genes from autotrophic ammonia-oxidizing bacteria</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>2213</fpage>–<lpage>2221</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11319103</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venter</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Remington</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heidelberg</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halpern</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rusch</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>,<name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Environmental Genome Shotgun Sequencing of the Sargasso Sea</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <year>2004</year>;<volume>304</volume>(<issue>5667</issue>): <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15001713</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poretsky</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewson</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zehr</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparative day/night metatranscriptomic analysis of microbial communities in the North Pacific subtropical gyre</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1358</fpage>–<lpage>1375</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1462-2920.2008.01863.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2008.01863.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19207571</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewson</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paerl</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tripp</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zehr</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karl</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Metagenomic potential of microbial assemblages in the surface waters of the central Pacific Ocean tracks variability in oceanic habitat</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>1981</fpage>–<lpage>1994</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewson</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poretsky</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tripp</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montoya</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zehr</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spatial patterns and light-driven variation of microbial population gene expression in surface waters of the oligotrophic open ocean</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1940</fpage>–<lpage>1956</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1462-2920.2010.02198.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2010.02198.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20406287</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martiny</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Occurrence of phosphate acquisition genes in <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> cells from different ocean regions</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1340</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1462-2920.2009.01860.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2009.01860.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19187282</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scanlan</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostrowski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazard</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dufresne</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garczarek</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname> <given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Ecological genomics of marine picocyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/MMBR.00035-08" xlink:type="simple">10.1128/MMBR.00035-08</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19487728</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palenik</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chromatic adaptation in marine <italic>Synechococcus</italic> strains</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>991</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157276</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collier</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grossman</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chlorosis induced by nutrient deprivation in <italic>Synechococcus</italic> sp. strain PCC 7942: not all bleaching is the same</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>174</volume>(<issue>14</issue>): <fpage>4718</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1624459</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Six</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>J-C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garczarek</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostrowski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dufresne</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blot</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Diversity and evolution of phycobilisomes in marine <italic>Synechococcus</italic> spp.: a comparative genomics study</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>R259</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18062815</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grote</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thrash</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huggett</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landry</surname> <given-names>ZC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carini</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giovannoni</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Streamlining and core genome conservation among highly divergent members of the SAR11 clade</article-title>. <source>MBio</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>e00252</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/mBio.00252-12" xlink:type="simple">10.1128/mBio.00252-12</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22991429</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giovannoni</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bibbs</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname> <given-names>J-C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stapels</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desiderio</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vergin</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Proteorhodopsin in the ubiquitous marine bacterium SAR11</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>438</volume>(<issue>7064</issue>): <fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16267553</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lami</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirchman</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Diurnal expression of SAR11 proteorhodopsin and 16S rRNA genes in coastal North Atlantic waters</article-title>. <source>Aquat Microb Ecol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steindler</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwalbach</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giovannoni</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Energy starved Candidatus Pelagibacter ubique substitutes light-mediated ATP production for endogenous carbon respiration</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>e19725</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0019725" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0019725</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21573025</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>López-Díaz</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrera</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santiago</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corredor</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bronk</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <article-title>A day in the life in the dynamic marine environment: how nutrients shape diel patterns of phytoplankton photosynthesis and carbon fixation gene expression in the Mississippi and Orinoco River plumes</article-title>. <source>Hydrobiologia</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>679</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robidart</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Church</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ascani</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bombar</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Ecogenomic sensor reveals controls on N2-fixing microorganisms in the North Pacific Ocean</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1175</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.244" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ismej.2013.244</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24477197</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bombar</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robidart</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rabines</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turk-Kubo</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Measurements of nitrogen fixation in the oligotrophic North Pacific Subtropical Gyre using a free-drifting submersible incubation device</article-title>. <source>J Plankton Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>727</fpage>–<lpage>739</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Futschik ME. cycle: Significance of periodic expression pattern in time-series data. R package version 1.22.0, 2009. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://itb.biologie.hu-berlin.de/~futschik/software/R/cycle/index.html" xlink:type="simple">http://itb.biologie.hu-berlin.de/~futschik/software/R/cycle/index.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Futschik</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herzel</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Are we overestimating the number of cell-cycling genes? The impact of background models on time-series analysis</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1063</fpage>–<lpage>1069</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btn072" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn072</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18310054</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Suzuki RS, Hidetoshi S. pvclust: Hierarchical Clustering with P-Values via Multiscale Bootstrap Resampling. 2014. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/pvclust/index.html" xlink:type="simple">http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/pvclust/index.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gentleman</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname> <given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bates</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bolstad</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dettling</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dudoit</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Bioconductor: open software development for computational biology and bioinformatics</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>R80</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15461798</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickham</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <source>ggplot2: elegant graphics for data analysis</source>. <edition>1st ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charif</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lobry</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>SeqinR 1.0–2: A contributed package to the R project for statistical computing devoted to biological sequences retrieval and analysis</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Bastolla</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roman</surname> <given-names>HE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vendruscolo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Structural approaches to sequence evolution: Molecules, Networks, Populations</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>. pp. <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0146706.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anders</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aboyoun</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagès</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gentleman</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>ShortRead: a Bioconductor package for input, quality assessment and exploration of high-throughput sequence data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2607</fpage>–<lpage>2608</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp450" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp450</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19654119</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>