<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-10-00627</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computational biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genomics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Metagenomics</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Community ecology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Community structure</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Ecological environments</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Marine environments</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Ecological metrics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Species diversity</subject>
                <subject>Species richness</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biodiversity</subject>
              <subject>Coastal ecology</subject>
              <subject>Marine ecology</subject>
              <subject>Microbial ecology</subject>
              <subject>Theoretical ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genomics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Metagenomics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Marine biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Coastal ecology</subject>
              <subject>Marine ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Microbiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Microbial ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Systems biology</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Microbiology</subject>
          <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
          <subject>Ecology</subject>
          <subject>Marine and Aquatic Sciences</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Taxonomic and Functional Diversity of Microbes at a Temperate Coastal Site: A ‘Multi-Omic’ Study of Seasonal and Diel Temporal Variation</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Seasonal and Diel Marine Bacterial Function</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gilbert</surname>
            <given-names>Jack A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Field</surname>
            <given-names>Dawn</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Swift</surname>
            <given-names>Paul</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Thomas</surname>
            <given-names>Simon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cummings</surname>
            <given-names>Denise</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Temperton</surname>
            <given-names>Ben</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Weynberg</surname>
            <given-names>Karen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Huse</surname>
            <given-names>Susan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hughes</surname>
            <given-names>Margaret</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Joint</surname>
            <given-names>Ian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Somerfield</surname>
            <given-names>Paul J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mühling</surname>
            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Plymouth Marine Laboratory, Plymouth, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne, Illinois, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Ecology and Evolution, University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>National Environment Research Council (NERC) Centre for Ecology and Hydrology, Wallingford, Oxfordshire, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Josephine Bay Paul Center for Comparative Molecular Biology and Evolution, Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>School of Biological Sciences, University of Liverpool, Liverpool, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><addr-line>TU Bergakademie Freiberg, IÖZ - Interdisciplinary Centre for Ecology, Freiberg, Germany</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Rodriguez-Valera</surname>
            <given-names>Francisco</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Universidad Miguel Hernandez, Spain</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">gilbertjack@gmail.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JAG DF IJ MM. Performed the experiments: JAG ST DC BT MH. Analyzed the data: JAG DF PS SH PJS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: KW MH SH. Wrote the paper: JAG DF IJ MM.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Jack A. Gilbert is a PLoS ONE Academic Editor. The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e15545</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gilbert et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>How microbial communities change over time in response to the environment is poorly understood. Previously a six-year time series of 16S rRNA V6 data from the Western English Channel demonstrated robust seasonal structure within the bacterial community, with diversity negatively correlated with day-length. Here we determine whether metagenomes and metatranscriptomes follow similar patterns. We generated 16S rRNA datasets, metagenomes (1.2 GB) and metatranscriptomes (157 MB) for eight additional time points sampled in 2008, representing three seasons (Winter, Spring, Summer) and including day and night samples. This is the first microbial ‘multi-omic’ study to combine 16S rRNA amplicon sequencing with metagenomic and metatranscriptomic profiling. Five main conclusions can be drawn from analysis of these data: 1) Archaea follow the same seasonal patterns as Bacteria, but show lower relative diversity; 2) Higher 16S rRNA diversity also reflects a higher diversity of transcripts; 3) Diversity is highest in winter and at night; 4) Community-level changes in 16S-based diversity and metagenomic profiles are better explained by seasonal patterns (with samples closest in time being most similar), while metatranscriptomic profiles are better explained by diel patterns and shifts in particular categories (i.e., functional groups) of genes; 5) Changes in key genes occur among seasons and between day and night (i.e., photosynthesis); but these samples contain large numbers of orphan genes without known homologues and it is these unknown gene sets that appear to contribute most towards defining the differences observed between times. Despite the huge diversity of these microbial communities, there are clear signs of predictable patterns and detectable stability over time. Renewed and intensified efforts are required to reveal fundamental deterministic patterns in the most complex microbial communities. Further, the presence of a substantial proportion of orphan sequences underscores the need to determine the gene products of sequences with currently unknown function.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Funding for this work was provided by a Natural Environmental Research Council (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nerc.ac.uk" xlink:type="simple">www.nerc.ac.uk</ext-link>) grant, NE/F00138X/1. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="17"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The diversity of bacteria, as revealed by 16S rRNA, is well-known to be extremely high <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Woese1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert1">[10]</xref>. Therefore it is expected that the functional (phenotypic) diversity of these organisms will also be vast. This is already evidenced by biogeographic studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Rusch1">[e.g. 11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Delong2">[8]</xref> that highlight the huge store of microbial proteins present in marine communities. For example, Rusch and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Rusch1">[11]</xref> found approximately 4.4 million unique genetic fragments in a study of 7.7 million sequences. However, to the best of our knowledge there have been no studies that have made direct comparisons of overall diversity at the 16S rRNA, metagenomic and metatranscriptomic levels over time.</p>
      <p>Here we apply such a ‘multi-omic’ approach to begin to unravel relationships between genetic and functional diversity in a temperate coastal marine microbial community. Marine bacteria demonstrate seasonal patterns in diversity with, generally, higher diversity during the winter than the summer in pelagic ecosystems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Murray1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert2">[14]</xref>. Numerous environmental factors have been suggested to influence this diversity (e.g. temperature and nutrients: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Fuhrman1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Andersson1">[15]</xref>), yet our characterization of the long-term coastal ocean observatory site, L4, in the Western English Channel (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.westernchannelobservatory.org.uk/all_parameters.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.westernchannelobservatory.org.uk/all_parameters.html</ext-link>) suggests that the robust seasonal pattern in species richness is most closely correlated to day length <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert2">[14]</xref>. It is possible that an ability of organisms to respond to day length could explain the resilience of “metabolic circadian oscillators”, allowing organisms to respond to changing environmental conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Mihalcescu1">[16]</xref>. Recently, the transcriptional profiles from one pair of night and a day samples of bacterioplankton in the oligotrophic North Pacific Ocean were examined <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Poretsky1">[17]</xref>, showing that transcriptional activity was correlated to the diel cycle and the estimated diversity of the COG functional categories was higher at night. While previous genomic and metagenomic research has mainly focused on the diel rhythm in photosynthetic microorganisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Vaulot1">[e.g. 18]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Yang1">[20]</xref>, we now extend this to the whole prokaryotic community, including the non-photosynthetic microorganisms, by comparing night- and day-time samples collected within the same 24 hr period.</p>
      <p>Specifically, we test two hypotheses about the microbial community found at L4. Firstly, that bacterial and archaeal <italic>functional potential</italic> (genetic capacity) and <italic>functional actuality</italic> (transcriptional response) will track diversity (based on the 16S rRNA marker) and show similar seasonal patterns. Secondly, that within short time periods, metatranscriptomes will show more differences than 16S rRNA and metagenomic profiles, reflecting the relationship between expression of particular sets of genes and environmental variation, such as on a day/night cycle.</p>
      <p>To test these hypotheses, datasets were generated from pelagic water samples taken from the L4 station during the day and night at 3 sampling time points in 2008: January, April and August, representing winter, spring and summer. Samples were collected once during day time and once during night in January and April, while in August four samples, taken at six hourly intervals, were collected over a 24-hour period. Bacterial and archaeal 16S rRNA V6 amplicon-pyrosequenced taxonomic profiling was used, to allow direct comparison of additional time points and the existing six year time series <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert2">[14]</xref> and to determine if Archaea show a similar seasonal trend to Bacteria. Shotgun sequencing of both DNA (metagenomes) and mRNA (metatranscriptomes) was employed to compare the taxonomic diversity with the <italic>functional potential</italic> (genetic capacity) and <italic>functional actuality</italic> (expressed genetic material) of the microbial community respectively, over time.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Water Sampling</title>
        <p>Surface water (0–2 m) samples were collected from the L4 sampling station (50.2518° N, 4.2089° W), part of the Western Channel Observatory (WCO, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.westernchannelobservatory.org.uk" xlink:type="simple">http://www.westernchannelobservatory.org.uk</ext-link>), on January 28<sup>th</sup>, April 22<sup>nd</sup>, August 27<sup>th</sup> and August 28<sup>th</sup> 2008. In January a sample was taken at 1500 h at the L4 station. A minimal-impact surface buoy with a drogue at 7 m depth, was deployed to track the surface water mass on a Lagrangian sampling approach. At 1900 h, approximately 2 hours after total darkness, a second sample was taken at 50.2611° N: 4.2435° W. In April, an initial sample was taken at 1600 h at the L4 station and, following a Lagrangian drift, a second sample was taken at 2200 h (1.5 h after darkness) at 50.253°N: 4.1875°W. In August, four samples were taken over a 24 h period, again using a Lagrangian approach. Sampling began at 1600 h on the 27<sup>th</sup> at L4, 2200 h (2 h after sunset) at 50.2545°N: 4.199°W, at 0400 h (2-hours before sunrise) on the 28<sup>th</sup> at 50.2678°N: 4.1723°W, and at 1000 h at 50.2665°N: 4.1486°W.</p>
        <p>For each sample, 20 L of seawater were collected from the surface (0–2 m) and pre-filtered through a Whatman GF/A filter (∼1.6 µm poresize). The filtrate was passed through a 0.22 µm Sterivex cartridge (Millipore) for a maximum of 30 minutes (approximately 10 L per Sterivex cartridge). Sterivex cartridges were pumped dry and then immediately snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen, transferred in liquid nitrogen back to the laboratory, barcoded <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Booth1">[32]</xref>, and stored at −80°C until nucleic acid extraction. Ambient water temperature, density, salinity, chlorophyll a, total organic nitrogen and carbon, nitrate, ammonia, silicate and phosphate concentration were also determined for each sampling occasion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t001"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>). Methods used for determining these variables are available on the WCO website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.westernchannelobservatory.org.uk/all_parameters.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.westernchannelobservatory.org.uk/all_parameters.html</ext-link>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0015545-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Environmental variables for each sampling occasion.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0015545-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28/01/2008</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28/01/2008</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22/04/2008</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22/04/2008</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26/08/2008</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26/08/2008</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27/08/2008</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27/08/2008</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14:00</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22:00</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14:00</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22:00</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16:00</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22:00</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">04:00</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10:00</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Temperature (°C)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.05</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Density (kg m<sup>−2</sup>)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1025.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1026.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1027.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1027.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1023.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1024.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1024.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1024.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Salinity (PSU)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.12</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Chlorophyll a (µg/L)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.81</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.20</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.32</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.24</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.80</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.91</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Total Organic Nitrogen (µmol L<sup>−1</sup>)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.331</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.453</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.897</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.773</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.837</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.329</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.018</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.145</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Total Organic Carbon (µmol L<sup>−1</sup>)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.185</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.168</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.247</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.413</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.761</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.482</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.015</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.671</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>NO<sub>2</sub> + NO<sub>3</sub> (µmol L<sup>−1</sup>)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.75</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Ammonia (µmol L<sup>−1</sup>)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.54</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>SRP (µmol L<sup>−1</sup>)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.53</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.32</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Silicate (µmol L<sup>−1</sup>)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.01</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.75</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Nucleic Acid Extraction</title>
        <p>DNA and RNA were isolated from each sample <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert3">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert4">[33]</xref>, barcoded <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Booth1">[32]</xref> and then stored at −80°C. DNA and mRNA-enriched cDNA were purified from the same pool using the techniques described in detail in Gilbert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert3">[25]</xref>. DNA was used for metagenomic and 16S rRNA V6 amplicon pyrosequencing analysis and mRNA-enriched cDNA was used for metatranscriptomic pyrosequencing analysis. All DNA and cDNA were pyrosequenced using the GS-FLX Titanium platform. All data are available on the CAMERA website under ‘Western Channel Observatory Microbial Metagenomic Study (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://web.camera.calit2.net" xlink:type="simple">http://web.camera.calit2.net</ext-link>) and MG-RAST under 4443360-63; 4443365-68 and 4444077, 4445065-68, 4445070, 4445081, 4444083 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://metagenomics.nmpdr.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://metagenomics.nmpdr.org/</ext-link>), as well as through the INSDC short reads archive under ERP000118 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERP0001180" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERP0001180</ext-link>). All submissions conform to the “Minimum information standards” recommended by the Genomic Standards Consortium (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t001"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Field1">[34]</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gensc.org/gc_wiki/index.php/MIENS" xlink:type="simple">http://gensc.org/gc_wiki/index.php/MIENS</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>16S rRNA V6 amplicon pyrosequencing</title>
        <p>16S rRNA V6 amplicon pyrosequencing was carried out as described by Huber et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Huber1">[35]</xref> and Gilbert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert1">[10]</xref>. For Bacteria, the primers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s005">Table S1</xref>) were used in multiplex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Huber1">[35]</xref>. All 8 samples were run in the same GS-FLX 454 pyrosequencing reaction using multiplex identifiers (MIDs). These were January day (<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">ACGAGTGCGT</named-content>), January night (<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">ACGCTCGACA</named-content>), April Day (<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">AGACGCACTC</named-content>), April Night (<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">AGCACTGTAG</named-content>), August 4pm (<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">ATCAGACACG</named-content>), August 10pm (<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">ATATCGCGAG</named-content>), August 4am (<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">CGTGTCTCTA</named-content>), August 10am (<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">CTCGCGTGTC</named-content>). All amplicons were sequenced using the 454 Corporation's GS-FLX instrument at the NERC-funded Advanced Genomics Facility at the University of Liverpool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.liv.ac.uk/agf/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.liv.ac.uk/agf/</ext-link>). Archaeal 16S rRNA amplicon pyrosequencing (for primer see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s005">Table S1</xref>) was performed at the International Census for Marine Microbes (ICoMM) Initiative laboratory at Woods Hole in September 2008 according to the method of Huber et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Huber1">[35]</xref>, again using the GS-flx platform.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>16S rRNA data processing</title>
        <p>The 16S rDNA sequence reads were filtered <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Huse1">[36]</xref> to remove all reads that did not have an exact match to the MID, the proximal primer or a near match to the distal primer, along with reads that contained Ns. Primer sequences were trimmed from both ends. Any reads less than 50 nt, or whose average quality score was less than 30 after trimming, were also removed. Taxonomic assignments were made to each trimmed high-quality sequence using GAST <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Huse2">[37]</xref>. The V6 pyrosequencing reads were compared to a database of V6 region sequences excised from the SILVA reference database of full-length rDNA sequences of known taxonomy. The taxonomy of each sequence was assigned the consensus of the nearest reference V6 sequence(s).</p>
        <p>Sequence-based clustering to create operational taxonomic units (OTUs) was based on the single-linkage preclustering (SLP) method introduced in Huse et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Huse3">[38]</xref>. To smooth some of the noise inherent in sequencing, a 2% single-linkage preclustering step was used to combine sequences likely to be variants from the same source amplicon. These clusters were then used as input to an average linkage clustering using MOTHUR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Schloss1">[39]</xref> based on pairwise alignments using ESPRIT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Sun1">[40]</xref>. The final clusters were created using 3, 6, and 10% clustering thresholds.</p>
        <p>Good's nonparametric coverage estimator was used to calculate the coverage obtained for the 16S rRNA V6 datasets using the formula C = 1−(<italic>n</italic>i/N)×100, where N =  total number of sequence reads analysed and <italic>n</italic>i  =  number of reads that occurred only once among the total number of reads tested <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Good1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Good2">[42]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Metagenomic and Metatranscriptomic profiling</title>
        <p>Primary analyses were performed using the Metagenome Rapid Annotation using Subsystem Technology (MG-RAST) bioinformatics server <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Meyer1">[30]</xref>. Additional manipulations of the data used custom-written programming scripts (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nebc.nerc.ac.uk/tools/scripts" xlink:type="simple">http://nebc.nerc.ac.uk/tools/scripts</ext-link>) and were processed on the Bio-Linux platform <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Field2">[43]</xref> unless otherwise indicated. For quality control the following sequences were removed from both metagenomes and metatranscriptomes (<italic>sequence-filter.pl</italic>): transcript fragments with &gt;10% non-determined base pairs (Ns); fragments &lt;75 bp in length, fragments with &gt;60% of any single base; exact duplicates (which result from aberrant dual reads during sequence analysis). The removal of artificial duplicate sequences (i.e. multiple reads which start at exactly the same position in a metagenome from a complex ecosystem, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-GomezAlvarez1">[44]</xref>) from the pyrosequenced data was rejected on the basis that the majority of metatranscriptomic duplicates may very well be natural, and as such comparative analysis between metagenomic and metatranscriptomic data could not be performed if removal was applied to one and not the other <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Niu1">[45]</xref>.</p>
        <p>All nucleic acid sequences were then compared against all three major ribosomal RNA databases (SILVA (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arb-silva.de/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.arb-silva.de/</ext-link>); RDP II (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/" xlink:type="simple">http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/</ext-link>); Greengenes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://greengenes.lbl.gov" xlink:type="simple">http://greengenes.lbl.gov</ext-link>) using the bacterial and archaeal 5S, 16S and 23S, and the eukaryotic 18S and 25S sequence annotator function of MG-RAST (e-value &lt;1×10<sup>−5</sup>; minimum length of alignment of 50 bp; minimum sequence nucleotide identity of 50%) and excluded if annotated as rRNA. All subsequent reads were considered to be valid DNA or valid putative mRNA derived sequences and were annotated against the SEED database using MG-RAST (e-value &lt;1×10<sup>−3</sup>; minimum length of alignment of 50 bp; minimum sequence nucleotide identity of 50%; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Meyer1">[30]</xref>) to produce an abundance matrix of functional genes and protein-derived predicted taxonomies across the DNA and mRNA samples. In addition all sequences were translated as previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert3">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Rusch1">[11]</xref> producing predicted open reading frames (pORFs) in all six reading frames, using the rule that a pORF had to have more than 40 amino acids. All proteins from all datasets were then clustered together using CD-hit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Li1">[46]</xref> at 95% amino acid identity over 80% of the length of the longest sequence in a cluster. Subsequently, the longest representative from each cluster was clustered at 60% amino acid identity over 80% of the length of the longest sequence to group these sequences by protein families <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert3">[e.g. 25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Rusch1">[11]</xref>. The relative abundance of each sample in a cluster was used to create an abundance matrix using the output cluster files from the CD-HIT program, the files containing the original fasta sequences and headers for each sample (<italic>abundanceMatrix-twoStep.pl)</italic>. Subsequently, all protein clusters with ≤2 representative pORFs were removed from the pORF matrix (<italic>MatrixParser.pv</italic>). To allow direct comparison all samples were randomly re-sampled (<italic>Daisychopper.pl</italic>) to the same number of pORFs or sequences across the clusters or functional/taxonomic SEED annotations, to equalize the sequencing effort. The abundance of each pORF cluster and functional/taxonomic SEED annotation was then analysed using non-parametric multivariate analyses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Clarke1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Clarke2">[48]</xref>. Firstly, all data were transformed by square root; then a separate Bray-Curtis similarity matrix was calculated for the protein clusters and SEED annotations for both the metagenomes and metatranscriptomes. The matrices were then clustered using hierarchical agglomerative clustering with group- average linkage to produce a dendrogram representing the scaled similarity between samples. Similarity profiles analysis, SIMPROF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Clarke3">[49]</xref> was used to test for multivariate structure. Nonmetric multidimensional scaling was used to ordinate similarities between samples. For the SEED annotations, similarities percentages breakdown, SIMPER <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Clarke1">[47]</xref> was used to determine which functional categories and SEED subsystems contributed most to differences between groups of samples (grouped by day/night and season). Good's coverage estimates (see above) were also calculated for metagenomic and metatranscriptomic pORFs as for 16S rRNA V6 sequences, where <italic>n</italic>i is the number of singleton pORFs.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <p>The bacterial community at the L4 site in the Western English Channel is seasonally structured, cycling through Winter, Summer, Autumn and Spring communities, and diversity shows a relationship with day-length <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert2">[14]</xref>. Here, we address whether metagenomic and metatranscriptomic profiles follow a similar pattern, extend our study of L4 to include time points taken at night and include Archaea in our analysis for the first time. Overall this study generated 5,720,488 sequences as summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t002"><bold>Tables 2</bold></xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t003"><bold>3</bold></xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t004"><bold>4</bold></xref><bold> and </bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t005"><bold>5</bold></xref>.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0015545-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
          <title>Comparison of bacterial 16S rRNA V6 fragment datasets from day and night samples in January, April and August.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0015545-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <italic>Bacteria 16S tags</italic>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">January</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">April</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">August 27th</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">August 28th</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19:30</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">04:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Original Sequences</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,945</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,294</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,064</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,970</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,956</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,914</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,413</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9,782</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57,338</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clustered Sequences</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,534</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,070</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,219</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,211</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9,534</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,759</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,913</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,133</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49,373</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Resampled sequencing effort (4070)</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OTUs (4070)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">331</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">558</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">177</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">199</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">189</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">174</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">192</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">189</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">999<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of singletons (4070) (%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">138 (42)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">307 (55)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74 (42)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86 (43)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76 (40)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (39)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87 (45)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83 (44)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">523<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref> (52)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good's Coverage (4070)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96.61</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.46</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.18</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97.89</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.13</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.35</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97.86</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97.96</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.39</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label/>
            <p>De-noising was performed using the SLP technique (Huse et al., 2010).</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt102">
            <label/>
            <p>*Total number of OTUs when combining all datasets together: therefore, OTUs from combined dataset, not a sum of OTUs from individual datasets. Coverage  =  (1−(number of singletons/number of resampled sequences)) x 100.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0015545-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
          <title>Comparison of archaeal 16S rRNA V6 fragment datasets from day and night samples in January and August.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0015545-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <italic>Archaea 16S rDNA</italic>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">January</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">April</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">August 27th</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">August 28th</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19:30</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">04:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Original Sequences</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57,030</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25,075</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17,822</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27,882</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">127,809</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sequences following de-noising</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54,058</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23,900</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16,771</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26,317</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121,046</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Resampled sequencing effort (16,771)</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OTUs (16,771)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of singletons (16,771) (%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (54)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (47)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (41)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (52)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref> (58)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good's Coverage (16,771)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.85</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.80</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.95</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.92</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.90</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Resampled sequencing effort (4070)</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OTUs (4070)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of singletons (4070) (%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (29)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (43)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (14)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (38)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref> (49)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good's Coverage (4070)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.83</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.51</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.95</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.88</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.81</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt103">
            <label/>
            <p>De-noising was performed using the SLP technique (Huse et al., 2010).</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt104">
            <label/>
            <p>*Total number of OTUs when combining all datasets together: therefore, OTUs from combined dataset, not a sum of OTUs from individual datasets. Coverage  =  (1−(number of singletons/number of resampled sequences))×100. Nr – not recorded.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0015545-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
          <title>Comparison of metagenomic datasets from day and night samples in January, April and August.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0015545-t004-4" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t004" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <italic>Metagenomes</italic>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">January</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">April</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">August 27th</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">August 28th</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19:30</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">04:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. Original DNA Sequences</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">616,793</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">784,823</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">637,801</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">493,003</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">620,759</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">524,953</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500,117</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">326,475</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,504,724</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Predicted ORFs (&gt;40aa pORFs)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">862,695</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,287,412</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,003,799</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">745,305</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">986,269</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">846,209</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">779,951</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">491,330</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,002,970</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF clusters (95%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">615,374</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,123,829</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">779,342</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">588,387</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">881,113</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">703,712</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">675,210</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">444,729</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,380,725<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">**</xref> (7,002,970 seqs)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF singletons (95%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">546,463</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,031,865</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">682,586</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">526,233</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">805,284</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">634,042</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">608,785</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">410,616</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,658,405<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">**</xref> (4,658,405 seqs)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF ‘families’ (60%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">423,674</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,031,904</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">678,547</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">528,213</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">801,760</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">637,542</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">620,403</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">419,461</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,418,324<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">**</xref> (5,380,725 seqs)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF singletons (60%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">352,938</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">962,073</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">609,351</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">486,712</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">740,032</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">589,839</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">577,027</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">398,202</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,822,888<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">**</xref> (3,822,888 seqs)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Resampled pORFs (66529)</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF clusters (95%) (66529)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56337</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64446</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61187</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59904</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65601</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63032</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64729</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65075</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">488903<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">**</xref> (532232 seqs)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF singletons (95%) (66529)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52891</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63378</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58691</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57779</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64818</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61068</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63359</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63945</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">468,449</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good's Coverage (66529)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.50</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.74</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.78</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.15</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.57</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.21</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.76</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.88</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.18</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. DNA seqs with functional annotation</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122,936</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">291,953</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">258,658</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">164,249</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">283,761</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">196,369</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">196,972</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126,392</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,641,290</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. DNA seqs without functional annotation (%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">493,857 (80)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">492,870 (63)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">379,143 (59)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">328,754 (67)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">336,998 (54)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">328,584 (63)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">303,145 (61)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200,083 (61)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,863,434 (64)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. DNA seqs with taxonomic annotation</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">190,326</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">417,920</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">349,888</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">241,541</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">379,911</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">288,356</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">304,003</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">186,421</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,358,366</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Resampled sequencing effort (186,421)</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of archaeal sequences (186,421)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19,055</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,150</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">777</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">561</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,370</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,093</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,585</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,244</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40,835</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of bacterial sequences (186,421)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161,899</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146,911</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">182,850</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">180,674</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">182,717</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">176,825</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">180,725</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">182,332</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,394,933</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt105">
            <label/>
            <p>**Number of protein clusters found when combining all datasets together: therefore, protein clusters from combined dataset, not a sum of clusters from individual datasets. Coverage  =  (1−(number of singletons/number of resampled sequences)) x 100.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0015545-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption>
          <title>Comparison of metatranscriptomic datasets from day and night samples in January, April and August.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0015545-t005-5" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t005" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Metatranscriptomes</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">January</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">April</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">August 27th</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">August 28th</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19:30</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">04:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10:00</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. Original cDNA Sequences</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139,880</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130,826</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">124,925</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147,492</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139,375</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">193,254</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154,865</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,030,617</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of sequences following filtering<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">***</xref></td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94,024</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">106,864</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84,916</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">109,577</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87,799</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">118,360</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111,568</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">713,108</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. mRNA following removal of rRNA</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61,831</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96,026</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41,378</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53,413</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33,149</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51,829</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55,006</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">392,632</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Predicted ORFs (&gt;40aa pORFs)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">143,169</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">211,374</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81,642</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">107,699</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77,985</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66,529</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">159,909</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">848,307</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF clusters (95%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98,871</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78,278</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35,648</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51,088</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28,167</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24,136</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68,080</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">350335<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref> (848,370 seqs)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF singletons (95%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82,464</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54,870</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25,925</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38,960</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19,600</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17,177</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50,246</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">262,767<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref> (262,767 seqs)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF ‘families’ (60%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84,598</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45,049</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19,131</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37,628</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,146</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,735</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41,480</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">230,505<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref> (350,335 seqs)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF singletons (60%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76,655</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30,720</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,869</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30,919</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9,857</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9,134</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32,662</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">187,083<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref> (187083 seqs)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Resampled pORFs (66529)</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF clusters (95%) (66529)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31026</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50354</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30334</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34217</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24848</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24136</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33191</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">205368<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref> (465703 seqs)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of pORF singletons (95%) (66529)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23038</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43687</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22394</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26840</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17373</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17177</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25636</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">157658</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good's Coverage (66529)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.37</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.33</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.34</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.66</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.89</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.18</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.47</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>nr</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.15</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. mRNA seqs with functional annotation</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,513</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31,990</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,845</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16,315</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,720</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,907</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,384</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101,674</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. mRNA seqs without functional annotation (%)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50,318 (81)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64,036 (67)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32,533 (79)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37,098 (69)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21,429 (65)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45,922 (89)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39,622 (72)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">290,958 (74)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. mRNA seqs with taxonomic annotation</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29,521</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30,778</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20,899</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26,398</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,456</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29,605</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38,304</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">190,961</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Resampled sequencing effort (15,456)</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of archaeal sequences (15,456)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">625</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">710</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of bacterial sequences (15,456)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,633</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,926</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,702</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,449</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,469</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,071</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,803</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92,053</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt106">
            <label/>
            <p>**Number of protein clusters found when combining all datasets together: therefore, protein clusters from combined dataset, not a sum of clusters from individual datasets.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt107">
            <label/>
            <p>***filtering out any sequence with &gt;10% Ns; &lt;75 bp; &gt;60% any single base; absolute duplicates. Coverage  =  (1−(number of singletons/number of resampled sequences)) x 100. Nr – not recorded.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Bacterial and archaeal diversity show seasonal patterns, and detectable archaeal richness is lower</title>
        <p>A total of 49,373 bacterial 16S rRNA V6 sequences were produced from eight samples, varying from 4,070 to 9,534 sequences per sample (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t002"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref>). Following random re-sampling, to equalize sample size to that of the smallest sample (4070 sequences) and enable comparison based on equal sequencing effort <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert1">[10]</xref>, and de-noising (i.e. the removal of spurious sequences based on the SLP technique), the bacterial community contained 999 distinct OTUs (please refer to methods for the level of demarcation for the OTUs). Three dominant phyla account for 97% of the total bacterial OTUs, Proteobacteria (86%), Bacteroidetes (9%) and Cyanobacteria (2%).</p>
        <p>Archaeal diversity, previously unstudied at the L4 site, was examined for a subset of samples, the two paired sets of samples taken January 28<sup>th</sup> and August 27<sup>th</sup> 2008 (i.e. four of the eight samples in this study). A total of 121,046 16S rRNA V6 sequences were generated, ranging from 16,771 to 54,058 per sample (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t003"><bold>Table 3</bold></xref>). In terms of detected OTUs, archaeal diversity was much lower than bacterial diversity. Both bacterial and archaeal diversity (richness, S) peaked in winter <bold>(</bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t002"><bold>Tables 2</bold></xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t003"><bold>3</bold></xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t004"><bold>4</bold></xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t005"><bold>5</bold></xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t006"><bold>6</bold></xref>), confirming previous findings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert2">[14]</xref>. After random-resampling of the archaeal data to adjust the size of all four samples to the smallest (16,771 sequences), the combined observed OTUs (S) for the four samples was only 111. The archaeal community was dominated by the Euryarchaeota (81%). Winter samples contained a larger number of OTUs (day + night average of 58) with the night time sample from January containing the highest observed number of OTUs (70). August showed 20 OTUs in the day-time and 27 OTUs at night. Following resampling of the archaeal dataset to the smallest bacterial dataset (4080 sequences), total archaeal diversity (richness) was only 6% that of bacterial diversity (63 versus 999 OTUs), with a maximum of 8% of the bacterial OTU richness in winter (January) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t003"><bold>Table 3</bold></xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0015545-t006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption>
            <title>Bacterial and archaeal diversity (S), species richness (d) and evenness (1-λ') for each sample.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0015545-t006-6" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.t006" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Archaea</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">S</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">d</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1-λ'</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">S</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">d</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1-λ'</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">January day</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">331</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8901</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.767</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8271</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>January night</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>558</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>67.02</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.9577</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>46</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>5.414</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.798</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">April day</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">177</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.18</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8289</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>April night</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>199</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>23.82</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.8745</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">August day 4pm</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">189</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.62</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9355</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.564</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6347</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>August night 10pm</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>174</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>20.81</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.9341</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>13</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>1.444</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.628</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>August night 4am</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>192</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>22.98</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.9265</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">August day 10am</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">189</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.62</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9247</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt108">
              <label/>
              <p>Diversity (S) is a measure of the number of unique OTUs derived from the 16S rRNA V6 pyrosequences. All datasets were randomly resampled to 4070 sequences, the size of the smallest archaeal dataset, to allow direct comparison of these bacterial and archaeal datasets. January Night has the highest evenness.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>Coverage of both bacterial and archaeal dominant taxa (defined as non-singleton OTUs) was high, but archaeal communities were better sampled. Using a uniform sample size of 4070 sequences (the smallest 16S rRNA dataset in the study), estimated coverage for bacteria ranged from a minimum of 92.5% of OTUs (night in January) to a maximum of 98.4% (10pm in August) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g001"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t002"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref>). For Archaea, all samples reached almost complete coverage (between 99.5% and 99.9% coverage) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g001"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t003"><bold>Table 3</bold></xref>). Additional sequencing of Archaeal 16S rRNA V6 fragments (when re-set to 16,771, the smallest Archaea dataset) beyond these 4070 sequences added only a few very rare taxa; for example, it did not increase coverage for the sample from August-4pm (already 99.95% coverage) while a maximum of 0.3% was added for the January-night sample (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g001"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t003"><bold>Table 3</bold></xref>). This confirms previous studies that suggested that the majority of the abundant, dominant microbes can be captured with as few as 2000 sequences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Caporaso1">[21]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0015545-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Good's estimate of coverage for bacterial and archaeal 16S rRNA V6 sequences resampled to 4,070 reads per sample (the smallest dataset), and for metagenomic and metatranscriptomic samples resampled to 66,529 (the smallest dataset).</title>
            <p>Values in <bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t002">Table 2</xref></bold>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>These results show that bacterial and archaeal diversity was highest in winter and that the majority of the abundant taxa were sampled in this study with only the very rare taxa remaining undetected. The largest numbers of singletons were found in winter (compared to spring and summer) and in night-time (compared to day-time) samples (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t002"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref><bold>–</bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t003"><bold>3</bold></xref>). The lowest estimates of coverage were for winter and night-time samples. Of course, these estimates of diversity may be biased by the coverage of the primers and amplification conditions, and key lineages could possibly remain undetected <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Engelbrektson1">[22]</xref>.</p>
        <p>We also examined the relative similarities of OTUs among time points. First, we made a direct comparison between the eight samples analysed in this study and the 12 monthly samples from L4 which were also collected in 2008, included in Gilbert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert2">[14]</xref>. Nonmetric multi dimensional scaling (NMDS) analysis of the combined 20 samples showed the strong seasonal structuring of the community at L4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g002"><bold>Fig. 2</bold></xref>). Day and night samples within the same 24 hour period were similar, although diel differences were greatest in winter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g002"><bold>Fig. 2</bold></xref>). Strikingly, intra-annual patterns were so strong that these eight new data point could be equally well be placed into any year of data collected from L4 – an example from 2003 is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g002"><bold>Fig. 2B</bold></xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0015545-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Non-parametric multidimensional scaling plot of similarities among 12 monthly sampling points from (A) 2008 and (B) 2003 (Gilbert et al., 2010) combined with the eight time points from the current study, based on square root transformed 16S rRNA V6-derived bacterial abundances and the Bray-Curtis similarity measure.</title>
            <p>Blue: samples from the current study; green: samples from the previous study. The line links adjacent samples in time from January to December. Day and night samples are shown in chronological order with day first and night second.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Further, hierarchical cluster analysis confirms that samples taken on the same date (day and night) were more similar than those taken from different seasons. For example, for Archaea, January and August daytime samples were only 52% similar, while similarities between day and night samples in winter and summer were 82% and 94%, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g003"><bold>Fig. 3B</bold></xref>). Likewise, for bacteria January and August, samples were only 36% similar but day and night samples were 60% and 70% similar, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g003"><bold>Fig. 3A</bold></xref>). Interestingly, for both Archaea and Bacteria divergence between day and night samples was greater in the winter samples compared to the summer samples (a shift from 82% to 94% for Archaea and 60% to 70% for Bacteria from January to August, respectively).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0015545-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Bacterial (A) and archaeal (B) community comparison for each time point examined using group-average clustering of data from Bray-Curtis similarity matrices.</title>
            <p>All samples were randomly-resampled to 4070 sequences; abundance data were transformed by square root. SIMPROF testing has been applied to branching structure: red lines indicate branches in which re-arrangement indicates no significant difference between communities. Note, the test cannot discriminate between pairs of samples.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Despite smaller diel changes, compared to inter-seasonal changes, these data show that dramatic shifts in community composition could occur on time scales as small as a matter of hours. For example, despite being only a day apart, bacterial communities on August 27<sup>th</sup> and 28<sup>th</sup> were only 64% similar and were significantly different according to the SIMPROF analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g003"><bold>Fig. 3A</bold></xref>). SIMPER analysis suggests that 10% of the difference is due to an 80 fold increase in the abundance of a <italic>Vibrio</italic> organism, and a 68 fold increase in an <italic>Alteromonas</italic> organism from the 27<sup>th</sup> to the 28<sup>th</sup> August. However, even following removal of these organisms the communities are still significantly different, suggesting that the differences are not due to a bloom of one or two organisms, but rather a fundamental shift in community composition.</p>
        <p>To explore the relative roles of dominant and rare taxa further, we tested whether the seasonal differences would remain if rare taxa were removed. Removing all OTUs with an abundance of less than 100 sequences (an arbitrary cut-off selected after inspection of the data) still yielded a statistically significant difference between seasons for both Bacteria and Archaea (ANOSIM R = 1.0, <italic>p&lt;</italic>0.01). Observed differences between day and night were considerably reduced following the removal of rare taxa (e.g. the similarity between day and night bacterial communities increased for January from ∼59% to ∼83%, for April from 69% to 88%, and for August from on average 72% to 88%) (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s001">Fig. S1A</xref>&amp;B</bold>). Second, we generated dendrograms from presence/absence transformation of the data to up-weight the role of the rarer taxa in the analysis. This led to a considerable decrease in similarity between all time points for both Bacteria and Archaea (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s001">Fig. S1C</xref>&amp;D</bold>). In Archaea it also led to a near-complete breakdown in similarity between day and night, with January day showing greater similarity to the August (day as well as night) communities (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s001">Fig. S1D</xref></bold>).</p>
        <p>Thus, both dominant and rare taxa show significant shifts between day and night samples. Three key examples support this observation. Firstly, in January, the overall most dominant organism (the most abundant OTU), which belongs to the SAR11 clade and comprised 25% of the community, showed a 40% reduction (from 1285 to 743 sequences) from day to night (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g004"><bold>Fig. 4A</bold></xref>). Secondly, in April, the night sample had a 17% reduction (1528 to 1268 sequences) in the second overall most abundant OTU, an unknown <italic>Rhodobacteraceae</italic> organism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g004"><bold>Fig. 4A</bold></xref>). Thirdly, the 3<sup>rd</sup> most abundant phylum, the Cyanobacteria, had a 15 fold day-to-night increase in January (17 to 258 sequences) and a 59 fold increase (6 to 350 sequences) in April (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g004"><bold>Fig. 4B</bold></xref>), perhaps as a result of nocturnal cell division due to the well-known circadian rhythm of most marine Cyanobacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Sweeney1">[e.g. 23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Binder1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Yang1">[20]</xref>. It is also possible that these differences result from the small changes in the salinity and temperature of the water body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g005">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0015545-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Percentage relative abundance of bacterial 16S rDNA V6 tags annotated to (A) all OTUs with an abundance of greater than 200 sequences and (B) all phyla with &gt;10 sequences (sum of all 8 datasets) following removal of the <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> and <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic>.</title>
            <p>All analyses were performed following random resampling to 4070 16S rRNA V6 sequences per dataset.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0015545-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Relationship between salinity and temperature for the 8 sampling points, demonstrating that each month sampled represents different conditions.</title>
            <p>The outlier in August is the 4pm-27<sup>th</sup> August sample.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Functional richness in metagenomic and metatranscriptomic samples is highest in winter and at night</title>
        <p>We analyzed ∼4.5 million combined microbial metagenomic reads, comprising ∼1.9 billion base pairs (bp) with an average read length of ∼350 bp across the eight samples, ranging from 326,475 to 784,823 sequences per sample (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t004"><bold>Table 4</bold></xref>). Seven metatranscriptomic datasets were also produced (the sample taken on August 28<sup>th</sup> at 10am was lost in transit) totaling ∼1 million sequences. Following ‘clean-up’ (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>), a total of 392,632 putative mRNA-derived sequences remained, totaling 159 million bp with an average of 272 bp per sequence. The sequencing effort for the metatranscriptomic analyses varied from 33,149 to 96,026 sequences per sample (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t005"><bold>Table 5</bold></xref>).</p>
        <p>For metagenomes and metatranscriptomes we used the number of predicted protein clusters to assess and compare gene/transcript richness (diversity). All predicted open reading frames (pORFs) were identified from the metagenomic and metatranscriptomic datasets, after random resampling to 66,529 sequences (smallest metatranscriptomic pORF dataset; this is larger than the smallest mRNA sequencing effort, because one sequences can yield more than one open reading frame) and then clustered into families at 95% amino acid identity (as per <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert3">[25]</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t004"><bold>Table 4</bold></xref><bold>–</bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t005"><bold>5</bold></xref>; <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s002">Fig. S2</xref></bold>). For metatranscriptomes, there was a clear seasonal trend with the winter samples showing more pORF clusters compared to the spring and summer samples (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t005"><bold>Table 5</bold></xref>; <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s002">Fig. S2</xref>).</bold> This pattern in transcript richness was strongly correlated to the corresponding 16S rRNA V6 richness (R = 0.87 for the 7 samples analysed for both diversity and transcriptomes). The highest average (day and night) number of unique pORFs among metatranscriptomes was in winter (41,856) with lower numbers in spring (34,057) and summer (29,880). Transcript diversity was higher at night compared to daytime samples within each season (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t005"><bold>Table 5</bold></xref>; <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s002">Fig. S2</xref></bold>).</p>
        <p>In contrast, the number of average (day and night) observed metagenomic pORF clusters varied little across seasons (spring  = 64,161, summer  = 62,959 and winter  = 60,743). This 3.5% average change in the abundance of metagenomic pORFs across seasons (day/night averaging; Jan–Apr  = 5%; Apr–Aug  = 2%; Jan–Aug  = 3.5) is low in comparison to the 20% average change in metatranscriptomes (day and night averaging; Jan–Apr  = 19%; Apr–Aug  = 12%; Jan–Aug; 29%). Although the observed lack of difference among metagenomes could be real it must be seen in the context of the low coverage obtained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g001"><bold>Fig. 1</bold></xref>). Good's estimator of coverage for these datasets, resampled to the size of the smallest dataset (66,529 – Aug 27th 10pm metatranscriptome), showed that compared to high coverage of 16S rRNA V6 sequences (see above), metatranscriptomes had an average coverage of only 62% and metagenomes only 8%. As expected, during January and April, metatranscriptomic coverage was greatest during the day when diversity was lowest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g001"><bold>Fig. 1</bold></xref>). However, the metagenomic samples from August had the lowest coverage, and the metatranscriptomes from August had the highest coverage, which correlated with an increase in the abundance of bacterial cells during the summer at L4. Typically, bacterial and archaeal cell numbers were less than 500,000 cells per millilitre in winter, between 500,000–800,000 in spring, but could reach &gt;2 million during June–August <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Mary1">[26]</xref>. With a four fold increase in cellular abundance, mitigated by an increase in dominance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t006"><bold>Table 6</bold></xref>), a decrease in metagenomic coverage is expected; conversely the sustained metatranscriptomic coverage is likely to be a direct result of the increased dominance of specific taxa, and hence specific transcripts.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Metagenomic profiles reflect seasonal trends associated with the 16S rRNA V6 analysis, but metatranscriptomes are more obviously structured by day/night changes</title>
        <p>Dendrograms derived from similarities among pORF groups based on sequence similarity (60% amino acid identity over 80% length) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g006"><bold>Fig. 6A&amp;B</bold></xref>) show that metagenomic pORF profiles were very dissimilar, with similarities of &lt;2% in all instances. Despite this high dissimilarity between samples, the 8 samples grouped into clusters by season; that is day and night samples from the same sampling day showed the greatest similarity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g006"><bold>Fig. 6A</bold></xref>), agreeing with the results from the 16S rRNA V6 comparison (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g003"><bold>Fig. 3</bold></xref>). Conversely, the same analysis with the metatranscriptomic data did not reveal any clear pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g006"><bold>Fig. 6B</bold></xref>). For example, the night time pORF transcriptomic profile from January and April were more similar to each other than the corresponding day-time samples from those two months which, however, did not group together. Some seasonal grouping of samples was still evident, as the three August samples were most similar to each other. However, SimProf analysis demonstrated that the August 27<sup>th</sup> 2200 h and 28<sup>th</sup> 0400 h night-time samples were statistically different to August 27<sup>th</sup> 1600 h day time sample (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g006"><bold>Fig. 6B</bold></xref>). This shows that diel differences in metatranscriptomic profiles were of the same order of magnitude, or greater, than seasonal differences.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0015545-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>(A) metagenomic predictions of protein families (60% clustering), (B) metatranscriptomic predictions of protein families (60% clustering).</title>
            <p>All comparisons based on random resampling of metagenomic and metatranscriptomic datasets to 66,529 sequences (smallest dataset). SIMPROF testing has been applied to branching structure: red lines indicate branches in which re-arrangement indicates no significant difference between communities.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Specific types of genes, most notably photosynthetic genes, show seasonal and diel differences in abundance</title>
        <p>Plots of the relative abundances of all SEED hierarchical functional categories in seasonal and day and night samples are shown for metagenomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g007"><bold>Fig 7</bold></xref>) and metatranscriptomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g008"><bold>Fig 8</bold></xref>). Overall, as expected, metagenomes were more similar across all samples than metatranscriptomes.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0015545-g007" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The average relative abundance metagenomic reads annotated to each hierarchy I subsystem from the SEED database compared between (A) each season and day and night for (B) January, (C) April and (D) August.</title>
            <p>Each dataset was randomly re-sampled prior to analysis.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0015545-g008" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g008</object-id>
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The average relative abundance of each metatranscriptomic fragments annotated to hierarchy I subsystem from the SEED database compared between (A) each season and day and night for (B) January, (C) April and (D) August.</title>
            <p>Each dataset was randomly re-sampled prior to analysis to the smallest metatranscriptome.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g008" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Interestingly, photosynthesis genes showed changes over time that reflects greater photosynthetic potential in the winter, and in the day-time relative to night-time. SIMPER analysis showed that shifts in photosynthesis genes contributed most to differences in community composition among seasons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g007"><bold>Fig. 7A</bold></xref>; <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s006">Table S2</xref></bold>; e.g. photosystem I, II and cytochrome B6-F <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s008">Table S4</xref></bold>). In fact photosynthetic genes were ten times more abundant in winter than in summer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g007"><bold>Fig. 7A</bold></xref>). As the metagenomes were produced from DNA isolated from organisms smaller than 1.6 µm, the observed changes probably reflect changes among picophytoplankton, so this corroborates a previous observation that winter conditions promote the development of pico- and micro-phytoplankton over macro-phytoplankton when compared to summer conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Rees1">[27]</xref>. Photosynthetic genes were also considerably more abundant at night in January and April (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g007"><bold>Fig. 7B&amp;C</bold></xref>). Interestingly, gene fragments annotated to proteorhodopsin had a stable abundance throughout the year, approximately 0.07% of the annotated functional profile from each sample (data not shown), demonstrating no seasonal or diel fluctuation. The metatranscriptomic photosynthetic profiles followed similar patterns to the metagenomes, with genes for photosynthesis being most abundant in January compared to April, and virtually absent in August (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g008"><bold>Fig. 8A</bold></xref>). Photosynthetic transcripts were most abundant in the day in all months; also they were most abundant during the winter, compared to the spring, compared to the summer following the abundance of the genes.</p>
        <p>Other seasonal differences in metagenomic profiles were highlighted by SIMPER analysis, including considerably higher winter abundance (compared to spring or summer) of archaeal genes associated with lipid synthesis, thermosome chaperonins, RNA polymerase, small subunit ribosomal proteins, DNA replication and rRNA modification (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s008">Table S4</xref></bold>). Archaea constituted a greater proportion of the genetic pool in winter (January) compared with April and August (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t006"><bold>Table 6</bold></xref>). Archaea have been previously found to be more abundant and diverse during the winter in Arctic communities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-AlonsoSez1">[28]</xref>. Diel differences were apparent among genes involved in respiratory metabolism, which were more abundant at night (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g007"><bold>Fig. 7B</bold></xref>). In contrast to those observed changes, there was little difference in the metagenomic profile between day and night in April (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g007"><bold>Fig. 7C</bold></xref>) and August (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g007"><bold>Fig. 7D</bold></xref>), suggesting a very stable functional potential. SIMPER analysis (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s009">Tables S5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s009">S5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s011">S7</xref></bold>) suggested that during August genes involved in virulence contributed ∼11% to the differences between day and night (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s007">Table S3</xref></bold>), and the most significant contributors within this group of virulence related genes were proteins involved in iron uptake and metabolism, as well as cadmium, zinc and cobalt resistance (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s011">Table S7</xref></bold>).</p>
        <p>Other seasonal differences in the metatranscriptomic seasonal profiles included a greater relative abundance of transcripts related to membrane transport, especially amino-acid transport, in summer when nutrients and DOM are least abundant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g008"><bold>Fig. 8A</bold></xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t001"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>; <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s003">Fig S3</xref></bold>). SIMPER analysis suggested that these differences contributed 13% of the dissimilarity between January and August samples (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s012">Table S8</xref></bold>). The diel metatranscriptional profiles for January demonstrated considerable difference in functions (in addition to photosynthesis) between day and night; for example, transcripts relating to nitrogen cycling were found mostly during the day and were primarily associated with ammonification (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g008"><bold>Fig. 8B</bold></xref>). Cell wall and capsule, and cell division and cycle were upregulated at night, suggesting a nocturnal increase in cell division, potentially associated with the Cyanobacteria. SIMPER analysis also indicated that the daytime upregulation of RNA and protein metabolism and the night time upregulation of virulence transcripts accounted for ∼34% of the dissimilarity between day and night (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s013">Table S9</xref></bold>). Similarly, April samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g008"><bold>Fig 8C</bold></xref>) showed a considerable upregulation in RNA metabolism during the day, primarily resulting from an increase in group I intron and RNA polymerase transcripts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g008"><bold>Fig 8C</bold></xref>). SIMPER analysis indicates that 30% of the dissimilarity was contributed by changes in RNA and protein metabolism and cellular regulation and signaling (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s013">Table S9</xref></bold>); interestingly, protein metabolism was driven by a night-time upregulation in universal GTPases suggesting a rapid shift in ribosomal activity at night. In August, transcripts with homology to membrane transport (as discussed above) were upregulated during the day, while transcripts associated with motility and chemotaxis, and the synthesis of cofactors, vitamins, prosthetic groups and pigments were considerably upregulated at night, suggesting that nocturnal motility and cellular activity (nucleotide and amino acid synthesis) were also upregulated; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g008"><bold>Fig 8D</bold></xref>). Membrane transport, RNA and carbohydrate metabolism (primarily driven by catabolism of ribose and deoxyribose sugars) contributed ∼39% to these differences (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s013">Table S9</xref></bold>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>The majority of differences between metagenomic and metatranscriptomic samples are due to orphaned genes and transcripts</title>
        <p>As in most metagenomic and metatranscriptomic projects involving diverse communities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-FriasLopez1">[e.g. 29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Gilbert3">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Poretsky1">[17]</xref>, only a small fraction of the predicted proteins identified in this study could be assigned an annotation using SEED subsystems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Meyer1">[30]</xref>. SEED subsystems are largely expected to best cover house-keeping genes and the best studied gene families <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0015545-Overbeek1">[31]</xref>. For this study, coverage of pORFs by SEED annotation ranged from 20–46% of each metagenomic dataset and 11–35% of the metatranscriptomic datasets (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t001"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>). There was no overall relationship between the observed coverage of each sample and the ability to annotate functions for each sequence (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s004">Fig. S4</xref></bold>). However, the percentage of annotated transcripts was highest in the night compared to day samples from January and April (although this was not observed in August), which inversely correlated with a reduction in metatranscriptomic coverage (R = −0.79, p&lt;0.05; <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0015545.s004">Fig. S4</xref></bold>).</p>
        <p>To further explore potential proteins of unknown function and their contributions to the functioning of these communities, we compared dendrograms generated from all predicted ORFs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g006"><bold>Fig. 6</bold></xref>) to only those that could be annotated against the SEED database (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g009"><bold>Fig. 9</bold></xref>) for both metagenomes and metatranscriptomes. It is obvious that the inclusion of unidentified predicted proteins caused a significant increase in the differences observed between samples. Strikingly, metagenomic sample similarity increased from an average of only ∼1% when comparing all predicted proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g006"><bold>Fig. 6A</bold></xref>) to &gt;90% when comparing only sequences that can be annotated to a SEED subsystem (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g009"><bold>Fig 9A</bold></xref>). For the metatranscriptomes, similarity still increased from an average of 17% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g006"><bold>Fig. 6B</bold></xref>) to ≥40% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0015545-g009"><bold>Fig 9B</bold></xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0015545-g009" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g009</object-id>
          <label>Figure 9</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Group-average clustering dendrograms comparing (A) metagenomic sequences annotated against SEED subsystems; (B) metatranscriptomic sequences annotated against SEED subsystems.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.g009" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In this study we tested the hypothesis that metagenomes and metatranscriptomes would track the overall diversity of 16S rRNA based community profiles and that they would show similar seasonal patterns. We found evidence to support this and interestingly, it is sets of unknown gene families that best distinguish among different samples through time. Detectable diversity is higher in winter, and at night within 24 hour periods, and this is potentially of particular relevance as there was more diversity in winter when nights are longer. Also, Lagrangian sampling demonstrates that even in complex communities with high diversity the robust temporal patterns of the marine microbial community observed in previous studies are still evident. Functional characterization using greater coverage in future studies should better elucidate these patterns. Using the Good's coverage estimates, we suggest that 20–30 time more sequencing effort than applied in this study (∼15 million sequences) is needed per metagenome, and 3–4 times more effort (1–1.5 million sequences) is needed per metatranscriptome, to provide equivalent coverage to the 16S rRNA V6 analysis.</p>
        <p>This study demonstrates the potential of multi-omics to elucidate the diversity and functional potential of ecosystems. It also provides a powerful base for developing further hypotheses from which to launch future research. In the near future we will be increasing the resolution across time and space (e.g. inclusion of the E1 sampling location at 25 km off the coast – <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.westernchannelobservatory.com" xlink:type="simple">www.westernchannelobservatory.com</ext-link>), the sequencing depth of these studies, and the range of ‘omic’ technologies applied (e.g. meta-metabolomics), to help parameterise future metabolic models of this ecosystem.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Dendrograms derived from16S rRNA V6 bacterial (A) and archaeal (B) community samples using group-average clustering of data and the Bray-Curtis similarity measure based on OTUs with &gt;100 sequences.</bold> Dendrograms derived from16S rRNA V6 bacterial (C) and archaeal (D) samples using group-average clustering of data using the Bray-Curtis similarity measure based on a presence-absence transformation of abundance data All samples were randomly-resampled to 4070 sequences. SIMPROF testing has been applied to branching structure: red lines indicate branches in which re-arrangement indicates no significant difference between communities.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Putative transcript and gene richness as calculated from the metatranscriptomes and metagenomes.</bold> Transcripts and genes sequences were translated into putative open reading frames (pORFs with &gt;40 amino acids), all resulting fasta files were resampled to 66,529 sequences (smallest dataset – see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t002">Table 2</xref>) and then clustered at 95% amino acid identity over 80% length of fragment. The number of unique clusters is reported here.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Principal component analysis of environmental variables demonstrating the seasonal differences in variables outlined in </bold>
            <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0015545-t003">
              <bold>Table 3</bold>
            </xref>
            <bold>.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Good's coverage estimates against the percentage of metagenomic and metatranscriptomic sequences that could be annotated against a SEED subsystem (e-value &lt;0.01).</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s005" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Bacterial and Archaeal 16S rRNA V6 specific primers used for amplification of the V6 region of 16S rRNA gene.</bold> Lowercase base pairs indicate the 454-GS-FLX A (for forward primers) or B (for reverse primers) adapter. Primers originate from Huber et al. (2007)</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s006" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s006" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>SIMPER analysis of the relative impact of different functional genes in providing differences between seasons for the metagenomic samples annotated against the Hierarchy 1 SEED subsystem database.</bold> All data were randomly re-sampled prior to analysis and the abundances were transformed by square root. Jan – January; Aug – August; Av.Abund – square root of average abundance; Contrib% - individual % contribution of that metabolic function to the difference between samples; Cum.% - Cumulative % contribution of metabolic functions to difference between samples.</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s007" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s007" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>SIMPER analysis of the relative impact of different functional genes in providing differences between day and night for each season for the metagenomic samples annotated against the Hierarchy 1 SEED subsystem database.</bold> All data were randomly re-sampled prior to analysis and the abundances were transformed by square root. Jan – January; Aug – August; Av.Abund – square root of average abundance; Contrib% - individual % contribution of that metabolic function to the difference between samples; Cum.% - Cumulative % contribution of metabolic functions to difference between samples.</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s008" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s008" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>SIMPER analysis of the contribution of functional genes to dissimilarities between seasons for the metagenomic samples annotated against the Hierarchy 1 SEED subsystem database.</bold> All data were randomly re-sampled prior to analysis and the abundances were transformed by square root. Av.Abund – square root of average abundance; Contrib% - individual % contribution of that metabolic function to the dissimilarities between samples; Cum.% - Cumulative % contribution of metabolic functions to dissimilarities between samples.</p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s009" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s009" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>SIMPER analysis of the contribution of different functional genes to dissimilarities between day and night samples in January for the metagenomic samples annotated against the Hierarchy 1 SEED subsystem database.</bold> All data were randomly re-sampled prior to analysis and the abundances were transformed by square root. Av.Abund – square root of average abundance; Contrib% - individual % contribution of that metabolic function to the dissimilarities between samples; Cum.% - Cumulative % contribution of metabolic functions to dissimilarities between samples.</p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s010" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s010" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>SIMPER analysis of the contribution of different functional genes to dissimilarities between day and night samples in April for the metagenomic samples annotated against the Hierarchy 1 SEED subsystem database.</bold> All data were randomly re-sampled prior to analysis and the abundances were transformed by square root. Av.Abund – square root of average abundance; Contrib% - individual % contribution of that metabolic function to the dissimilarities between samples; Cum.% - Cumulative % contribution of metabolic functions to dissimilarities between samples.</p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s011" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s011" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S7</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>SIMPER analysis of the contribution of different functional genes to dissimilarities between day and night samples in August for the metagenomic samples annotated against the Hierarchy 1 SEED subsystem database.</bold> All data were randomly re-sampled prior to analysis and the abundances were transformed by square root. Av.Abund – square root of average abundance; Contrib% - individual % contribution of that metabolic function to the dissimilarities between samples; Cum.% - Cumulative % contribution of metabolic functions to dissimilarities between samples.</p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s012" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s012" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S8</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>SIMPER analysis of the relative impact of different functional genes in providing differences between seasons for the metatranscriptomic samples annotated against the Hierarchy 1 SEED subsystem database.</bold> All data were randomly re-sampled prior to analysis and the abundances were transformed by square root. Jan – January; Aug – August; Apr – April; Av.Abund – square root of average abundance; Contrib% - individual % contribution of that metabolic function to the difference between samples; Cum.% - Cumulative % contribution of metabolic functions to difference between samples.</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0015545.s013" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0015545.s013" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S9</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>SIMPER analysis of the relative impact of different functional genes in providing differences between day and night for each season for the metatranscriptomic samples annotated against the Hierarchy 1 SEED subsystem database.</bold> All data were randomly re-sampled prior to analysis and the abundances were transformed by square root. Jan – January; Aug – August; Av.Abund – square root of average abundance; Contrib% - individual % contribution of that metabolic function to the difference between samples; Cum.% - Cumulative % contribution of metabolic functions to difference between samples.</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors thank Neil Hall from the NERC/University of Liverpool Advanced Genomics Facility for sequencing and his sage advice, and the crew of the PML research vessel, Plymouth Quest, for their assistance with the sampling.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Woese1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woese</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>Bacterial evolution.</article-title>             <source>Microbiol. Rev</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>221</fpage>             <lpage>271</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-DeLong1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Environmental Diversity of Bacteria &amp; Archaea, Systematic Biol.</article-title>             <volume>50</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>9</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Curtis1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scannell</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Estimating prokaryotic diversity and its limits. Proc. Natl.</article-title>             <source>Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>99</volume>             <fpage>10494</fpage>             <lpage>10499</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Wellington1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wellington</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krsek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Resolving functional diversity in relation to microbial community structure in soil: exploiting genomics and stable isotope probing.</article-title>             <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>295</fpage>             <lpage>301</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Handelsman1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Handelsman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Metagenomics: application of genomics to uncultured microorganisms.</article-title>             <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>             <volume>68</volume>             <issue>4</issue>             <fpage>669</fpage>             <lpage>85</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Oremland1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oremland</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capone</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuhrman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Whither or wither geomicrobiology in the era of ‘community metagenomics’.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>572</fpage>             <lpage>578</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Delong1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delong</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Microbial community genomics in the ocean.</article-title>             <source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>459</fpage>             <lpage>69</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Delong2">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delong</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mincer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Community genomics among stratified microbial assemblages in the ocean's interior.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>311</volume>             <fpage>496</fpage>             <lpage>503</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Sogin1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sogin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huse</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Microbial diversity in the deep sea and the underexplored “rare biosphere”.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>             <volume>103</volume>             <fpage>12115</fpage>             <lpage>12120</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Gilbert1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swift</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newbold</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Seasonal succession of microbial communities in the Western English Channel using 16S rRNA-tag pyrosequencing.</article-title>             <source>Env. Microb</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <issue>12</issue>             <fpage>3132</fpage>             <lpage>3139</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Rusch1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rusch</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heidelberg</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>The Sorcerer II Global Ocean Sampling Expedition: Northwest Atlantic through Eastern Tropical Pacific.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>e77</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.0050077" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pbio.0050077</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Murray1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Seasonal and Spatial Variability of Bacterial and Archaeal Assemblages in the Coastal Waters near Anvers Island, Antarctica.</article-title>             <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>             <volume>64</volume>             <issue>7</issue>             <fpage>2585</fpage>             <lpage>2595</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Fuhrman1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuhrman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwalbach</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Annually reoccurring bacterial communities are predictable from ocean conditions.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>103</volume>             <fpage>13104</fpage>             <lpage>13109</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Gilbert2">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somerfield</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Temperton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joint</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Day-length is central to maintaining consistent seasonal diversity in marine bacterioplankton.</article-title>             <source>Available from Nature Precedings</source>             <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/10101/npre.2010.4406.1" xlink:type="simple">http://hdl.handle.net/10101/npre.2010.4406.1</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Andersson1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riemann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertilsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Pyrosequencing reveals contrasting seasonal dynamics of taxa within Baltic Sea bacterioplankton communities: Bacterioplankton dynamics in the Baltic Sea.</article-title>             <source>The ISME Journal</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>171</fpage>             <lpage>181</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Mihalcescu1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mihalcescu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsing</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leibler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Resilient circadian oscillator revealed in individual cyanobacteria.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>430</volume>             <fpage>81</fpage>             <lpage>85</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Poretsky1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poretsky</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zehr</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Comparative day/night metatranscriptomic analysis of microbial communities in the North Pacific subtropical gyre.</article-title>             <source>Environ. Microbiol</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>1358</fpage>             <lpage>75</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Vaulot1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaulot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chisholm</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Growth of Prochlorococcus, a photosynthetic prokaryote, in the equatorial pacific ocean.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>268</volume>             <fpage>1480</fpage>             <lpage>1482</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Dong1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>How a cyanobacterium tells time.</article-title>             <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>541</fpage>             <lpage>546</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Yang1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pando</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Oudenaarden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Circadian Gating of the Cell Cycle Revealed in Single Cyanobacterial Cells.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>327</volume>             <fpage>1522</fpage>             <lpage>26</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Caporaso1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauber</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg-Lyons</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozupone</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Global patterns of 16S rRNA diversity at a depth of millions of sequences per sample.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.1000080107" xlink:type="simple">www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.1000080107</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Engelbrektson1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Engelbrektson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wrighton</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zvenigorodsky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Experimental factors affecting PCR-based estimates of microbial species richness and evenness.</article-title>             <source>The ISME Journal</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <issue>5</issue>             <fpage>642</fpage>             <lpage>647</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Sweeney1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgese</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>A circadian rhythm in cell division in a prokaryote, the cyanobacterium Synechococcus WH7803.</article-title>             <source>J Phycol</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>183</fpage>             <lpage>186</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Binder1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chisholm</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Cell cycle regulation in marine Synechococcus sp. strains.</article-title>             <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>             <volume>61</volume>             <fpage>708</fpage>             <lpage>717</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Gilbert3">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Detection of Large Numbers of Novel Sequences in the Metatranscriptomes of Complex Marine Microbial Communities.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <issue>8</issue>             <fpage>e3042</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0003042" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0003042</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Mary1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mary</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biegala</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burkill</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Seasonal dynamics of bacterioplankton community structure at a coastal station in the western English Channel.</article-title>             <source>Aquatic Microbial Ecology</source>             <volume>42</volume>             <fpage>119</fpage>             <lpage>126</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Rees1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joint</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donald</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Early spring bloom phytoplankton-nutrient dynamics at the Celtic Sea Shelf Edge.</article-title>             <source>Deep-Sea Research I</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>483</fpage>             <lpage>510</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-AlonsoSez1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Sáez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasol</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balagué</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedrós-Alio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Winter-to-summer changes in the composition and single-cell activity of near-surface Arctic prokaryotes.</article-title>             <source>Environmental Microbiology</source>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1462-2920.2008.01674.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2008.01674.x</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-FriasLopez1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frias-Lopez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyson</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>From the cover: microbial community gene expression in ocean surface waters.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>105</volume>             <fpage>3805</fpage>             <lpage>10</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Meyer1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paarmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Souza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>The metagenomics RAST server - a public resource for the automatic phylogenetic and functional analysis of metagenomes.</article-title>             <source>BMC bioinformatics</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>386</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Overbeek1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Overbeek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhuri</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>The subsystems approach to genome annotation and its use in the project to annotate 1000 genomes. .</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>             <volume>7;33</volume>             <issue>17</issue>             <fpage>5691</fpage>             <lpage>702</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Booth1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thurston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Handlebar: a flexible, web-based inventory manager for handling barcoded samples.</article-title>             <source>Biotechniques</source>             <volume>42</volume>             <issue>3</issue>             <fpage>300</fpage>             <lpage>02</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Gilbert4">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooley</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulakova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Potential for Phosphonate utilisation by marine bacteria in temperate coastal waters.</article-title>             <source>Environmental microbiology</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <issue>1</issue>             <fpage>111</fpage>             <lpage>25</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Field1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrity</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selengut</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Towards a richer description of our complete collection of genomes and metagenomes: the “Minimum Information about a Genome Sequence” (MIGS) specification.</article-title>             <source>Nat Biotech</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <issue>5</issue>             <fpage>541</fpage>             <lpage>7</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Huber1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mark Welch</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huse</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Microbial population structures in the deep marine biosphere.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>97</fpage>             <lpage>100</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Huse1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sogin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mark Welch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Accuracy and quality of massively parallel DNA pyrosequencing.</article-title>             <source>Genome Biology</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>R143</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Huse2">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huse</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dethlefsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mark Welch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Relman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Exploring Microbial Diversity and Taxonomy Using SSU rRNA Hypervariable Tag Sequencing.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Genetics</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e1000255</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Huse3">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huse</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sogin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Ironing out the wrinkles in the rare biosphere through improved OTU clustering.</article-title>             <source>Env. Microbiol</source>             <comment>10.1111/j.1462-2920.2010.02193.x</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Schloss1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schloss</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westcott</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryabin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Introducing mothur: Open source, platform-independent, community-supported software for describing and comparing microbial communities.</article-title>             <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/AEM.01541-09" xlink:type="simple">10.1128/AEM.01541-09</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Sun1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>ESPRIT: estimating species richness using large collections of 16S rRNA pyrosequences.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>             <volume>37</volume>             <fpage>e76</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Good1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Good</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1953</year>             <article-title>The population frequencies of species and the estimation of the population parameters.</article-title>             <source>Biometrika</source>             <volume>40</volume>             <fpage>237</fpage>             <lpage>264</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Good2">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Good</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toulmin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1956</year>             <article-title>The number of new species and the increase of population coverage when a sample is increased.</article-title>             <source>Biometrika</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>45</fpage>             <lpage>63</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Field2">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Houten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Bioinformatics for Biologists: from Famine to Feast.</article-title>             <source>Nature Biotechnology</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>801</fpage>             <lpage>803</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-GomezAlvarez1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Alvarez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Systematic artifacts in metagenomes from complex microbial communities.</article-title>             <source>The ISME Journal</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>1314</fpage>             <lpage>1317</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Niu1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Artificial and natural duplicates in pyrosequencing reads of metagenomic data.</article-title>             <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>             <volume>2010, 11</volume>             <fpage>187</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-11-187" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2105-11-187</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Li1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godzik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Cd-hit: a fast program for clustering and comparing large sets of protein or nucleotide sequences.</article-title>             <source>Bioinformatics</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>1658</fpage>             <lpage>59</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Clarke1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Non-parametric multivariate analyses of changes in community structure.</article-title>             <source>Australian Journal of Ecology</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>117</fpage>             <lpage>143</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Clarke2">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorley</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>PRIMER v6: User Manual/Tutorial.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Plymouth, UK</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>PRIMER-E</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0015545-Clarke3">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warwick</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>The taxonomic distinctness measure of biodiversity: weighting of step lengths between hierarchical levels.</article-title>             <source>Mar Ecol Prog Ser</source>             <volume>184</volume>             <fpage>21</fpage>             <lpage>29</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>