<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-10272</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032817</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Agriculture</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Agroecology</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Forestry</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Agroecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Ecosystems</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Zoology</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Chemistry</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Organic chemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Organic acids</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Chemistry</subject>
          <subject>Ecology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Forestry Alters Foraging Efficiency and Crop Contents of Aphid-Tending Red Wood Ants, <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Foraging Efficiency and Crop Contents of Wood Ants</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Johansson</surname>
            <given-names>Therese</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gibb</surname>
            <given-names>Heloise</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
            <sup>¤</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">          <addr-line>Department of Wildlife, Fish, and Environmental Sciences, University of Agricultural Sciences, Umeå, Sweden</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gronenberg</surname>
            <given-names>Wulfila</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Arizona, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">therese.johansson@slu.se</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: HG TJ. Performed the experiments: TJ HG. Analyzed the data: TJ HG. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: TJ HG. Wrote the paper: TJ HG.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="fn1">
          <label>¤</label>
          <p>Current address: Department of Zoology, La Trobe University, Bundoora, Victoria, Australia</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e32817</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Johansson, Gibb</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>Forest management alters species behaviours, distributions and interactions. To evaluate forestry effects on ant foraging performance, we compared the quality and quantity of honeydew harvested by ants among clear-cuts, middle-aged and mature spruce-dominated stands in boreal forests in Sweden. Honeydew quality was examined using honeydew collected by squeezing the gasters of laden <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic> workers. We used fifteen laden individuals at each study site (four replicates of each stand age) and analysed honeydew chemical composition with gas chromatography-mass spectroscopy. To compare the quantity of honeydew collected by individual ants, we collected and weighed five ants moving up and five ants moving down each of ten trees at the twelve sites (totally 1200 ants). The concentration of trehalose in honeydew was lower in clear-cuts compared with middle aged and mature stands, and similar trends were shown for sucrose, raffinose and melezitose, indicating poorer honeydew quality on clear cuts. Concentrations of the amino acid serine were higher on clear-cuts. The same trend occurred for glutamine, suggesting that increased N-uptake by the trees after clear cutting is reflected in the honeydew of aphids. Ants in mature stands had larger heads and carried proportionally more honeydew and may therefore be more efficient foragers. Human alternation of habitats through clear-cutting thus affects food quality and worker condition in <italic>F. aquilonia</italic>. This is the first study to show that honeydew quality is affected by anthropogenic disturbances, likely contributing to the reduction in size and abundance of <italic>F. aquilonia</italic> workers and mounds after clear cutting.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The study was funded by The Swedish Research Council for Environment, Agricultural Sciences, and Spatial Planning (FORMAS)(grant to HG, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.formas.se/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.formas.se/</ext-link>) and by a grant to TJ from the Swedish Governmental Agency for Innovation Systems (VINNOVA). (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vinnova.se/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.vinnova.se/</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="7"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Anthropogenic disturbance, mainly through urbanization, forestry and agriculture, has severe impacts on ecosystems worldwide, affecting ecosystem processes, habitat structure and species composition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Grove1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Harrison1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Zanette1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Akasaka1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Krzyzanowski1">[5]</xref>. Effects on species interactions, such as competition, predation and parasitism are also commonly reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Kareiva1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Kruess1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Didham1">[8]</xref>. Although effects of anthropogenic disturbances on pollination are well known <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Cunningham1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Pauw1">[10]</xref>, effects on other mutualisms, such as that commonly occurring between ants and hemiptera, are poorly understood <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Gibb1">[11]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Mutualisms with hemiptera are vital for ants in most ecosystems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Blthgen1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Davidson1">[13]</xref>. The digestive systems of behaviourally and numerically dominant arboreal ants are highly specialised for the kind of carbohydrate-rich and protein-poor diets obtained from feeding on hemipteran exudates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Davidson2">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Cook1">[15]</xref>. Energetically expensive levels of activity and aggression may be promoted by the reliable sugar resource provided by the hemipterans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Way1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Room1">[17]</xref>. Because ant-hemiptera mutualisms result in significant quantities of energy being available to ants and therefore promote activities such as predation and seed dispersal that have broader effects on ecosystems, ant-hemiptera mutualisms may be considered to be keystone interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Styrsky1">[18]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Plant exudates play a key role for the carbon and nitrogen budgets of many ant species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Blthgen2">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Hlldobler1">[20]</xref>. Honeydew contains a broad range of sugars and amino acids of varying importance to ants. Previous studies suggest that honeydew quality varies between different environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Blthgen3">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Woodring1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Vlkl1">[23]</xref>. Food quality may alter caste determination and size variation within castes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Hlldobler1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Clmencet1">[24]</xref>, with poor quality food resulting in smaller adult body size <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Sorvari1">[25]</xref> and potentially altering foraging efficiency and size-dependent allocation of tasks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Evison1">[26]</xref>. Differences in food quality resulting from anthropogenic disturbances may therefore have significant effects on the success of ants.</p>
      <p>Despite the keystone role of ant-hemiptera mutualisms, few studies have examined how they are affected by anthropogenic disturbances. In Scandinavia, intensive forestry has dramatically changed the structure and species composition of the boreal forest, with significant impacts on many species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Berg1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Thor1">[28]</xref>, including the dominant red wood ants of the <italic>Formica rufa</italic> group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Punttila1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Kilpelinen1">[30]</xref>. Land management alters ant use of hemipteran resources <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Gibb1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Sorvari1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Gibb2">[31]</xref> and clear-cutting results in reduced colony survival, rates of reproduction and immunity for red wood ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Sorvari2">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Sorvari3">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Sorvari4">[34]</xref>. Approximately 85% of the dry mass of the diet of red wood ants consists of honeydew from arboreal aphids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Domisch1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Rosengren1">[36]</xref>, yet it is unclear whether forest management affects the quality of this resource or the capacity of individual workers to harvest it. In this study, we address the following questions: 1) Does the composition of sugars and amino acids in ant-collected honeydew depend on stand age? and 2) Does worker body size have consistent effects on honeydew load in stands of different ages?</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Study area and species</title>
        <p>All study sites were situated in Norway spruce (<italic>Picea abies</italic>) dominated forest in the middle boreal zone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Ahti1">[37]</xref> of northern Sweden between the latitudes of 63.6°N and 64.5°N and longitudes of 19.7°E and 20.7°E. Scots pine (<italic>Pinus sylvestris</italic>) and birches (<italic>Betula pendula</italic> and <italic>B. pubescens</italic>) were also common in the stands. The herb layer was dominated by dwarf shrubs (mostly <italic>Vaccinium myrtillis</italic>) and mosses (<italic>Pleurozium schreberi</italic>, <italic>Hylocomium splendens</italic>, <italic>Sphangnum</italic> spp.). On clear-cuts, <italic>Deschampsia flexuosa</italic> often dominated the herb layer. Soils were moist and of the sandy moraine type.</p>
        <p><italic>Formica aquilonia</italic> Yarrow is the most common <italic>F. rufa</italic> group species in the central boreal region of Fennoscandia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Collingwood1">[38]</xref>. In boreal forest, red wood ants (<italic>Formica rufa</italic> group) are ecologically dominant and form mutualisms with aphids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Gibb2">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Domisch1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Savolainen1">[39]</xref>. In the study sites, <italic>F. aquilonia</italic> tends the aphids <italic>Cinara pruinosa</italic> (Hartig) and <italic>C. piceicola</italic> (Cholodkovsky)(<italic>pers. obs.</italic> by Heloise Gibb, identified by R. Danielsson, University of Lund). Previous studies report that <italic>F. aquilonia</italic> is affected by forest succession, being more common in old forests and in larger old-forest fragments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Punttila2">[40]</xref>.</p>
        <p>We selected 12 study sites with established populations of the red wood ant <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic> for the study. Four study sites were in mature stands (tree age 80–100 years , mean basal diameter 7.4 cm, mean height 17.9 m), four in middle aged stands (30–40 years , mean basal diameter 4.9 cm, mean height 8.3 m) and four on clear cuts with 5–10 retention trees per ha (1–4 years, mean basal diameter 1.2 cm, mean height 2.1 m). Basal diameter includes all trees including saplings &gt;1 cm. Stands of different ages were geographically interspersed. Each study plot supported several nests of <italic>F. aquilonia</italic>. All necessary permits were obtained for the described field studies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Honeydew collection</title>
        <p>Honeydew was collected from fifteen laden <italic>F. aquilonia</italic> workers travelling down spruce trees after harvesting honeydew at each of the twelve study sites in July 2008. Ant crop contents have been shown to closely resemble the source, although there can be minor changes in sucrose, glucose and fructose concentrations due to enzymatic activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Blthgen1">[12]</xref>. We assumed that any changes in sugar concentrations as a result of enzymatic activity would be consistent amongst stand ages because ants were of the same species and collected at similar distances from their nests. We did not directly control the source of the honeydew since we did not have access to the tree crowns while collecting honeydew. However, aphid surveys in the same stands were used to determine the main honeydew producers in the stands.</p>
        <p>We collected honeydew from the crops of worker ants by gently squeezing their gasters, such that they regurgitated liquid into a 1.5 ml eppendorf vial. Cloudy samples representing contamination with haemolymph were discarded (as per Blüthgen et al. 2004) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Blthgen3">[21]</xref>. We weighed each vial before and after collecting the honeydew to obtain an exact weight for each sample. To prevent degradation, samples were kept on ice in the field, and then stored at −80°C on return to the laboratory.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Chemical analyses</title>
        <p>Samples weighing between 1 and 10 mg were analysed, resulting in 10–12 samples per stand and a total of 137 samples used in the analyses. The chemical composition (sugars and amino acids) of the honeydew were analysed with gas chromatography-mass spectroscopy (GC-MS) at the Metabolomics facilities at Umeå University.</p>
        <p>We used solvent-based extraction with internal standards added to the sample prior to extraction. The sample and 250–2525 µl of extraction medium so that the ratio sample/extraction medium was kept at 0,002 (chloroform/MeOH/H<sub>2</sub>O; 2∶6∶2) including stable isotope reference compounds were added to an Eppendorf tube. The extraction was performed in an MM 301 vibration mill (Retsch GmbH &amp; Co. KG, Haan, Germany). After extraction, the samples were derivatized 16 h of at room temperature. For the GC-MS analysis, one µL of the derivatized sample was injected by an Agilent 7683 autosampler into an Agilent 6890 gas chromatograph (J&amp;W Scientific). The column effluent was introduced into the ion source of a Pegasus III time-of-flight mass spectrometer, GC-TOFMS (Leco Corp., St Joseph, MI, USA). All data were processed by ChromaTOF (1.00) software (Leco Corp.). Each sample was normalized before the multivariate analysis. Normalization is essential if the samples are not identical, e.g., if there are differences in sample weight or volume, or a purification or derivatization step is involved that might result in variations in recovery. We divided the response values (area counts) by the sample weight and the intensity of one or more internal standards. For a more detailed description of the extraction, derivatization and analysis steps see Gullberg et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Gullberg1">[41]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Aphid surveys</title>
        <p>We performed surveys of aphids from spruce trees with honeydew harvesting ants present, on clear days in July 2006. We used eight sites in each age category. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Gibb2">[31]</xref>. Aphids were counted and some specimens were identified in the laboratory in 2006. In 2011 we did a more detailed determination of samples from 10 of the stands (4 clear cuts, 3 middle aged stands and 3 old stands) so that the assemblage composition of aphids could be compared among stand types. Three branches were taken from five different spruce trees or saplings in each of the sites. Branches were collected from the upper canopy, just below the tree crown, in all site types as it was not possible to safely reach the crown in old stands. We used ladders to access canopies in middle-aged stands and experienced climbers to reach the canopy of spruce trees in old stands. At all sites, branches were cut at the base and bagged. On the ground, we beat the branches and collected aphids and other insects were from the beating tray using an aspirator. The stands selected for the more detailed analysis were the same stands that were used for the honeydew sampling. However one old stand from the same area but not sampled for honeydew was added to increase the sample size for old stands.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Mass of honeydew harvested</title>
        <p>To compare the mass of honeydew collected by individual ants in different stand ages we collected ants moving up and down trees on fine days in July 2008. Ten spruce trees with <italic>F. aquilonia</italic> activity were selected at each site between 0.5 and 35 m from a central nest. We collected five ants moving up and five ants moving down each of the ten trees at four sites belonging to each of the three stand ages for a total of 1200 ants. We did not specifically select ants with laden and non-laden gasters because we aimed to compare harvesting efficiency per ant. To effectively collect ants we used an aspirator built from a battery driven vacuum cleaner. This method was selected as ants proved less likely to squirt formic acid (and therefore lose weight) when removed using an aspirator than by forceps. Ants were placed in a cold box (approximately 5°C) in the field and were later frozen for 3 days at −20°C to ensure that they were killed. Ants were weighed individually in the lab and any needles or prey items were removed before weighing.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Statistical analyses</title>
        <p>To test for differences in honeydew composition among stand ages we used PERMANOVA (permutational multivariate analysis of variance) in Primer 6 [Primer 42,43]. We performed separate analyses for total honeydew composition, carbohydrates and amino acids. Because the concentrations were not directly comparable among compounds, we standardised each compound (so that the sum of area counts for each compound from all samples was 1 (100%)) and fourth root transformed the data before analysis to both reduce the influence of the most abundant compounds and assess changes in proportional abundance of compounds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Clarke1">[44]</xref>. We used the Bray-Curtis similarity measure which is not affected by joint absences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Field1">[45]</xref>, 5000 permutations of the data, and performed the permutations of residuals under a reduced model. Pair-wise tests were used to detect which stand ages differed from each other <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Anderson1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Anderson2">[46]</xref>.</p>
        <p>We tested for differences among stand ages for identified carbohydrates and amino acids with relevance to ants using the GLM procedure in SAS 9.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-SAS1">[47]</xref>. After examining the residual plots, the data was log(x+1)-transformed before the analysis to correct for heterogeneity in variances. If significant stand age effects occurred, we examined the effect using Tukey's honestly significant difference (HSD) test.</p>
        <p>We tested for differences in abundance of the most abundant aphids and their relation (quota <italic>Cinara pruinosa/Cinara piceicola</italic>) among stand types using Kruskal-Wallis test in JMP 8 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-SAS2">[48]</xref>. When we found significant differences we performed pair wise comparisons among the stand types using Mann-Whitney U-tests.</p>
        <p>We used SMATR (Standardised Major Axis Tests &amp; Routines, Version 2) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Falster1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Warton1">[50]</xref> to test for differences in the relationship between head width and body mass between stands of different ages and ants ascending and descending trees. When slopes were not different, we also tested for differences in the elevation and position of regression lines. We used the step down Bonferroni method of Holm to correct for multiple comparisons within each analysis (ANOVAS for sugars and amino acids, U-tests for aphid abundances and SMATR-analyses) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-SAS1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Rice1">[51]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Effects of stand age on honeydew composition</title>
        <p>We found 132 compounds in our honeydew samples, including 20 carbohydrates, seven amino acids, nine organic acids, fatty acids, a mineral acid and 85 unidentified compounds. Identified compounds that were not used in our analysis are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032817.s001">Table S1</xref>. We found no significant differences in the total composition of honeydew or in the composition of amino acids among stands of different ages. For carbohydrates there was a trend of different composition in clear cuts compared with old stands (PERMANOVA, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032817-t001">Table 1</xref>). However, when the identified sugars and amino acids were analysed separately we found that the concentration of trehalose was smaller in clear-cuts than in middle-aged and mature stands. Similar, non-significant trends could be seen for sucrose, raffinose and melezitose (ANOVA, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032817-t002">Table 2</xref>). Among amino acids, clear-cuts had the highest concentration of serine, mature stands were intermediate and middle-aged stands had the lowest concentration. A similar, but non-significant trend was detected for glutamine (ANOVA, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032817-t002">Table 2</xref>). After corrections for multiple comparisons none of the trends for sugars and amino acids were significant. However, the Bonferroni correction procedure is often thought to be overly conservative <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Cabin1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Garcia1">[53]</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0032817-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032817.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Results from PERMANOVA comparing the chemical composition of honeydew harvested by <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic> among stands of different ages.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0032817-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0032817.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Source</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pseudo-F</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>All compounds</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stand age</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.259</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Site(Stand age)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.05</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Carbohydrates</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stand age</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.22</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.075</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Site(Stand age)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.80</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Amino acids</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stand age</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.55</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.227</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Site(Stand age)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.47</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>Degrees of freedom are 2 for stand age and 9 for site(stand age).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0032817-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032817.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title>F-values, and significance of mixed model ANOVA testing the effect of stand age on honeydew composition and mean ± SE for sugars and amino acids in honeydew harvested by <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic> in stands of different ages.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0032817-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0032817.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Compound</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">ANOVA</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">CC (K area counts)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">MID (K area counts)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">OLD (K area counts)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stand age</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Site(Stand age)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mean</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SE</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mean</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SE</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mean</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SE</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>SUGARS</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Erlose</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.45</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">151.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fructose</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.28</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1084.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1099.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">172.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1160.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Glucose 1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.34</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.59</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2286.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">466.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1865.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">448.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2216.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">477.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Glucose 2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">670.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">143.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">569</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">664.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">144.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lactose</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.86</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.34</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">528.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1750.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Melezitose</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">†</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.74<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">628.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">842.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">838</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nigerose</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.78</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.78<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2454.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">830.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1692.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">943.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2505.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1140.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Palatinose</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.62</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4293.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3567.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1754.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1621.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">416.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">664.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Raffinose</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">†</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1102.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">865.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2277.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1005.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1438.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">485.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sucrose</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.85<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">†</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Trehalose</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.89<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">††</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2415.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">554.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3762.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">707.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4142.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">602.9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Turanose</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.44</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">884.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">192.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">649.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">265.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">864.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">220.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>AMINO ACIDS</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Allothreonine/Threonine</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.32</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Glutamine</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.53<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">†</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.35</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">205.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Leucine</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.69</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.92<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ornithine</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.42</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phenylalanine</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.24</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Serine</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">††</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Valine</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.89<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">±</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label/>
              <p>Degrees of freedom are 2 for stand age and 9 for site(stand age).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>†</label>
              <p> = &lt;0.1 before corrections for multiple comparisons;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label>††</label>
              <p> = p&lt;0.05 before corrections for multiple comparisons;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label>*</label>
              <p><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt106">
              <label>**</label>
              <p><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt107">
              <label/>
              <p>Concentrations are presented in kilo area counts as retrieved from the GC/MS analysis. CC = clear cut, MID = middle aged stands, OLD = old stands.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>In the aphid survey, we sampled in total 2108 aphids from spruce trees with honeydew harvesting ants present. The samples were dominated by <italic>Cinara piceicola</italic> (1641 specimens) and <italic>Cinara pruinosa</italic> (164 specimens). Four specimens could not be determined and 299 were determined as <italic>Cinara</italic> sp. Both determined <italic>Cinara</italic> species were more abundant in clear cuts compared with middle aged and old stands but the pattern was only significant for <italic>C. piceicola</italic> (Kruskal-Wallis test, p = 0.018). The quota of <italic>C. pruinosa/C. piceicola</italic> did not differ among stand types (Kruskal-Wallis test, p = 0.883) but <italic>C. piceicola</italic> dominated the samples in clear cuts (quota 0.07±0.04, mean±SE) and <italic>C. pruinosa</italic> in old stands (quota 5.33±5.33, mean±SE), middle aged stands were intermediate (quota 0.88±0.82, mean±SE).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Effects of body size and stand age on forager mass</title>
        <p>Ants descending trees were laden and thus heavier than ants ascending trees for all stand ages. The slope of the regression of body mass on head width was significantly lower for ants ascending than ants descending trees for stands of all ages (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032817-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032817-g001">Figure 1</xref>). This suggests that ants with larger heads carry more honeydew relative to their mass and may therefore be more efficient. For both ascending and descending ants, there were no differences in slope between stand ages.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0032817-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032817.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Relationship between body mass and head width for ants ascending and descending trees in stands of different ages.</title>
            <p>Line equations are: descending ants: clear-cut: y = −0.015+0.015x, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.65; middle-aged: y = −0.015+0.015x, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.64; mature: y = −0.017+0.015x, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.57; ascending ants: clear-cut: y = −0.012+0.012x, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.73; middle-aged: y = −0.011+0.012x, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.71; and mature: y = −0.012+0.012x, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.80.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0032817.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0032817-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032817.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
            <title>Test-statistic and significance from the SMATR analysis comparing the slopes of lines for the relationship between head width and body mass for <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic> workers ascending and descending trees.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0032817-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0032817.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Clear-cut</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Middle-aged</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mature</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stand age</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Foragers</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Descending</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ascending</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Descending</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ascending</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Descending</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clear-cut</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ascending</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Middle-aged</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Descending</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ascending</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mature</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Descending</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ascending</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt108">
              <label>*</label>
              <p><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05 after Bonferroni stepwise corrections for multiple comparisons.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>We also tested for differences in the elevation of lines with equal slopes, i.e., within the groups of ascending and descending ants. For ascending ants, line elevation differed significantly between stands of different ages (Wald statistic<sub>(2)</sub> = 24.0, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001), with elevation being highest in mature stands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032817-g001">Figure 1</xref>). This suggests that ants in mature stands are heavier relative to head width than those in other stand ages. Line position for ascending ants was not affected significantly by stand age (Wald statistic<sub>(2)</sub> = 4.4, <italic>p</italic> = 0.110).</p>
        <p>For descending ants, line elevation differed significantly between stands of different ages (Wald statistic<sub>(2)</sub> = 10.1, <italic>p</italic> = 0.006) and was significantly lower in clear-cuts than in other stand ages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032817-g001">Figure 1</xref>), while line position did not differ between stands of different ages (Wald statistic<sub>(2)</sub> = 4.0, <italic>p</italic> = 0.134). This suggests that ants on clear-cuts may harvest slightly less honeydew in proportion to their head width.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Honeydew composition</title>
        <p>Both sugar and amino acid concentrations tended to differ between stands of different ages, indicating that the quality of honeydew changes in response to forest management. Trends were similar for both univariate and multivariate analyses. The concentration of several sugars was lowest in clear-cuts. This trend was significant only for the disaccharide trehalose and only before corrections for multiple comparisons. Trehalose is the blood sugar of insects and typically makes up 30–35 percent of the honeydew sugar content <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Hlldobler1">[20]</xref>, but is also found in the haemolymph of ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Schilman1">[54]</xref>. The origin of the trehalose in our samples is most probably honeydew because cloudy samples representing contamination with haemolymph were not used in the analysis. The nutritional value of trehalose relative to other sugars is unclear, but lower concentrations of trehalose and other sugars in honeydew on clear-cuts may contribute to the reduced success of <italic>F. aquilonia</italic>.</p>
        <p>Raffinose, sucrose, and melezitose showed a similar trend to trehalose. Sucrose is nutritionally important for ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Warner1">[55]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Blthgen4">[56]</xref>, but the value of melezitose, which commonly makes up 50–60 percent of honeydew sugars, is unclear <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Hlldobler1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Fischer1">[57]</xref>. Mutualist aphids increase the melezitose content of honeydew when tended <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Fischer2">[58]</xref>, possibly because melezitose indicates the presence of sugar rich honeydew to ants (e.g. <italic>Lasius niger</italic> on <italic>Tanacetum vulgare</italic>, Germany) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Woodring1">[22]</xref>. Although melezitose has been reported to be of nutritional value to some ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Detrain1">[59]</xref>, other studies suggest that it is of low nutritional value to most insects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Wckers1">[60]</xref> and can even be toxic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Zoebelein1">[61]</xref>, so may be merely tolerated by ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Blthgen4">[56]</xref>. The sugar content of honeydew in combination with the presence of melezitose may thus be the critical factor in determining the extent of ant-attendance in aphids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Fischer3">[62]</xref>. If melezitose is produced in response to ant tending, lower concentrations of melezitose on clear-cuts may indicate that aphids are attended less frequently by ants than in other stand ages. Ant activity on trees on clear-cuts is low relative to mature forests, yet aphids are extremely abundant on saplings in clear-cuts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Gibb2">[31]</xref>, suggesting that aphids may indeed be tended less in these sites.</p>
        <p>In addition to sugars frequently observed in honeydew from aphids, our chemical analyses with GC-TOFMS identified several additional sugars e.g. nigerose and palatinose (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032817-t002">Table 2</xref>), but they did not differ in concentrations among stand types. As we don't know the absolute concentrations of these sugars it is hard to estimate their relative importance. Further studies with this improved technology (GC-TOFMS) including measures of absolute concentrations are needed to reveal the function and relative importance of more unusual sugars in honeydew.</p>
        <p>Concentrations of several amino acids were higher on clear-cuts than in older forests. Clear-cutting leads to increased availability of nitrogen in the soil for several years after cutting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Ring1">[63]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Piirainen1">[64]</xref> and soil scarification further speeds up this effect <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Smolander1">[65]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Smolander2">[66]</xref>. Trees on clear cuts also contain more N in the needles than trees in older stands <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Sah1">[67]</xref>, so increased N-uptake by the trees after clear cutting may explain the increased amino acid content of aphid honeydew. Of the amino acids affected, serine is a major precursor to formic acid <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Hefetz1">[68]</xref>, so may be critical in colony defence behaviours, while glutamine is a storage protein for workers and reproductive castes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Wheeler1">[69]</xref>. Ant species that commonly collect nectar or honeydew may exhibit higher preferences for sources rich in proteins or amino acids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Kay1">[70]</xref>. This may reflect nitrogen limitation in their diet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Yanoviak1">[71]</xref>, which could be a result of decreases in prey availability after clear-cutting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Atlegrim1">[72]</xref>. It is thus possible that increased nitrogen availability in honeydew on clear-cuts has positive effects on some aspects of ant biology.</p>
        <p>The aphid surveys revealed that the ant tended <italic>Cinara pruinosa</italic> and <italic>Cinara piceicola</italic> dominated as honeydew producers in all stand types so it is highly probable that the collected honeydew arise from these two species. The numbers of aphids varied both among and within stands and both species often occurred on the same tree so it was impossible to know which species was the source of the honeydew. The higher abundance of both species on clear cuts might be a result of the sampling procedure since it was not possible to reach the tree crowns in middle aged and old stands. Although <italic>Cinara piceicola</italic> dominated the samples in clear cuts and <italic>C. pruinosa</italic> in old stands with middle aged stands intermediate the statistical analyses did not reveal a difference in the quota <italic>C. pruinosa/C. piceicola</italic>, probably because the low sample size in old stands. Honeydew composition differs among aphid species but also within species e.g. depending on host plant and ant attendance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Fischer2">[58]</xref>. Because the same species of ant-attended aphids dominated in all stand ages in this study, and honeydew was collected from ants that highly probably had harvested their honeydew from aphid-colonies tended by the ants, differences in honeydew composition are likely to depend on site factors rather than differences in the source of honeydew.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Determinants of honeydew harvest by individual workers</title>
        <p>Head width-mass slopes were steeper for descending than ascending ants, indicating that large ants harvested more honeydew than small ants. Ascending ants in mature forests weighed more for their size, suggesting that they may have been in better condition than ants in younger stands. However, they did not harvest more honeydew than ants in other stand ages. Both ascending and descending ants in clear-cuts weighed less than those in middle-aged and mature forests. Consistent with our findings, Sorvari and Hakkarainen (2009) showed that <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic> worker size, body fat-content and worker-generated nest temperature all decrease in response to clear-cutting. Previous studies suggest that food availability may determine the size of ant workers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Clmencet1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Johnson1">[73]</xref> and that large workers may be superior foragers and defenders of nests <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Evison1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Rosengren2">[74]</xref>. However, differences in the mass gain of ants between stands of different ages at these study sites were small and non-significant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Gibb2">[31]</xref>, even with a large sample size, so consequences for the colony are difficult to determine.</p>
        <p>Despite suggestions that honeydew limitation is responsible for the decline of wood ants after clear-cutting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Sorvari1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Punttila1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Domisch2">[75]</xref>, results from a previous study in the same stands show that in clear-cuts, ants harvest 77% of the honeydew mass that they harvest in mature stands <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Gibb2">[31]</xref>. This is probably a result of the high abundance of seedlings with high aphid loads in clear-cuts, which may compensate for the lack of mature trees. We thus suggest that changes in honeydew composition after clear-cutting may also play an important role in the inferior worker condition on clear-cuts.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Implications for conservation</title>
        <p>This is the first study to show that honeydew quality is affected by anthropogenic disturbances. It suggests that changes in resource quality resulting from clear-cutting cascade through food chains. This may be particularly important for closely interacting species, such as those involved in mutualisms. We suggest that the reported poorer condition of <italic>F. aquilonia</italic> on clear-cuts is the result of changes in honeydew quality. Changes in food quality may thus exacerbate the changes in resource quantity and microclimate reported in previous studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Gibb2">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Domisch1">[35]</xref> and thus explain reported reductions in size and abundance of <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic> mounds following clear-cutting. Other honeydew-dependent organisms, such as microbes, may also be affected by this change in quality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Stadler1">[76]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0032817-Michelsen1">[77]</xref>. Thus, changes in honeydew quality due to forestry may have further consequences for species and ecosystem functions beyond those reported here.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0032817.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0032817.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Mean and SE for chemical compounds in honeydew harvested by <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic> in different stand ages. Concentrations are presented in kilo area counts as retrieved from the GC/MS analysis (K area counts). Data for the sugars and amino acids that were used in the statistical analyses are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032817-t002">Table 2</xref>.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Krister Lundgren for performing the chemical analyses and Thomas Moritz for help with identification of compounds. Nils Eriksson determined the aphids. Ylva Nordström assisted in the field.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Grove1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grove</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Saproxylic insect ecology and the sustainable management of forests.</article-title>             <source>Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>23</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Harrison1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruna</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Habitat fragmentation and large-scale conservation: what do we know for sure?</article-title>             <source>Ecography</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>225</fpage>             <lpage>232</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Zanette1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanette</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tremont</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Food shortage in small fragments: Evidence from an area-sensitive passerine.</article-title>             <source>Ecology</source>             <volume>81</volume>             <fpage>1654</fpage>             <lpage>1666</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Akasaka1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akasaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takamura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsuhashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Effects of land use on aquatic macrophyte diversity and water quality of ponds.</article-title>             <source>Freshwater Biology</source>             <volume>55</volume>             <fpage>909</fpage>             <lpage>922</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Krzyzanowski1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krzyzanowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almuedo</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Cumulative impacts of natural resource development on ecosystems and wildlife: an annotated bibliography for British Columbia.</article-title>             <comment>FORREX Series</comment> v + 43           </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Kareiva1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kareiva</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>Habitat fragmentation and the stability of predator prey interaction.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>326</volume>             <fpage>388</fpage>             <lpage>390</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Kruess1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruess</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tscharntke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>Habitat fragmentation, species loss, and biological control.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>264</volume>             <fpage>1581</fpage>             <lpage>1584</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Didham1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Didham</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghazoul</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stork</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Insects in fragmented forests: a functional approach.</article-title>             <source>TREE</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>255</fpage>             <lpage>260</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Cunningham1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Depressed pollination in habitat fragments causes low fruit set.</article-title>             <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source>             <volume>267</volume>             <fpage>1149</fpage>             <lpage>1152</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Pauw1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pauw</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Collapse of a pollination web in small conservation areas.</article-title>             <source>Ecology</source>             <volume>88</volume>             <fpage>1759</fpage>             <lpage>1769</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Gibb1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Does the availability of arboreal honeydew determine the prevalence of ecologically dominant ants in restored habitats?</article-title>             <source>Insectes Sociaux</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>405</fpage>             <lpage>412</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Blthgen1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blüthgen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Competition for composition: Lessons from nectar-feeding ant communities.</article-title>             <source>Ecology</source>             <volume>85</volume>             <fpage>1479</fpage>             <lpage>1485</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Davidson1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snelling</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Explaining the abundance of ants in lowland tropical rainforest canopies.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>300</volume>             <fpage>969</fpage>             <lpage>972</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Davidson2">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Resource discovery versus resource domination in ants: a functional mechanism for breaking the trade-off.</article-title>             <source>Ecological Entomology</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>484</fpage>             <lpage>490</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Cook1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Nutritional and functional biology of exudate-feeding ants.</article-title>             <source>Entomologica Experimentalis et Applicata</source>             <volume>118</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>10</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Way1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Way</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1958</year>             <article-title>The influence of other ant species on biological control of <italic>Oecophylla longinoda</italic> (Latr).</article-title>             <source>Proceedings of the Xth International Congress of Entomology</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>595</fpage>             <lpage>596</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Room1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Room</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1975</year>             <article-title>Relative distributions of ant species in cocoa plantations in Papua New Guinea.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Applied Ecology</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>47</fpage>             <lpage>61</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Styrsky1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Styrsky</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eubanks</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Ecological consequences of interactions between ants and honeydew-producing insects.</article-title>             <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B - Biological Sciences</source>             <volume>274</volume>             <fpage>151</fpage>             <lpage>164</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Blthgen2">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blüthgen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebauer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Disentangling a rainforest food web using stable isotopes: dietary diversity in a species-rich ant community.</article-title>             <source>Oecologia</source>             <volume>137</volume>             <fpage>426</fpage>             <lpage>435</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Hlldobler1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hölldobler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <source>The Ants</source>             <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Blthgen3">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blüthgen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gottsberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Sugar and amino acid composition of ant-attended nectar and honeydew sources from an Australian rainforest.</article-title>             <source>Austral Ecology</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>418</fpage>             <lpage>429</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Woodring1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodring</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiedemann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Völkl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Honeydew amino acids in relation to sugars and their role in the establishment of ant-attendance hierarchy in eight species of aphids feeding on tansy (<italic>Tanaceum vulgare</italic>).</article-title>             <source>Physiological Entomology</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>311</fpage>             <lpage>319</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Vlkl1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Völkl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodring</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Ant-aphid mutualisms: the impact of honeydew production and honeydew sugar composition on ant preferences.</article-title>             <source>Oecologia</source>             <volume>118</volume>             <fpage>483</fpage>             <lpage>491</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Clmencet1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clémencet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doums</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Habitat-related microgeographic variation of worker size and colony size in the ant <italic>Cataglyphis cursor</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Oecologia</source>             <volume>152</volume>             <fpage>211</fpage>             <lpage>218</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Sorvari1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorvari</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hakkarainen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Forest clear-cutting causes small workers in polydomous wood ant <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Annales Zoologici Fennici</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>431</fpage>             <lpage>438</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Evison1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evison</surname><given-names>SEF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnieks</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>New roles for majors in <italic>Atta</italic> leafcutter ants.</article-title>             <source>Ecological Entomology</source>             <volume>32</volume>             <fpage>451</fpage>             <lpage>454</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Berg1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>Å</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehnström</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gustavsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallingbäck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonsell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>Threatened plant, animal and fungus species in Swedish forests: Distribution and habitat associations.</article-title>             <source>Conservation Biology</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>718</fpage>             <lpage>731</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Thor1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Red-listed lichens in Sweden: habitats, threats, protection, and indicator value in boreal coniferous forest.</article-title>             <source>Biodiversity and Conservation</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>59</fpage>             <lpage>72</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Punttila1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Punttila</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haila</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pajunen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tukia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Colonization of clear-cut forests by ants in the southern Finnish taiga - a quantitative survey.</article-title>             <source>Oikos</source>             <volume>61</volume>             <fpage>250</fpage>             <lpage>262</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Kilpelinen1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilpeläinen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Punttila</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finér</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niemelä</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domisch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Distribution of ant species and mounds (<italic>Formica</italic>) in different-aged managed spruce stands in eastern Finland.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Applied Entomology</source>             <volume>132</volume>             <fpage>315</fpage>             <lpage>325</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Gibb2">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Forest succession and harvesting of hemipteran honeydew by boreal ants.</article-title>             <source>Annales Zoologici Fennici</source>             <volume>47</volume>             <fpage>99</fpage>             <lpage>110</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Sorvari2">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorvari</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hakkarainen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Wood ants are wood ants: deforestation causes population declines in the polydomous wood ant <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Ecological Entomology</source>             <volume>32</volume>             <fpage>707</fpage>             <lpage>711</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Sorvari3">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorvari</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hakkarainen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rantala</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Immune defense of ants is associated with changes in habitat characteristics.</article-title>             <source>Environmental Entomology</source>             <volume>37</volume>             <fpage>51</fpage>             <lpage>56</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Sorvari4">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorvari</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hakkarainen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Deforestation reduces nest mound size and decreases the production of sexual offspring in the wood ant <italic>Formica aquilonia</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Annales Zoologici Fennici</source>             <volume>42</volume>             <fpage>259</fpage>             <lpage>267</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Domisch1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Domisch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finér</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuvonen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niemelä</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Risch</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Foraging activity and dietary spectrum of wood ants (<italic>Formica rufa</italic> group) and their role in nutrient fluxes in boreal forests.</article-title>             <source>Ecological Entomology</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>369</fpage>             <lpage>377</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Rosengren1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosengren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundström</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>The interaction between red wood ants, Cinara aphids, and pines. A ghost of mutualism past?</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huxley</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Ant-Plant interactions</source>             <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>80</fpage>             <lpage>91</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Ahti1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahti</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hämet-Ahti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jalas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1968</year>             <article-title>Vegetation zones and their sections in northwestern Europe.</article-title>             <source>Annales Botanici Fennici</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>169</fpage>             <lpage>211</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Collingwood1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collingwood</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1979</year>             <source>The Formicidae (Hymenoptera) of Fennoscandia and Denmark</source>             <publisher-loc>Klampenborg, Denmark</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Scandinavian Science Press Ltd</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Savolainen1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vepsäläinen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wuorenrinne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Ant assemblages in the taiga biome: testing the role of territorial wood ants.</article-title>             <source>Oecologia</source>             <volume>81</volume>             <fpage>481</fpage>             <lpage>486</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Punttila2">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Punttila</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Succession, forest fragmentation, and the distribution of wood ants.</article-title>             <source>Oikos</source>             <volume>75</volume>             <fpage>291</fpage>             <lpage>298</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Gullberg1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gullberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordström</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sjöström</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Design of experiments: an efficient strategy to identify factors influencing extraction and derivatization of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> samples in metabolomic studies with gas chromatography/mass spectrometry.</article-title>             <source>Analytical Biochemistry</source>             <volume>331</volume>             <fpage>283</fpage>             <lpage>295</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Ltd1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ltd</surname><given-names>P-E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <source>Primer 6.2.1</source>             <publisher-loc>Plymouth, UK</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>PRIMER-E Ltd</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Anderson1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <source>NPMANOVA: a FORTRAN computer program for non-parametric multivariate analysis of variance (for any two-factor ANOVA design) using permutation tests</source>             <publisher-loc>New Zealand</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Department of Statistics, University of Auckland</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Clarke1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Non-parametric multivariate analyses of changes in community structure.</article-title>             <source>Australian Journal of Ecology</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>117</fpage>             <lpage>143</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Field1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warwick</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1982</year>             <article-title>A practical strategy for analysing multispecies distribution patterns.</article-title>             <source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>37</fpage>             <lpage>52</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Anderson2">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorley</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <source>PERMANOVA+ for PRIMER: Guide to Software and Statistical Methods</source>             <publisher-loc>Plymouth, UK</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>PRIMER-E</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-SAS1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">SAS Institute I</collab>             <year>2003</year>             <source>SAS. 9.1 ed</source>             <publisher-loc>Cary, NC</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>SAS Institute, Inc</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-SAS2">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">SAS Institute I</collab>             <year>2008</year>             <source>JMP 8</source>             <publisher-loc>Cary, NC</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>SAS Institute, Inc</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Falster1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Falster</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warton</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>SMATR: Standardised major axis tests and routines, Version 2 SMATR website.</article-title>             <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bio.mq.edu.au/ecology/SMATR" xlink:type="simple">http://www.bio.mq.edu.au/ecology/SMATR</ext-link>. Accessed 2009 Jun 12</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Warton1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warton</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falster</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westoby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Bivariate line-fitting methods for allometry.</article-title>             <source>Biological Reviews</source>             <volume>81</volume>             <fpage>259</fpage>             <lpage>291</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Rice1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Analyzing tables of statistical tests.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>223</fpage>             <lpage>225</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Cabin1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabin</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>To Bonferroni or not to Bonferroni: when and how are the questions.</article-title>             <source>Bulletin of the Ecological Society of America</source>             <volume>81</volume>             <fpage>246</fpage>             <lpage>248</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Garcia1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Escaping the Bonferroni iron claw in ecological field studies.</article-title>             <source>Oikos</source>             <volume>105</volume>             <fpage>657</fpage>             <lpage>663</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Schilman1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schilman</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roces</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Haemolymph sugar levels in a nectar-feeding ant: dependence on metabolic expenditure and carbohydrate deprivation.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Comparative Physiology B</source>             <volume>178</volume>             <fpage>157</fpage>             <lpage>165</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Warner1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffrahn</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Feeding preferences of white-footed ants, <italic>Technomyrmex albipes</italic> (Hymenoptera: Formicidae), to selected liquids.</article-title>             <source>Sociobiology</source>             <volume>44</volume>             <fpage>403</fpage>             <lpage>412</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Blthgen4">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blüthgen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Preferences for sugars and amino acids and their conditionality in a diverse nectar-feeding ant community.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source>             <volume>73</volume>             <fpage>155</fpage>             <lpage>166</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Fischer1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Völkl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schopf</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Age-specific patterns in honeydew production and honeydew composition in the aphid <italic>Metopeurum fuscoviridae</italic>: implications for ant-attendance.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Insect Physiology</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>319</fpage>             <lpage>326</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Fischer2">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shingleton</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Host plant and ants influence the honeydew sugar composition of aphids.</article-title>             <source>Functional Ecology</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <issue>4</issue>             <fpage>544</fpage>             <lpage>550</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Detrain1">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Detrain</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verheggen</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wathelet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haubruge</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Aphid-ant mutualism: how honeydew sugars influence the behaviour of ant scouts.</article-title>             <source>Physiological Entomology</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>168</fpage>             <lpage>174</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Wckers1">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wäckers</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Gustatory response by the hymenopteran parasitoid <italic>Cotesia glomerata</italic> to a range of nectar and honeydew sugars.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>2863</fpage>             <lpage>2877</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Zoebelein1">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoebelein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1956</year>             <article-title>Der Honigtau als Nahrung der Insekten, Teil I.</article-title>             <source>Zeitschrift für Angewandte Entomologie</source>             <volume>38</volume>             <fpage>369</fpage>             <lpage>416</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Fischer3">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Völkl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Honeydew production and honeydew sugar composition of polyphagous black bean aphid, <italic>Aphis fabae</italic> (Hemiptera: Aphididae) on various host plants and implications for ant-attendance.</article-title>             <source>European Journal of Entomology</source>             <volume>102</volume>             <fpage>155</fpage>             <lpage>160</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Ring1">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Effects of previous N fertilizations on soil-water pH and N concentrations after clear-felling and soil scarification at a <italic>Pinus sylvestris</italic> site.</article-title>             <source>Scandinavian Journal of Forest Research</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>7</fpage>             <lpage>16</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Piirainen1">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piirainen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finér</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mannerkoski</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Effects of forest clear-cutting on the carbon and nitrogen fluxes through podzolic soil horizons.</article-title>             <source>Plant and Soil</source>             <volume>239</volume>             <fpage>301</fpage>             <lpage>311</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Smolander1">
        <label>65</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smolander</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heiskanen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Soil N and C transformations in two forest clear-cuts during three years after mounding and inverting.</article-title>             <source>Canadian Journal of Soil Science</source>             <volume>87</volume>             <fpage>251</fpage>             <lpage>258</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Smolander2">
        <label>66</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smolander</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paavolainen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mälkönen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>C and N transformations in forest soil after mounding for regeneration.</article-title>             <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source>             <volume>134</volume>             <fpage>17</fpage>             <lpage>28</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Sah1">
        <label>67</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sah</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilvesniemi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Effects of clear-cutting and soil preparation on natural N-15 abundance in the soil and needles of two boreal conifer tree species.</article-title>             <source>Isotopes in environmental and health studies</source>             <volume>42</volume>             <fpage>367</fpage>             <lpage>377</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Hefetz1">
        <label>68</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hefetz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1978</year>             <article-title>Biosynthesis of formic acid by the poison glands of Formicinae ants.</article-title>             <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>             <volume>543</volume>             <fpage>484</fpage>             <lpage>496</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Wheeler1">
        <label>69</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Storage proteins in ants (Hymenoptera: Formicinae).</article-title>             <source>Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology</source>             <volume>112B</volume>             <fpage>15</fpage>             <lpage>19</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Kay1">
        <label>70</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Applying optimal foraging theory to access nutrient availability ratios for ants.</article-title>             <source>Ecology</source>             <volume>83</volume>             <fpage>1935</fpage>             <lpage>1944</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Yanoviak1">
        <label>71</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yanoviak</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaspari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Community structure and the habitat templet: ants in the tropical forest canopy and litter.</article-title>             <source>Oikos</source>             <volume>89</volume>             <fpage>259</fpage>             <lpage>266</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Atlegrim1">
        <label>72</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atlegrim</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sjöberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Effects of clear-cutting and selective felling in Swedish Boreal coniferous forest: Response of invertebrate taxa eaten by birds.</article-title>             <source>Entomologica Fennica</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>79</fpage>             <lpage>90</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Johnson1">
        <label>73</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Semi-claustral colony funding in the seed-harvester ant <italic>Pogonomyrmex californicus</italic>: a comparative analysis of colony funding strategies.</article-title>             <source>Oecologia</source>             <volume>132</volume>             <fpage>60</fpage>             <lpage>67</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Rosengren2">
        <label>74</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosengren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherix</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pamilo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1985</year>             <article-title>Insular ecology of the red wood ant <italic>Formica truncorum</italic> 1. Polydomous nesting population size and foraging.</article-title>             <source>Mitteilungen der Schweizerischen Entomologischen Gesellschaft</source>             <volume>58</volume>             <fpage>147</fpage>             <lpage>176</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Domisch2">
        <label>75</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Domisch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurgensen</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Red wood ant mound densities in managed boreal forests.</article-title>             <source>Annales Zoologici Fennici</source>             <volume>42</volume>             <fpage>277</fpage>             <lpage>282</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Stadler1">
        <label>76</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Aphid honeydew and its effect on the phyllosphere microflora of <italic>Picea abies</italic> (L) Karst.</article-title>             <source>Oecologia</source>             <volume>108</volume>             <fpage>771</fpage>             <lpage>776</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032817-Michelsen1">
        <label>77</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michelsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graglia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonasson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sleep</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Differential responses of grass and a dwarf shrub to long-term changes in soil microbial biomass C N and P following factorial addition of NPK fertilizer fungicide and labile carbon to a heath.</article-title>             <source>New Phytologist</source>             <volume>143</volume>             <fpage>523</fpage>             <lpage>538</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>