<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-10843</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099884</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Parasitology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Cloning, Expression and Characterization of UDP-N-Acetylglucosamine Enolpyruvyl Transferase (MurA) from <italic>Wolbachia</italic> Endosymbiont of Human Lymphatic Filarial Parasite <italic>Brugia malayi</italic></article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Characterization of MurA from <italic>Wolbachia</italic> of <italic>Brugia malayi</italic></alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahab</surname><given-names>Mohd</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>Meenakshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>Manisha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>Kalyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Misra-Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>Shailja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR), Anusandhan Bhawan, New Delhi, India</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Division of Parasitology, CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh, India</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Electron Microscopy, CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh, India</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlow</surname><given-names>Clotilde K. S.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>New England Biolabs, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">shailja_cdri@rediffmail.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MS SMB. Performed the experiments: MS MV MP. Analyzed the data: MS MV KM SMB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SMB KM. Wrote the paper: MS SMB.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>e99884</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Shahab et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p><italic>Wolbachia,</italic> an endosymbiont of filarial nematode, is considered a promising target for treatment of lymphatic filariasis. Although functional characterization of the <italic>Wolbachia</italic> peptidoglycan assembly has not been fully explored, the <italic>Wolbachia</italic> genome provides evidence for coding all of the genes involved in lipid II biosynthesis, a part of peptidoglycan biosynthesis pathway. UDP-N-acetylglucosamine enolpyruvyl transferase (MurA) is one of the lipid II biosynthesis pathway enzymes and it has inevitably been recognized as an antibiotic target. In view of the vital role of MurA in bacterial viability and survival, MurA ortholog from <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endosymbiont of <italic>Brugia malayi</italic> (<italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA) was cloned, expressed and purified for further molecular characterization. The enzyme kinetics and inhibition studies were undertaken using fosfomycin. <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was found to be expressed in all the major life stages of <italic>B. malayi</italic> and was immunolocalized in <italic>Wolbachia</italic> within the microfilariae and female adults by the confocal microscopy. Sequence analysis suggests that the amino acids crucial for enzymatic activity are conserved. The purified <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was shown to possess the EPSP synthase (3-phosphoshikimate 1-carboxyvinyltransferase) like activity at a broad pH range with optimal activity at pH 7.5 and 37°C temperature. The apparent affinity constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>) for the substrate UDP-N-acetylglucosamine was found to be 0.03149 mM and for phosphoenolpyruvate 0.009198 mM. The relative enzymatic activity was inhibited ∼2 fold in presence of fosfomycin. Superimposition of the <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA homology model with the structural model of <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic> (<italic>Hi-</italic>MurA) suggests binding of fosfomycin at the same active site. The findings suggest <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA to be a putative antifilarial drug target for screening of novel compounds.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>The financial supports in the form of research fellowships by Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR), New Delhi, India to MS, MV and MP along with the financial assistance in the form of CSIR Network Project SPLenDID were gratefully acknowledged. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All the data related to sequences (gene and amino acids) can be found on the NCBI. The related accession no and the URL are written in the manuscript.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p><italic>Wolbachia</italic> are the maternally inherited intracellular gram negative alphaproteobacteria widely spread among arthropods and filarial nematodes exhibiting a diverse range of associations with their host. In filarial nematodes, they exhibit vertical transmission via oocytes that has promoted evolutionary adaptation and a mutualistic relationship.</p>
<p>Lymphatic filariasis (LF), the cause of long-term disability in tropical and sub-tropical countries is caused by the filarial nematodes, <italic>Wuchereria bancrofti</italic> and <italic>Brugia</italic> species. Over 120 million people are currently infected and one third of these develop major morbidity world-wide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-WHO1">[1]</xref>. Currently used antifilarial drugs interrupt transmission of infection by principally killing the larval stage called microfilariae (mf) without much effect on the adult parasites. Since the adult filarial worms can survive up to decade in the vertebrate host, repeated annual treatments are recommended for several years to bring the mf density to a very low level that will not transmit infection. <italic>Wolbachia</italic> is obligatory for most species of filarial nematodes as evidenced by the killing of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> following tetracycline and doxycycline treatment that impairs the development and fecundity of worms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Taylor1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Voronin1">[5]</xref>. However, the antibiotics require long course of treatment and are not recommended for use in the young children and pregnant women <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Ghedin1">[6]</xref>. In absence of an adulticidal drug together with the threat of drug resistance to mainstay filaricides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-James1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Wolstenholme1">[8]</xref>, identification and characterization of novel antifilarial drug targets and discovery of novel classes of compounds with different mode of action is urgently required. <italic>Wolbachia</italic> bears extremely low number of predicted genes (∼806) as compared to other bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Foster1">[9]</xref> which include several unique potential targets <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Pfarr1">[10]</xref>. Investigations on a few proteins/enzyme pathways of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> have recently been undertaken such as <italic>Wolbachia</italic> surface protein (WSP), heat shock protein 60 (HSP60), independent phosphoglycerate mutase (<italic>i</italic>PGM), pyruvate phosphate dikinase (PPDK), enzymes regulating heme, lipid II and lipoprotein biosynthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Shahab1">[11]</xref>, NAD-dependent DNA ligase (<italic>w</italic>Bm-LigA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Shrivastava1">[12]</xref> and transcription factor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Li1">[13]</xref>. Specific inhibitors of few <italic>Wolbachia</italic> enzymes have been investigated recently. The benzimidazoles have been shown to inhibit heme biosynthesis pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Lentz1">[14]</xref>, acyldepsipeptides inhibit Clp peptidase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Schiefer1">[15]</xref> and heteroaryl compounds target rsmD-like rRNA methyltransferase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Rana1">[16]</xref>. These inhibitors also exhibited antifilarial activity reassuring <italic>Wolbachia</italic> as a promising antifilarial drug target.</p>
<p>Peptidoglycan (PG), an essential component of the cell wall provides structural integrity to bacteria against internal osmotic pressure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Vollmer1">[17]</xref>. The enzymes linked to PG synthesis remain conserved among the bacterial species. These have no mammalian counterpart and therefore present an attractive drug target. The annotated genome of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> reveals the presence of genes required for lipid ΙΙ precursors for PG biosynthesis including UDP-N-acetylglucosamine enolpyruvyl transferase (MurA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Foster1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Vollmer2">[18]</xref>. However, the role of lipid ΙΙ in <italic>Wolbachia</italic> remains unclear since other genes involved in PG synthesis such as those responsible for polymerization of glycans are absent. It is well known that MurA catalyzes the first committed step in the cell wall biosynthesis of bacteria and transfers an enolpyruvyl group from phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP) to UDP-N-acetylglucosamine (UDPAG) to form UDP-N-acetylglucosamine enolpyruvate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Bugg1">[19]</xref> which is a precursor to UDP-N-acetylmuramate, a requisite building block of bacterial cell wall (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g001">Figure 1</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Barreteau1">[20]</xref>. However, it has also been shown that inhibition of lipid II synthesis brings about a detrimental effect on <italic>Wolbachia</italic> within the insect cell lines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Vollmer2">[18]</xref>. The deletion/inactivation of MurA gene of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Brown1">[21]</xref>, <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Du1">[22]</xref>, and <italic>Staphylococcus. aureus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Blake1">[23]</xref> has been shown to cause their death and this has been investigated extensively.</p>
<fig id="pone-0099884-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>The first cytoplasmic step of the peptidoglycan biosynthesis.</title>
<p>MurA catalyses the formation of UDP-N-acetylglucosamine-enolpyruvyl from phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP) and UDP-N-acetylglucosamine (UDPAG).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>In view of high homology of the protein encoded by UDP-N-acetylglucosamine enolpyruvyl transferase gene in all the related bacteria, it is quite likely that <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA may also perform similar function in <italic>B. malayi</italic> endosymbiont. The structure prediction studies in the current study establish that the key amino acids required for MurA enzymatic activity are conserved in <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA. In addition, fosfomycin brought about an irreversible inhibition in <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA activity as also reported earlier in other bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Marquardt1">[24]</xref>. The current investigation deals with the cloning, expression, purification and characterization of <italic>B. malayi Wolbachia</italic> MurA.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Animals, Parasites, Infection</title>
<p>Rodent host <italic>Mastomys coucha</italic> (GRA ‘Giessen’ strain) were infected with <italic>B. malayi</italic> (sub-periodic strain) by subcutaneous inoculation of 100 third stage infective larvae (L3) isolated from laboratory bred mosquito vector <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> using Baermann technique <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Suzuki1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Sanger1">[26]</xref>. Jirds (<italic>Mastomys unguiculatus</italic>) were infected with 150–200 <italic>B. malayi</italic> infective larvae by the intraperitoneal route <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-McCall1">[27]</xref>. Adult parasites and microfilariae (mf) were recovered from the peritoneal cavity of jird infected 15–20 weeks earlier. Adult parasites were made free of host tissues under the dissecting microscope and mf were pelleted by passing the peritoneal wash through a 5.0-µm membrane filter in sterile phosphate buffer saline (PBS-pH 7.2). Euthanization of animals was done by injecting overdose of Intraval Sodium (100 mg/kg). Efforts were made to minimize suffering and reduce the number of animals used. All studies involving animals are reported in accordance with the ARRIVE guidelines for reporting experiments involving animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Kilkenny1">[28]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Ethics Statement</title>
<p>The animals used in the study were housed in climatically controlled pathogen free rooms at National Animal Laboratory Centre, CSIR - Central Drug Research Institute, Lucknow, India and fed with standard pellet diet with water <italic>ad libitum</italic>. This study was approved by the Animal Ethics Committee of CSIR - Central Drug Research Institute, Lucknow, India constituted under the rules and guidelines of the Committee for the Purpose of Control and Supervision of Animals (CPCSEA), Government of India (1998). The study bears approval nos. IAEC/2011/120 &amp; IAEC/2011/145.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Genomic DNA Isolation, Amplification and Cloning of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA Gene</title>
<p>Adult worms were harvested from the euthanized jirds. Worms were washed repeatedly in PBS and genomic DNA was isolated following manufacturer’s protocol (PureLink Genomic DNA mini kit-Invitrogen). The genomic DNA from adult also contains genomic DNA of <italic>Wolbachia.</italic> 1278 bp <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA gene (KEGG - <italic>w</italic>Bm0740) was amplified from the extracted genomic DNA using forward sense primer - <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<underline>GGATCC</underline>ATGCATAAAATATTAGTAAGGAGTAAC-3′</named-content> and reverse antisense primer - <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<underline>CTCGAG</underline>TCAAGGAATAGAGATATCGGCCC-3′</named-content> containing restriction sites <italic>Bam</italic>HI and <italic>Xho</italic>I (underlined), respectively. The amplification was carried out by mixing 1 µM of each primer, 200 µM of each deoxynucleoside triphosphate (dNTPs), 0.5 unit <italic>Taq</italic> DNA polymerase, 1x PCR buffer, and 1.5 µM MgCl<sub>2</sub> (all from Fermentas) in a thermocycler (Bio-Rad) under conditions at initial denaturation at 94°C/4 min, 29 cycles at 94°C/45 sec, 48°C/45 sec, 72°C/1.30 min and 1 cycle at 72°C/20 min. The amplified PCR product was electrophoresed in agarose gel and eluted by gel extraction kit (PureLink Gel Extraction kit, Invitrogen). Eluted product (∼1278 bp) was sub-cloned into pTZ57R/T (T/A) cloning vector (Fermentas) and transformed into competent <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5α cells. The transformants were screened for the presence of recombinant plasmids with the desired insert by gene specific PCR under similar conditions as mentioned above. Cloning was performed at <italic>Bam</italic>HI and <italic>Xho</italic>I site in bacterial expression vector pET28a (Novagen) and the plasmid from positive clones was sequenced to confirm the insert.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title><italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA Gene Expression in Various Stages of <italic>B. malayi</italic></title>
<p>Different life stages of <italic>B. malayi,</italic> viz. adult, mf and L3 were recovered as detailed above. RNA was extracted using the TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen) and quantified with a GeneQuant apparatus (Bio-Rad). After treatment with DNase I to remove genomic DNA contamination, 3 µg of total RNA from each life stage was used for cDNA synthesis using a first-strand cDNA synthesis kit (Sigma-Aldrich, USA). The target gene was amplified using cDNAs applying conditions as mentioned above. For negative controls, PCR was performed with total RNA in absence of reverse transcriptase, in order to rule out any possibility of DNA contamination in the total RNA samples.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Expression, Purification and Western Blot</title>
<p>The expression of recombinant <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was checked in bacterial cells by transforming the recombinant construct in <italic>E. coli</italic> - Rosetta(DE3)pLysS strain (Novagen). The transformed cells were inoculated into 5 ml Luria-Bertani medium and allowed to grow at 37°C in a shaker at 220 rpm. Cultures in logarithmic phase (OD<sub>600</sub>∼0.5–0.6) were induced for 3 h with different concentration of isopropyl-β-D-thiogalatopyranoside (IPTG) at 37°C. The over-expression of the recombinant (r) <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was analyzed by 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate - polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) after Coomassie brilliant blue R-250 (Sigma-Aldrich) staining.</p>
<p>For purification, 300 ml Luria-Bertani medium containing 100 µg/ml-chloramphenicol and 50-µg/ml kanamycin were inoculated with freshly transformed pET28a recombinant construct and grown at 37°C/220 rpm to an OD of ∼0.6. For expressing the recombinant protein in soluble form, the culture was further grown at 24°C for 20 min., induced by the addition of 0.2 mM IPTG and further grown for 22 h at 24°C/130 rpm. The recombinant <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was purified by affinity chromatography using Ni<sup>2+</sup> chelating resin which binds to (His)-6-tag fusion peptide derived from the pET28a vector. Harvested cell pellet was re-suspended in 15 ml of chilled lysis buffer (20 mM Tris-pH 7.4, 300 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 10% Glycerol, 1% Triton X-100, 0.5 mM phenyl-methanesulfonyl fluoride [PMSF], 5 mM β-mercaptoethanol) and incubated for 45 min on ice with 1mg/ml of lysozyme (Sigma-Aldrich). The suspension was disrupted by sonication (20 cycles; 10 sec pulse at 20% amplitude with 30 sec interval after each pulse) on ice, and pelleted at 12,500 rpm for 30 min. The supernatant was incubated at 4°C for 1 h with 3 ml Ni-NTA resin (Qiagen,) in a column pre-equilibrated with lysis buffer. The column was subsequently washed with lysis buffer only and then with wash buffer (20 mM Tris-pH 7.4, 300 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 150 µM PMSF) containing different concentrations of imidazole (20, 40 and 60 mM). The purified recombinant protein was eluted with wash buffer containing 300 mM imidazole. All the washing, elution and dialysis step were performed at 4°C. For purity check, 100 µl from each eluted fraction was mixed with an equal volume of 2x sample buffer (10 mg/ml Bromophenol Blue, 4.4% SDS, 0.5 M Tris-Cl, 300 mM β-mercaptoethanol) and analyzed on 10% SDS-PAGE along with un-induced sample fraction. The protein was dialyzed against Buffer A (20 mM Tris-Cl-pH 7.4, 250 mM NaCl, 50 mM imidazole) and subsequently against Buffer B (20 mM Tris-Cl-pH 7.4, 250 mM NaCl). Concentration of the eluted fractions was estimated by the Bradford method using Bovine serum albumin (BSA) as standard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Bradford1">[29]</xref>. The resolved purified recombinant protein was transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane in a mini-blot transfer assembly (Bio-Rad). The membrane was blocked in 3% skimmed milk for 2 h at room temperature (RT). After blocking, the membrane was incubated at RT with mouse anti-His antibody (Novagen, USA) at 1∶2000 dilution. The membrane was washed thrice with PBS containing 0.5% Tween 20 and then incubated with goat anti-mouse IgG-HRP conjugate (Sigma, USA) at a dilution of 1∶10,000 for 2 h at RT. The blot was developed with 3,3′-diaminobenzidine tetra hydrochloride (DAB) and H<sub>2</sub>O<italic><sub>2</sub></italic> (Sigma-Aldrich).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Raising Polyclonal Antibodies Against <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA</title>
<p>For the generation of polyclonal antibodies to <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA, 20 µg of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA recombinant protein mixed with Fruend’s complete adjuvant (FCA, Sigma, USA) in 100 µl volume was administered subcutaneously in six eight-week old BALB/c mice. Further two booster doses of same amount of protein were given with Fruend’s incomplete adjuvant (FIA, Sigma, USA) on the day 15 and 21 post first immunization. Anti-<italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA serum was collected from the blood collected on day 30 post first immunization.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Stage Specific Endogenous Presence of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA Enzyme</title>
<p>To observe the presence of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA protein in adults, L3 and mf of <italic>B. malayi,</italic> the crude extracts from each life stage were resolved on 10% SDS-PAGE prior to the Western blot. The target protein was recognized with polyclonal antibody to <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA. Crude extract were prepared by homogenization and sonication of 20 adult worms (female and male), ∼4000 L3 and ∼5000 mf in 400 µl PBS, each containing protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma, USA) followed by the centrifugation at 12,000×g for 30 min. Samples for SDS-PAGE were prepared by mixing the supernatants with an equal volume of 2x sample buffer and heated for 5 min at 100°C. The separated protein fractions from SDS-PAGE were then transferred to the nitrocellulose membrane and the remaining steps were same as appended above for His-fused <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA Western blotting except that the anti-<italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA mouse serum was used as a primary antibody (1∶5000 dilutions). The purified recombinant <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA served as a positive control.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2h">
<title>Immunolocalization of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA in <italic>B. malayi</italic> by Confocal Microscopy</title>
<p>For observing the <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA distribution in the parasites, confocal microscopy was undertaken. The adult female worm and mf were fixed overnight in 4% paraformaldehyde in M9 buffer (22 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 42 mM Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 86 mM NaCl, and 1 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>. 7H2O; pH 7.2) at 4°C and further processed, as described earlier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Haegeman1">[30]</xref>. Anti-<italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA polyclonal antibody was used as primary antibody (1∶500) while FITC (Fluorescein isothiocyanate; Sigma) conjugated IgG (1∶200) was used as the secondary antibody, both diluted in the M9 buffer with 0.5% BSA respectively. After every step washing was done four times with the M9 buffer containing 0.05% Tween-20. The worms and mf were incubated with 4′,6′- diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, 100 ngml<sup>−1</sup>; Sigma) for 5 min for the DNA staining and parasites were mounted on glass slide in 90% glycerol and 10% p-phenyenediamine (Sigma, USA) in PBS. Slides were analyzed under a Carl Zeiss LSM 510 META (Zeiss, Jena, Germany) confocal laser scanning microscope equipped with 405nm diode, Argon multiline (458, 477, 488, 514nm), 561 nm DPSS and HeNe 633 nm lasers. Plan-apochromat 63X/1.4 NA oil DIC objective and Plan-apochromat 40X/0.95 NA DIC objective along with appropriate excitation and emission filter sets were used for imaging. 488 nm and 405 nm laser lines were used for excitation of FITC and DAPI respectively. As a negative control, the same procedure was executed after treating parasites with BALB/c preimmune serum.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2i">
<title>Sequence Analysis and Phylogeny</title>
<p>BLASTP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi" xlink:type="simple">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>) search was made with the <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA as the query sequence for identifying similar domain sequences. Domain analysis was done on SMART server <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Schultz1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Letunic1">[32]</xref>. To identify the conserved regions, sequence alignments of MurA were generated with ClustalW2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Larkin1">[33]</xref>. Phylogenetic tree was constructed by neighbor-joining methods using the programs NEIGHBOR and PROTDIST of the PHYLIP package v3.6 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Felsenstein1">[34]</xref>. The programs SEQBOOT and CONSENSE from the same package were used to estimate the confidence limits of branching points from 1000 bootstrap replication. For this, twenty four homologous protein sequences of MurA were retrieved from NCBI databases using BLASTP and aligned using ClustalW software and these are; <italic>Deinococcus radiodurans</italic> (NP_294847.1), <italic>Thermotoga maritima</italic> (NP_227924.1), <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> (YP_006700754.1), <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> (WP_002367154.1), <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> (NP_391557.1), <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> (YP_008443514.1), <italic>Porphyromonas gingivalis</italic> (WP_021679280.1), <italic>Treponema pallidum</italic> (NP_218469.1), <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> (WP_010254843.1), <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> (NP_215831.1), <italic>Synechocystis sp.</italic> (NP_442129.1), <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> (WP_000346463.1), <italic>Neisseria meningitidis</italic> (WP_002245281.1), <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> (WP_000410583.1), <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (WP_001545447.1), <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic> (YP_005829704.1), <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (WP_009875898.1), <italic>Acinetobacter calcoaceticus</italic> (WP_005049013.1), <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endosymbiont of <italic>Onchocerca ochengi</italic> (YP_006555880.1), <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endosymbiont of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (NP_966909.1), <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endosymbiont strain TRS of <italic>Brugia malayi</italic> (YP_198570.1), <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endosymbiont of <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> (WP_007302175.1), <italic>Rickettsia prowazekii</italic> (NP_220950.1) and <italic>Aquifex aeolicus</italic> (NP_213879.1). Viewing and re-annotation were done on FigTree v1.4 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree" xlink:type="simple">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree</ext-link>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2j">
<title><italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA Activity Assay</title>
<p>In <italic>E. coli</italic>, MurA catalyzed the enzymatic reaction with the release of free inorganic phosphate (P<sub>i</sub>) and this method was used for the enzymatic assays. Reaction was performed in a 96 well plate at 37°C for 10 min in a final volume of 50 µl reaction mixture containing 50 mM Tris-HCl-pH 7.5, 10 mM KCl, 1 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 10% (v/v) glycerol, 0.6 mM UDPAG (Sigma), and 3 µg of pre-dialyzed <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA as described earlier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Marquardt1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Mizyed1">[35]</xref>. 1 mM PEP (Sigma) was added to initiate the reaction. The amount of P<sub>i</sub> released due to PEP cleavage was quantified by malachite green assay kit following manufacturer’s protocol (Cayman Chemical Company, USA). Absorbance was read at 620 nm and compared with the standard phosphate solutions. Standard curve was plotted using phosphate standards and regression analysis was performed to estimate the liberated P<sub>i</sub>. For controls, the reaction conditions remained same as mentioned above however <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was either inactivated by boiling or it was not added to the reaction mixture. The pH and temperature conditions for optimal enzymatic reaction were assessed at different pH (4–10) and temperature (10–80°C) ranges. For examining the effects of different ions, reactions were performed by replacing KCl with 10 mM of NaCl, NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, CaCl<sub>2</sub>, MgCl<sub>2</sub>, MnCl<sub>2</sub>, CuCl<sub>2</sub>, NiCl<sub>2</sub>, CoCl<sub>2</sub> and FeSO<sub>4.</sub></p>
</sec><sec id="s2k">
<title>Determination of Kinetic Constants</title>
<p>To determine the kinetic constants at optimum pH and temperature, the above enzymatic assay was performed in presence of various concentration of one substrate with a fixed concentration of another one. Varying concentration of UDPAG (0.0 to 6.4 mM) in presence of 1 mM PEP or varying concentration of PEP (0.0 to 6.4 mM) in presence of 5 mM UDPAG was used. Samples were analyzed at 620 nm for the P<sub>i</sub> activity over a period of 10 minutes. The average activity (nmol P<sub>i</sub>/min) was determined and eventually <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> and V<italic><sub>max</sub></italic> values were estimated by fitting the curve through non-linear regression by plotting Michaelis-Menton graph <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Johnson1">[36]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2l">
<title>Inhibition of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA Activity by Fosfomycin</title>
<p>Fosfomycin inhibits MurA by making a covalent adduct with the active residue. To determine its inhibitory effects on enzymatic activity, different concentrations (1 to 50 mM) of fosfomycin were pre-incubated with the assay mixture for 15 min and the enzymatic reactions were initiated by addition of 5 mM of PEP. Fosfomycin acts as a PEP analogue, therefore to examine the competitive profile with the PEP, another assay was performed in which the reaction was initiated with different concentrations (1–50 mM) of PEP and a fixed concentration (30 mM) of fosfomycin. The activity was analyzed for both the assays as mentioned above except for the longer incubation time of 1 h due to expected low release of inorganic phosphate. Concentrations of all the other substrates were same as in the activity assay reaction mixture.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2m">
<title>Homology Modeling</title>
<p>For examining the perseverance of the active sites and the probable interactions with fosfomycin, a homology model of the <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was generated using Phyre<sup>2</sup> server - Imperial College, London <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Kelley1">[37]</xref>, which has different component suite for efficient modeling (multi-template modeling by Poing 1.0, template detection by HHpred 1.51 and disorder prediction by Psi-pred 2.5). The generated model was further refined through ModRefiner server <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Xu1">[38]</xref>. For evaluation and validation of the model, Ramachandran Plot was generated from PROCHECK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Laskowski1">[39]</xref>. Knowledge-based energy curve for calculating z-score was done by using ProSA-web <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Sippl1">[40]</xref>. Secondary structure analysis was carried out on PDBsum server <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Laskowski2">[41]</xref>. All the visualizations were performed on PyMOL (The Pymol Molecular Graphics System, Schrödinger, LLC).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2n">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>All the measurements were performed in triplicate and repeated thrice to correct the trial errors. Data were analyzed with the help of statistical software GraphPad Prism (version 6.01).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Sequence and Phylogenetic Analysis</title>
<p>Database search revealed that MurA gene exists in nearly all the bacterial species. <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA shares high degree of similarity with MurA homologues of other <italic>Wolbachia</italic> species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g002">Figure 2</xref>). It exhibits 88.94 and 80.71% homology with MurA of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (NP_966909) and <italic>Culex molestus</italic> (CDH88571) respectively. Varying degree of similarity was observed with others bacterial species such as, 41.05% with <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (WP_023568349), 42.24% with <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> (WP_001887759), 40.57% with <italic>Haemophilius influenzae</italic> (YP_005827986), 41.23% with <italic>Bordetella pertusis</italic> (WP_014906110), 43.68% with <italic>Rickettsia rickettsii</italic> (WP_012151046), 43.06% with <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> (WP_023396463) and 35.53% with <italic>Chlamydia pecurum</italic> (YP_008583337). In addition, the residues involved in ligand interactions in MurA of <italic>E. coli</italic> (Cys115, Asp305, Lys22, Arg120, Asp369 and Leu370) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Du1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Takahata1">[42]</xref> are conserved among <italic>Wolbachia</italic> of above hosts and also in above bacterial species except <italic>C. pecurum</italic> where the residue complementary to Cys115 of <italic>E. coli</italic> is aspartate. It should be noted that MurA of <italic>C. pecurum</italic> with aspartate substitution is resistant to fosfomycin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-McCoy1">[43]</xref>. Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA via neighbor-joining method displays strong similarity with MurA of other <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endosymbionts and it formed a distinct clade as a characteristic of α-proteobacteria apart from the MurA of the other proteobacteria. Gram positive bacterial species have two copies of MurA in contrast to gram negative bacteria (including <italic>Wolbachia</italic>) which contain only one copy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Brown1">[21]</xref>. Phylogenetic analysis suggests that two genes of MurA have possibly evolved by duplication of one gene, or from an even more ancient source as suggested by BLAST homology searches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Du1">[22]</xref>. Thus the phylogram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g003">Figure 3</xref>) clearly suggests that MurA gene is evolutionary conserved and may have followed a different path during the time course of evolution. Analysis of the <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA domain architecture revealed the predicted EPSP synthase (3-phosphoshikimate 1-carboxyvinyltransferase) as the main domain (amino acid, 8 to 414).</p>
<fig id="pone-0099884-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>ClustalW analysis of the amino acid sequences of MurAs.</title>
<p>Sequences from various organisms were aligned (NCBI reference numbers are given in parenthesis). <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endosymbiont of <italic>B. malayi</italic> - wBm_MurA (YP_198570.1), <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> - wDm_MurA (NP_966909), and <italic>Culex molestus</italic> - wCm_MurA (CDH88571); <italic>E. coli</italic>_MurA (WP_023568349), <italic>Vibrio cholerae -</italic> V.chl_MurA (WP_001887759), <italic>Haemophilius influenzae</italic> - H.infl_MurA (YP_005827986), <italic>Bordetella pertusis -</italic> B.per_MurA (WP_014906110), <italic>Rickettsia rickettsii</italic> - R.rick_MurA (WP_012151046), <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae -</italic> S.pne_MurA (WP_023396463) and <italic>Chlamydia pecurum</italic> - C.pec_MurA (YP_008583337). Conserved motifs are marked and boxed, white letters with black background indicate identical amino acid positions/sequence from various organisms, red star shows the residues involved in the ligand interactions during catalysis. The alignment figure was generated using the ESPript 3.0 server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://espript.ibcp.fr/ESPript/cgi-bin/ESPript.cgi" xlink:type="simple">http://espript.ibcp.fr/ESPript/cgi-bin/ESPript.cgi</ext-link>).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0099884-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Phylogenetic tree showing divergence of MurA.</title>
<p>Tree was constructed by NJ method as implemented by the PHYLIP 3.6 package using the input sequences with 1,000 bootstrap replicates. The scale bar represents 0.05 expected amino acid replacement per site as estimated by the program PRODIST of the same package. Number at the nodes represents the age constraint to mean path lengths. Major groups of bacteria are included with the abbreviation given to gram-positive bacteria (GP), <italic>Cytophaga-Flexibacter-Bacteroids</italic> (CFB) and intracellular <italic>Wolbachia</italic> (<italic>Wolb</italic>). Graphical version of the tree was drawn on FigTree program.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title><italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was Cloned, Expressed and Purified</title>
<p>The <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA gene of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> of <italic>B. malayi</italic> was successfully amplified and cloned in T/A vector. It was further sub-cloned in bacterial expression vector pET28a which was transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> Rosetta strain. The recombinant construct was confirmed by restriction digestion with respective enzymes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g004">Figure 4A</xref>) and also sequenced and it did not show any alteration in the amplified product. The soluble form of recombinant <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was expressed with fused (His)- tag at 24°C after inducing with 0.2 mM IPTG for 22 h at 24°C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). Extraction and purification yielded 0.3 mg of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA per liter of culture. The recombinant protein was localized with anti-His antibody through Western blot at ∼51 kDa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g004">Figure 4C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0099884-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Confirmation of cloned construct, expression, purification and Western blotting of recombinant <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA.</title>
<p><bold>A:</bold> The cloned gene within the expression vector pET28a was checked by restriction-digestion. Lane 1, molecular size marker (GeneRuler 1 kb Plus DNA Ladder, Thermo Scientific); lane 1–2, Restricted plasmid (insert-1278 bp); lane 3, un-restricted construct (pET28a containing the insert). <bold>B:</bold> Coomassie-stained SDS-polyacrylamide gel of recombinant <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA over-expressed in Rosetta(DE3)pLysS <italic>E. coli</italic> strain with a His tag fusion protein. Lane 1, molecular mass markers (Puregene 4 Color Prestain protein ladder, Genetix); lane 2, uninduced <italic>E. coli</italic> lysate; lane 3; <italic>E. coli</italic> lysate after 22 h induction with 0.2 mM IPTG at 24°C; lane 4, flowthrough after passing the supernatant through an Ni-NTA column; lane 5, 10 column volumes eluted with wash buffer containing 60 mM imidazole; lane 6, purified <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA recombinant fusion protein eluted with wash buffer containing 300 mM imidazole. <bold>C:</bold> Western blot developed with diaminobenzidine using mouse anti-His monoclonal antibody as primary antibody and HRP-conjugated anti-mouse IgG (lane 2) as secondary antibody; lane 1, molecular mass markers (Puregene 4 Color Prestain protein ladder, Genetix).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title><italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA is Present in the Various Life-stages of <italic>B. malayi</italic></title>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g005">Figure 5A</xref>, the <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA gene was found to be expressed in all the major life-stages of <italic>B. malayi</italic> which can be related to the presence of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> in all these stages. The polyclonal antibodies raised against the recombinant <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA protein reacted in the blot with <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA present in the crude extracts prepared from adults, L3 and mf. A characteristic band was visualized at ∼47 kDa while the purified <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA taken as a positive control protein revealed ∼51 kDa band (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). This marginal shifting in recombinant <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA protein band could be either due to presence of His-tag, or some processing of MurA <italic>in vivo,</italic> or the presence of unintentional extra residues at N and C terminus of the recombinant protein during cloning.</p>
<fig id="pone-0099884-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Stage specific expression of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA gene and the enzyme.</title>
<p><bold>A:</bold> Expression of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA gene. The full-length DNA (1278 bp, <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA gene) was amplified from the cDNA of three life- stages of <italic>B. malayi</italic> using gene specific primers. Lane 1, molecular size markers (GeneRuler 1 kb DNA Ladder, Thermo Scientific); lane 2, infective larvae; lane 3, adults (both sexes); lane 4, microfilariae. Lane 5, 6 and 7 are controls containing PCR products from infective larvae, adults and microfilariae respectively in absence of reverse transcriptase. <bold>B:</bold> Endogenous protein (<italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA) expression. Western blot was performed with anti-<italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA antibody to confirm the presence of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA. Lane 1, molecular mass markers (Puregene 4 Color Prestain protein ladder, Genetix); lane 2, microfilariae; lane 3, infective larvae; lane 4, adult worms (both sexes); and lane 5, purified <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA protein (positive control).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Confocal Immune Localization Revealed the Endogenous Presence of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA in Adult <italic>B. malayi</italic> and mf</title>
<p>The polyclonal antibody raised against <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA in BALB/c mice reacted with <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA protein within the adult female worm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g006">Figure 6</xref>). Green fluorescence signal generated by binding of fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC) tagged secondary antibody indicated the presence of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA expressed in <italic>Wolbachia</italic> within the uteri of the adult female worm and hypodermal lateral chords. The adult treated with the pre-immune BALB/c serum did not reveal such signal. <italic>Wolbachia</italic> and <italic>B. malayi</italic> DNA showed blue staining with DAPI (4′,6′–diamidino-2-phenylindole). <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was also localized as intense green signals in the isolated mf while those incubated with the pre-immune serum did not show any fluorescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g007">Figure 7</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0099884-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Immunolocalization of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA in female <italic>B. malayi</italic> adult worm by confocal microscopy.</title>
<p><bold>A–A’’’ &amp; B–B’’’:</bold> Adult female worm was incubated with anti-<italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA polyclonal antibody followed by re-incubation with secondary FITC-IgG antibody and counterstaining with DAPI. <bold>C–C’’’:</bold> Adult female worm incubated with pre-immune serum followed by incubation with secondary FITC-IgG antibody and counterstaining with DAPI (control). A, B and C images are in Phase contrast; A’ and B’ demonstrate green fluorescence signal (dots) generated by FITC confirming the presence of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA; C’ has no green fluorescence signal in absence of specific antibody; A’’, B’’, C’’ show blue signals produced by DAPI indicating the presence of nuclear DNA; A’’’, B’’’, C’’’ are the merged images of phase contrast and the fluorescence. All the images were captured at 63X oil objective. u, uteri and c, lateral chord.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0099884-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Immunolocalization of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA in microfilariae of <italic>B. malayi</italic> by confocal microscopy.</title>
<p><bold>A–A’’’:</bold> Microfilariae were incubated with anti-<italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA polyclonal antibody followed by re-incubation with secondary FITC-IgG antibody and counterstaining with DAPI. <bold>B–B’’’:</bold> Microfilariae were incubated with pre-immune serum followed by incubation with secondary FITC-IgG antibody and counterstaining with DAPI (control). A, B images are in Phase contrast; A’ demonstrate green fluorescence signal (dots) generated by FITC confirming the presence of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA; B’ has no green fluorescence signal in absence of specific antibody; A’’, B’’ show blue signals produced by DAPI indicating the presence of nuclear DNA; A’’’, B’’’ are the merged images of phase contrast and the fluorescence. All the images were captured at 63X oil objective.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Kinetics of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA</title>
<p>The optimal pH and temperature were found to be 7.5 and 37°C respectively for enzymatic reaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g008">Figure 8A &amp; B</xref>). The reaction mixture containing <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA exhibited the release of inorganic phosphate unlike controls where the recombinant enzyme was either absent or was heat inactivated (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0099884.s001">Figure S1</xref>). The enzyme activity was inhibited in presence of manganese, copper, cobalt, ferrous and zinc ions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g008">Figure 8C</xref>). Other ions have negligible effect on the activity as compared to potassium which was found to promote activity just like sodium. Based on initial velocity and the optimal conditions, the steady state kinetics was directly calculated. The <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> values for substrates were: UDPAG, 0.03149 mM; PEP, 0.009198 mM and the V<italic><sub>max</sub></italic> value for UDPAG and PEP were calculated as 1.397 mM/min/mg and 0.5378 mM/min/mg respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g009">Figure 9A &amp; B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0099884-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>Effect of temperature, pH and ions on <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA enzymatic activity.</title>
<p><bold>A:</bold> Temperature dependent enzyme activity profile assayed at various temperatures (20–60°C). <bold>B:</bold> pH dependent enzymatic activity at various pH (4.5–10). <bold>C:</bold> Effect of different ions (10 mM) on <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA activity as compared to the control with no ions. Each Data point represents average of the three independent measurements. <italic>Error bars</italic> represent corresponding SEM.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0099884-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption>
<title>Kinetics profile of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA and inhibition of enzymatic activity by fosfomycin.</title>
<p><bold>A:</bold> The effect of UDPAG concentration on <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA activity (<italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>: 0.03149 mM). <bold>B:</bold> The effect of PEP concentration on <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA activity (<italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>: 0.009198 mM). <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> values were calculated by using the Michaelis-Menton plot. <bold>C:</bold> Relative effect of the fosfomycin on <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA activity. <bold>D:</bold> The effect of PEP concentration on the inhibitory activity of fosfomycin, A value on X-axis is without fosfomycin. Each Data point represents an average of the three independent measurements. <italic>Error bars</italic> represent corresponding SEM.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3f">
<title>Inhibitory Effect of Fosfomycin</title>
<p>Fosfomycin inactivates <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA enzyme activity in a concentration dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g009">Figure 9C</xref>). The enzymatic activity was found to be decreased by almost 2 fold at 50 mM concentration of fosfomycin at a fixed concentration of PEP. As the concentration of PEP increased, the enzymatic activity also increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g009">Figure 9D</xref>). This suggests that fosfomycin is a competitive inhibitor for <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA as its inhibitory effect can be overcome by increasing the concentration of PEP.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3g">
<title>Homology Modeling</title>
<p>The three dimensional model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g010">Figure 10C</xref>) was 100% simulated at &gt;90% confidence by using three different bacterial MurA as structure templates <italic>viz</italic>., <italic>E. coli</italic> (PDB: 1UAE) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Skarzynski1">[44]</xref>, <italic>H. influenzae</italic> (PDB: 2RL1) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Yoon1">[45]</xref> and <italic>Enterobacter cloacae</italic> (PDB: 1EJD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Eschenburg1">[46]</xref> selected by sequence similarity with <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA. The Ramachandran plot for a refined <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA homology model revealed that 91.9% residues were in the most favored region, 5.5% in the additional allowed region, 2.1% in the generously allowed region and 0.5% in the disallowed region (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0099884.s002">Figure S2A</xref>), thus making the model geometrically acceptable. The z-score of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA homology modelfitted well within the range of experimentally determined similar X-ray solved protein structures (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0099884.s002">Figure S2B</xref>). The secondary structure analysis provides details that can be used to determine their topological features alongside the existing MurA solved structures. The final model consisted of 18 helices, 6 sheets, 24 strands, 5 beta hairpins, 1 beta bulge, 4 beta alpha beta motifs, 37 helix-helix interactions, 22 beta turns and 2 gamma turns which were consistent with the known MurA structures (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0099884.s002">Figure S2C</xref>). The model also has a surface loop containing the active site Cys124 at the specific region which was predicted to interact with the fosfomycin during enzyme inactivation. An overlay of our <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA modeled complex with the MurA of <italic>H. influenzae</italic> template liganded with fosfomycin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g010">Figure 10B</xref>) reveal proper superimposition of the active site in both the structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099884-g010">Figure 10D</xref>). It is therefore suggested that the inhibitor (fosfomycin) would interact with the Cys124 of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA as in case of MurA of <italic>H. influenzae.</italic></p>
<fig id="pone-0099884-g010" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption>
<title>The homology modeling.</title>
<p><bold>A (cyan):</bold> Shows the simple unliganded structural model of MurA of <italic>H. influenzae</italic> (<italic>Hi</italic>-MurA, PDB: 2RL1). <bold>B:</bold> Technical view of the fosfomycin interactions during inhibition of the <italic>Hi</italic>-MurA. <bold>C (magenta):</bold> 3D refined homology structure model of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA. <bold>D:</bold> Superimposition of the <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA homology model with the structure model of <italic>Hi-</italic>MurA. Green stretch (Cys124) in the loop of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA model fits with a similar green stretch (Cys115) of <italic>Hi</italic>-MurA which is the active site for fosfomycin.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.g010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p><italic>Wobachia</italic> was first identified in 1924 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Hertig1">[47]</xref> however, it created enormous interest among scientific community in recent years. Up to 76% of the insect species along with other invertebrates including nematodes are reported to be infected with <italic>Wolbachia</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Hilgenboecker1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Werren1">[49]</xref>. In filarial nematodes, <italic>Wolbachia</italic> exerts control over the host viability and fecundity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Fenn1">[50]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Taylor2">[51]</xref>. Moreover, their role in the development of filarial pathology as a result of immune responses generated against the endosymbiont and/or their released products has also been established <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Bandi2">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Punkosdy1">[53]</xref>. Fully annotated genome of <italic>Wolbachi</italic>a of <italic>B. malayi</italic> and other known <italic>Wolbachia</italic> provides opportunities for delineating functional pathways involved in host-parasite interaction. Peptidoglycan (PG) biosynthesis is one of the pathways within the bacteria which are essential for both cell division and cell wall elongation processes. Till date, only two reports are available on the functional attributes of the enzymes involved in PG synthesis in <italic>Wolbachia</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Vollmer2">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Henrichfreise1">[54]</xref>. In the current investigation, characterization of one of such enzyme i.e. UDP-N-acetylglucosamine enolpyruvyl transferase of <italic>B. malayi Wolbachia</italic> (<italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA) has been undertaken which is evolutionary conserved throughout the bacterial species. The gene sequence of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was successfully cloned, over-expressed and purified. We faced initial difficulty in purifying this His-tagged recombinant enzyme in soluble form since majority of the expressed protein was present in the inclusion bodies while soluble part contained very small amount of the protein. The protein present in the soluble part did not bind to Ni-NTA beads. Several attempts were made to bring the protein in soluble fraction such as low temperature, low IPTG concentration, purification buffers and variable pH which resulted in to marginal increase in its solubility. The recombinant enzyme was functionally active and appeared as ∼51 kD protein. The gene expression and the protein immuno-blotting studies indicated the presence of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA in adult worm, microfilariae and infective larvae of <italic>B. malayi</italic>. Localization of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA by confocal microscopy using anti-<italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA antibody further demonstrated its presence in the <italic>Wolbachia</italic> within the hypodermal chord and inside the uteri of female parasite i.e. in the developing embryos and mf. All this indicates that the enzyme is abundant during various stages of development of <italic>B. malayi</italic>. <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA contains a single active EPSP synthase (pfam) domain that catalyses the chemical reaction with the release of inorganic phosphate. The optimal activity assay conditions such as pH and temperature defined the catalytic profile of the enzyme and the optimal enzymatic reaction occurred at pH 7.5. Interestingly, the cytoplasmic pH in <italic>E. coli</italic> is also maintained at pH 7.5 which may possibly reflect the activity of this enzyme at similar pH <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Padan1">[55]</xref>. <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA was active at various temperatures with optimal activity at 37°C. Several ions did not exhibit any significant effect on the enzyme activity except potassium which markedly enhanced it. The <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> value of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA for the substrate UDPAG (0.03149 mM) was comparatively lower than that of other bacterial MurAs (<italic>E. cloacae,</italic> 0.080 mM; <italic>S. pneumoniae,</italic> 0.244 mM; <italic>S. mutans,</italic> 0.12 mM and <italic>S. aureus,</italic> 0.168 mM) with the only exception being <italic>E. coli</italic> (0.015 mM) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Gautam1">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Li2">[57]</xref>. For PEP (0.009198 mM) the value was higher than that of <italic>E. coli</italic> (0.0004 mM) and <italic>E. cloacae</italic> (0.0083 mM), while lower than that of <italic>S. mutans</italic> (0.086 mM) and <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> (0.037 mM) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Gautam1">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Li2">[57]</xref>. On the basis of these <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> values, <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA appears to have lower affinity for both the substrates (UDPAG &amp; PEP) as compared to that of <italic>E. coli</italic> MurA. It is difficult to explain the inferior substrate affinity in the current investigation may be attributed to the intracellular adaptation of symbiotic <italic>Wolbachia</italic> in <italic>B. malayi</italic>. Fosfomycin, a broad spectrum antibiotic irreversibly inhibits MurA. It acts as a PEP analogue and binds to MurA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Brown1">[21]</xref> leading to bacterial lysis and death <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Kahan1">[58]</xref>. <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA enzymatic activity was demonstrated to be reduced in the presence of fosfomycin, however, PEP at increasing concentrations limits this inhibitory effect suggesting that fosfomycin competes with the PEP for its activity. Sequence and alignment analysis of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA with other bacterial MurA shows conservation of five important amino acid residues viz. Lys22, which participates in the formation of covalent adducts with PEP and fosfomycin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Samland1">[59]</xref>, Cys115 and Asp305, which are involved in the product release and the final deprotonation step <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Eschenburg2">[60]</xref>, Asp369 and Leu370 which facilitate interaction of fosfomycin with MurA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Takahata1">[42]</xref> (all a.a. residues with ref. to <italic>E. coli</italic>). In <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> and <italic>C. trachomatis,</italic> it has been reported that a single change in the active site (cysteine by aspartate) makes MurA resistant to fosfomycin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-McCoy1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-DeSmet1">[61]</xref>. Further, there is no replacement of active cysteine residue in <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA demonstrating the nature of inhibition characteristic of fosfomycin. The conservation of these residues in the sequence further encourages us to investigate the consequences of differences in the active sites within <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA structure. Thus a homology model based on three different well characterized bacterial MurA templates was developed. The <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA structure is likely to contain 2 domains connected via double stranded linker containing fosfomycin active site. Superimposition of the <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA model with that of <italic>H. influenzae</italic> demonstrated structural similarity in the fosfomycin binding site. Needless to say that residues belonging to active moieties in <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA enzyme are well conserved.</p>
<p>As inferred from the annotated genome of <italic>Wolbachia</italic>, the full machinery of the PG biosynthesis is yet to be investigated. It has been suggested that <italic>Wolbachia</italic> has to retain lipid II biosynthesis setup in order to maintain cell division process <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Henrichfreise1">[54]</xref>. Being intracellular, the fully polymerized cell wall of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> appears to be impractical and unusable <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Henrichfreise1">[54]</xref>. MurA enzyme of the lipid II metabolism pathway is considered to be a validated antibacterial drug target. Several MurA inhibitors have been evaluated <italic>in vitro</italic> against bacterial MurAs and have exhibited excellent enzyme inhibitory activities. However, none was found very useful <italic>in vivo</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Baum1">[62]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0099884-Silver1">[63]</xref>. The possible reason could have been their inability to cross the cytoplasmic bacterial membranes. In that case, drug delivery system would be an excellent method to target intracellular <italic>Wolbachia</italic>. Design and chemical synthesis of analogues of MurA inhibitors should be taken up to speed up the antifilarial drug discovery process and specific targeting of compounds to the filarial parasites within the lymphatic system.</p>
<p>To conclude the <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA enzyme does not appear to be very different from other bacterial MurA and possesses quite similar sequence statistics along with active site residues and kinetic profile. Since this enzyme is constitutively expressed within the endosymbiont in all the major life stages we investigated and <italic>Wolbachia</italic> is required for worm survival and growth, <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA may serve as a putative antifilarial drug target. The design and chemical synthesis of new molecules based on the available structure of MurA inhibitors is warranted to discover new adulticidal antifilarial agent.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0099884.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Malachite Green Assay of recombinant </bold><bold><italic>w</italic></bold><bold>Bm-MurA at 37°C.</bold> The enzymatic reaction mixture with boiled <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA (A), without <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA (B) and (C) with purified recombinant <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA. Each Data point represents average of the five independent measurements. <italic>Error bars</italic> represent corresponding SEM.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0099884.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0099884.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Quality and assessment of the </bold><bold><italic>w</italic></bold><bold>Bm-MurA homology model. A:</bold> Ramachandran plot from the PROCHECK server revealed the acceptable geometry of the <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA homology model. <bold>B:</bold> The z-score of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA homology model. The score (−10.67) generated through ProSA-web server is within the range of experimentally similar X-ray solved MurA protein structures. <bold>C:</bold> Diagrammatic representation of the secondary structural elements of <italic>w</italic>Bm-MurA.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Mr. A. K. Roy for their excellent technical assistance in the maintenance of the <italic>B. malayi</italic> infection in the laboratory. We also thank Dr. Kavita Singh, electron microscopy unit of CSIR-CDRI for help in carrying out confocal studies. This manuscript bears CSIR-CDRI Communication No. 8699.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0099884-WHO1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">WHO</collab> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Global Programme to Eliminate Lymphatic Filariasis: progress report in 2011</article-title>. <source>Weekly Epidemiological Record</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>346</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Taylor1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoerauf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title><italic>Wolbachia</italic> bacteria of filarial nematodes</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Today</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Bandi1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Genchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corona</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Venco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Effects of tetracycline on the filarial worms <italic>Brugia pahangi</italic> and <italic>Dirofilaria immitis</italic> and their bacterial endosymbionts <italic>Wolbachia</italic></article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Langworthy1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langworthy</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Renz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mackenstedt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henkle-Duhrsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Bronsvoort</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Macrofilaricidal activity of tetracycline against the filarial nematode <italic>Onchocerca ochengi</italic>: elimination of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> precedes worm death and suggests a dependent relationship</article-title>. <source>Proc Biol Sci</source> <volume>267</volume>: <fpage>1063</fpage>–<lpage>1069</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Voronin1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voronin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steven</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Autophagy regulates <italic>Wolbachia</italic> populations across diverse symbiotic associations</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>E1638</fpage>–<lpage>1646</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Ghedin1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghedin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hailemariam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DePasse</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oksov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title><italic>Brugia malayi</italic> gene expression in response to the targeting of the <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endosymbiont by tetracycline treatment</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e525</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-James1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Drug resistance mechanisms in helminths: is it survival of the fittest</article-title>? <source>Trends Parasitol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>328</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Wolstenholme1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolstenholme</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fairweather</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Samson-Himmelstjerna</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sangster</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Drug resistance in veterinary helminths</article-title>. <source>Trends Parasitol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Foster1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganatra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamal</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Makarova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Wolbachia</italic> genome of <italic>Brugia malayi</italic>: endosymbiont evolution within a human pathogenic nematode</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e121</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Pfarr1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfarr</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoerauf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The annotated genome of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> from the filarial nematode <italic>Brugia malayi</italic>: what it means for progress in antifilarial medicine</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e110</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Shahab1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Misra-Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Combating Mosquito-Borne Lymphatic Filariasis with Genomics Technologies: Enabling Novel Drug Discovery for Neglected Tropical Diseases</article-title>. <source>Curr Pharmacogenomics Person Med</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Shrivastava1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nag</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Misra-Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of NAD+-dependent DNA ligase from <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endosymbiont of lymphatic filarial parasite <italic>Brugia malayi</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e41113</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Li1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carlow</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Characterization of transcription factors that regulate the type IV secretion system and riboflavin biosynthesis in <italic>Wolbachia</italic> of <italic>Brugia malayi</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e51597</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Lentz1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lentz</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halls</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hannam</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niebel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strubing</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A selective inhibitor of heme biosynthesis in endosymbiotic bacteria elicits antifilarial activity in vitro</article-title>. <source>Chem Biol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Schiefer1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiefer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vollmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lammer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Specht</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lentz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The ClpP peptidase of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endobacteria is a novel target for drug development against filarial infections</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>1790</fpage>–<lpage>1800</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Rana1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqi</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Misra-Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of an rsmD-like rRNA methyltransferase from the <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endosymbiont of <italic>Brugia malayi</italic> and antifilarial activity of specific inhibitors of the enzyme</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>3843</fpage>–<lpage>3856</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Vollmer1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vollmer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Pedro</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Peptidoglycan structure and architecture</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Vollmer2"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vollmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schiefer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Julicher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Requirement of lipid II biosynthesis for cell division in cell wall-less <italic>Wolbachia</italic>, endobacteria of arthropods and filarial nematodes</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Microbiol</source> <volume>303</volume>: <fpage>140</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Bugg1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bugg</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Intracellular steps of bacterial cell wall peptidoglycan biosynthesis: enzymology, antibiotics, and antibiotic resistance</article-title>. <source>Nat Prod Rep</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Barreteau1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barreteau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kovac</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boniface</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gobec</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cytoplasmic steps of peptidoglycan biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Brown1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vivas</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>MurA (MurZ), the enzyme that catalyzes the first committed step in peptidoglycan biosynthesis, is essential in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>177</volume>: <fpage>4194</fpage>–<lpage>4197</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Du1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sylvester</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chalker</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Two active forms of UDP-N-acetylglucosamine enolpyruvyl transferase in gram-positive bacteria</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>182</volume>: <fpage>4146</fpage>–<lpage>4152</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Blake1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Neill</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mengin-Lecreulx</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bostock</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The nature of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> MurA and MurZ and approaches for detection of peptidoglycan biosynthesis inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Marquardt1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marquardt</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Kinetics, stoichiometry, and identification of the reactive thiolate in the inactivation of UDP-GlcNAc enolpyruvoyl transferase by the antibiotic fosfomycin</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>10646</fpage>–<lpage>10651</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Suzuki1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seregeg</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>A mass dissection technique for determining infectivity rate of filariasis vectors</article-title>. <source>Jpn J Exp Med</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Sanger1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanger</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lammler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimmig</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Filarial infections of <italic>Mastomys natalensis</italic> and their relevance for experimental chemotherapy</article-title>. <source>Acta Trop</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-McCall1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyong-Sun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Mongolian jirds (<italic>Meriones unguiculatus</italic>) infected with <italic>Brugia pahangi</italic> by the intraperitoneal route: a rich source of developing larvae, adult filariae, and microfilariae</article-title>. <source>J Parasitol</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>436</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Kilkenny1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilkenny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuthill</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Improving bioscience research reporting: the ARRIVE guidelines for reporting animal research</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1000412</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Bradford1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Haegeman1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haegeman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanholme</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vandekerckhove</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claeys</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>An endosymbiotic bacterium in a plant-parasitic nematode: member of a new <italic>Wolbachia</italic> supergroup</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1045</fpage>–<lpage>1054</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Schultz1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milpetz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ponting</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>SMART, a simple modular architecture research tool: Identification of signaling domains</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>5857</fpage>–<lpage>5864</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Letunic1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Letunic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doerks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>SMART 7: recent updates to the protein domain annotation resource</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>D302</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Larkin1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackshields</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chenna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGettigan</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2947</fpage>–<lpage>2948</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Felsenstein1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Felsenstein J (2005) PHYLIP (Phylogeny Inference Package) version 3.6. Distributed by the author. Department of Genome Sciences, University of Washington, Seattle.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Mizyed1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizyed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oddone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Byczynski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berti</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>UDP-N-acetylmuramic acid (UDP-MurNAc) is a potent inhibitor of MurA (enolpyruvyl-UDP-GlcNAc synthase)</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>4011</fpage>–<lpage>4017</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Johnson1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goody</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Original Michaelis Constant: Translation of the 1913 Michaelis-Menten Paper</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>8264</fpage>–<lpage>8269</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Kelley1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Protein structure prediction on the Web: a case study using the Phyre server</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Xu1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Improving the physical realism and structural accuracy of protein models by a two-step atomic-level energy minimization</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>2525</fpage>–<lpage>2534</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Laskowski1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laskowski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>MacArthur</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>PROCHECK: a program to check the stereochemical quality of protein structures</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Crystallography</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Sippl1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sippl</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Recognition of errors in three-dimensional structures of proteins</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Laskowski2"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laskowski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>PDBsum new things</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>D355</fpage>–<lpage>D359</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Takahata1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiraishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maebashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of fosfomycin resistance in clinical isolates of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-McCoy1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandlin</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maurelli</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>In Vitro and In Vivo Functional Activity of <italic>Chlamydia</italic> MurA, a UDP-N-Acetylglucosamine Enolpyruvyl Transferase Involved in Peptidoglycan Synthesis and Fosfomycin Resistance</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source> <volume>185</volume>: <fpage>1218</fpage>–<lpage>1228</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Skarzynski1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skarzynski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mistry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wonacott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Structure of UDP-N-acetylglucosamine enolpyruvyl transferase, an enzyme essential for the synthesis of bacterial peptidoglycan, complexed with substrate UDP-N-acetylglucosamine and the drug fosfomycin</article-title>. <source>Structure</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1465</fpage>–<lpage>1474</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Yoon1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Crystal structure of UDP-N-acetylglucosamine enolpyruvyl transferase from <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic> in complex with UDP-N-acetylglucosamine and fosfomycin</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1032</fpage>–<lpage>1037</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Eschenburg1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eschenburg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schonbrunn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Comparative X-ray analysis of the un-liganded fosfomycin-target murA</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>290</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Hertig1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hertig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolbach</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name> (<year>1924</year>) <article-title>Studies on Rickettsia-Like Micro-Organisms in Insects</article-title>. <source>J Med Res</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Hilgenboecker1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilgenboecker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammerstein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schlattmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Telschow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Werren</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>How many species are infected with <italic>Wolbachia</italic>? – a statistical analysis of current data</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiology Letters</source> <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Werren1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Werren</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baldo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title><italic>Wolbachia</italic>: master manipulators of invertebrate biology</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>741</fpage>–<lpage>751</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Fenn1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaxter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Are filarial nematode <italic>Wolbachia</italic> obligate mutualist symbionts</article-title>? <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Taylor2"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bandi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoerauf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>Wolbachia</italic> bacterial endosymbionts of filarial nematodes</article-title>. <source>Adv Parasitol</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>284</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Bandi2"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trees</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brattig</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title><italic>Wolbachia</italic> in filarial nematodes: evolutionary aspects and implications for the pathogenesis and treatment of filarial diseases</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Punkosdy1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Punkosdy</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lasater</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tzertzinis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Detection of serum IgG antibodies specific for <italic>Wolbachia</italic> surface protein in rhesus monkeys infected with <italic>Brugia malayi</italic></article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source> <volume>184</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Henrichfreise1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henrichfreise</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schiefer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nzukou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poellinger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Functional conservation of the lipid II biosynthesis pathway in the cell wall-less bacteria <italic>Chlamydia</italic> and <italic>Wolbachia</italic>: why is lipid II needed</article-title>? <source>Mol Microbiol</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>913</fpage>–<lpage>923</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Padan1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Padan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zilberstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schuldiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>pH homeostasis in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>650</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Gautam1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gautam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rishi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tewari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>UDP-N-acetylglucosamine enolpyruvyl transferase as a potential target for antibacterial chemotherapy: recent developments</article-title>. <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Li2"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Identification and Characterization of a MurA, UDP-N-Acetylglucosamine Enolpyruvyl Transferase from Cariogenic <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>Journal of Hard Tissue Biology</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Kahan1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahan</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kahan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cassidy</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kropp</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>The mechanism of action of fosfomycin (phosphonomycin)</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source> <volume>235</volume>: <fpage>364</fpage>–<lpage>386</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Samland1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samland</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amrhein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macheroux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Lysine 22 in UDP-N-acetylglucosamine enolpyruvyl transferase from <italic>Enterobacter cloacae</italic> is crucial for enzymatic activity and the formation of covalent adducts with the substrate phosphoenolpyruvate and the antibiotic fosfomycin</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>13162</fpage>–<lpage>13169</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Eschenburg2"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eschenburg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Priestman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schonbrunn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Evidence that the fosfomycin target Cys115 in UDP-N-acetylglucosamine enolpyruvyl transferase (MurA) is essential for product release</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>280</volume>: <fpage>3757</fpage>–<lpage>3763</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-DeSmet1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Smet</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kempsell</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Alteration of a single amino acid residue reverses fosfomycin resistance of recombinant MurA from <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>3177</fpage>–<lpage>3184</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Baum1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>EZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montenegro</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Licata</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of new inhibitors of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> MurA enzyme</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>3182</fpage>–<lpage>3188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0099884-Silver1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Does the cell wall of bacteria remain a viable source of targets for novel antibiotics</article-title>? <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>996</fpage>–<lpage>1005</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>