<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117243</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-40576</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Robustness of Plant-Pollinator Assemblages: Linking Plant Interaction Patterns and Sensitivity to Pollinator Loss</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">The Robustness of Plant-Pollinator Assemblages</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Astegiano</surname>
<given-names>Julia</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Massol</surname>
<given-names>François</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Vidal</surname>
<given-names>Mariana Morais</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Cheptou</surname>
<given-names>Pierre-Olivier</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Guimarães</surname>
<given-names>Paulo R.</given-names>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>CEFE UMR 5175, CNRS—Université de Montpellier—Université Paul-Valéry Montpellier—EPHE campus CNRS, Montpellier, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Departamento de Ecologia, Instituto de Biociências, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Laboratoire GEPV, CNRS UMR 8198, Université Lille 1, Villeneuve d’Ascq, France</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Vamosi</surname>
<given-names>Steven M</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Calgary, CANADA</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JA FM POC PRG. Performed the experiments: JA MMV. Analyzed the data: JA MMV. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JA FM MMV POC PRG. Wrote the paper: JA FM MMV POC PRG.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">juastegiano@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>3</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<elocation-id>e0117243</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>9</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>20</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Astegiano et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<p>Most flowering plants depend on pollinators to reproduce. Thus, evaluating the robustness of plant-pollinator assemblages to species loss is a major concern. How species interaction patterns are related to species sensitivity to partner loss may influence the robustness of plant-pollinator assemblages. In plants, both reproductive dependence on pollinators (breeding system) and dispersal ability may modulate plant sensitivity to pollinator loss. For instance, species with strong dependence (e.g. dioecious species) and low dispersal (e.g. seeds dispersed by gravity) may be the most sensitive to pollinator loss. We compared the interaction patterns of plants differing in dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability in a meta-dataset comprising 192 plant species from 13 plant-pollinator networks. In addition, network robustness was compared under different scenarios representing sequences of plant extinctions associated with plant sensitivity to pollinator loss. Species with different dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability showed similar levels of generalization. Although plants with low dispersal ability interacted with more generalized pollinators, low-dispersal plants with strong dependence on pollinators (i.e. the most sensitive to pollinator loss) interacted with more particular sets of pollinators (i.e. shared a low proportion of pollinators with other plants). Only two assemblages showed lower robustness under the scenario considering plant generalization, dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability than under the scenario where extinction sequences only depended on plant generalization (i.e. where higher generalization level was associated with lower probability of extinction). Overall, our results support the idea that species generalization and network topology may be good predictors of assemblage robustness to species loss, independently of plant dispersal ability and breeding system. In contrast, since ecological specialization among partners may increase the probability of disruption of interactions, the fact that the plants most sensitive to pollinator loss interacted with more particular pollinator assemblages suggest that the persistence of these plants and their pollinators might be highly compromised.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>JA was supported by grant 2011/09951-2 and grant 2012/04941-1 (São Paulo Research Foundation-FAPESP, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fapesp.br" xlink:type="simple">http://www.fapesp.br</ext-link>); MMV was supported by grant 2010/11633-6 (São Paulo Research Foundation-FAPESP, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fapesp.br" xlink:type="simple">http://www.fapesp.br</ext-link>); FM and POC are researchers from the CNRS; and PRG Jr. was supported by grant 2009/54422-8 (São Paulo Research Foundation-FAPESP, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fapesp.br" xlink:type="simple">http://www.fapesp.br</ext-link>) and CNPq. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="2"/>
<table-count count="0"/>
<page-count count="16"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The robustness of plant-pollinator assemblages to species loss is a main concern of basic and applied Ecology since 87.5% of flowering plants and most crops directly consumed by humans depend in some degree on pollinators to reproduce [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Understanding how the organization of plant-pollinator interactions may influence species persistence is central to predict the consequences of species loss [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Ultimately, ecological interactions are shaped by traits and therefore trait-based descriptions of species interactions may provide insights into the organization of interacting assemblages [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In this context, a main challenge is to understand how traits shaping species interaction patterns also influence the sensitivity of species to the loss of interaction partners [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p>
<p>Plant-pollinator assemblages show consistent patterns in the organization of interactions among species [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In these assemblages, only a few species of plants and pollinators are extremely generalized i.e. interact with a high number of species [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Generalists are central to the nested structure of plant-pollinator assemblages, in which ecologically specialized species interact with subsets of species interacting with more generalized species [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. As a consequence, the loss of generalized species decreases the robustness of plant-pollinator assemblages to subsequent species loss [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Thus, the persistence of generalists may increase the persistence of the whole assemblage [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p>
<p>In plants, pollination of generalists should be less affected by pollinator loss due to pollinator redundancy [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Indeed, generalized plants tend to interact both with generalized and specialized pollinators [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], which may lead to lower fluctuation of pollinator service [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and to lower risk of reproductive failure when specialized pollinators go extinct [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. However, plant sensitivity to pollinator loss is not only affected by interaction patterns among plants and pollinators but also by plant breeding system [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p>
<p>Plant breeding systems modulate the dependence of plants on pollinators to produce seeds [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Among biotically pollinated plants, self-incompatible and dioecious species are strongly dependent on pollinator services, since pollination will only occur when pollinators have previously visited flowers of compatible and male conspecific plants, respectively. In contrast, self-compatible species may be less dependent on pollinators because a single visit of pollinators to each individual flower may allow reproduction. Plants having mechanisms to produce seeds without pollinator visits may be even less dependent. As generalization on pollinators may evolve if it decreases the risk of reproductive failure when pollinators fluctuate in abundance [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], plants with different breeding systems may show different levels of generalization [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Species depending more on pollinators may interact with multiple pollinator species [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] whereas plants interacting with fewer pollinator species may be less dependent on pollinators [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Moreover, pollinator-dependent plants would be expected to interact with more generalized pollinators, minimizing temporal fluctuation in pollination services [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p>
<p>Plant dispersal ability may also modulate plant sensitivity to pollinator loss. Higher dispersal ability has been associated with lower dependence on pollinators (i.e. self-compatibility or autonomous self-pollination) because only plants with the ability to produce seeds without pollinators should reproduce in sites were pollinators are absent (Baker’s law) [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In contrast, it has recently been shown in theoretical studies that fluctuations in pollination levels may lead to the evolution of two alternative syndromes: outcrossers with high dispersal ability or selfers with low dispersal [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Indeed, high dispersal ability may increase the persistence of dioecious species [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In this sense, if strongly dependent species can locally persist by dispersing seeds from sites where pollinators are present, then their persistence may be less dependent on local pollinator services. Thus, the patterns of interaction of plants may also be modulated by dispersal ability, with highly dispersing plants interacting with fewer and/or more specialized pollinator species and low-dispersal plants being more generalists and/or interacting with generalized pollinators.</p>
<p>In this study, we investigated how plant interaction patterns varied with plant sensitivity to pollinator loss. We also explored how this variation might influence the robustness of plant-pollinator assemblages. We compiled information on plant breeding system and dispersal mode for 192 species from 13 published plant-pollinator networks. We described the patterns of interaction for each plant species, i.e. its contribution to network nestedness, its degree of ecological generalization on pollinators [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], and the mean level of generalization of its pollinators. Specifically, we asked how these patterns were associated with the dependence of plants on pollinators and their dispersal ability. We predicted that plants with strong dependence on pollinators or low dispersal ability may show higher degree of generalization on pollinators, higher contribution to nestedness and interact with more generalized pollinators. In addition, we investigated how the association of plant generalization, dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability may affect the robustness of plant-pollinator assemblages by simulating sequences of species extinctions. We expected that scenarios where plant generalization level and biological traits affected the probability of extinction of plants would lead to less robust networks than scenarios only considering plant generalization and as robust as the random scenario—i.e. where no plant trait affected plant sensitivity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Plant interaction patterns and sensitivity to pollinator loss</title>
<p>We characterized the interaction pattern of 339 plant species belonging to 13 qualitative plant-pollinator networks available at the interaction web database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nceas.ucsb.edu/interactionweb/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nceas.ucsb.edu/interactionweb/</ext-link>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). We used three network metrics to characterize the patterns of interaction of each species: plant contribution to nestedness, plant ecological generalization on pollinators (hereafter plant generalization) and mean ecological generalization of plant interaction partners (hereafter mean pollinator generalization). Plant contribution to nestedness measured how much the interactions of a given plant species overlapped, on average, with those of other plant species in the network, following [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] (see “Plant contribution to nestedness” in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec013">supporting information</xref>). We first calculated the proportion of pollinator species shared between a given plant and each plant species of the network. Then, for each plant, the average proportion of pollinators shared with the other plant species represented its contribution to nestedness. To calculate plant contribution to nestedness we used the ANINHADO software [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The generalization of a given plant species was characterized by the proportion of pollinator species that interacted with it [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], k<sub>p</sub>/S<sub>A</sub>, where k<sub>p</sub> was the number of pollinator species interacting with the focal plant species and S<sub>A</sub> was the number of pollinator species of the network. The generalization level of each pollinator interacting with a given plant species was calculated as k<sub>a</sub>/S<sub>P</sub>, where k<sub>a</sub> was the number of plant species that interacted with a given pollinator and S<sub>P</sub> was the plant richness species of the network. The mean pollinator generalization for a given plant species was obtained as the mean of the generalization level of all pollinators interacting with the focal plant species.</p>
<p>We used information on breeding system and dispersal mode to estimate, respectively, plant dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability. Data on breeding system and dispersal mode was obtained for 192 of the initial 339 species (58%; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). For most of the plant species, data on these traits was extracted from published articles (<xref rid="pone.0117243.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). When different studies were available for the same species, we prioritized information obtained in the same study region where networks were characterized. Data on the two traits for 6% of species was obtained from researchers working with those plants. Dispersal mode was also obtained from seed-trait databases (7.5% of species; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). In 7% of plants, dispersal mode was assigned by the analysis of images of the dispersal units and according to [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p>
<p>We grouped the large diversity of plant breeding systems in three categories depicting the degree of dependence of plants on pollinators to produce seeds. Species where classified as: (i) strongly dependent plants, including self-incompatible and dioecious species, and obligate outcrossers; (ii) intermediately dependent plants, including self-compatible species and facultative outcrossers; and (iii) slightly dependent plants, including autonomous self-pollinating, agamospermous, cleistogamous, and facultative autogamous species. Dispersal mode was coded in two classes depicting dispersal ability: (i) low-dispersal plants, including species dispersed by gravity (with or without diaspore explosion), and ants; (ii) high-dispersal plants, including species dispersed by vertebrates, wind and water.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p>We evaluated how plant interaction patterns varied among plants differing in their dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability. In our analysis, plant generalization, contribution to nestedness and mean generalization of pollinators were the response variables, and dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability the explanatory factors. Since residuals of linear models were not normally distributed but variances among groups were homogeneous, we chose to use the distance-based non-parametric analysis of variance introduced by Anderson [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Thus, we computed p-values using permutation tests (n = 9999 permutations). We performed these permutation analyses using the Adonis function included in the Vegan package on R [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Particularities of each assemblage such as species richness and connectance (i.e. the proportion of possible interactions actually recorded) could influence the value of the response variables. Thus, permutations were performed among species within networks. To determine <italic>a posteriori</italic> pair-wise differences between levels of factors that influenced the response variables, we performed separated permutation tests following [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Data on plants occurring in more than one network (6 species) were included only once in the analyses by randomly choosing one of these networks. Including or not these 6 species in the analyses did not change the results.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness</title>
<p>We evaluated how plant sensitivity to pollinator loss might influence network robustness by simulating plant extinctions. We used 10 networks, excluding three networks from this analysis due to limited information on both the dependence of plants on pollinators and plant dispersal abilities (&lt; 60% of the species) (<xref rid="pone.0117243.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). Among these 10 networks, species without information on a given trait were randomly assigned with equal probability to one category of the trait at the beginning of each simulation of extinction events.</p>
<p>We evaluated network robustness under different simulated scenarios of plant extinctions. We used a fully factorial design leading to eight simulated scenarios in which each plant trait (i.e. plant generalization, dependence on pollinators or dispersal ability) or the combination of these traits determined plant sensitivity to pollinator extinction (see <xref rid="pone.0117243.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref> for a full description of the scenarios). Plant sensitivity depending on species generalization represented the ability of plants to cope with fluctuations on the abundances of pollinators or even pollinator loss, associated with pollinator redundancy (e.g. the reproduction of plants interacting with few pollinators is more likely to be pollen limited [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]). Thus, plants interacting with multiple pollinators were considered to be less sensitive to pollinator loss than those interacting with a few species. In the case of plant dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability, plant sensitivity represented the ability of plants to cope with pollinator decline with alternative strategies, e.g. autonomous self-pollination or seeds arriving from other sites. Then, species with slight dependence on pollinators and/or high dispersal ability (e.g. wind or animal dispersed) were less sensitive to pollinator loss. Simulated scenarios also included a random scenario under which no plant trait affected plant sensitivity. This random scenario represented a null model to compare the effects of the other scenarios on assemblage robustness [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].</p>
<p>To perform extinction sequences, we assigned probabilities of extinction to each plant species according to plant generalization, dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability as follows. For scenarios only considering one of these traits, we first ranked all the species according to a decreasing order of sensitivity to pollinator loss, as explained above. Thus, in the case of plant dependence on pollinators, strongly dependent species were considered the most sensitive whereas slightly dependent species were the least sensitive. In relation to dispersal ability, low-dispersal plants were considered the most sensitive whereas high-dispersal species were the least sensitive. In the case of plant generalization on pollinators, higher generalization was associated with lower sensitivity to pollinator loss. Secondly, for the N species within each category of each trait we sampled N extinction probabilities from a truncated exponential distribution, where the lambda parameter was randomly chosen among values ranging from 10 to 25. Thus, species belonging to more sensitive categories were first ranked and received higher extinction probabilities. Then, we computed the mean extinction probability of the sampled values for each trait category and assigned this mean value to all plants within the category. Finally, we normalized the probability values across all species (i.e. we made the sum of all probabilities equal to 1) to obtain the final probability of extinction for each species. In scenarios taking into account any combination of traits, we assigned extinction probabilities according to each trait as explained above, and we multiplied the set of probabilities for each species. Then, we normalized these probability values across species in order to obtain the final probability of extinction for each species. In the random scenario, all species received the same probability of extinction calculated as 1/S<sub>P</sub>.</p>
<p>We performed 1000 sequences of plant extinction for each scenario. Each sequence included the sequential removal of all plant species. A pollinator species died out if all their interacting plants were extinct. After the removal of each plant species, we computed the percentage of surviving pollinator species. Then, we assessed the robustness of the networks following each sequence of extinction by computing the area under the curve describing the proportion of remaining pollinator species against the proportion of plants that went extinct [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Areas that are close to one represent networks that are robust to plant extinction, since large percentages of extinctions are needed until significant secondary extinctions of pollinators are observed. On the other hand, areas that are close to zero correspond to very fragile networks, in which extinction of a small proportion of plant species leads to the extinction of a high proportion of pollinator species [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Simulations were performed in MATLAB [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. We obtained mean values of robustness for each scenario and then we compared the differences between means of a-priori planned pair-wise comparisons (see <xref rid="pone.0117243.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.s012" ref-type="supplementary-material">S12</xref> Tables). We calculated the 95% confidence intervals for differences between means and we considered that the difference between scenarios was significant when the confidence interval did not include the zero value [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Plant interaction patterns and sensitivity to pollinator loss</title>
<p>Plant generalization did not differ among species with different dependence on pollinators (<italic>F</italic><sub>1, 192</sub> = 0.68, <italic>P</italic> = 0.4; <xref rid="pone.0117243.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A and B</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Table</xref>) or dispersal ability (<italic>F</italic><sub>1, 192</sub> = 1.85, <italic>P</italic> = 0.18; <xref rid="pone.0117243.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A and B</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Table</xref>). However, low-dispersal plants interacted, on average, with more generalized pollinators (<italic>F</italic><sub>1, 192</sub> = 11.26, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0013; <xref rid="pone.0117243.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Table</xref>). Low-dispersal plants showed higher contribution to nestedness than high-dispersal plants (<italic>F</italic><sub>1, 192</sub> = 7.62, <italic>P</italic> = 0.006; <xref rid="pone.0117243.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1E</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Table</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0117243.s015" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig.</xref>). However, the relationship between dispersal ability and nestedness was modulated by plant dependence on pollinators (<italic>F</italic><sub>1, 192</sub> = 7.19, <italic>P</italic> = 0.006; <xref rid="pone.0117243.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1E</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0117243.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Table</xref>). Thus, species with low dispersal ability and slight dependence on pollinators showed the highest contribution to nestedness (<xref rid="pone.0117243.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1E</xref>). Species with strong dependence on pollinators and high dispersal ability showed intermediate mean values of contribution to nestedness (<xref rid="pone.0117243.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1E</xref>) that did not differ significantly from the other groups. By contrast, low-dispersal plants with strong dependence on pollinators were among those that showed the lowest contributions to nestedness (<xref rid="pone.0117243.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1E</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0117243.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.g001</object-id>
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant interaction patterns and sensitivity to pollinator loss.</title>
<p>Box-plots of plant generalization (“a” and “b”), mean pollinator generalization (“c” and “d”) and plant contribution to nestedness (“e”) of species differing in dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability. Black lines within boxes represent median values. Upper and lower limits of boxes represent 1<sup>st</sup> and 3<sup>rd</sup> quartiles, respectively. Boxes were drawn with widths proportional to the number of observations in each group. In (a) and (c), “Strong”, “Inter” and “Slight” refer to strongly, intermediately and slightly dependent plants, respectively. In (b) and (d), “Low” and “High” refer to high and low-dispersal plants, respectively. In (e) “Strong-Low”, “Inter-Low” and “Slight-Low” refer to plants with strong, intermediate and low dependence on pollinators and slight dispersal ability, whereas “Strong-high”, “Inter-high” and ‘Slight-high” refer to plants with high, intermediate and low dependence on pollinators and high dispersal ability. The probability of obtaining a difference higher than that observed among groups is also shown. Abbreviations: Inter = intermediate.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness</title>
<p>The proportion of pollinator species surviving after plant extinction followed a slow-decaying curve under most of the scenarios (<xref rid="pone.0117243.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). The robustness of plant-pollinator networks varied depending on which plant trait or combination of traits influenced plant probability of extinction (<xref rid="pone.0117243.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.s012" ref-type="supplementary-material">S12</xref> Tables). In most assemblages (80%), networks were more robust when the sequence of extinctions depended on differences in generalization among plant species whether or not the other biological traits affected extinction probabilities (<xref rid="pone.0117243.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.s012" ref-type="supplementary-material">S12</xref> Tables). Seven networks (70%) showed lower robustness when all species had the same probability of extinction (random scenario) and under scenarios where plant loss was influenced only by plant dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability or these two traits (80%; <xref rid="pone.0117243.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). In two networks (Schemske and Dupont) robustness was similar among all scenarios and in two networks (Ramirez and Vázquez) robustness under the random scenario was similar to robustness observed under the scenario considering plant generalization and the two biological traits (<xref rid="pone.0117243.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0117243.s012" ref-type="supplementary-material">S12</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.s014" ref-type="supplementary-material">S14</xref> Tables).</p>
<fig id="pone.0117243.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.g002</object-id>
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Proportion of pollinator species surviving under different scenarios of plant extinction representing plant sensitivity to pollinator loss in 10 plant-pollinator networks. Scenarios where plant extinction probability was linked to plant generalization (with or without taking into account other traits) were drawn in black. Scenarios that did not consider plant generalization into plant extinction probability were drawn in grey.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Differences in the robustness of networks among the set of scenarios where plant generalization influenced the sequence of extinctions varied across assemblages. Most networks (80%) showed similar robustness to extinction sequences determined by the combination of the three traits and to extinctions only based on plant generalization (<xref rid="pone.0117243.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.s008" ref-type="supplementary-material">S8</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.s011" ref-type="supplementary-material">S11</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.s014" ref-type="supplementary-material">S14</xref> Tables). Only two networks were less robust when the three traits were considered (Medan I and Medan II; <xref rid="pone.0117243.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s009" ref-type="supplementary-material">S9</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0117243.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material">S10</xref> Tables).</p>
<p>Differences in the robustness of networks between the random scenario and the set of scenarios where extinction sequences were determined by plant dependence and/or dispersal also varied across assemblages. Half of assemblages showed similar robustness between scenarios where extinction probabilities were associated to either one or both biological traits and random scenarios (Barrett, Dupont, Elberling, Motten and Vázquez; <xref rid="pone.0117243.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.s011" ref-type="supplementary-material">S11</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0117243.s014" ref-type="supplementary-material">S14</xref> Tables). The scenario considering plant dispersal and dependence on pollinators led to less robust networks than the random scenario in three assemblages (Medán I, Medán II and Ramirez; <xref rid="pone.0117243.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0117243.s009" ref-type="supplementary-material">S9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material">S10</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0117243.s012" ref-type="supplementary-material">S12</xref> Tables).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Focusing on how traits determining species sensitivity to partner loss may influence species patterns of interaction may improve our understanding of the impacts of species loss on assemblage maintenance [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Contrary to what we hypothesized, generalist plants were not more sensitive to pollinator loss. We showed that low dispersal plants interacted with more generalized pollinators and that the contribution of plants to nestedness was associated with the interaction among biological traits. Slightly dependent low dispersal plants were those contributing more to nestedness whereas species showing the highest sensitivity to pollinator loss were among those species showing the lowest contribution. Finally, in most assemblages (80%) considering plant generalization and biological traits as determinants of species probability of extinction led to networks of similar robustness to scenarios only including plant generalization. Below, we discuss the implications of our results in light of how plant species may persist locally and how this persistence will maintain plant-pollinator assemblages.</p>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Plant interaction patterns and sensitivity to pollinator loss</title>
<p>Since functional redundancy among pollinators may lead to less fluctuating pollination service in generalist plants [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], species depending more on pollinators to produce seeds (e.g. dioecious or self-incompatible species) are expected to be more generalists. Alternatively, to cope with fluctuations in pollinator service species depending more on pollinators may be expected to be better dispersers [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], as a way to buffer local pollination limitation. Although a good ability to colonize has traditionally been associated with low dependence on pollinators—i.e., self-compatibility or autonomous self-pollination [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]—, the association between strong dependence on pollinators and high dispersal has been predicted by theoretical studies and both trends have been observed in empirical studies [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Our results showed that plants more sensitive to pollinator loss did not showed higher ecological generalization on pollinators. Species with strong dependence on pollinators and high dispersal ability might persist under unfavorable pollination environments by receiving seeds from other sites whereas low-dispersal plants with autonomous self-pollination mechanisms might assure their reproduction by performing self-pollination.</p>
<p>Moreover, low-dispersal plants interacted with more generalized pollinators which might fluctuate less in abundance and thus may provide a more reliable pollination service [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Thus, the interaction with pollinators that visit multiple plant species—a pervasive pattern in pollination networks [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]—might also be an alternative pathway for the persistence of low-dispersal plants. However, the interaction with more generalized pollinators might also increase the arrival of heterospecific pollen to stigmas, negatively affecting the reproduction of plants [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The quantity of heterospecific pollen delivered by generalist pollinators might depend on how pollinator foraging behavior can be affected by the more likely patchy distribution of low dispersal plants [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</p>
<p>Higher overlap of interactions with other species may also increase species persistence [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. An indirect positive effect may exist among plants interacting with the same pollinators since the persistence of any of the plant species may allow the persistence of pollinators and thus maintain the pollination service of other plants [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The highest contribution to nestedness was observed in plants with slight dependence on pollinators, i.e. plants that can reproduce even when pollinators are scarce. Therefore, the persistence of slightly dependent plants despite temporal fluctuations of pollinator abundance might facilitate the persistence of more sensitive plants. However, we also found that plants having the highest sensitivity to pollinator loss—i.e., strongly dependent, low-dispersal species—where among the groups of plants showing the lowest contribution to nestedness. Ecological specialization between interacting partners may contribute to increase the vulnerability of interactions to disruption [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], which might compromise the persistence of these highly sensitive plants and their pollinators.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness</title>
<p>Plant-pollinator assemblages may show high robustness on average to the random extinction of species, but face higher fragility when generalists are lost earlier in the sequence of extinctions [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. We assessed network robustness under scenarios of plant extinction representing plant sensitivity to pollinator loss associated with two key biological traits: plant dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability. In accordance with previous studies [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], the early collapse of networks was not observed under the different scenarios of species extinction. Thus, plant-pollinator networks may be tolerant to the loss of more sensitive plants. However, this tolerance relies on the assumption that pollinators are functionally redundant which is still unknown for most of plant-pollinator networks [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p>
<p>Since generalization implies redundancy of interaction partners, more robust assemblages can be expected when extreme generalists are the least likely to be lost [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The higher robustness of scenarios where extinction sequences depended on plant generalization compared to scenarios where generalization was not considered is in agreement with that expectation. Moreover, the lower robustness of networks under scenarios where extinction order depended only on either plant dependence on pollinators or dispersal ability may be explained by the earlier removal of generalized plants. The early extinction of generalists lies with the similar generalization levels we found among plants with different dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability, i.e. generalist plants may show both high and low sensitivity to pollinator loss. However, as the nested structure of interactions may explain the robustness of plant-pollinator assemblages [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], differences in network robustness among scenarios might be associated, indeed, to differences in contribution to nestedness among species. When extinction sequences depended on dispersal, plants being removed earlier may decrease network nestedness, as low-dispersal (more sensitive) plants were those contributing more to the nested structure. The interaction of strongly dependent, low-dispersal plants with more particular sets of pollinators may explain why scenarios considering dependence on pollinators with or without dispersal ability led to less robust networks than scenarios including plant generalization. Contribution to nestedness may partially increase with species ecological generalization [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], which may explain why scenarios where generalists were less likely to be lost were more robust.</p>
<p>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss has been included into simulated scenarios of plant extinction in two previous studies, by using plant-pollinator frequency of interactions as a surrogate of species dependence on interaction partners [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. By removing either pollinators or plants, Kaiser-Bunbury et al. [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] showed that the early removal of most important interaction partners (i.e. with the strongest interaction frequencies) led to less robust networks than scenarios assuming the early removal of generalists. Vieira &amp; Almeida-Neto [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] included plant dependence on pollinators into extinction scenarios by considering interaction frequency among plants and pollinators, and by assigning different levels of dependence on pollinators to whole plant communities of real networks (i.e. plants of the same community had the same ability to self-pollinate). They showed that lower mean plant ability to self-pollinate increased the number of co-extinctions per extinction event, decreasing network robustness to the loss of generalists [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. In contrast, we found that when breeding system, dispersal ability and plant generalization influenced the sequences of plant extinction only two networks showed lower robustness than under the generalization scenario. Thus, one of the next questions to be addressed is to what extent adding pollinator effectiveness may evidence the influence of biological traits on network robustness. Asymmetric dependencies seem to be the rule in mutualistic networks [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] and species importance for interaction partners (i.e. species strength) has been reported to be positively associated with species generalization [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Thus, we hypothesize that the extinction of more sensitive plants does not cause the co-extinction of shared pollinators and other plants, because highly sensitive plants interacted with more particular sets of pollinators. However, we recognize that the influence of pollinator effectiveness on plant persistence and thus on community robustness remains to be empirically tested.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions and Future Directions</title>
<p>Our results suggest that networks might be tolerant to pollinator loss because plants that are central to network organization may have alternative strategies to cope with pollen limitation, which may allow their persistence under unfavorable pollinator environments. Thus, focusing on network organization as a determinant of assemblage robustness might be a good approximation to estimate the fragility of plant-pollinator networks to species loss. However, more complete understanding of the importance of plant sensitivity to pollinator loss should be achieved by studying the effects of functional redundancy within pollinators of more generalist species, including how per-visit effectiveness and species local abundance relate to each other and with temporal fluctuation in pollinator abundance, three important features that may influence species generalization level [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Moreover, although the nested structure of plant-pollinator assemblages may provide higher metacommunity robustness to habitat loss [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], more sensitive plants interacting with more particular pollinator assemblages may be more prone to be lost. Since plant breeding system and dispersal ability may modulate plant response to habitat fragmentation [<xref rid="pone.0117243.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0117243.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], future studies assessing how changes in landscape configuration affect the relationships between plant interaction patterns and plant sensitivity to pollinator loss may improve our understanding of the effects of one of the major threats to biodiversity.</p>
<p>We thank Silvana Buzato, Pedro Jordano, Miguel Fortuna and the Guimarães (Miúdo) Lab for discussions on the ideas presented in this manuscript. To Alfredo Valido, Alicia Sérsic, Andrea Cosacov and Nelson Ramirez for providing information and specific bibliography on species traits. To Alejandra Tapia for advice with statistical analyses. To Lauren Ponisio and three anonymous reviewers for comments on the manuscript.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>General information of the plant-pollinator networks from the Interaction Web Database used in this study.</title>
<p>Network, Habitat type, localization, total number of plant and pollinator species (Sp), connectance (c), degree of nestedness (NODF), and percentage of plant species with information on dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability (% Plants DP &amp; DA) are shown for each network. References as stated at the IWDB are also shown. Networks with their original name in italic are those that were used in simulations of plant extinction. For abbreviation purposes we used the surname of the first author to refer to each network.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s002" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant interaction patterns and sensitivity to pollinator loss.</title>
<p>Network, species, family, dependence on pollinators (DP), dispersal ability (DA), plant generalization, contribution to nestedness (nestedness) and mean generalization of pollinators of the plant species used in this study. Data on plant generalization, nestedness and mean generalization of pollinators were obtained as described in the M&amp;M section. The first citation appearing in the column “Reference” refers to the bibliographic source from which data on dependence on pollinators was extracted and the second one refers to data on dispersal ability. Only one reference is presented when information on both traits was extracted from the same source. Three references are shown when more than one reference was available for one of the traits. “Strong”, “Inter” and “Slight” refer to strongly, intermediately and slightly dependent plants, respectively, in the column referring to dependence on pollinators (DP). “Low” and “High” refer to high and low-dispersal plants, respectively, in the column referring to dispersal ability (DA).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s003" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s003" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Scenarios linking plant probability of extinction to different plant traits associated with plant sensitivity to pollinator loss (i.e. plant generalization, dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability) or combinations of these traits. The random scenario (no trait is considered) was also explored.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s004" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s004" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S4 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant interaction patterns and sensitivity to pollinator loss: partition of variation and permutation analyses results.</title>
<p>Sum of squares (SS), degrees of freedom (df), mean squares (MS), and F-ratio are shown for plant generalization on pollinators, contribution to nestedness and mean pollinator generalization. Probability values (p) obtained from permutation analyses are also shown.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s005" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s005" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S5 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Mean differences of robustness (Mean) between pairs of scenarios, and minimum (CI min) and maximum (CI max) limits of the 95% confidence interval of each difference are shown for the Barrett network. Pairwise comparisons were planned a-priori. Scenarios: dependence on pollinators (DP), dispersal ability (DA), dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability (DPDA), random (R), dependence on pollinators and generalization (DPG), dispersal ability and generalization (DAG), dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability and generalization (DPDAG) and generalization (G).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s006" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s006" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S6 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Mean differences of robustness (Mean) between pairs of scenarios, and minimum (CI min) and maximum (CI max) limits of the 95% confidence interval of each difference are shown for the Dupont network. Pairwise comparisons were planned a-priori. Scenarios: dependence on pollinators (DP), dispersal ability (DA), dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability (DPDA), random (R), dependence on pollinators and generalization (DPG), dispersal ability and generalization (DAG), dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability and generalization (DPDAG) and generalization (G).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s007" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s007" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S7 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Mean differences of robustness (Mean) between pairs of scenarios, and minimum (CI min) and maximum (CI max) limits of the 95% confidence interval of each difference are shown for the Elberling network. Pairwise comparisons were planned a-priori. Scenarios: dependence on pollinators (DP), dispersal ability (DA), dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability (DPDA), random (R), dependence on pollinators and generalization (DPG), dispersal ability and generalization (DAG), dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability and generalization (DPDAG) and generalization (G).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s008" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s008" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S8 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Mean differences of robustness (Mean) between pairs of scenarios, and minimum (CI min) and maximum (CI max) limits of the 95% confidence interval of each difference are shown for the Kevan network. Pairwise comparisons were planned a-priori. Scenarios: dependence on pollinators (DP), dispersal ability (DA), dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability (DPDA), random (R), dependence on pollinators and generalization (DPG), dispersal ability and generalization (DAG), dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability and generalization (DPDAG) and generalization (G).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s009" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s009" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S9 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Mean differences of robustness (Mean) between pairs of scenarios, and minimum (CI min) and maximum (CI max) limits of the 95% confidence interval of each difference are shown for the Medán II network. Pairwise comparisons were planned a-priori. Scenarios: dependence on pollinators (DP), dispersal ability (DA), dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability (DPDA), random (R), dependence on pollinators and generalization (DPG), dispersal ability and generalization (DAG), dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability and generalization (DPDAG) and generalization (G).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s010" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s010" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S10 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Mean differences of robustness (Mean) between pairs of scenarios, and minimum (CI min) and maximum (CI max) limits of the 95% confidence interval of each difference are shown for the Medán I network. Pairwise comparisons were planned a-priori. Scenarios: dependence on pollinators (DP), dispersal ability (DA), dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability (DPDA), random (R), dependence on pollinators and generalization (DPG), dispersal ability and generalization (DAG), dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability and generalization (DPDAG) and generalization (G).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s011" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s011" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S11 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Mean differences of robustness (Mean) between pairs of scenarios, and minimum (CI min) and maximum (CI max) limits of the 95% confidence interval of each difference are shown for the Motten network. Pairwise comparisons were planned a-priori. Scenarios: dependence on pollinators (DP), dispersal ability (DA), dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability (DPDA), random (R), dependence on pollinators and generalization (DPG), dispersal ability and generalization (DAG), dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability and generalization (DPDAG) and generalization (G).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s012" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s012" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S12 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Mean differences of robustness (Mean) between pairs of scenarios, and minimum (CI min) and maximum (CI max) limits of the 95% confidence interval of each difference are shown for the Ramirez network. Pairwise comparisons were planned a-priori. Scenarios: dependence on pollinators (DP), dispersal ability (DA), dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability (DPDA), random (R), dependence on pollinators and generalization (DPG), dispersal ability and generalization (DAG), dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability and generalization (DPDAG) and generalization (G).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s013" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s013" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S13 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Mean differences of robustness (Mean) between pairs of scenarios, and minimum (CI min) and maximum (CI max) limits of the 95% confidence interval of each difference are shown for the Schemske network. Pairwise comparisons were planned a-priori. Scenarios: dependence on pollinators (DP), dispersal ability (DA), dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability (DPDA), random (R), dependence on pollinators and generalization (DPG), dispersal ability and generalization (DAG), dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability and generalization (DPDAG) and generalization (G).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s014" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s014" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S14 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant sensitivity to pollinator loss and network robustness.</title>
<p>Mean differences of robustness (Mean) between pairs of scenarios, and minimum (CI min) and maximum (CI max) limits of the 95% confidence interval of each difference are shown for the Vazquez network. Pairwise comparisons were planned a-priori. Scenarios: dependence on pollinators (DP), dispersal ability (DA), dependence on pollinators and dispersal ability (DPDA), random (R), dependence on pollinators and generalization (DPG), dispersal ability and generalization (DAG), dependence on pollinators, dispersal ability and generalization (DPDAG) and generalization (G).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117243.s015" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117243.s015" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Plant contribution to nestedness and dispersal ability.</title>
<p>Box-plots of plant contribution to nestedness of species with different dispersal ability. Black lines within boxes represent median values. Upper and lower limits of boxes represent 1<sup>st</sup> and 3<sup>rd</sup> quartiles, respectively. Boxes were drawn with widths proportional to the number of observations in each group. “Low” and “High” refer to low and high-dispersal plants, respectively.</p>
<p>(TIFF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ollerton</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winfree</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tarrant</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>How many flowering plants are pollinated by animals?</article-title> <source>Oikos</source> <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname> <given-names>A-M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaissiere</surname> <given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cane</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steffan-Dewenter</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Importance of pollinators in changing landscapes for world crops</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Biol Sci</source> <volume>274</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17164193</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashworth</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quesada</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casas</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilar</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oyama</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Pollinator-dependent food production in Mexico</article-title>. <source>Biol Conserv</source> <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>1050</fpage>–<lpage>1057</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bascompte</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Disentangling the web of life</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>325</volume>: <fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1170749" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1170749</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19628856</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGill</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enquist</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiher</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westoby</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Rebuilding community ecology from functional traits</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16701083</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Díaz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Purvis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelissen</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mace</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donoghue</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Functional traits, the phylogeny of function, and ecosystem service vulnerability</article-title>. <source>Ecol Evol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>2958</fpage>–<lpage>2975</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ece3.601" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/ece3.601</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24101986</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vidal</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pires</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guimarães</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Large vertebrates as the missing components of seed-dispersal networks</article-title>. <source>Biol Conserv</source> <volume>163</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordano</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bascompte</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olesen</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Invariant properties in coevolutionary networks of plant–animal interactions</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saavedra</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stouffer</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uzzi</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bascompte</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Strong contributors to network persistence are the most vulnerable to extinction</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>478</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature10433" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature10433</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21918515</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bascompte</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jordano</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melián</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olesen</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The nested assembly of plant–animal mutualistic networks</article-title>. <source>PNAS</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>9383</fpage>–<lpage>9387</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12881488</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Memmott</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waser</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname> <given-names>MV</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Tolerance of pollination networks to species extinctions</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B</source> <volume>271</volume>: <fpage>2605</fpage>–<lpage>2611</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15615687</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezende</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lavabre</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guimarães</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jordano</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bascompte</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Non-random coextinctions in phylogenetically structured mutualistic networks</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>448</volume>: <fpage>925</fpage>–<lpage>928</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17713534</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser‐Bunbury</surname> <given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muff</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Memmott</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caflisch</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The robustness of pollination networks to the loss of species and interactions: a quantitative approach incorporating pollinator behaviour</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>442</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1461-0248.2009.01437.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2009.01437.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20100244</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrera</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Variation in mutualisms: the spatio-temporal mosaic of an insect pollinator assemblage</article-title>. <source>Biol J Linn Soc</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waser</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chittka</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname> <given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ollerton</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Generalization in pollination systems, and why it matters</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>1043</fpage>–<lpage>1060</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steffan–Dewenter</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tscharntke</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Fruit set of highland coffee increases with the diversity of pollinating bees</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B</source> <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>955</fpage>–<lpage>961</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12803911</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zamora</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <chapter-title>Ecological factors that promote the evolution of generalization in pollination systems</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Waser</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ollerton</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Plant-pollinator interactions: from specialization to generalization</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>. pp. <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ladley</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molloy</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terry</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Cascading effects of bird functional extinction reduce pollination and plant density</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>331</volume>: <fpage>1068</fpage>–<lpage>1071</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1199092" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1199092</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21292938</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahli</surname> <given-names>HF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conner</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Characterizing ecological generalization in plant–pollination systems</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16514533</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vázquez</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aizen</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Asymmetric specialization: a pervasive feature of plant-pollinator interactions</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>1251</fpage>–<lpage>1257</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashworth</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilar</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galetto</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aizen</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Why do pollination generalist and specialist plant species show similar reproductive susceptibility to habitat fragmentation?</article-title> <source>J Ecol</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>719</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Do mutualisms matter? Assessing the impact of pollinator and disperser disruption on plant extinction</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans R Soc Lond B</source> <volume>344</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcock</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neiland</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Pollination failure in plants: why it happens and when it matters</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>270</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12049924</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilar</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashworth</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galetto</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aizen</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Plant reproductive susceptibility to habitat fragmentation: review and synthesis through a meta‐analysis</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>968</fpage>–<lpage>980</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16913941</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenster</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martén‐Rodríguez</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Reproductive assurance and the evolution of pollination specialization</article-title>. <source>Int J Plant Sci</source> <volume>168</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bawa</surname> <given-names>KS</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Pollinators of tropical dioecious angiosperms: a reassessment? No, not yet</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>460</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arroyo</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armesto</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Evolution of autonomous selfing accompanies increased specialization in the pollination system of <italic>Schizanthus</italic> (Solanaceae)</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>1168</fpage>–<lpage>1176</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3732/ajb.0800306" xlink:type="simple">10.3732/ajb.0800306</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21628267</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martén-Rodríguez</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fenster</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Pollen limitation and reproductive assurance in Antillean Gesnerieae: a specialists vs. generalist comparison</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20380205</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aizen</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashworth</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galetto</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Reproductive success in fragmented habitats: do compatibility systems and pollination specialization matter?</article-title> <source>J Veg Sci</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>892</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12463509</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name> (<year>1955</year>) <article-title>Self-compatibility and establishment after ‘long distance’ dispersal</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>Support for Baker’s law as a rule</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>853</fpage>–<lpage>856</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheptou</surname> <given-names>P-O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Massol</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Pollination fluctuations drive evolutionary syndromes linking dispersal and mating system</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/599303" xlink:type="simple">10.1086/599303</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19456266</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massol</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheptou</surname> <given-names>P-O</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evolutionary syndromes linking dispersal and mating system: the effect of autocorrelation in pollination conditions</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>591</fpage>–<lpage>598</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01134.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01134.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21271998</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heilbuth</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilves</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otto</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The consequences of dioecy for seed dispersal: modeling the seed‐shadow handicap</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>880</fpage>–<lpage>888</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11430648</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ollerton</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Killick</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamborn</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whiston</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Multiple meanings and modes: on the many ways to be a generalist flower</article-title>. <source>Taxon</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>728</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida‐Neto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guimarães</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guimarães</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loyola</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ulrich</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A consistent metric for nestedness analysis in ecological systems: reconciling concept and measurement</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>1227</fpage>–<lpage>1239</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guimarães</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guimarães</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Improving the analyses of nestedness for large sets of matrices</article-title>. <source>Envir Mod Soft</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1512</fpage>–<lpage>1513</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olesen</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jordano</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Geographic patterns in plant-pollinator mutualistic networks</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>2416</fpage>–<lpage>2424</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlop</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>French</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leishman</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Predicting dispersal spectra: a minimal set of hypotheses based on plant attributes</article-title>. <source>J Ecol</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>933</fpage>–<lpage>950</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A new method for non‐parametric multivariate analysis of variance</article-title>. <source>Aust Ecol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warton</surname> <given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Distance‐based multivariate analyses confound location and dispersion effects</article-title>. <source>Methods Ecol Evol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">R project for Statistical computing (2013).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steets</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vamosi</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazer</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burd</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Pollen limitation of plant reproduction: pattern and process</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>497</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunne</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname> <given-names>ND</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Network structure and biodiversity loss in food webs: robustness increases with connectance</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>558</fpage>–<lpage>567</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgos</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ceva</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perazzo</surname> <given-names>RPJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devoto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medan</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Why nestedness in mutualistic networks?</article-title> <source>J Theor Biol</source> <volume>249</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17897679</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname> <given-names>MJO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Memmott</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The robustness of a network of ecological networks to habitat loss</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>844</fpage>–<lpage>852</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/ele.12117" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/ele.12117</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23692559</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">MATLAB and Statistics Toolbox Release 2007a, The MathWorks, Inc., Natick, Massachusetts, United States.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Confidence intervals rather than P values: estimation rather than hypothesis testing</article-title>. <source>British Med J</source> <volume>292</volume>: <fpage>746</fpage>–<lpage>750</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3082422</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ackerman</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roubik</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Can extinction risk help explain plant–pollinator specificity among euglossine bee pollinated plants?</article-title> <source>Oikos</source> <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>1821</fpage>–<lpage>1827</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheptou</surname> <given-names>P-O</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Clarifying Baker’s law</article-title>. <source>Ann Bot</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>633</fpage>–<lpage>641</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/aob/mcr127" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/aob/mcr127</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21685434</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roubik</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ackerman</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Long-term ecology of euglossine orchid-bees (Apidae: Euglossini) in Panama</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>333</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aizen</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vazquez</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <chapter-title>Flower performance in human-altered habitats</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Harder</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name>,<name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname> <given-names>SCH</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Ecology and evolution of flowers</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>. pp. <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuett</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vamosi</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetic community context influences pollen delivery to <italic>Allium cernuum</italic></article-title>. <source>Evolutionary biology</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cresswell</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A comparison of bumblebees’ movements in uniform and aggregated distributions of their forage plant</article-title>. <source>Ecol Ent</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bastolla</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fortuna</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pascual-García</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrera</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luque</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The architecture of mutualistic networks minimizes competition and increases biodiversity</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>458</volume>: <fpage>1018</fpage>–<lpage>1020</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature07950" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature07950</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19396144</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lever</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nes</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bascompte</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The sudden collapse of pollinator communities</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/ele.12236" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/ele.12236</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24386999</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aizen</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sabatino</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tylianakis</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Specialization and rarity predict nonrandom loss of interactions from mutualist networks</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>335</volume>: <fpage>1486</fpage>–<lpage>1489</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1215320" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1215320</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22442482</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allesina</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Stability criteria for complex ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>483</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature10832" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature10832</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22343894</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pitchford</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plank</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Disentangling nestedness from models of ecological complexity</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>487</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature11214" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature11214</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22722863</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Vieira MC, Almeida-Neto M (2014) A simple stochastic model for complex coextinctions in mutualistic networks: robustness decreases with connectance. Ecol Lett, in press.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bascompte</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jordano</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olesen</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Asymmetric coevolutionary networks facilitate biodiversity maintenance</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>312</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16627742</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guimarães</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rico-Gray</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dos Reis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname> <given-names>JN</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Asymmetries in specialization in ant–plant mutualistic networks</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc B</source> <volume>273</volume>: <fpage>2041</fpage>–<lpage>2047</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16846911</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortuna</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bascompte</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Habitat loss and the structure of plant–animal mutualistic networks</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>286</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16958893</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0117243.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McConkey</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corlett</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campos-Arceiz</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brodie</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Seed dispersal in changing landscapes</article-title>. <source>Biol Conserv</source> <volume>146</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>