<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125888</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-43616</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Recent Origin of the Methacrylate Redox System in <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 through Horizontal Gene Transfer</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Horizontal Gene Transfer of the Methacrylate Redox System</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Arkhipova</surname>
<given-names>Oksana V.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Meer</surname>
<given-names>Margarita V.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Mikoulinskaia</surname>
<given-names>Galina V.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff004" ref-type="aff"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zakharova</surname>
<given-names>Marina V.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Galushko</surname>
<given-names>Alexander S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff005" ref-type="aff"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff006" ref-type="aff"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" deceased="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Akimenko</surname>
<given-names>Vasilii K.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Kondrashov</surname>
<given-names>Fyodor A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff007" ref-type="aff"><sup>7</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Scryabin’s Institute of Biochemistry and Physiology of Microorganisms, Pushchino 142290, Russia</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Bioinformatics and Genomics Programme, Centre for Genomic Regulation (CRG) 88 Dr. Aiguader, 08003 Barcelona, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF), 08003 Barcelona, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Branch of Shemyakin &amp; Ovchinnikov’s Institute of Bioorganic Chemistry, Pushchino 142290, Russia</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff005"><label>5</label> <addr-line>Agrophysical Research Institute RAS, Saint-Petersburg 195220, Russia</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff006"><label>6</label> <addr-line>Tomsk State University, Tomsk, 634050, Russia</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff007"><label>7</label> <addr-line>Institució Catalana de Recerca i Estudis Avançats (ICREA), 23 Pg. Lluís Companys, 08010 Barcelona, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Weiner</surname>
<given-names>Joel H.</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Alberta, CANADA</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: OVA MVM GVM MVZ ASG VKA FAK. Performed the experiments: OVA MVM GVM MVZ FAK. Analyzed the data: OVA MVM GVM MVZ ASG FAK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: OVA MVM GVM MVZ FAK. Wrote the paper: OVA MVM ASG FAK.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">aroksan@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>11</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e0125888</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>28</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>5</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Arkhipova et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0125888" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<p>The origin and evolution of novel biochemical functions remains one of the key questions in molecular evolution. We study recently emerged methacrylate reductase function that is thought to have emerged in the last century and reported in <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> strain AM-1. We report the sequence and study the evolution of the operon coding for the flavin-containing methacrylate reductase (Mrd) and tetraheme cytochrome <italic>с</italic> (Mcc) in the genome of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1. Different types of signal peptides in functionally interlinked proteins Mrd and Mcc suggest a possible complex mechanism of biogenesis for chromoproteids of the methacrylate redox system. The homologs of the Mrd and Mcc sequence found in <italic>δ-Proteobacteria</italic> and <italic>Deferribacteres</italic> are also organized into an operon and their phylogenetic distribution suggested that these two genes tend to be horizontally transferred together. Specifically, the <italic>mrd</italic> and <italic>mcc</italic> genes from <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 are not monophyletic with any of the homologs found in other <italic>Geobacter</italic> genomes. The acquisition of methacrylate reductase function by <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 appears linked to a horizontal gene transfer event. However, the new function of the products of <italic>mrd</italic> and <italic>mcc</italic> may have evolved either prior or subsequent to their acquisition by <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The work has been supported by a grant of the HHMI International Early Career Scientist Program (55007424), the Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness (EUI-EURYIP-2011-4320) as part of the EMBO YIP program, two grants from the Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness, "Centro de Excelencia Severo Ochoa 2013–2017 (Sev-2012-0208)" and (BFU2012-31329), the European Union and the European Research Council under grant agreement 335980_EinME. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="5"/>
<table-count count="2"/>
<page-count count="15"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All generated data are available from the GenBank sequence repository with accession number CP010430.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Anaerobic bacteria frequently use unsaturated organic compounds as terminal electron acceptors [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Among such forms of respiration, fumarate respiration of anaerobes has been studied most extensively [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. During fumarate respiration bacterial cells reduce fumarate in the cytosol (e.g. <italic>Wolinella succinogenes</italic> and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>) or in the periplasm (as in <italic>Shewanella</italic>). The cytosolic fumarate-reducing enzyme complex is located at the inner side of the cytoplasmic membrane and consists of 3 or 4 protein subunits [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Periplasmic fumarate reductases of the bacterial genus <italic>Shewanella</italic> are soluble monomers belonging to the flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic> family [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Data on enzyme systems and electron transport chain components that use other double-bond compounds as terminal electron acceptors are often fragmentary and contradictory or completely absent [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p>
<p>Anaerobic bacterium <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 was isolated in the study of decomposition of methacrylate industry waste [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 strain is capable of complete oxidation of acetate coupled to reduction of methacrylate (2-methylpropenoate), an anthropogenic compound that serves as the terminal acceptor of the bacterial reductase chain [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The study of <italic>Geobacter</italic> species (<italic>Deltaproteobacteria</italic>) is of applied interest due to their significant role in bioremediation of radioactive metals [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. They serve as important agents in the global cycles of metals and carbon, reducing Fe(III) to Fe(II) and U(VI) to U(IV), oxidizing acetate and other organic compounds and participating in humus decomposition. Furthermore, they are fumarate-respiring organisms [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and electrotrophs [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p>
<p>Transformation of methacrylate to isobutyrate occurs in the periplasm of bacterium <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> АМ-1 [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] by the periplasmic flavin-containing methacrylate reductase Mrd (50 kDa) [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Mrd activity depends on periplasmic tetraheme cytochrome <italic>c</italic> Mcc (30 kDa), which is the physiological electron donor for this enzyme. Furthermore, the two-component methacrylate redox system catalyzes reduction of acrylate, which is a compound found in nature [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], at a rate comparable to that for synthetic methacrylate, while lacking fumarate reduction [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p>
<p>Membranes of bacterium <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> АМ-1 contain menaquinone-8 (menaquinone with 8 isoprene residues in the side chain), which transfers reducing equivalents to the methacrylate redox system from the citric acid cycle [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The electron carrier from menaquinone to Mcc remains unknown, although the periplasmic cytochromes <italic>c</italic> (12.5 and 15.5 kDa) and the membrane cytochrome <italic>c</italic> (67.6 kDa) are possible candidates [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p>
<p>N-terminal amino acid sequences, 27 and 29 amino acids in length, respectively, were identified from purified Mrd and Mcc [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Previous analysis suggested that the Mrd sequence was homologous to flavocytochromes <italic>c</italic> in several bacterial and a few archaeal genomes [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, the length of the Mrd fragment was not long enough to perform a comprehensive sequence analysis of the two proteins that have recently evolved into the methacrylate redox system. Furthermore, the Mcc amino acid sequence has not been investigated.</p>
<p>Methacrylate, a common monomer in polymer plastics and resins, is strictly a man-made molecule [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. It is also the main substrate of the methacrylate redox system and, therefore, methacrylate-based respiration might have evolved sometime in the second half of the 20<sup>th</sup> century. The <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 strain is the only one known strain capable of methacrylate respiration [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and, therefore, the sequences of the methacrylate redox system genes provide an unparalleled opportunity to study the evolutionary history of a novel system of respiration.</p>
<p>Here we report the sequence of the two genes of the methacrylate redox system from the <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> АМ-1 genome, analyze their translation products and study their evolutionary origins.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Organization of the mrd and mcc genes in the Geobacter sulfurreducens AM-1 genome</title>
<p>We sequenced the genome of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1, obtaining a draft with a single contig. To localize the <italic>mrd</italic> and <italic>mcc</italic> genes, we mapped the previously identified short 27 and 29 amino acid sequences [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] to the genome sequence. We found that the genes coding for Mrd and Mcc were arranged linearly and organized in one transcription unit (<xref rid="pone.0125888.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). The <italic>mrd</italic> gene (1581 bp) was separated by 56 nucleotides from <italic>mcc</italic> (696 bp). The genes were flanked by a transposase gene 3297 nucleotides upstream of <italic>mrd</italic> separated from <italic>mrd</italic> by two pseudogenes and GTP cyclohydrolase gene 505 nucleotides downstream of <italic>mcc</italic>. Both flanking genes have the same orientation as <italic>mrd</italic> and <italic>mcc</italic>.</p>
<fig id="pone.0125888.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Organization of the operon of the methacrylate redox system in <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1.</title>
<p>The putative promoter is marked as small flag, ρ-independent transcriptional terminators are marked by parentheses. Conservative sequences of promoter -35, -10 and sites of the binding of transcriptional factors are enclosed in frames.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Putative promoter sites were found in close proximity to the predicted start codon. The sequences found 75 to 97 bp upstream of the translation start codon are similar to the consensus promoter sequences typically found -10 to -35 from the transcription start site. Furthermore, two transcription factor binding sites are predicted in this region, supporting the hypothesis that the promoter is a common regulatory element of the redox operon. A potential ρ-independent transcriptional terminator (energy of terminator -8.9) was found 75 nucleotides downstream of <italic>mcc</italic>. A second potential transcriptional terminator (terminator energy -9.4) is located in the spacer between the two genes and partially overlapped the <italic>mcc</italic> gene. The extra transcription termination signal located between the genes in the operon implies a complex regulation of the redox system at the transcriptional level.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Evolution of the methacrylate redox system</title>
<p>To elucidate the evolutionary history of the methacrylate redox system, we searched for orthologues of <italic>mrd</italic> and <italic>mcc</italic>. First, we searched for homologs in the eleven <italic>Geobacter</italic> genomes available in GenBank. For <italic>mrd</italic> the closest homologs by protein sequence divergence were found in three strains: <italic>G</italic>. <italic>lovleyi</italic> SZ (YP_001951186.1, YP_001953845.1, YP_001953762.1), <italic>G</italic>. <italic>bemidjiensis</italic> Bem (YP_002140822.1, YP_002140385.1) and <italic>Geobacter</italic> sp. M21 (YP_003023900.1) (<xref rid="pone.0125888.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125888.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2a</xref>). One of the homologs from <italic>G</italic>. <italic>lovleyi</italic> SZ, capable of chlororespiration, was the only protein from this list (YP_001951186.1) that does not contain the heme-binding sites CXXCH. Other homologous sequences found in <italic>Geobacter</italic> genomes have 4 heme-binding sites and different regions of their sequence are homologous to either Mrd or Mcc from the methacrylate redox system of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 (Tables <xref rid="pone.0125888.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0125888.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref>; Fig <xref rid="pone.0125888.g002" ref-type="fig">2a</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0125888.g002" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). Homology of Mcc from <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 was observed for N-terminal amino acid sequence of <italic>Geobacter</italic> species flavocytochromes (usually 125 amino acids from the N-terminus). Sequence identity of Mrd with the flavocytochromes was higher (see column 5 of Tables <xref rid="pone.0125888.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0125888.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref>) than for the region homologous to Mcc, and found in the C-terminal region (usually between the 140<sup>th</sup> and 590<sup>th</sup> amino acids). Thus, the methacrylate redox system homologs of bacteria of the genus <italic>Geobacter</italic> are often present as one multifunctional flavoprotein, combining functions of electron delivery and catalysis of reduction.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0125888.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Homologs of methacrylate reductase (Mrd).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0125888.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank accession number</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annotated function</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Similarity / Identity</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of alignment with Mrd, e-value</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length, calculated Mr (kDa) of immature protein</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of cleavable signal peptide (length)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tat-motif</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heme-binding sites CXXCH</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>methacrylate reductase</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>100/100</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>526 aa 57.2 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tat (55 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RRDFLK</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Anaeromyxobacter</italic> sp. K</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_002134140.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>78/64</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>96, 0.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>515 aa 55.5 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tat (38 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RRAMLK</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Anaeromyxobacter dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_002492269.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>78/64</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>96, 0.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>515 aa 55.6 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tat (38 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RRAMLK</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Anaeromyxobacter dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-C</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_465303.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>78/62</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>96, 0.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>515 aa 55.7 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tat (38 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RRAILK</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Desulfatibacillum alkenivorans</italic> AK-01</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_002429921.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>78/65</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>95, 0.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>511 aa 54.9 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tat (42 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RRSVIK</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Deferribacteres</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Denitrovibrio acetiphilus</italic> DSM 12809</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_003505239.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>78/62</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>95, 0.0</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>507 aa 55.0 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tat (40 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RRGLLQ</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter lovleyi</italic> SZ</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_001951186.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>53/39</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>96, 8e</bold><sup><bold>-97</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>517 aa 56.0 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tat (43 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RRSFLK</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter lovleyi</italic> SZ</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_001953845.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>54/39</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>87, 2e</bold><sup><bold>-71</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>596 aa 63.3 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (25 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter lovleyi</italic> SZ</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_001953762.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>51/38</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>90, 5e</bold><sup><bold>-72</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>589 aa 61.7 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (26 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter bemidjiensis</italic> Bem</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_002140822.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>55/40</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>88, 1e</bold><sup><bold>-78</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>598 aa 63.3 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (25 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter bemidjiensis</italic> Bem</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_002140385.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>51/38</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>88, 5e</bold><sup><bold>-72</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>591 aa 61.5 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (21–27 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter</italic> sp. M21</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_003023900.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>55/40</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>88, 1e</bold><sup><bold>-78</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>598 aa 63.2 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (25 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Γ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Shewanella frigidimarina</italic> NCIMB 400</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_749210.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>55/38</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>95, 8e</bold><sup><bold>-91</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>510 aa 54.9 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tat (35 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RRHFLK</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Γ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Shewanella frigidimarina</italic> NCIMB 400</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_751265.1 (Ifc</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>53/36</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>86, 3e</bold><sup><bold>-76</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>588 aa 63 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (22 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Γ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Shewanella frigidimarina</italic> NCIMB 400</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_751192.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>50/34</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>93, 1e</bold><sup><bold>-64</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>507 aa 53.8 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tat (34 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RRNIIK</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Γ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Shewanella oneidensis</italic> MR-1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NP_716599.1 (Fcc</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>periplasmic fumarate reductase FccA</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>54/38</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>86, 2e</bold><sup><bold>-72</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>596 aa 62.4 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (25 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Γ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Shewanella oneidensis</italic> MR-1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NP_720136.1<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>urocanate reductase SO_4620</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>39/36</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>89, 2e</bold><sup><bold>-83</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>582 aa 62.2 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (30 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Γ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Shewanella frigidimarina</italic> NCIMB 400</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Q07WU7.2<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Periplasmic fumarate reductase; flavocytochrome c</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>51/35</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>84, 2e</bold><sup><bold>-63</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>596 aa 63.0 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (25 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Е-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Wolinella succinogenes</italic> DSM 1740</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NP_906388.1<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic> flavin subunit FccA</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>51/35</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>87, 2e</bold><sup><bold>-67</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>515 aa 55.9 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tat (34 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RRDLIK</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>* The last three proteins in the table have lower sequence similarity with methacrylate reductase. They were included in the table as they have been characterized biochemically.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0125888.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Homologs of cytochrome <italic>c</italic> (Mcc).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0125888.t002g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank accession number</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annotated function</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Similarity / Identity</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of alignment with Mcc, e-value</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length, calculated Mr (kDa) of immature protein</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of cleavable signal peptide (length)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heme-binding sites CXXCH</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>cytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>100/100</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>231 aa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (23 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4–7</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Anaeromyxobacter</italic> sp. K</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_002134139.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hypothetical protein AnaeK_1781</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>55/42</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>84, 9e</bold><sup><bold>-40</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>221 aa 22.9 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (21–24 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Anaeromyxobacter dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_002492268.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hypothetical protein A2cp1_1860</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>56/42</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>85, 2e</bold><sup><bold>-39</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>221 aa 22.9 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (24 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Anaeromyxobacter dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-C</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_465304.1<xref rid="t002fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hypothetical protein Adeh_2097</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>56/42</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>84, 3e</bold><sup><bold>-47</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>233 aa 24.1 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (24 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Desulfatibacillum alkenivorans</italic> AK-01</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_002429920.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hypothetical protein Dalk_0747</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>51/40</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>44, 2e</bold><sup><bold>-15</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>109 aa 12.1 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>no</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Deferribacteres</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Denitrovibrio acetiphilus</italic> DSM 12809</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_003505238.1<xref rid="t002fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hypothetical protein Dacet_2522</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>48/36</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>94, 1e</bold><sup><bold>-32</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>208 aa 22.9 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (18 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter lovleyi</italic> SZ</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_001953845.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>54/44</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>42, 1e</bold><sup><bold>-13</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>596 aa 63.3 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (25 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter lovleyi</italic> SZ</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_001953762.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>50/39</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>42, 4e</bold><sup><bold>-10</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>589 aa 61.7 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (26 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter bemidjiensis</italic> Bem</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_002140822.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>48/42</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>41, 2e</bold><sup><bold>-11</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>598 aa 63.3 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (25 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter bemidjiensis</italic> Bem</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_002140385.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>59/44</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>35, 1e</bold><sup><bold>-12</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>591 aa 61.5 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (21–27 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter</italic> sp. M18</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_004200524.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>62/51</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>35, 3e</bold><sup><bold>-14</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>584 aa 60.7 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (22–23 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Δ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Geobacter</italic> sp. M21</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_003023900.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>48/42</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>41, 7e</bold><sup><bold>-11</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>598 aa 63.2 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (25 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Γ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Shewanella frigidimarina</italic> NCIMB 400</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Q07WU7.2 (Fcc</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>fumarate reductase flavoprotein subunit; flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>53/38</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>48, 6e</bold><sup><bold>-11</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>596 aa 63.0 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (25 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Shewanella frigidimarina</italic> NCIMB 400</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_751265.1 (Ifc</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome c</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>51/39</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>40,1e</bold><sup><bold>-09</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>588 aa 63 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (22 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Γ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Shewanella frigidimarina</italic> NCIMB 400</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YP_751191.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>tetraheme cytochrome <italic>c</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>50/34</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>41, 6e</bold><sup><bold>-07</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>122 aa 13.9 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (22 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Γ-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Shewanella oneidensis</italic> MR-1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NP_716599.1 (Fcc</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>periplasmic fumarate reductase FccA</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>59/46</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>35, 3e</bold><sup><bold>-10</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>596 aa 62.4 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (25 амк)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Β-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Parasutterella excrementihominis</italic> YIT 11859</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>WP_008864032.1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hypothetical protein HMPREF9439_01147</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>50/33</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>80, 7e</bold><sup><bold>-25</bold></sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>208 aa 22.7 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (19 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6–7</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Е-Proteobacteria</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Wolinella succinogenes</italic> DSM 1740</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NP_906387.1<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic> heme subunit</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>44/28</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>51, 0.002</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>146 aa 16.6 kDa</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sec (26 aa)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>*Annotated by us.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p>**The last protein in the table has lower sequence similarity than others. It was included because it has been characterized biochemically.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="pone.0125888.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Phylogeny reconstructions for Mrd (A) and Mcc (B) homologs.</title>
<p>Unrooted trees are shown with posterior probabilities. Unlabeled nodes have a posterior probability of 1. The following sequences were used. A (Mrd): <italic>D</italic>. <italic>alkenivorans</italic> AK-01 (YP_002429921.1), <italic>D</italic>. <italic>acetiphilus</italic> DSM 12809 (YP_003505239.1), <italic>A</italic>. <italic>dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-1 (YP_002492269.1), <italic>A</italic>. <italic>dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-C (YP_465303.1), <italic>S</italic>. <italic>marimammalium</italic> (WP_018370472.1), <italic>S</italic>. <italic>frigidimarina</italic> NCIMB 400 (YP_751265.1), <italic>G</italic>. <italic>lovleyi</italic> SZ (YP_001953845.1, YP_001953762.1), <italic>G</italic>. <italic>bemidjiensis</italic> Bem (YP_002140822.1, YP_002140385.1), <italic>Geobacter</italic> sp. M21 (YP_003023900.1). B (Mcc): <italic>P</italic>. <italic>excrementihominis</italic> YIT 11859 (WP_008864032.1), <italic>D</italic>. <italic>alkenivorans</italic> AK-01 (YP_002429920.1), <italic>D</italic>. <italic>acetiphilus</italic> DSM 12809 (YP_003505238.1), <italic>A</italic>. <italic>dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-C (YP_465304.1), <italic>G</italic>. <italic>bemidjiensis</italic> Bem (YP_002140822.1, YP_002140385.1), <italic>G</italic>. <italic>lovleyi</italic> SZ (YP_001953845.1), <italic>G</italic>. sp. M18 (YP_004200524.1), <italic>G</italic>. sp. M21 (YP_003023900.1).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>A diversity of other cytochrome <italic>c</italic> protein sequences were found to be coded in <italic>Geobacter</italic> genomes [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], which were much more diverged than the <italic>Geobacter</italic> homologs we considered in our phylogenetic analysis. None of these distantly related genes were considered in our analysis.</p>
<p>Homologs of both Mrd and Mcc with higher sequence identity were found outside the <italic>Geobacter</italic> genus in a few species with a broad phylogenetic distribution, indicating a complex evolutionary origin of these proteins in <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1. The distribution of Mrd homologs varied across bacterial clades. The closest of the identifiable Mrd homologs (78% similarity; <xref rid="pone.0125888.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125888.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2a</xref>), which were annotated as flavoproteins, were from <italic>δ-Proteobacteria</italic>: <italic>Anaeromyxobacter dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-C (YP_465303.1), <italic>A</italic>. <italic>dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-1 (YP_002492269.1), <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sp</italic>. K (YP_002134140.1) and <italic>Desulfatibacillum alkenivorans</italic> AK-01 (YP_002429921.1) and <italic>Deferribacteres</italic>: <italic>Denitrovibrio acetiphilus</italic> DSM 12809 (YP_003505239.1).</p>
<p>Interestingly, the same species that harbor the closest homologs of Mrd also have the closest homologs of Mcc (48–58% similarity; <xref rid="pone.0125888.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125888.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2b</xref>): <italic>A</italic>. <italic>dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-C (YP_465304.1), <italic>A</italic>. <italic>dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-1 (YP_002492268.1), <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sp</italic>. K (YP_002134139.1), <italic>D</italic>. <italic>alkenivorans</italic> AK-01 (YP_002429920.1), <italic>D</italic>. <italic>acetiphilus</italic> DSM 12809 (YP_003505238.1). We annotated them as multiheme cytochrome <italic>c</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0125888.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The redox systems of these organisms were represented by two proteins with their genes organized in one transcriptional unit. The only exception to having a close homologue of both Mdr and Mcc was <italic>Parasutterella excrementihominis</italic> YIT 11859 (β-Proteobacterium) that had a close homolog only of Mcc (WP_008864032.1, <xref rid="pone.0125888.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125888.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2b</xref>).</p>
<p>To confirm that the <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 Mrd and Mcc homologs found in other <italic>Geobacter</italic> species are not their direct orthologues, we performed a phylogenetic analysis of the homologs, including several of the sequences from the <italic>Geobacter</italic> genus that were most similar to Mrd of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1. The analysis showed that <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 Mrd and Mcc share a closer common ancestor with sequences from distant clades of bacteria, confirming that the methacrylate redox system genes, <italic>mrd</italic> and <italic>mcc</italic>, were likely acquired by <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 through recent horizontal gene transfer and that their orthologues are not present in the sequenced <italic>Geobacter</italic> genomes (Fig <xref rid="pone.0125888.g002" ref-type="fig">2a</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0125888.g002" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Products of the methacrylate redox system genes</title>
<p>The protein coded by <italic>mrd</italic> has 526 amino acids (Mr 57.2 kDa). The N-terminal amino acid sequence contains a 55 amino acid-long signal peptide with the Tat-motif RRDFLK in position 25 (<xref rid="pone.0125888.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125888.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Thus, the mature protein is predicted to contain 471 amino acids (estimated Mr 51.4 kDa). Previous results have shown that the mature Mrd has 1 mol FAD [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]; therefore, the Mr of the mature Mrd with FAD should be 52.2 kDa, which is consistent with experimental data. We validated the start and flanking regions of <italic>mrd</italic> by Sanger sequencing of both strands, which were identical to the sequences obtained through the next generation sequencing of the entire genome. Thus, the unusually long predicted signal peptide was confirmed not to result from sequencing or assembly error.</p>
<fig id="pone.0125888.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Multiple protein sequence alignment of Mrd coded in <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 and its closest flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic> homologs from <italic>Desulfatibacillum alkenivorans</italic> AK-01 (YP_002429921.1); <italic>Denitrovibrio acetiphilus</italic> DSM 12809 (YP_003505239.1) and <italic>Anaeromyxobacter dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-1 (YP_002492269.1).</title>
<p>Amino acid sequences of Mrd homologs (YP_002134140.1, YP_002492269.1, YP_465303.1) of all three mentioned representatives of the genus <italic>Anaeromyxobacter</italic> are very similar. Therefore, we used the sequences of the Mrd homolog only from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-1 (YP_002492269.1) as one representative of the genus. Cleavable signal peptides of Tat type are underlined; the Tat motif is shown in bold. Conserved pyrophosphate-binding sites and amino acids presumably involved in catalysis are highlighted in green. Probable proton donor is marked in red.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The <italic>mcc</italic> gene codes for a protein 231 amino acids long (Mr 24.5 kDa). The N-terminal region contains a shorter Sec-type signal peptide of 23 amino acids (<xref rid="pone.0125888.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125888.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) with the mature protein predicted to have 208 amino acids (Mr 22.1 kDa). Previous experiments showed that the mature Mcc had 4 mol of heme <italic>c</italic> and a Mr of nearly 30 kDa [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Consistent with these results, we found four heme-binding motifs CXXCH [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] with the GENE RUNNER program. The Mr of a mature Mcc with 4 hemes is 24.8 kDa, substantially lower than expected. A visual analysis of the Mcc sequence revealed three more heme-binding motifs CXXCH, which brought the Mr of the mature Mcc with 7 hemes to 27.9 kDa (<xref rid="pone.0125888.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0125888.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Multiple protein sequence alignment of Mcc from <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 and its cytochrome <italic>c</italic> homologs from <italic>Anaeromyxobacter dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-1 (YP_002492268.1); <italic>Parasutterella excrementihominis</italic> YIT 11859 (WP_008864032.1) and <italic>Denitrovibrio acetiphilus</italic> DSM 12809 (YP_003505238.1).</title>
<p>Amino acid sequences of Mcc homologs (YP_002134139.1, YP_002492268.1, YP_465304.1) of all three representatives of the genus <italic>Anaeromyxobacter</italic> are very similar. We used the sequences of the Mcc homolog only from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>dehalogenans</italic> 2CP-1 (YP_002492268.1) as one representative of the genus. The amino acid sequences of protein YP_002429920 from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>alkenivorans</italic> AK-01 (YP_002429920.1), which is not shown here, is much shorter than those included, which makes it difficult to analyze. Cleavable signal peptides of Sec type are underlined. Heme-binding sites are marked in italics and highlighted in yellow. Sites, detected by GENERUNR program, are in bold.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The closest of the identifiable homologs of Mrd (<xref rid="pone.0125888.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2a</xref>) are likely FAD-binding proteins and flavocytochromes <italic>c</italic>, as indicated by the conserved phosphate-binding regions of N-termini (<xref rid="pone.0125888.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). The phosphate-binding site is typical for all FAD- and NAD(P)H-dependent oxidoreductases: xhxhGxGxxGxxxhxxh(x)<sub>8</sub>hxhE(D), where x—any amino acid, h—hydrophobic amino acid [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In the case of Mrd this site was located between amino acids 69 and 98 of the immature protein (<xref rid="pone.0125888.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). The central part of the consensus, GxGxxG, is a glycine-rich part of the loop, linking the first β-sheet in the Rossmann fold with the first α-helix directed to the pyrophosphate residue for charge compensation. Generally this motif has β-strand-turn-β-strand structure and forms a flexible clamp, surrounding and anchoring the pyrophosphate of FAD [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Another conservative FAD-binding site, which is an eleven amino acid segment T(S)xxxxxF(Y)hhGD(E) [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], was present in amino acid sequences of Mrd and its homologs. The site was slightly truncated, without the first threonine while all other amino acids were present (487–491).</p>
<p>The heme-binding sites of Mcc homologs identified by the phylogenetic analysis (<xref rid="pone.0125888.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2b</xref>) are shown in <xref rid="pone.0125888.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>. Their presence suggests that these homologs, not annotated as having any function, are cytochromes <italic>c</italic>, containing four heme-binding sites (YP_002429920.1) in <italic>D</italic>. <italic>alkenivorans</italic> AK-01 or seven heme-binding sites in the other species.</p>
<p>The Mrd sequence of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 had a higher level of similarity with its homologs (<xref rid="pone.0125888.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) than Mcc of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 (<xref rid="pone.0125888.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). This observation is consistent with a relatively poor conservation of cytochromes <italic>c</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and probably with evolutionary early origin of the flavin-containing Mrd homologs.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The methacrylate redox system genes in the genome of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 appear to be arranged in a single operon. The clear absence of orthologs in the genomes of several other <italic>Geobacter</italic> genomes, coupled with a lack of closely-related orthologs in genomes of bacteria from any other closely related genus, strongly suggests that the methacrylate redox system genes were acquired recently by the <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 strain (<xref rid="pone.0125888.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). The intriguing similarity of the phylogenetic distribution of the closely related homologs of both genes, <italic>mrd</italic> and <italic>mcc</italic>, suggests that these two genes tend to be horizontally transferred together, confirming their close functional relationship. The high congruence of the evolutionary history of the <italic>mrd</italic> and <italic>mcc</italic> genes is consistent with their organization into a single operon and confirms their joint functional role.</p>
<fig id="pone.0125888.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title>An unrooted phylogeny reconstruction of 16s RNA from the strains coding for <italic>mrd</italic> and <italic>mcc</italic> homologs or from their closest relatives.</title>
<p>The branch on which the horizontal gene transfer of the operon carrying the <italic>mrd</italic> and <italic>mcc</italic> genes has occurred is indicated by a red mark.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0125888.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Unfortunately, for most of the identified homologs experimental data of their enzyme specificity are not available. Such lack of experimental data precludes us from understanding whether or not the acquisition of the methacrylate reducing function occurred before or after the horizontal gene transfer. Furthermore, even the closest of the identified homologs were evidently too diverged to be identified as the origin of the horizontal gene transfer. This conclusion is based on the observation of the divergence of Mrd and Mcc sequences from their closest homologs in comparison to the high similarity of genomes of different <italic>Geobacter</italic> species.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, some experimentally characterized proteins can be distinguished among the homologs of the methacrylate redox system. The characterized homologs of Mrd include flavoprotein FccA (NP_906388.1) from <italic>Wolinella succinogenes</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], an urocanate reductase SO_4620 (NP_720136.1; [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]) and periplasmic fumarate reductases Fcc<sub>3</sub> (Q07WU7.2; [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125888.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]), Ifc<sub>3</sub> (YP_751265.1; [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]) and Fcc<sub>3</sub> (NP_716599.1; [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]) from bacteria of the genus <italic>Shewanella</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0125888.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). <italic>Shewanella</italic>’s periplasmic fumarate reductases are cytochromes <italic>c</italic> homologs as well (<xref rid="pone.0125888.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Therefore, the methacrylate redox system and its homologs reduce the double bonds of unsaturated organic compounds (such as acrylate, methacrylate, urocanate, fumarate), using them as terminal acceptors of reducing equivalents. None of the species or strains described previously are known to grow by respiration of methacrylate.</p>
<p>Conserved amino acids (histidine-461 and arginines—R501 and R353, <xref rid="pone.0125888.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>), found in the Mrd sequence, may stabilize the transition state during catalysis by providing delocalization of the negative charge of the intermediate carbanion, in a similar manner as in <italic>Shewanella</italic> fumarate reductases [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Point mutagenesis showed that the arginine homologous to R353 of Mrd is the proton donor for the carbanion [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The fumarate reductase arginine homologous to R501 in Mrd interacts through its guanidino group with both oxygen atoms of a carboxyl group of succinate, positioning it parallel to the isoalloxazine ring [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Mrd does not have two other conserved residues that interact with succinate or fumarate. It has a tryptophan instead of histidine at position 311 and valine instead of serine or threonine at position 324. Since these amino acids are also involved in substrate binding, it is possible that their absence is due to substrate specificity of Mrd of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1.</p>
<p>Biogenesis of chromoproteids of the methacrylate redox system probably occurs via different mechanisms. The immature Mrd protein has a longer and less hydrophobic Tat-type signal peptide sequence (<xref rid="pone.0125888.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125888.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>), characteristic for <italic>Bacteria</italic>, <italic>Archaea</italic> and chloroplast proteins. Such proteins are transported through the membrane after folding [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. A Sec-type signal peptide sequence was found in the immature Mcc protein (<xref rid="pone.0125888.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125888.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). Such proteins are translocated across the membrane before the acquisition of tertiary structure [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], with heme attachment occurring in the periplasm [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Thus, both the Tat- and Sec-type secretory mechanisms are likely to be required for maturation of the methacrylate redox system proteins.</p>
<p>Genes of the methacrylate redox system components of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 are organized similarly to genes for their closest homologs in four representatives of <italic>δ-Proteobacteria</italic> and one representative of <italic>Deferribacteres</italic> (see <xref rid="sec002" ref-type="sec">RESULTS</xref>). Thus, it is possible that these organisms may also either be able to grow using methacrylate as a terminal electron acceptor or at least show some methacrylate-reducing activity.</p>
<p>The methacrylate redox system is representative of a comprehensive family of flavocytochromes <italic>c</italic> and flavoproteins with reducing properties. These reducing complexes probably use a natural substrate, for example, acrylate produced by marine bacteria [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The rates of reduction of acrylate and methacrylate by the methacrylate redox system are comparable [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] supporting the hypothesis of the use of some natural substrate by these proteins. Methacrylate reduction may be an additional characteristic of this redox system.</p>
<p>Components of the methacrylate redox system from <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 and lyase of dimethylsulphoniopropionate (DMSP) of DddY-type from marine microorganisms have some similar features: 1) a distribution in certain groups of proteobacteia, 2) gene organization with cytochrome <italic>c</italic> genes adjacent to the enzyme genes (reductase or lyase) and 3) presence of cleavable signal peptide in the immature enzymes. The enzyme DddY catalyzes the cleavage of DMSP to the volatile compound dimethyl sulphide (DMS) and the toxic acrylate [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. We suggest that the reductase evolved to transform the toxic acrylate, formed by lyases, to a less toxic compound. These cytochromes <italic>c</italic>, whose genes are located near the reductase or lyase genes, may be homologous.</p>
<p>The methacrylate redox system evolved from a cytochrome <italic>c</italic> and a flavoprotein. These proteins were recently acquired by horizontal gene transfer by <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 either before or after the evolution of the substrate specificity. Furthermore, these proteins likely constitute an adaptive mechanism to allow growth in sludge microbial communities, in particular, in wastewater of plastic manufacture factories.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Experimental Procedures</title>
<p>The <italic>object of investigation</italic> was anaerobic bacterium <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 from the culture collection of Laboratory of microorganisms adaptation at the Institute of Biochemistry and Physiology of Microorganisms (Pushchino, Russia).</p>
<p>The <italic>subject of investigation</italic> was the operon containing genes <italic>mrd</italic> and <italic>mcc</italic> of the methacrylate redox system of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1.</p>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Genome sequencing</title>
<p>The draft genome sequences were obtained by pair-end library and mate pair library sequences by Illumina HiSeq 2000. The resulting contigs were submitted to GenBank under the accession numbers of CP010430.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Genome assembly</title>
<p>The genome was assembled de novo using SOAPdenovo [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], Velvet [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] and SPAdes Genome Assembler [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The quality of assembly was estimated by running QUAST [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and by aligning of the contigs to the full genomes of <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> available in GenBank: <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> KN400 and <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> PCA. The alignments were done with Mauve [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].</p>
<p>The contigs obtained by SPAdes turned out to be the best. Nevertheless, SPAdes failed to assemble the genome into one sequence. We used SSPACE [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] for scaffolding. This allowed us to obtain the genome as just one contig. After this we applied GapFiller [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] for closing gaps.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Sequence analysis</title>
<p><italic>Detection of the mrd and mcc</italic> genes of the bacterium <italic>G</italic>. <italic>sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 and <italic>comparative amino acid analysis</italic> were performed with the BLAST program [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] from the National Center of Biotechnology Information server, National Library of Medicine, USA (NCBI; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>).</p>
<p><italic>Analysis of nucleotide sequences</italic> of the studied operon was carried out using the Vector NTI program [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The presence and types of <italic>promoters and terminators</italic> were detected with a series of programs, available on the site <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://linux1.softberry.com/" xlink:type="simple">http://linux1.softberry.com</ext-link>.</p>
<p><italic>The sequencing of the mrd start and mrd flanking regions</italic> was performed by the Sanger method with oligonucleotide primers FA2 (<monospace>5’-ACGCTTCTCAACCAGACCGG</monospace>) and RA2 (<monospace>5’-CATCGGTCCAAGCGTTATATTCAC</monospace>). Amplification for the nucleotide sequencing was performed by the PCR method using oligonucleotide primers—FG1 (<monospace>5’-CAGAACAGGCCACGCTTTGC</monospace>) and RG1 (<monospace>5’- GTGCGGTACTTGCTGTGCCC</monospace>).</p>
<p>All amino acid sequences of proteins and nucleotide sequences of genes are available in the <italic>Databases</italic> GenBank, Gene, Genome, Nucleotide, Protein from the server of the NCBI.</p>
<p><italic>Determination of the cleavable signal peptides</italic> was conducted with the programs PRED-TAT [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] and SignalP [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], available on servers of the Department of Computer Science and Biomedical Informatics, University of Central Greece, Lamia, Greece (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.compgen.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.compgen.org</ext-link>) and the Center for Biological Sequence Analysis, Department of Systems Biology, Technical University of Denmark, Lyngby, Denmark (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk</ext-link>).</p>
<p>Program GENERUNR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.generunner.net/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.generunner.net</ext-link>) was used for the <italic>detection of conserved amino acid sequences and calculation of molecular weight</italic>. The number of hemes in homological proteins was predicted as number of heme-binding sites CXXCH (where C is cysteine, H is histidine, X is any amino acid) [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p>
<p><italic>Multiple protein sequence alignment</italic> of methacrylate redox system components and their homologs was performed with MUSCLE [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Phylogenies were reconstructed using the MrBayes v3.2 program [<xref rid="pone.0125888.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], with mcmc = 3000000 and burnin = 2500 for sump and sumt.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>Our author Dr., Prof. Akimenko Vasilii K. (1942–2013) passed away during work on the article. Prof. Akimenko was a leading biochemist in IBPM RAS and active researcher until last days. A number of his work remains unfinished. We mourn premature care of Prof. Akimenko Vasilii.</p>
<p>We thank Heinz Himmelbauer and the CRG Genomic Unit for the sequencing.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arkhipova</surname> <given-names>OV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akimenko</surname> <given-names>VK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Unsaturated organic acids as terminal electron acceptors for reductase chains of anaerobic bacteria</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source> <year>2005</year>;<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ackrell</surname> <given-names>BAC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gunsalus</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cecchini</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Structure and function of succinate dehydrogenase and fumarate reductase</chapter-title>. <source>Chemistry and biochemistry of flavoenzymes</source> Ed. <name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, Florida</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hägerhäll</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Succinate:quinone oxidoreductases. Variations on a conserved theme</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>1320</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9210286</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemos</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miguel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quinol:fumarate oxidoreductases and succinate: quinone oxidoreductases: phylogenetic relationships, metal centres and membrane attachment</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <year>2002</year>;<volume>1553</volume>: <fpage>158</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11803024</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iverson</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Catalytic mechanisms of complex II enzymes: A structural perspective</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>1827</volume>: <fpage>648</fpage>–<lpage>657</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bbabio.2012.09.008" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.bbabio.2012.09.008</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22995215</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kröger</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Bacterial electron transport to fumarate</chapter-title>. <source>Diversity of bacterial respiratory systems</source> Ed. <name name-style="western"><surname>Knowles</surname> <given-names>C.J.</given-names></name> <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, Florida</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>. <year>1980</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kröger</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geisler</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemma</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Theis</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenger</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bacterial fumarate respiration</article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source> <year>1992</year>;<volume>158</volume>: <fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kröger</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Unden</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fumarate respiration of <italic>Wolinella succinogenes</italic>: enzymology, energetics and coupling mechanism</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <year>2002</year>;<volume>1553</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11803015</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pealing</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manson</surname> <given-names>FDC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sequence of the gene encoding flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic> from <italic>Shewanella putrefaciens</italic>: a tetraheme flavoenzyme that is a soluble fumarate reductase related to the membrane-bound enzymes from other bacteria</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <year>1992</year>;<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>12132</fpage>–<lpage>12140</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pealing</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manson</surname> <given-names>FDC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Purification and properties of a novel cytochrome: flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic> from <italic>Shewanella putrefaciens</italic></article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <year>1994</year>;<volume>302</volume>: <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>593</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8093012</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobbin</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butt</surname> <given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Characterization of a flavocytochrome that is induced during the anaerobic respiration of Fe<sup>3+</sup> by <italic>Shewanella frigidimarina</italic> NCIMB 400</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <year>1999</year>;<volume>342</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10455032</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bamford</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobbin</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hemmings</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Open conformation of a flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>3</italic></sub> fumarate reductase</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Biol</source> <year>1999</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1104</fpage>–<lpage>1107</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10581549</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsapin</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenberghe</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nealson</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cusanovich</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Identification of a small tetraheme cytochrome <italic>c</italic> and a flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic> as two of the principal soluble cytochromes <italic>c</italic> in <italic>Shewanella oneidensis</italic> strain MR1</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source> <year>2001</year>;<volume>67</volume>: <fpage>3236</fpage>–<lpage>3244</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11425747</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maier</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification of the gene encoding the sole physiological fumarate reductase in <italic>Shewanella oneidensis</italic> MR-1</article-title>. <source>J Basic Microbiol</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12872312</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Isolation and characterization of a transposon mutant of <italic>Shewanella putrefaciens</italic> MR-1 deficient in fumarate reductase</article-title>. <source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9351256</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leys</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsapin</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nealson</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cusanovich</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Beeumen</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Structure and mechanism of the flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic> fumarate reductase of <italic>Shewanella putrefaciens</italic> MR-1</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Biol</source> <year>1999</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1113</fpage>–<lpage>1117</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10581551</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galushko</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Obraztsova</surname> <given-names>AYa</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shtarkman</surname> <given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laurinavichyus</surname> <given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akimenko</surname> <given-names>VK</given-names></name>. <article-title>An anaerobic acetate-oxidizing bacterium transforming methacrylic acid</article-title>. <source>Doklady Biological Sciences</source> <year>1994</year>;<volume>335</volume>: <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikoulinskaia (Arkhipova)</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akimenko</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galushko</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thauer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedderich</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cytochrome <italic>c</italic>-dependent methacrylate reductase from <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1</article-title>. <source>Eur J Biochem</source> <year>1999</year>;<volume>263</volume>: <fpage>346</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10406941</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caccavo</surname> <given-names>FJR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lonergan</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovley</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stolz</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McInerney</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title><italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens sp</italic>. <italic>nov</italic>., a hydrogen- and acetate-oxidizing dissimilatory metal-reducing microorganism</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source> <year>1994</year>;<volume>60</volume>: <fpage>3752</fpage>–<lpage>3759</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7527204</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nevin</surname> <given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woodard</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hinlein</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostendorf</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovley</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <article-title><italic>Geobacter bemidjiensis</italic> sp. nov. and <italic>Geobacter psychrophilus</italic> sp. nov., two novel Fe(III)-reducing subsurface isolates</article-title>. <source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source> <year>2005</year>;<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>1667</fpage>–<lpage>1674</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16014499</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ritalahti</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Apkarian</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos-Hernández</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanford</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title><italic>Geobacter lovleyi</italic> sp. nov. strain SZ, a novel metal-reducing and tetrachloroethene-dechlorinating bacterium</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>2775</fpage>–<lpage>2782</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16597982</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amos</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gentry</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>W-M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Criddle</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Detection and quantification of <italic>Geobacter lovleyi</italic> strain SZ: implications for bioremediation at tetrachloroethene- and uranium-impacted sites</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>6898</fpage>–<lpage>6904</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17827319</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galushko</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schink</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oxidation of acetate through reactions of the citric acid cycle by <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> in pure culture and in syntrophic coculture</article-title>. <year>2000</year>;<source>Arch Microbiol</source> <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11131021</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lovley</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Powering microbes with electricity: direct electron transfer from electrodes to microbes</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol Rep</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1758-2229.2010.00211.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1758-2229.2010.00211.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23761228</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galushko</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikulinskaya (Arkhipova)</surname> <given-names>OV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laurinavichyus</surname> <given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Obraztsova</surname> <given-names>AYa</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akimenko</surname> <given-names>VK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Periplasmic location of methacrylate reductase in cells of the strictly anaerobic bacterial strain AM-1</article-title>. <source>Microbiology (Engl. Transl. Mikrobiologiya (Russia))</source> <year>1996</year>;<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>432</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Maarel</surname> <given-names>MJEC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Bergeijk</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Werkhoven</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laverman</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meijer</surname> <given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stam</surname> <given-names>WT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Cleavage of dimethylsulfoniopropionate and reduction of acrylate by <italic>Desulfovibrio acrylicus</italic> sp.nov</article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source> <year>1996</year>;<volume>166</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arkhipova</surname> <given-names>OV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chuvochina</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trutko</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cytochromes <italic>c</italic> of the anaerobic methacrylate reducer <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1475-2875-8-296" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1475-2875-8-296</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20015392</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arkhipova</surname> <given-names>OV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikulinskaya</surname> <given-names>GV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galushko</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparative analysis of the N-terminal sequence of <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> AM-1 methacrylate reductase</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>564</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stickler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhein</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Polymethacrylates</chapter-title>. <source>Ulmann’s Encyclopedia of Industrial Chemistry</source> <publisher-name>Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co.</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>KGaA, Weinheim</publisher-loc> <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Methė</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paulsen</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heidelberg</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Genome of <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic>: metal reduction in subsurface environments</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>302</volume>: <fpage>1967</fpage>–<lpage>1969</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14671304</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aklujkar</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chavan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Risso</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname> <given-names>HE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The genome of <italic>Geobacter bemidjiensis</italic>, exemplar for the subsurface clade of <italic>Geobacter</italic> species that predominate in Fe(III)-reducing subsurface environments</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>490</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-11-490" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2164-11-490</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20828392</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagarajan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klimes</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zengler</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>De novo assembly of the complete genome of an enhanced electricity-producing variant of <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> using only short reads</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aklujkar</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krushkal</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiBartolo</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lapidus</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Land</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovley</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <article-title>The genome sequence of <italic>Geobacter metallireducens</italic>: features of metabolism, physiology and regulation common and dissimilar to <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiology</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2180-9-109" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2180-9-109</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19473543</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname> <given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aklujkar</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovley</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparative genomic analysis of <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> KN400, a strain with enhanced capacity for extracellular electron transfer and electricity production</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>471</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-13-471" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2164-13-471</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22967216</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovley</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution from a respiratory ancestor to fill syntrophic and fermentative niches: comparative genomics of six <italic>Geobacteraceae</italic> species</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-10-103" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2164-10-103</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19284579</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovley</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of electron transfer out of the cell: comparative genomics of six <italic>Geobacter</italic> genomes</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source> <year>2010</year>.<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-11-40" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2164-11-40</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20078895</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonkovsky</surname> <given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Structural analysis of heme proteins: implications for design and prediction</article-title>. <source>BMC Structural Biology</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eschenbrenner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chlumsky</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khanna</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strasser</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jorns</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Organization of the multiple coenzymes and subunits and role of the covalent flavin link in the complex heterotetrameric sarcosine oxidase</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <year>2001</year>;<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>5352</fpage>–<lpage>5367</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11330998</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanks</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Protein kinases 6. The eukaryotic protein kinase superfamily: kinase (catalytic) domain structure and classification</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source> <year>1995</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>576</fpage>–<lpage>596</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7768349</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eggink</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vriend</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terpstra</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Witholt</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Rubredoxin reductase of <italic>Pseudomonas oleovorans</italic>. Structural relationship to other flavoprotein oxidoreductases based on one NAD and two FAD fingerprints</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <year>1990</year>;<volume>212</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2319593</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klimmek</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ringel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kröger</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>A periplasmic flavoprotein in <italic>Wolinella succinogenes</italic> that resembles the fumarate reductase of <italic>Shewanella putrefaciens</italic></article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>169</volume>: <fpage>424</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9560424</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogachev</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertsova</surname> <given-names>YV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bloch</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verkhovsky</surname> <given-names>MI</given-names></name>. <article-title>Urocanate reductase: identification of a novel anaerobic pathway in <italic>Shewanella oneidensis</italic> MR-1</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>1452</fpage>–<lpage>1463</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/mmi.12067" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/mmi.12067</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23078170</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname> <given-names>EHJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pealing</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Physiological function and regulation of flavocytochrome <italic>c</italic><sub>3</sub>, the soluble fumarate reductase from <italic>Shewanella putrefaciens</italic> NCIMB 400</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>144</volume>: <fpage>937</fpage>–<lpage>945</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9579067</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doherty</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pealing</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miles</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moysey</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walkinshaw</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Identification of the Active Site Acid/Base Catalyst in a Bacterial Fumarate Reductase: A Kinetic and Crystallographic Study</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <year>2000</year>;<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>10695</fpage>–<lpage>10701</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10978153</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagos</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolaou</surname> <given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liakopoulos</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsirigos</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Combined prediction of Tat and Sec signal peptides with Hidden Markov Models</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2811</fpage>–<lpage>2817</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btq530" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq530</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20847219</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thöny-Meyer</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ritz</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hennecke</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cytochrome <italic>c</italic> biogenesis in bacteria: a possible pathway begins to emerge</article-title>. <source>Molecular Microbiology</source> <year>1994</year>;<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8057830</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curson</surname> <given-names>ARJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Todd</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname> <given-names>AWB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Catabolism of dimethylsulphoniopropionate: microorganisms, enzymes and genes</article-title>. <source>Nature Rev Microbiol</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>849</fpage>–<lpage>859</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro2653" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrmicro2653</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21986900</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>SOAPdenovo2: an empirically improved memory-efficient short-read de novo assembler</article-title>. <source>Gigascience</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/2047-217X-1-18" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/2047-217X-1-18</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23587118</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zerbino</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birney</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Velvet: algorithms for de novo short read assembly using de Bruijn graphs</article-title>. <source>Genome Research</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>821</fpage>–<lpage>882</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gr.074492.107" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/gr.074492.107</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18349386</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bankevich</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nurk</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antipov</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gurevich</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dvorkin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kulikov</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>SPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing</article-title>. <source>J Comput Biol</source> 2012;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/cmb.2012.0021" xlink:type="simple">10.1089/cmb.2012.0021</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22506599</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurevich</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saveliev</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vyahhi</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tesler</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>QUAST: quality assessment tool for genome assemblies</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1072</fpage>–<lpage>1075</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btt086" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt086</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23422339</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darling</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mau</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perna</surname> <given-names>NT</given-names></name>. <article-title>ProgressiveMauve: multiple genome alignment with gene gain, loss and rearrangement</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e11147</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0011147" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0011147</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20593022</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boetzer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henkel</surname> <given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pirovano</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Scaffolding pre-assembled contigs using SSPACE</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>578</fpage>–<lpage>579</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btq683" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq683</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21149342</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boetzer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pirovano</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Toward almost closed genomes with GapFiller</article-title>. <source>GenomeBiol</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>R56</fpage></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altschul</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madden</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schäffer</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>3389</fpage>–<lpage>3402</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moriyama</surname> <given-names>EN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Vector NTI, a balanced all-in-one sequence analysis suite</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinform</source> <year>2004</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>378</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15606974</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname> <given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunak</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Heijne</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>SignalP 4.0: discriminating signal peptides from transmembrane regions</article-title>. <source>Nature Methods</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>785</fpage>–<lpage>786</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.1701" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nmeth.1701</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21959131</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>. <article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <year>2004</year>;<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1792</fpage>–<lpage>1797</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0125888.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teslenko</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Mark</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayres</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Darling</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Höhna</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>MrBayes 3.2: efficient Bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model space</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>542</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/sys029" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/sysbio/sys029</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22357727</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>