<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-24936</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117093</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Signatures of Natural Selection at the <italic>FTO</italic> (Fat Mass and Obesity Associated) Locus in Human Populations</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>FTO</italic> and Selection</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Xuanshi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="econtrib001"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Weidle</surname>
<given-names>Kerstin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="econtrib001"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Schröck</surname>
<given-names>Kristin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Tönjes</surname>
<given-names>Anke</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Schleinitz</surname>
<given-names>Dorit</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Breitfeld</surname>
<given-names>Jana</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Stumvoll</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Böttcher</surname>
<given-names>Yvonne</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Schöneberg</surname>
<given-names>Torsten</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Kovacs</surname>
<given-names>Peter</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>IFB AdiposityDiseases, University of Leipzig, Leipzig, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Bioinformatics Group, Department of Computer Science, University of Leipzig, Leipzig, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Medicine, University of Leipzig, Leipzig, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Institute of Biochemistry, Department of Medicine, University of Leipzig, Leipzig, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Ge</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AT PK TS MS YB. Performed the experiments: XL KW KS. Analyzed the data: XL KW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: DS JB YB. Wrote the paper: XL KW TS YB PK.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="econtrib001"><p>‡ These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">peter.kovacs@medizin.uni-leipzig.de</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>3</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<elocation-id>e0117093</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>6</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>18</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Liu et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<sec>
<title>Background and aims</title> 
<p>Polymorphisms in the first intron of <italic>FTO</italic> have been robustly replicated for associations with obesity. In the Sorbs, a Slavic population resident in Germany, the strongest effect on body mass index (BMI) was found for a variant in the third intron of <italic>FTO</italic> (rs17818902). Since this may indicate population specific effects of <italic>FTO</italic> variants, we initiated studies testing <italic>FTO</italic> for signatures of selection in vertebrate species and human populations.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Methods</title> 
<p>First, we analyzed the coding region of 35 vertebrate <italic>FTO</italic> orthologs with Phylogenetic Analysis by Maximum Likelihood (PAML, ω = dN/dS) to screen for signatures of selection among species. Second, we investigated human population (Europeans/CEU, Yoruba/YRI, Chinese/CHB, Japanese/JPT, Sorbs) SNP data for footprints of selection using DnaSP version 4.5 and the Haplotter/PhaseII. Finally, using ConSite we compared transcription factor (TF) binding sites at sequences harbouring <italic>FTO</italic> SNPs in intron three.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Results</title> 
<p>PAML analyses revealed strong conservation in coding region of <italic>FTO</italic> (ω&lt;1). Sliding-window results from population genetic analyses provided highly significant (p&lt;0.001) signatures for balancing selection specifically in the third intron (e.g. Tajima’s D in Sorbs = 2.77). We observed several alterations in TF binding sites, e.g. <italic>TCF3</italic> binding site introduced by the rs17818902 minor allele.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Conclusion</title> 
<p>Population genetic analysis revealed signatures of balancing selection at the <italic>FTO</italic> locus with a prominent signal in intron three, a genomic region with strong association with BMI in the Sorbs. Our data support the hypothesis that genes associated with obesity may have been under evolutionary selective pressure.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This project was supported by grants from the Boehringer Ingelheim Foundation to P.K., from the IFB AdiposityDiseases (ADI-K50D and ADI-K7-45 to Y.B. and ADI-K60E to P.K.), and from the Collaborative Research Center granted by the DFG (CRC 1052; B03). The work was further funded by the German Research Foundation (BO 3147/4-1 to Y.B.). IFB AdiposityDiseases is supported by the Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF), Germany, FKZ: 01EO1001. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="2"/>
<table-count count="3"/>
<page-count count="13"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Obesity is a complex disease with an estimated heritability of 40–70% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref001">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref002">2</xref>] The existence of genetic factors is well supported by a number of polymorphisms identified in recent genome-wide association studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref003">3</xref>]. Single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the fat mass and obesity-associated gene (<italic>FTO</italic>) locus seem to be among the eminent factors associated with obesity measures such as body mass index (BMI). The associations between <italic>FTO</italic> variants and BMI have been robustly replicated in populations with different ethnic backgrounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref004">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref007">7</xref>]. The human <italic>FTO</italic> maps on 16q12.2 and encodes a 2-oxoglutarate-dependent nucleic acid demethylase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref008">8</xref>]. The SNP rs9939609 representing a cluster of variants with strong associations to BMI and overweight is located in the first intron [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref005">5</xref>]. Whereas these associations have initially been shown in cohorts of European origin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref005">5</xref>], they could not be replicated in an African sample and the Han Chinese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref010">10</xref>]. On the other hand, in the Sorbs—a population of Slavic origin residing in Eastern Germany, in addition to the association signal in the first intron, the strongest association to BMI was found for the SNPs mapping to intron three [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref011">11</xref>]. These findings indicate specific effects of <italic>FTO</italic> alleles in Sorbs and raise the question, whether <italic>FTO</italic> has been subject to natural selection and so, does show population specific patterns of selection.</p>
<p>Considering the “thrifty genotype” hypothesis which states that an evolutionarily advantageous increased capacity to store energy may result in obesity and type 2 diabetes (T2D) in Western-lifestyle societies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref012">12</xref>], genes associated with obesity and T2D have become attractive targets of evolutionary studies. Until recently, there has not been a strong evidence for consistent patterns of selection at loci associated with T2D which would provide conclusive confirmation of the thrifty genotype hypothesis. It has been shown more recently that in a locus-by-locus study, 14 loci associated with T2D, and to a lesser extent, obesity, from European, Africans and East Asian populations appear to have undergone selection, however there is no positive selection evidence found when all the T2D loci were analyzed together [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref013">13</xref>].</p>
<p>Since comprehensive data regarding <italic>FTO</italic> evolution are sparse, we initiated studies searching for signatures of selection in vertebrates and human populations. To test for the conservation of the protein-coding sequence on the inter-species level, we calculated the ratio of non-synonymous to synonymous base exchanges (ω = d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub>) of the coding region in 35 vertebrate <italic>FTO</italic> orthologs with Phylogenetic Analysis by Maximum Likelihood (PAML). Furthermore, we investigated SNP data for footprints of selection using DnaSP version 4.5 and the Haplotter/PhaseII in human population of Yoruba from Ibadan, Nigeria (YRI), Utah residents with Northern and Western European ancestry (CEU), East Asians, (ASN), Han Chinese from Beijing, China (CHB), and Japanese from Tokyo, Japan (JPT)). Finally, we examined <italic>in silico</italic> the possible impact of <italic>FTO</italic> SNPs in intron 3 on transcription factor (TF) binding sites.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>All studies were approved by the ethics committee of the University of Leipzig. All subjects gave written informed consent.</p>
<sec id="sec002a">
<title>Phylogenetic Analyses by Maximun Likelihood (PAML)</title>
<p>PAML [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref014">14</xref>] provides a program CODEML to estimate the level of gene conservation by calculating the d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub> ratio ω (d<sub>N</sub>: non-synonymous mutation substitution rate, d<sub>S</sub>: synonymous mutation substitution rate). In the present study, ω was calculated in PAML version 4.1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref015">15</xref>]. The coding sequences of 35 vertebrate <italic>FTO</italic> orthologs were extracted from Ensembl (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ensembl.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ensembl.org</ext-link>) and the NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) databases. Species and accession numbers are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s001">S1 Table</xref>. Subsequently, all coding sequences were aligned by a widely used progressive alignment method, ClustalW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref016">16</xref>] within MEGA 6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref017">17</xref>]. Phylogenetic tree was conducted by Neighbor-Joining (NJ) algorithm using aligned coding sequences in MEGA 6. The evolutionary distances were computed by Jukes-Cantor model which is the best predicted model giving by jModeltest 2.1.5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref018">18</xref>]. 1,000 bootstrap searches were performed to infer the phylogenetic tree and bootstrap consensus phylogenetic tree. The initial input for PAML analysis is displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0117093.g001">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone.0117093.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.g001</object-id>
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Neighbor-joining phylogenetic tree of 35 species on <italic>FTO</italic> coding sequences showing the evolutionary relationship.</title>
<p>The bootstrap consensus tree inferred from 1000 replicates is generated to present the evolutionary relationship among 35 species on <italic>FTO</italic> coding sequences which were retrieved from Ensembl or NCBI. Accession numbers are listed at <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s001">S1 Table</xref>. Alignment was carried out by ClustalW (1581 nucleotides left) and phylogenetic tree is constructed by neighbor-joining method in MEGA6. Branches corresponding to partitions reproduced in less than 50% bootstrap replicates did no display. This tree works as the initial tree for further PAML analysis.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.g001"/>
</fig>
<p>Due to the fact that the power to detect positive selection is reduced when the rates across sites are averaged, diverse tests were adopted according to recommendations for real data analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref019">19</xref>]. The tests conducted include the one-ratio model (M0), free-ratio [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref020">20</xref>], nearly neutral (M1a), positive selection (M2a) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref021">21</xref>], discrete (M3) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref022">22</xref>], beta (M7), and beta&amp;ω (M8) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref023">23</xref>]. The likelihood ratio tests (LRT = 2 (<italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub>–<italic>l</italic><sub>0</sub>), 2Δl, where <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>l</italic><sub>0</sub> are the log likelihoods from two models respectively) are conducted to every two nested models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref024">24</xref>] in order to identify which model better fits to the data. LRTs and nested models are briefly introduced as followed: the M0 model is a plain model in which the same d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub> ratio is assumed for all branches in the phylogeny [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref020">20</xref>]. The free-ratio model is the most general model, where an independent d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub> ratio is assumed for every branch [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref020">20</xref>]. The first LRT involves the M0 model and the free-ratio model which can be compared to survey if the d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub> ratios ω differ among lineages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref020">20</xref>]. Paired M0 model and M3 models can be tested by the second LRT, which is to analyze if ω varies among sites. In the discrete model, M3, three site classes, each of them with an independently estimated ω which also allows for sites with ω &gt; 1, are estimated over a general discrete distribution. For each site class the proportion <italic>p</italic> is given [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref022">22</xref>]. The third LRT compares the M1a model and M2a model. M1a postulates a class of sites with ω = 0 and a second class of sites with 0 &lt; ω &lt; 1, where in the M2a model a third class of sites is added (ω &gt;1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref025">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref024">24</xref>]. The fourth LRT is between M7 model and M8 model, which has more power to detect positively selected sites, as both models allow for sites with 0 &lt; ω &lt; 1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref023">23</xref>]. For M7 a beta distribution for ω over sites is assumed, which is limited to the interval (0, 1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref023">23</xref>]. In M8 another site class is added with ω valuated from the data set which allows sites with ω &gt; 1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref023">23</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002b">
<title>SNPs selection and population genetic measures</title>
<p>Population genetic measures were calculated with DnaSP version 4.50.0.3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref026">26</xref>], Sweep [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref027">27</xref>], and the iHS (integrated haplotype score) tool available under <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hgdp.uchicago.edu/" xlink:type="simple">http://hgdp.uchicago.edu/</ext-link>. In the Sorbs cohort, a self-contained ethnic group in Eastern Germany, which has been described in detail elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref011">11</xref>], closely related subjects (Identity by descent/IBD &gt; 0.05, calculated by PLINK v1.01 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref028">28</xref>] ) were removed from the analyses. Further inclusion criteria were: minor allele frequency (MAF) &gt; 0.01, Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) &gt; 0.0001, missingness per SNP &lt; 0.05, and missingness per sample &lt; 0.07. According to these standards, genotype data for 307 SNPs within the <italic>FTO</italic> locus (positions ranging from 52013417 to 52997859 bp, NCBI build 35/hg17) in 34 individuals were extracted from an available dataset obtained by genotyping DNA from about 1000 Sorbs with 500K/6.0 Affymetrix GeneChip arrays (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s002">S2 Table</xref>).</p>
<p>Additionally, data of the HapMap populations (YRI, CEU, ASN, CHB, JPT) were downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hapmap.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.hapmap.org/</ext-link> and filtered for the same SNPs genotyped in the Sorbs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s002">S2 Table</xref>). As the CEU and YRI comprise parent/child trios, analyses were performed without SNP data of the children. Haplotype reconstruction in all populations was performed with PHASE version 2.1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref029">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref030">30</xref>].</p>
<p>DnaSP provides population genetic measures like Tajima’s D [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref031">31</xref>], Fu and Li’s D*, and Fu and Li’s F* [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref032">32</xref>], which all detect deviations from the normal distribution of common or rare alleles in neutral evolution. The iHS is based on different levels of linkage disequilibrium (LD) surrounding selected allele region compared to the background allele at the same position. Suggestive evidence for natural selection is defined as iHS &lt; −1.5 or &gt; 1.5, powerful selection is iHS &lt; −2 or &gt;2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref033">33</xref>]. The calculated fixation index (Fst) is a measure for the extent of variations in allele frequency between populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref034">34</xref>]. Population differentiation increased by local adaptation may result in larger Fst values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref035">35</xref>].</p>
<p>For the HapMap populations, standardized iHS and Fst values were also provided by the Haplotter (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hg-wen.uchicago.edu/selection/haplotter.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://hg-wen.uchicago.edu/selection/haplotter.htm</ext-link>.) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref036">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref037">37</xref>]</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002c">
<title>Transcription factor binding sites</title>
<p>To uncover alleles that may change binding sites in intron three, sequences surrounding eight obesity associated SNPs (20bp up—and downstream) within <italic>FTO</italic> intron three were downloaded from UCSC genome browser (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.ucsc.edu/" xlink:type="simple">http://genome.ucsc.edu/</ext-link>). Comparing transcription factor binding probabilities of sequences carrying either the major or the minor alleles were performed using ConSite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref038">38</xref>]. Sequences included in the analysis are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s004">S4 Table</xref>. We particularly analyzed transcription factors specifically in vertebrates, as it is well acknowledged that functional transcription factor binding sites are conserved among close species, where substitutions occur mostly at nonfunctional positions when the evolutionary distance of species increases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref039">39</xref>]. ConSite incorporates the datasets from JASPAR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref040">40</xref>] and ConSite summarizing transcription factor binding profiles as well as phylogenetic footprinting algorithms for additional constraints further improving prediction algorithms. The noise level of ConSite compared to other single sequence analysis is reduced by ∼ 85% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref038">38</xref>]. The program has been applied to several studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref041">41</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref043">43</xref>] and has been validated in functional experiments both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref042">42</xref>].</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="results" id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec003a">
<title>Phylogenetic Analyses by Maximum Likelihood (PAML)</title>
<p>PAML analysis revealed that the coding region of <italic>FTO</italic> is highly conserved among all studied species (average ω = 0.1616). The LRT statistic for lineage-specificity model (M0 <italic>vs</italic>. free-ratio) was calculated as 2Δl = 63.74. Compared with a χ<sup>2</sup> distribution under d.f. = 66, the difference between these two models was not significant indicating that the ω is not different among lineages. This suggests no differences in the direction and magnitude of selection acting on <italic>FTO</italic> coding regions of each species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref044">44</xref>]. The second LRT was conducted between M0 model and M3 model. The significance of the result of LRT (2Δl = 193.47, d.f. = 4 ) pointed to the M3 model. In this case, ω varied among sites within a species instead of having a constant value, and the substitution rate between non-synonymous and synonymous mutations fluctuated within <italic>FTO</italic> coding region of each species. In the last two LRTs, non-significant results were detected which suggested null neutral hypothesis (M1a and M7) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref045">45</xref>]. In summary, positive selection cannot be inferred for any of the sites in coding sequences. All data are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0117093.t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0117093.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<title>PAML analysis of <italic>FTO</italic>.</title>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0117093.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.t001"/>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"><bold>Model</bold></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"><bold>Parameter Estimates</bold></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"><bold>In L</bold></th>
<th align="center" colspan="4" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>LRT</bold></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Models</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2Δl</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>d.f.</italic></bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p-value</bold></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M0</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ω<sub>0</sub> = 0.1616</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1462.43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">M0 <italic>vs. free-ratio</italic></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">63.74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">66</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">0.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>free-ratio</italic></td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">variable</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1430.56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M3</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<sub>0</sub> = 0.40765, p<sub>1</sub> = 0.39476, p<sub>2</sub> = 0.19759, ω<sub>0</sub> = 0.00264. ω<sub>1</sub> = 0.12330, ω<sub>2</sub> = 0.90116</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1365.70</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M0 <italic>vs</italic>. M3</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193.47</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M1a</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<sub>0</sub> = 0.79894, p<sub>1</sub> = 0.20106, ω<sub>0</sub> = 0.05695, ω<sub>1</sub> = 1.00000</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1378.39</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">M1a <italic>vs</italic>. M2a</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">0.61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">0.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M2a</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<sub>0</sub> = 0.79860, p<sub>1</sub> = 0.16914, p<sub>2</sub> = 0.03227, ω<sub>0</sub> = 0.06053, ω<sub>1</sub> = 1.00000, ω<sub>2</sub> = 1.90635</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1378.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M7</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.21277, q = 0.75616</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1367.96</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">M7 <italic>vs</italic>. M8</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">3.71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">0.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M8</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<sub>0</sub> = 0.94790, p = 0.26173, q = 1.37577 (p<sub>1</sub> = 0.05210), w = 1.63117</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1366.10</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001">
<p>All values computed under default settings. InL: log likelihood, LRT = likelihood ratio test to detect positive selection, <italic>d.f</italic>. = degrees of freedom.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003b">
<title>Population genetic measures</title>
<p>The analyses with DnaSP provided strong evidence for a non-neutral evolution of the <italic>FTO</italic> locus. Across the whole gene locus (1 Mb), Tajima’s D showed significant deviations from the normal distribution of alleles (summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0117093.t002">Table 2</xref>). The sliding-window analyses further supported these findings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0117093.g002">Fig. 2</xref>). Interestingly, Tajima’s D seemed to be slightly higher in the third intron than in the first intron. Furthermore, the values across the studied populations in the third intron were more consistent when compared with the first intron which showed decreased Tajima’s D in Asian populations (Japanese and Chinese; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0117093.t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0117093.g002">Fig. 2</xref>). In line with Tajima’s D, also Fu and Li’s D* and Fu and Li’s F* tests showed significant deviations from neutrality in the investigated populations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0117093.t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0117093.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.g002</object-id>
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Tajima’s D within the <italic>FTO</italic> locus from five populations showing signals of selection.</title>
<p>Sliding window analysis of Tajima’s D in the whole gene locus (∼ 1 Mb) was conducted with DnaSP version 4.50.0.3. Populations of European, African, Chinese, Japanese and Sorbs were included in the analysis. Closely related individuals were removed, i.e. trios from Chinese and Japanese populations and individuals with IBD &gt; 0.05 from Sorbs. Higher values of Tajima’s D were observed at the intron 3.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.g002"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pone.0117093.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Results of the DnaSP Analyses.</title>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0117093.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.t002"/>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Data</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>n</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SNPs</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tajima’s D</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>p</italic></bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Fu and Li’s D<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">*</xref></bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>p</italic></bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Fu and Li’s F<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">*</xref></bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>p</italic></bold></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="9" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>FTO</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CEU</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8228</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4349</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1269</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHB</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.173</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0845</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5467</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JPT</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3878</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7632</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4324</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sorbs</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.605</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1099</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7689</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YRI</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8541</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5895</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2467</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="9" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Intron 1</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CEU</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76787</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30288</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn005">#</xref></sup></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26319</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHB</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8609</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn005">#</xref></sup></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91378</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24036</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JPT</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90727</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn005">#</xref></sup></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91378</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28686</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sorbs</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48058</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32095</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn005">#</xref></sup></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09295</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YRI</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67329</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88863</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63200</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="9" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Intron 3</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CEU</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.378</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4607</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn005">#</xref></sup></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5645</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHB</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7264</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4261</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn005">#</xref></sup></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2333</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JPT</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0817</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4261</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn005">#</xref></sup></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3809</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sorbs</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7653</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4762</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn005">#</xref></sup></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.275</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YRI</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4569</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">***</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4607</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn005">#</xref></sup></td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5984</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001">
<p>n = number of haplotypes</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t002fn002">
<p>* <italic>p</italic>&lt;0,05</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t002fn003">
<p>** <italic>p</italic>&lt;0,02</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t002fn004"><p>*** <italic>p</italic>&lt;0,001</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t002fn005"><p><sup>#</sup> 0,1&gt;<italic>p</italic>&gt;0,05</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t002fn006"><p><italic>FTO</italic>: 52.297.274–52.696.065 bp; rs1421091 - rs2689269 on Human May 2004 (NCBI35/hg17), Intron 1: 52.326.794–52401034bp; rs7203521 - rs6499646, Intron 3: 52.421.901–52.434.067 bp; rs7204916 - rs7205213</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>From the publicly available data, the Haplotter showed iHS top scores &gt; 2 in the CEU on the <italic>FTO</italic>-region, e.g. for rs7193144 and rs8050136 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s003">S3 Table</xref>). All SNPs in the third intron had rather low iHS-values. These results were not significant according to the published map of recent positive selection in the human genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref036">36</xref>]. The unstandardized iHS values calculated with the iHS-tool supported publically available data in the Haplotter (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0117093.t003">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s003">S3 Table</xref>). It is noteworthy that in the Sorbs, the iHS for SNPs in the third intron (rs17818902 and rs17818920) was nearly three times higher than in the CEU sample (1.468 vs. 0.590). Notably, the strength of association with BMI positively correlated with the unstandardized iHS <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0117093.t003">Table 3</xref>. iHS values indicate that no long haplotype was observed for variants in <italic>FTO</italic>. The Fst values between comparisons were close to zero among variants which indicated no significant population differences (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0117093.t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0117093.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Population genetic measures on unstandardized iHS and Fst.</title>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0117093.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.t003"/>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/>
<th align="center" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Unstandardized iHS</bold></th>
<th align="center" colspan="4" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Fst</bold></th>
<th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1"><bold><italic>p</italic>/beta</bold></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SNP</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>p</italic> (BMI)</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Intron</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sorbs</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CEU</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CHB</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>JPT</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YRI</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CEU vs. Sorbs</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CHB vs. Sorbs</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>JPT vs. Sorbs</bold></th>
<th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>YRI vs. Sorbs</bold></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs1861869</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01465</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.294</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.766</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.212</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.839</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0040</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1283</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0919</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0081</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="15" valign="top" colspan="1">0.068/−0.501</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs1861868</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00938</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.869</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.029</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.049</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.005</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.310</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0017</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0912</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0592</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0558</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs9940700</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07348</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.539</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.618</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.401</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.693</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0021</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4219</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3889</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2070</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs9939973</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005447</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.667</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.411</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.865</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.664</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.429</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0059</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0751</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0543</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0062</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs9940128</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01583</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.667</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.411</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.866</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.665</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.429</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0059</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0751</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0543</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0062</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs9922047</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01035</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.400</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.220</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.876</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.006</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.171</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0063</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0034</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0034</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0781</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs16952522</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1976</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. a.</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. a.</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.994</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.746</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. a.</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0020</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0016</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0150</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0055</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs17817288</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006795</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.274</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.500</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.294</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.534</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.537</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0060</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0067</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0064</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0135</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs1477196</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02183</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.197</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.057</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.701</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.891</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. a.</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0045</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0053</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0053</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1362</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs1121980</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004003</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.529</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.179</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.197</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.109</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.370</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0059</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0751</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0543</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0059</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs7193144</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003387</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.826</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.550</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.727</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.649</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.740</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0053</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1005</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0664</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0063</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs16945088</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5796</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.989</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.220</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.380</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.338</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.914</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0061</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0064</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0062</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0924</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs8050136</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003092</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.747</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.361</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.741</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.667</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.280</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0047</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1005</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0664</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0032</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs9939609</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008727</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.375</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.361</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.411</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.019</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0047</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1005</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0664</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0049</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs9930506</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02465</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.748</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.220</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.741</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.667</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.133</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0059</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0751</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0482</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0789</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs11075994</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9537</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.912</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.772</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.149</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.493</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0043</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0041</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0201</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0332</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="4" valign="top" colspan="1">0.041/−0.959</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs1421090</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1254</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.598</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.309</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.916</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.480</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0132</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1470</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1807</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0276</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs9972717</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7354</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.106</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.648</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. a.</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. a.</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. a.</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0050</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0761</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0522</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1063</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs10852522</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001739</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.146</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.111</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.896</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0054</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0456</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0037</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0053</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs10521308</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7355</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. a.</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. a.</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.943</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.439</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.072</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0174</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0387</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0387</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0061</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="8" valign="top" colspan="1">0.009/0.881</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs17818902</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000632</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.468</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.590</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.101</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.915</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.888</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0154</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0011</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0015</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0598</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs17818920</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0007213</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.468</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.590</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.101</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.915</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.888</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0154</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0011</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0015</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0598</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs8053367</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0009839</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.760</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.348</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.427</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.348</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0029</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0062</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0006</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0029</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs8053740</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001025</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.760</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.348</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.427</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.348</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0029</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0062</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0006</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0029</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs7203051</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001116</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.760</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.348</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.427</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.348</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0029</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0062</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0006</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0038</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs7205009</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001319</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.760</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.348</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.427</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.348</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0029</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0062</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0006</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0029</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs7205213</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001292</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.871</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.348</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.460</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.399</td>
<td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0009</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0067</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0011</td>
<td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0044</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p><italic>p</italic> = <italic>p</italic>-value for association to BMI in the Sorbs; iHS = integrated Haplotype score; CEU = Central Europeans; CHB = Han Chinese from Beijing; JPT = Japanese from Tokyo; YRI = Yoruba from Ibadan; n. a. = not available</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003c">
<title>Transcription factor binding sites</title>
<p>To elucidate the potential functional mechanisms underlying the strong association of variants in <italic>FTO’s</italic> third intron with BMI in the Sorbs, we investigated <italic>in silico</italic> the impact of SNPs on predicting putative transcription factor binding sites (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s005">S5 Table</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s005">S5 Table</xref>, minor alleles at variants rs17818902 showing the top association signal with BMI in the Sorbs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref011">11</xref>] and rs8053740 predicted novel binding sites for two transcription factors TCF3 and SOX17, respectively.</p>
<p>Further, at rs8053367 the presence of the minor allele led to binding of multiple transcription factors, namely FREAC-2, HNF-3beta, HFH-1, HFH-2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s005">S5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s006">S6</xref> Tables), while the binding site of transcription factor Irf-1 seemed to be significantly compromised. Finally, minor alleles of rs17818920 and rs7205213 led to alterations in binding sites for HLF, SOX17 and HNF-3beta (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s005">S5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s006">S6</xref> Tables).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec004">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Polymorphisms in the <italic>FTO</italic> gene have been shown to be associated with obesity in different ethnic groups of European and other ancestries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref003">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref005">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref007">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref046">46</xref>]. Whereas associations with SNPs in the first intron have been robustly replicated, in the Sorbs, the strongest effects on BMI were found for variants in the third intron [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref011">11</xref>]. To address specific associations of <italic>FTO</italic> variants in Sorbs, we aimed to test the gene for signatures of selection in mammals and particularly in human populations.</p>
<p>PAML-analyses on <italic>FTO</italic> coding sequence from 35 vertebrates revealed constant results with ω &lt; 1. In the NearlyNeutral (M1a) model, most sites in the coding sequence were under strong (∼80%) purifying selection or neutral mutation (∼20%) and experienced a very high rate of synonymous substitutions, thus suggesting strong gene conservation. This underlines the biological importance of the gene, as functionally relevant genes are expected to be highly conserved and thus subject to purifying selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref047">47</xref>]. The fact that <italic>FTO</italic> is subject to purifying selection is consistent with findings of Ohashi <italic>et al</italic>. who studied the genetic architecture of <italic>FTO</italic> polymorphisms in oceanic populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref048">48</xref>]. However, considering purifying selection being an important means of evolution to maintain the optimized form of a gene, it cannot be excluded that <italic>FTO</italic> variants were positively selected in the past when the ability to store energy was beneficial.</p>
<p>It is of note that PAML analysis only examined the coding sequence, however most of the obesity-associated SNPs, like rs9939609 and rs17818920, map in the intronic regions. Therefore, test statistics such as iHS and Fst which are independent from coding regions are inevitable in evolutionary analyses. It has been stated before that at least in the oceanic populations <italic>FTO</italic> does not seem to comply with the thrifty genotype hypothesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref048">48</xref>]. The analyses in these populations have only considered polymorphisms in the first intron. In the context of our present data, further studies systematically targeting the <italic>FTO</italic> locus in populations of different ethnic backgrounds will be inevitable. As we show in the present study, neither iHS nor Fst values indicate positive selection for any allele from the third intron in individual groups or groups of populations (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0117093.s007">S1 Fig.</xref>). Thus, consistent with studies in oceanic populations, our data would not support the thrifty genotype hypothesis. In contrast, other population genetic measures like Tajima’s D, Fu and Li’s D*, and Fu and Li’s F* suggest the signature of balancing selection in <italic>FTO</italic> on a significant level. Detection of balancing selection might be explained by the fact that whereas Tajima’s D considers the sites themselves in terms of allele frequencies, it does not take into account the surrounding regions of sites through addressing LD (such as iHS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref049">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref050">50</xref>]. This is interesting when considering that polymorphisms in the third intron showed the strongest association with BMI in the Sorbs from Germany [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref011">11</xref>]. Remarkably, in the first intron, Tajima’s D is rather low in Asian populations when compared with European Caucasians, which might at least in part explain ethnic specificity in the genotype-phenotype associations with SNPs in this gene region. However, it has to be noted that Tajima’s D was consistent across studied populations in the third intron, which does not seem to support a population specific pattern of selection for the Sorbs. Rather than that, the specific association of <italic>FTO</italic> variants in the third intron with BMI in the Sorbs is more likely to be explained by specific environmental factors interacting with the genetic background in the Sorbs.</p>
<p>Given the fact that the strongest effects on BMI in the Sorbs is on the third intron, rs17818902, we also investigated its potential impact on the transcription factor binding sites. In <italic>silico</italic> analyses using publically available transcription factor databases suggested that the minor rs17818902 allele would predict a novel binding site for TCF3 and that of rs8053740 for SOX17. TCF3 acts as a transcriptional regulator involved in the initiation of neuronal differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref051">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref052">52</xref>] whereas SOX17 is an important player in the regulation of embryonic development and in the determination of the cell fate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref053">53</xref>]. However, the causal functional variant remains to be discovered. Thus, studies on pathways downstream of TCF3 may pave the path for better understanding the mechanism underlying associations of FTO with obesity. Nevertheless, it has to be acknowledged that a recent study strongly suggested a direct interaction of noncoding regions in the first intron of <italic>FTO</italic> showed enhancer activity with the promoter of the homeobox gene <italic>IRX3</italic> thus regulating IRX3 expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref054">54</xref>]. However, the clear association connecting functional variants in the first intron and obesity remains vague. Secondly, the experiments of loss of function on <italic>IRX3</italic> were conducted in human cerebellum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref055">55</xref>]. In contrast, there is strong evidence for the role of FTO in the complex pathophysiology of obesity (systematically reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref056">56</xref>]). For example, it has been showed that the highest expression of FTO is in the brain region controlling food intake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref008">8</xref>] and that hypothalamic-specific manipulation of Fto affects food intake in rats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0117093.ref057">57</xref>].</p>
<p>In conclusion, population genetic analyses revealed balancing signatures of selection at the <italic>FTO</italic> locus with a prominent signal in the third intron, a genomic region with strong association with BMI in the Sorbs. Data provide some evidence supporting evolutionary selective pressure on genes associated with obesity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117093.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.s001">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Species included in the PAML analyses.</title>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117093.s002" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.s002">
<label>S2 Table</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>FTO</italic> SNPs included in the analyses.</title>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117093.s003" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.s003">
<label>S3 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Population genetic measures according to Haplotter Phase II.</title>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117093.s004" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.s004">
<label>S4 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Sequences included in transcription factor binding sites analysis.</title>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117093.s005" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.s005">
<label>S5 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Differences in putative transcription factor binding predicted by SNPs in intron three of the <italic>FTO</italic>.</title>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117093.s006" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.s006">
<label>S6 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Functional characteristics of the identified transcription factors.</title>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0117093.s007" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0117093.s007">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>FTO</italic> intron three with linkage disequilibrium (LD) structure, unstandardized iHS and Fst.</title>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank all those who participated in the studies. We thank Stefano Berto (University of Leipzig) for his helpful comments and suggestions in regard to evolutionary analyses.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref001">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stunkard</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foch</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hrubec</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>A twin study of human obesity</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <volume>256</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/jama.1986.03380010055024" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/jama.1986.03380010055024</ext-link>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3712713</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref002">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maes</surname> <given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neale</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eaves</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Genetic and environmental factors in relative body weight and human adiposity</article-title>. <source>Behav Genet</source> <volume>27</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9519560</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref003">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Speliotes</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willer</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berndt</surname> <given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monda</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thorleifsson</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Association analyses of 249,796 individuals reveal 18 new loci associated with body mass index</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>42</volume> (<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>937</fpage>–<lpage>948</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.686" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ng.686</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20935630</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref004">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dina</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyre</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallina</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durand</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Korner</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Variation in FTO contributes to childhood obesity and severe adult obesity</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>39</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>724</fpage>–<lpage>726</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17496892</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref005">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frayling</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Timpson</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weedon</surname> <given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeggini</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freathy</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A common variant in the FTO gene is associated with body mass index and predisposes to childhood and adult obesity</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>316</volume> (<issue>5826</issue>): <fpage>889</fpage>–<lpage>894</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1141634" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1141634</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17434869</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref006">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yajnik</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janipalli</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhaskar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kulkarni</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freathy</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>FTO gene variants are strongly associated with type 2 diabetes in South Asian Indians</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source> <volume>52</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>252</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00125-008-1186-6" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00125-008-1186-6</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19005641</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref007">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hotta</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakata</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuo</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamohara</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kotani</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Variations in the FTO gene are associated with severe obesity in the Japanese</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>53</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>546</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10038-008-0283-1" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10038-008-0283-1</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18379722</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref008">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerken</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Girard</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tung</surname> <given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Webby</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saudek</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The obesity-associated FTO gene encodes a 2-oxoglutarate-dependent nucleic acid demethylase</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>318</volume> (<issue>5855</issue>): <fpage>1469</fpage>–<lpage>1472</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1151710" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1151710</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17991826</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref009">
<label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennig</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulford</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sirugo</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rayco-Solon</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hattersley</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>FTO gene variation and measures of body mass in an African population</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Genet</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2350-10-21" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2350-10-21</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19265514</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref010">
<label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <string-name>Loos</string-name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruth</surname> <given-names>J F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Variants in the fat mass- and obesity-associated (FTO) gene are not associated with obesity in a Chinese Han population</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source> <volume>57</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>264</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17959933</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref011">
<label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tonjes</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeggini</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacs</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bottcher</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schleinitz</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Association of FTO variants with BMI and fat mass in the self-contained population of Sorbs in Germany</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <volume>18</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ejhg.2009.107" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ejhg.2009.107</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19584900</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref012">
<label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>NEEL</surname> <given-names>JV</given-names></name> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>Diabetes mellitus: a “thrifty” genotype rendered detrimental by “progress”</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">13937884</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref013">
<label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayub</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moutsianas</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panoutsopoulou</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colonna</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Revisiting the thrifty gene hypothesis via 65 loci associated with susceptibility to type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>94</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>176</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ajhg.2013.12.010" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ajhg.2013.12.010</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24412096</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref014">
<label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>PAML: a program package for phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood</article-title>. <source>Comput Appl Biosci</source> <volume>13</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>556</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9367129</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref015">
<label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>PAML 4: phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>24</volume> (<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1586</fpage>–<lpage>1591</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483113</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref016">
<label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>22</volume> (<issue>22</issue>): <fpage>4673</fpage>–<lpage>4680</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref017">
<label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Filipski</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MEGA6: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 6.0</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>30</volume> (<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>2725</fpage>–<lpage>2729</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst197" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/molbev/mst197</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref018">
<label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darriba</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taboada</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doallo</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>jModelTest 2: more models, new heuristics and parallel computing</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source> <volume>9</volume> (<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>772</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.2109" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nmeth.2109</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22847109</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref019">
<label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anisimova</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bielawski</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Accuracy and power of the likelihood ratio test in detecting adaptive molecular evolution</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>18</volume> (<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1585</fpage>–<lpage>1592</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11470850</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref020">
<label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Likelihood ratio tests for detecting positive selection and application to primate lysozyme evolution</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>15</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>573</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9580986</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref021">
<label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Likelihood models for detecting positively selected amino acid sites and applications to the HIV-1 envelope gene</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>148</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>929</fpage>–<lpage>936</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9539414</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref022">
<label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swanson</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vacquier</surname> <given-names>VD</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Maximum-likelihood analysis of molecular adaptation in abalone sperm lysin reveals variable selective pressures among lineages and sites</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>17</volume> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1446</fpage>–<lpage>1455</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11018152</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref023">
<label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Codon-substitution models for heterogeneous selection pressure at amino acid sites</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>155</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10790415</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref024">
<label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wendy</surname> <given-names>S W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Bayes empirical bayes inference of amino acid sites under positive selection</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>22</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1107</fpage>–<lpage>1118</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15689528</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref025">
<label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>Wendy SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Accuracy and power of statistical methods for detecting adaptive evolution in protein coding sequences and for identifying positively selected sites</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>168</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>1041</fpage>–<lpage>1051</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1534/genetics.104.031153" xlink:type="simple">10.1534/genetics.104.031153</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15514074</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref026">
<label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rozas</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rozas</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>DnaSP, DNA sequence polymorphism: an interactive program for estimating population genetics parameters from DNA sequence data</article-title>. <source>Comput Appl Biosci</source> <volume>11</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>621</fpage>–<lpage>625</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8808578</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref027">
<label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabeti</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reich</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <string-name>Levine</string-name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haninah</surname> <given-names>ZP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richter</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Detecting recent positive selection in the human genome from haplotype structure</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>419</volume> (<issue>6909</issue>): <fpage>832</fpage>–<lpage>837</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12397357</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref028">
<label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Purcell</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neale</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Todd-Brown</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manuel</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>81</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>559</fpage>–<lpage>575</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/519795" xlink:type="simple">10.1086/519795</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17701901</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref029">
<label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donnelly</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A new statistical method for haplotype reconstruction from population data</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>68</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>978</fpage>–<lpage>989</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/319501" xlink:type="simple">10.1086/319501</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11254454</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref030">
<label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheet</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Accounting for decay of linkage disequilibrium in haplotype inference and missing-data imputation</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>76</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>462</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/428594" xlink:type="simple">10.1086/428594</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15700229</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref031">
<label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tajima</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Statistical method for testing the neutral mutation hypothesis by DNA polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>123</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2513255</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref032">
<label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname> <given-names>YX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Statistical tests of neutrality of mutations</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>133</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>709</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8454210</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref033">
<label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Southam</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soranzo</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frayling</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname> <given-names>MI</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Is the thrifty genotype hypothesis supported by evidence based on confirmed type 2 diabetes- and obesity-susceptibility variants</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source> <volume>52</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1846</fpage>–<lpage>1851</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00125-009-1419-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00125-009-1419-3</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19526209</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref034">
<label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewontin</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krakauer</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Distribution of gene frequency as a test of the theory of the selective neutrality of polymorphisms</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>74</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">4711903</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref035">
<label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akey</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Genomic insights into positive selection</article-title>. <source>Trends in Genetics</source> <volume>22</volume> (<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>446</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16808986</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref036">
<label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voight</surname> <given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kudaravalli</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A map of recent positive selection in the human genome</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>4</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>e72</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.0040072" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040072</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16494531</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref037">
<label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frazer</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ballinger</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hinds</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stuve</surname> <given-names>LL</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A second generation human haplotype map of over 3.1 million SNPs</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>449</volume> (<issue>7164</issue>): <fpage>851</fpage>–<lpage>861</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature06258" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature06258</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17943122</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref038">
<label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandelin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname> <given-names>WW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenhard</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>ConSite: web-based prediction of regulatory elements using cross-species comparison</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>32</volume> (Web Server issue): <fpage>W249</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkh372" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/nar/gkh372</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215389</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref039">
<label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moses</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname> <given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iyer</surname> <given-names>VN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>MONKEY: identifying conserved transcription-factor binding sites in multiple alignments using a binding site-specific evolutionary model</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>5</volume> (<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>R98</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2004-5-12-r98" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/gb-2004-5-12-r98</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15575972</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref040">
<label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandelin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alkema</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engstrom</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname> <given-names>WW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenhard</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>JASPAR: an open-access database for eukaryotic transcription factor binding profiles</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>32</volume> (Database issue): <fpage>D91</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkh012" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/nar/gkh012</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681366</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref041">
<label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulzer</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stitzel</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morken</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huyghe</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchsberger</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>A Common Functional Regulatory Variant at a Type 2 Diabetes Locus Upregulates ARAP1 Expression in the Pancreatic Beta Cell</article-title>. <source>The American Journal of Human Genetics</source> <volume>94</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ajhg.2013.12.011" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ajhg.2013.12.011</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24439111</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref042">
<label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melas</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lennartsson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vakifahmetoglu-Norberg</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aberg</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Allele-specific programming of Npy and epigenetic effects of physical activity in a genetic model of depression</article-title>. <source>Transl Psychiatry</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e255</fpage>. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/tp.2013.31" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/tp.2013.31</ext-link>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/tp.2013.31" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/tp.2013.31</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23652932</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref043">
<label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friese</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altshuler</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miramontes-Gonzalez</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hightower</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-22 and promoter motif polymorphisms at the Chga locus in genetic hypertension: functional and therapeutic implications for gene expression and the pathogenesis of hypertension</article-title>. <source>Human Molecular Genetics</source> <volume>22</volume> (<issue>18</issue>): <fpage>3624</fpage>–<lpage>3640</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/hmg/ddt213" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/hmg/ddt213</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23674521</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref044">
<label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bielawski</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Statistical methods for detecting molecular adaptation</article-title>. <source>Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution</source> <volume>15</volume> (<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>496</fpage>–<lpage>503</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11114436</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref045">
<label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzger</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Evidence of positive selection at codon sites localized in extracellular domains of mammalian CC motif chemokine receptor proteins</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-10-139" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2148-10-139</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20459756</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref046">
<label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Common variation in the fat mass and obesity-associated (FTO) gene confers risk of obesity and modulates BMI in the Chinese population</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source> <volume>57</volume> (<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>2245</fpage>–<lpage>2252</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db08-0377" xlink:type="simple">10.2337/db08-0377</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18487448</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref047">
<label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mutation-selection models of codon substitution and their use to estimate selective strengths on codon usage</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>25</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>579</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msm284" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/molbev/msm284</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18178545</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref048">
<label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohashi</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naka</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Natsuhara</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamauchi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>FTO polymorphisms in oceanic populations</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>52</volume> (<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1031</fpage>–<lpage>1035</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17928949</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref049">
<label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Identification of Selection Footprints on the X Chromosome in Pig</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>9</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>e94911</fpage> EP -. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0094911" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0094911</ext-link>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0094911" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0094911</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24740293</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref050">
<label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pybus</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dall’Olio</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luisi</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uzkudun</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carreno-Torres</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>1000 Genomes Selection Browser 1.0: a genome browser dedicated to signatures of natural selection in modern humans</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>42</volume> (Database issue): <fpage>D903</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkt1188" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/nar/gkt1188</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24275494</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref051">
<label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maandag</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Izon</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amsen</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kruisbeek</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>E2A proteins are required for proper B cell development and initiation of immunoglobulin gene rearrangements</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>79</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>892</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8001125</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref052">
<label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shy</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuen</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Opposing effects of Tcf3 and Tcf1 control Wnt stimulation of embryonic stem cell self-renewal</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>13</volume> (<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>762</fpage>–<lpage>770</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ncb2283" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ncb2283</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21685894</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref053">
<label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niakan</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maehr</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vokes</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodolfa</surname> <given-names>KT</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Sox17 promotes differentiation in mouse embryonic stem cells by directly regulating extraembryonic gene expression and indirectly antagonizing self-renewal</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>24</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gad.1833510" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/gad.1833510</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20123909</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref054">
<label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smemo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tena</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gamazon</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakabe</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Obesity-associated variants within FTO form long-range functional connections with IRX3</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>507</volume> (<issue>7492</issue>): <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature13138" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature13138</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24646999</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref055">
<label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorkin</surname> <given-names>DU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Genetics: Closing the distance on obesity culprits</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>507</volume> (<issue>7492</issue>): <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature13212" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature13212</ext-link>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature13212" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature13212</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24646989</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref056">
<label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loos</surname> <given-names>Ruth JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeo</surname> <given-names>Giles SH</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The bigger picture of FTO--the first GWAS-identified obesity gene</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Endocrinol</source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrendo.2013.227" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrendo.2013.227</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24247219</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0117093.ref057">
<label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tung</surname> <given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayuso</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Rahilly</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Hypothalamic-specific manipulation of Fto, the ortholog of the human obesity gene FTO, affects food intake in rats</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>5</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>e8771</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0008771" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0008771</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20098739</object-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>