<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-06735</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computational biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genetic polymorphism</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genetic polymorphism</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Evolutionary genetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genetic polymorphism</subject>
                <subject>Natural selection</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Population biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genetic polymorphism</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Rheumatology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Osteoarthritis</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
          <subject>Rheumatology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Positive Selection on the Osteoarthritis-Risk and Decreased-Height Associated Variants at the <italic>GDF5</italic> Gene in East Asians</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Positive Selection on the <italic>GDF5</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Dong-Dong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Gui-Mei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Jin</surname>
            <given-names>Wei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Yan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Ya-Ping</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Resources and Evolution, Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Laboratory for Conservation and Utilization of Bio-resource, Yunnan University, Kunming, China</addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mailund</surname>
            <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Aarhus University, Denmark</addr-line>
      </aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">zhangyp@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: DDW GML WJ YPZ. Performed the experiments: GML WJ. Analyzed the data: DDW YL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: DDW YL GML WJ. Wrote the paper: DDW YPZ.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e42553</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><permissions>
        
        <copyright-holder>Wu et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions><abstract>
        <p>GDF5 is a member of the bone morphogenetic protein (BMP) gene family, and plays an important role in the development of the skeletal system. Variants of the gene are associated with osteoarthritis and height in some human populations. Here, we resequenced the gene in individuals from four geographically separated human populations, and found that the evolution of the promoter region deviated from neutral expectations, with the sequence evolution driven by positive selection in the East Asian population, especially the haplotypes carrying the derived alleles of 5′ UTR SNPs rs143384 and rs143383. The derived alleles of rs143384 and rs143383, which are associated with a risk of osteoarthritis and decreased height, have high frequencies in non-Africans and show strong extended haplotype homozygosity and high population differentiation in East Asian. It is concluded that positive selection has driven the rapid evolution of the two osteoarthritis osteoarthritis-risk and decreased height associated variants of the human <italic>GDF5</italic> gene, and supports the suggestion that the reduction in body size during the terminal Pleistocene and Holocene period might have been an adaptive process influenced by genetic factors.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31061160189). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="9"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Humans are characterized by many unique traits, such as cognitive ability, language speaking, special skeletal anatomy, and susceptibility to diseases, which distinguish us from our closest relative, the chimpanzee (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Varki1">[1]</xref>). In addition, modern humans exhibit substantial phenotypic variation, e.g., susceptibility to diseases, metabolism, skin pigmentation, eye and hair color, body mass, height, and craniofacial differences shaped by the skeletal system. Many studies have examined the genetic bases of the evolutionary patterns of these phenotypes and have identified the role of positive selection on genes in processes such as brain development in the human lineage and skin pigmentation among modern human populations (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Sabeti1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Wu1">[3]</xref>). Similarly, in our previous studies we had concluded that positive selection in human skeletal genes had driven population differentiation in non-African populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Wu2">[4]</xref>, and identified a few skeletal genes that were subjected to this natural selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-He1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Wu3">[6]</xref>. To better understand the evolutionary forces acting upon skeletal genes, and associated traits, here we studied another critical skeletal gene, <italic>GDF5</italic>, in modern human populations.</p>
      <p>GDF5 (growth differentiation factor 5) is a member of the bone morphogenetic protein (BMP) gene family and the TGF-beta superfamily and plays an essential role in the skeletal development. GDF5 is expressed in the primordial cartilage of appendicular skeleton, with little expression in the axial skeleton such as vertebrae and ribs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Chang1">[7]</xref>, and is required for the normal formation of bones and joints in the limbs, skull, and axial skeleton <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Settle1">[8]</xref>. Several kinds of skeletal disorders (e.g., acromesomelic dysplasia, Hunter-Thompson Type <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Thomas1">[9]</xref>; brachydactyly, type C <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Yang1">[10]</xref>; chondrodysplasia, Grebe type <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Thomas2">[11]</xref>; fibular hypoplasia and complex brachydactyly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-FaiyazUlHaque1">[12]</xref>) are caused by mutations in the <italic>GDF5</italic> gene. The allele A of the SNP rs143383 in the 5′ promoter region of the <italic>GDF5</italic> gene was found to be associated with an increased risk of osteoarthritis, and shows decreased transcriptional activity of <italic>GDF5</italic> in chondrogenic cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Miyamoto1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Chapman1">[15]</xref>. In addition, this allele is associated with decreased height, which may be due to the lower expression of <italic>GDF5</italic> that could lead to a reduction in limb bone growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Sanna1">[16]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The functional importance of <italic>GDF5</italic> in skeletal development raises the possibility that this gene may contribute to the evolution of the human skeletal system. Evidence indicates that the human skeletal system has evolved rapidly since the advent of agriculture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Larsen1">[17]</xref> suggesting that the selective pressures on skeletal genes changed during this process. Indeed, skeletal genes do demonstrate high population differentiation among different human populations, which was driven by positive selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Wu2">[4]</xref>. The genetic basis, however, of the evolution of human skeletal system largely remains undocumented. Here we studied the population variation of the human <italic>GDF5</italic> gene by sequencing alleles from 142 individuals from four geographically separated populations from Africa, Europe, East Asia and South Asia. Positive selection was identified as operating on the 5′ UTR region of the gene in the East Asian population, with the target of selection being the derived alleles of the SNPs rs143384 and rs143383.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Of the 284 chromosomes sequenced, 13 mutations were identified in the 1359 bp exon 1 region, which includes 5′ UTR and some coding sequences of <italic>GDF5</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). To better study the sequence variation, we used the SNPs to construct haplotypes using the PHASE program <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Stephens1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Stephens2">[19]</xref>, and identified 16 haplotypes. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0042553-t001">Table 1</xref> summarizes the population genetics data, including values for the nucleotide diversity, Tajima's D, Fu and Li's D, D*, F and F*, and Fay and Wu's H (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). Population demographic history is the major confounding factor affecting the detection of positive selection. For example, negative values of Tajima's D can be attributed to population expansion, positive selection, or negative selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Sabeti1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Bamshad1">[20]</xref>, therefore, we used coalescence simulations, incorporating best-fit demographic parameters for the populations including European, African, and East Asian <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Schaffner1">[21]</xref>, to better understand the demographic histories of the populations. The results of the simulations indicated it was mostly positive selection rather than demographic effect that generated the variation of <italic>GDF5</italic>, although the factor of demographic effect can not be excluded absolutely. In the East Asian population, Fu and Li's D, and D* demonstrated significantly lower values with a <italic>P</italic>-value lower than 0.05. In the 875 bp sequenced exon 2 region 4 mutations were detected and 6 haplotypes were constructed. For this region the population variation did not deviate from the expectation of neutrality (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0042553-t002">Table 2</xref>). The observations for the exon 2 data support the hypothesis that positive selection, and not demographic history, operated on the 5′ UTR region, as demographic history should influence all parts of the gene similarly, and thus would be expected to produce the same pattern of polymorphisms in both the exons 1 and 2 regions. The difference in the patterns seen in the exon 1 and exon 2 regions thus means that demographic history cannot explain the exon 1 pattern.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0042553-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Structure of the human <italic>GDF5</italic> gene structure.</title>
          <p>The human <italic>GDF5</italic> gene is composed of two exons. The two regions sequenced in this study are denoted by the two rectangles.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0042553-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
          <title>Population statistics summary of exon1 region.</title>
        </caption><alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0042553-t001-1" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Exon1 region (1359 bp, 12 SNPs)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nucleotide Diversity</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tajima's D</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's D</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's F</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's D*</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's F*</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fay and Wu's H</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">African (N<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref> = 66)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.209E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.451</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.052</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.129</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.067</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.115</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.703</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">European (N = 72)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.954E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.652</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.207</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.077</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.189</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.089</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.176</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">East Asian (N = 76)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.897E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.446</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>−2.693</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.292</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>−2.583</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.205</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.217</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">South Asian (N = 70)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.097E-03</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.470</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.230</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.365</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.239</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.370</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.865</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Whole populations (N = 284)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.052E-03</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.604</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.531</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.422</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.507</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.404</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.761</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label/>
            <p>The bolds are values significantly lower than 0 with P-value&lt;0.05 by simulating human demographic history incorporating human best-fit model.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt102">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>is the number of chromosomes.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0042553-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
          <title>Population statistics summary of exon 2 region.</title>
        </caption><alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0042553-t002-2" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Exon2 region (875 bp, 4 SNPs)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nucleotide Diversity</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tajima's D</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's D</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's F</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's D*</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's F*</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fay and Wu's H</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">African (N = 66)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.082E-03</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.976</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.508</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.059</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.486</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.042</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.386</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">European (N = 72)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.665E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.331</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.011</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.708</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.991</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.688</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.333</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">East Asian (N = 76)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.360E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.639</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.540</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.204</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.521</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.188</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.069</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">South Asian (N = 70)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.488E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.653</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.713</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.163</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.715</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.163</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.298</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Whole populations (N = 284)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.115E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.409</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.816</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.273</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.804</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.263</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.132</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives></table-wrap>
      <p>Within the 5′ UTR region of the <italic>GDF5</italic> gene there are two SNPs, rs143384 (A/G, derived allele is A) and rs143383 (A/G, derived allele is A), which have high derived allele frequencies in the East Asian population (61.84%, and 60.53%, respectively, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). These two SNPs demonstrate significantly strong linkage disequilibrium (r<sup>2</sup> = 0.857). We divided the 5′ UTR haplotypes into those carrying a derived allele and those carrying an ancestral allele of the SNPs. In the East Asian population only one haplotype carried the A-A pattern composed by the two derived SNP alleles and has a frequency of 60.53% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>). The high derived allele frequency was driven mostly by positive selection, to generate high haplotype homogeneity and was not destroyed by recombination. In contrast, the A-A haplotype is not found in our sequenced Africans (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>). The World-wide allele frequency distribution also did not find the A-A allele in the sequenced Africans, despite the high derived allele frequencies in non-African populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g003">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0042553-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>SNP allele frequencies in the <italic>GDF5</italic> gene.</title>
          <p>(A) Allele frequencies of haplotypes constructed using SNP rs143384 and rs143383 in four separate populations and the whole population. (B) Derived allele frequencies of the two SNPs in the four populations and the whole population.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="pone-0042553-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g003</object-id>
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>World-wide allele frequency distribution of the two SNPs rs143384 and rs143383.</title>
          <p>The data were downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hgdp.uchicago.edu/" xlink:type="simple">http://hgdp.uchicago.edu/</ext-link>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The derived allele A of SNP rs143384 is contained by two haplotypes, and these haplotypes demonstrate lower nucleotide diversity, lower Tajima's D, and significant lower Fu and Li's D* and F* (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05) relative to haplotypes carrying the ancestral allele G (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0042553-t003">Table 3</xref>). The derived allele of the other SNP, rs143383, is contained by only one haplotype, which has a frequency of 60.53%. Haplotypes carrying the derived alleles also diverge from the others in the phylogenetic network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). In the Africans, there are no derived alleles at these two SNPs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g003">Fig. 3</xref>), which indicates that these two SNPs were generated mostly after the “out of African” event. We also calculated the allele age of the derived alleles using the formula <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which considered that allele evolved under a model of neutral evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Slatkin1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Kimura1">[23]</xref>, where p is the allele frequency and t is age, measured in units of 2*N (effective population size) generations. With a generation time of 20–25 years and N = 10000, the ages of the derived alleles of SNPs rs143384 and rs143383 are 311,552∼389,440, 307,950∼384,937 years, respectively. These results suggest that the derived alleles could not reach the high observed frequencies (61.84%, 60.53%) under neutral evolution after the event of “out of Africa”, which only occurred about 100,000 years ago <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Nei1">[24]</xref>. This suggests that positive selection may have been driving these two derived alleles to high frequencies.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0042553-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g004</object-id>
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Median-joining phylogenetic network of the 16 haplotypes at at the exon 1 region.</title>
          <p>Each haplotype is represented by a circle with its area proportional to its frequency. The ancestral haplotype is outlined by a black line. The two haplotypes in the ellipse are the haplotypes that carry the derived allele at SNPs rs143383 and rs143384.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0042553-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
          <title>Population statistics summary of haplotypes carrying derived allele A and ancestral allele G of SNP rs143384.</title>
        </caption><alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0042553-t003-3" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rs143384 derived allele A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Allele Frequency</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nucleotide Diversity</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tajima's D</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's D</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's F</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's D*</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's F*</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">African (N = 0)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">European (N = 38)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.78%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>N.A.</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">East Asian (N = 47)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.84%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.395E-05</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.702</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.752</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.033</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>−2.984</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>−3.026</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">South Asian (N = 26)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.39%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.736E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.869</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.973</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.527</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.968</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.518</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Whole populations (N = 111)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.08%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.302E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.493</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.300</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.811</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.288</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.798</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rs143384 ancestral allele G</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Allele Frequency</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nucleotide Diversity</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tajima's D</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's D</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's F</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's D*</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fu and Li's F*</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">African (N = 66)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.209E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.451</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.052</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.129</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.067</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.115</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">European (N = 34)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.22%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.846E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.075</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.341</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.650</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.302</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.611</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">East Asian (N = 29)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.16%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.111E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.824</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.100</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.028</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.958</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.889</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">South Asian (N = 44)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.61%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.585E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.408</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.090</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.220</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.064</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.196</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Whole populations (N = 173)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.92%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.421E-04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.230</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.179</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.431</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.152</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.407</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt103">
            <label/>
            <p>Bolds are values significantly lower than 0 with P-value&lt;0.05 detected by DnaSP v 5.0 program.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt104">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>European population contains only one haplotype carrying derived allele of rs143384.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <p>Further evidence for positive selection comes from the high population differentiation of the SNPs rs143384 and rs143383 among human populations. Here, we computed the Fst values of the SNPs based on three human populations using African (YRI), European (CEU), and East Asian (EA) data from HapMap to evaluate population differentiation. Fst values among the three populations at SNPs rs143383 and rs143384 are 0.544 and 0.499, respectively, which are higher than the Fst values of other SNPs in the gene regions of chromosome 20 (99.1%, 98.4% percentile rank) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). Fst for the two SNPs between European and African are 0.664 and 0.597, for rs143383 and rs143384, respectively, values that are higher than the Fst values of SNPs in gene region of chromosome 20 (99.6%, 99.3% percentile rank) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g005">Fig. 5D</xref>). Fst for the two SNPs between East Asian and African are 0.735 and 0.705, for rs143383 and rs143384, respectively, values that are higher than the Fst values of SNPs in the gene regions of chromosome 20 (99.5%, 99.3% percentile rank) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>). The Fst values of the two SNPs between East Asian and European, however, are not significantly higher (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>). To further refine our analysis we performed a sliding window analysis of Fst values of other SNPs on chromosome 20 using a 50 kb window size and 25 kb step size. The Fst values of the two <italic>GDF5</italic> SNPs between Europeans and Africans are higher than the 95% percentile rank value for 50 kb regions of chromosome 20 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g005">Fig. 5E</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0042553-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g005</object-id>
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Fst distribution of SNPs across chromosome 20 gene regions.</title>
          <p>(A): Fst among the three populations vs minor allele frequencies (MAF). Big green dot and triangle represent SNPs rs143383 and rs143384. (B) Fst between East Asians and Europeans vs minor allele frequencies (MAF). (C) Fst between East Asians and Africans vs minor allele frequencies (MAF). (D) Fst between Africans and Europeans vs minor allele frequencies (MAF). (E) Sliding window analysis of Fst. Purple, black, brown and gray lines represent Fst among the three populations, Fst between East Asians and Africans, Fst between Africans and Europeans, Fst between East Asians and Europeans, respectively. The vertical line represents the position of <italic>GDF5</italic> gene. Black and brown horizontal lines represent the 95% percentile rank values of Fst values between East Asians and Africans and Fst between Africans and Europeans, respectively.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>To better understand the evolutionary pattern of <italic>GDF5</italic> in the human population we studied the extended haplotype homozygosity (EHH) of the <italic>GDF5</italic> exon 1 region in four populations, using the entire chromosome 20 phased haplotypes as empirical data. In the East Asian population, the major haplotype at the <italic>GDF5</italic> exon 1 and promoter core region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g004">Fig. 4</xref>, haplotype in the ellipse), which contains the derived alleles of SNPs rs143383 and rs143384, reached 10.8986, 4.6377, and 6.7391 at 300 kb, 500 kb and 1000 kb upstream of <italic>GDF5</italic> core region, all of which are higher than the 95% percentile rank values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). These values support the conclusion that positive selection targeted the derived alleles of SNPs rs143383 and rs143384 in the East Asian population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g006">Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0042553-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g006</object-id>
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <title>REHH of the core haplotypes on chromosome 20 and <italic>GDF5</italic>.</title>
          <p>REHH distributions at (A) 300 kb, (B) 500 kb, and (C) 1000 kb upstream and downstream of the core haplotypes. The two lines represent the 99% and 95% percentile rank values. Big dots are the major haplotype at the <italic>GDF5</italic> gene. (D) REHH of the major core haplotype at the <italic>GDF5</italic> gene at varying physical distances (kb).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>We employed an approach described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Voight1">[25]</xref> to roughly estimate the ages of derived alleles of SNPs rs143384 and rs143383, using formula EHH≈Pr (Homozygosity) = e<sup>−2rg</sup>, namely, −ln(EHH)≈g*2r, where Pr(Homozygosity) is the probability that two chromosomes are homozygous at recombination distance r from the core, given identity by decent from a common ancestor g generations ago. Here, we used linear regression of −ln (EHH) and 2r to evaluate the value of g based on the EHH data in East Asian. As in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g007">Fig. 7</xref>, the age of derived allele of SNP rs143384, t = g*25 = 499.2*25 = 12,480 years, and the age of derived allele of SNP 143383, t = g*25 = 488.1*25 = 12,203 years.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0042553-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g007</object-id>
        <label>Figure 7</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Evaluation of the ages of the derived alleles of SNPs rs143383 and rs143384 by linear regression of −ln(EHH) and 2r.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Our previous study indicated that positive selection operated on skeletal genes in non-African populations, including Europeans and East Asians <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Wu2">[4]</xref>. Here, we describe positive selection acting in East Asian populations on a skeletal gene, <italic>GDF5</italic>, which plays a crucial role in the skeletal system. Positive selection probably targeted the derived alleles of SNPs rs143383 and rs143384 in the <italic>GDF5</italic> gene. The advantage of the derived alleles of these two SNPs is not clear. Strong evidence indicates that the derived allele of SNP rs143383 is associated with an increased risk of osteoarthritis, which is associated with decreased transcriptional activity of the <italic>GDF5</italic> gene in chondrogenic cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Miyamoto1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Sanna1">[16]</xref>. Lower expression of <italic>GDF5</italic> should lead to a reduction in limb bone growth and, as expected, the derived allele of rs143383 is associated with decreased height <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Sanna1">[16]</xref>. The two SNPs demonstrate significantly strong linkage disequilibrium, with the frequencies of the A-A and G-G haplotypes being 37.68% and 58.80%, respectively. The function of rs143383 on the expression of <italic>GDF5</italic> is influenced by the state of the rs143384 SNP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Egli1">[26]</xref>. Positive selection has driven the frequency of the derived alleles of these two SNPs to very high levels, leading to the associated decrease in height and increased risk of osteoarthritis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g008">Fig. 8</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0042553-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g008</object-id>
        <label>Figure 8</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Positive natural selection operated upon the derived alleles of SNPs rs143384 and rs143383.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0042553.g008" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>There is a decline in average human body mass, both in size and stature, began in the Late Pleistocene and early Holocene (∼12,000 years BP) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Ruff1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Hawks1">[28]</xref>. During this period, humans transited from lifestyle of close-contact ambush hunting of large mammals to the foraging and collecting of small animals. With the advent of agriculture, humans could produce food rather than needing to foraging for food <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Ruff1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Hawks1">[28]</xref>. Technological improvements decreased the selective advantage of having a larger body, which is metabolically expensive to maintain. Nutritional inadequacies and the spread of infectious disease during the Holocene may also help explain the reductions in human body size <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Ruff1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Hawks1">[28]</xref>. Changes associated with food production appeared to be developmental rather than genetic, however, the reduction in body size may also be due to genetic factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Ruff1">[27]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The ages of the derived alleles of SNPs rs143383 and rs143384 are ∼12,000 years supporting the hypothesis that the Late Pleistocene–Early Holocene decline in human body size results from a genetic factor that was driven by positive selection. Humans with smaller body size might have some advantages, and thus elevated probability of survival, due to the poor socio-economic conditions under nutritional stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Frisancho1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Stini1">[30]</xref>. The decline in body size continued through the Neolithic, after which it was reversed in Europeans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Ruff1">[27]</xref>. It had been concluded that when humans migrated to Europe they increased their body mass and height to facilitate their adaptation to this cold climatic area <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Leppaeluoto1">[31]</xref>.</p>
      <p>A question raised by our analysis is how can variants associated with diseases be positively selection for a fitness advantage? There are two main reasons to resolve this paradox. First, some characters that were adaptively evolved in the past may become maladaptive in a changing environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Wu1">[3]</xref>. For <italic>GDF5</italic>, the derived alleles might have been positively selection for their advantage in the past, such as lower height, which would have increased survival in an environment with a lack of food. That advantage, however, may no longer be necessary. This would be similar to the example of the seven-repeat (7R) allele of the human dopamine receptor D4 (<italic>DRD4</italic>) gene. The 7R allele is associated with attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), however, people carrying this allele may have had an advantage in moving from one place to another during the colonization of world, and thus was driven to high frequency by positive selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Ding1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Harpending1">[33]</xref>. A second reason is gene pleiotropy. Pleiotropy means that a mutation that is advantageous in one instance can be unfavorable in another <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Wu1">[3]</xref>. Osteoarthritis is probably a byproduct of the rapid evolution of human skeletal system. Furthermore, osteoarthritis is a disease associated with ageing, and is rare in individuals below the age of 45 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Southam1">[14]</xref>. This means that the disease of osteoarthritis contributes very little to the fitness of the patient, as it only affects them after reproducing.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Sequencing of <italic>GDF5</italic> alleles in modern humans</title>
        <p><italic>GDF5</italic> gene sequences from a total of 142 unrelated human individuals, including 33 Africans, 36 Europeans, 38 East Asians and 35 South Asians, were chosen randomly from the Human Genome Diversity Cell Line Panel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Cann1">[34]</xref>, were amplified by PCR and sequenced for two regions that include the two exons of the <italic>GDF5</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0042553-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). DNA sequencing was performed on an ABI 3730 automated DNA sequencer. Primer and PCR condition are available on request. Sequences were analyzed by DNAStar software. <italic>GDF5</italic> allele sequences of all individuals were submitted to GenBank under accession numbers GU831600–GU831883.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Population variation analysis based on the re-sequenced data</title>
        <p>SNPs detected in the resequenced <italic>GDF5</italic> alleles were used to construct haplotypes using the program PHASE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Stephens1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Stephens2">[19]</xref>. Median-joining network for the inference of haplotype genealogy was constructed by Network 4.5.1.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Bandelt1">[35]</xref>. The derived allele of each SNP was determined by comparing with the chimpanzee and orangutan sequences from UCSC genome database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.ucsc.edu/" xlink:type="simple">http://genome.ucsc.edu/</ext-link>). Nucleotide diversity, which is the mean pairwise sequence difference, was calculated by the program DnaSP 5.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Librado1">[36]</xref>. A series population genetics parameters, Tajima's D <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Tajima1">[37]</xref>, Fu and Li's D, F, D*, and F* <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Fu1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Fu2">[39]</xref>, and Fay and Wu's H <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Fay1">[40]</xref>, were used to measure deviation from neutrality in each population. Demographic history and natural selection can both generate similar patterns of population variation. For example, negative values of Tajima's D, Fu and Li's D, F, D*, F* can be due to either positive selection or population expansion. Accordingly, coalescent simulations were constructed that incorporate the best-fit demographic parameters, as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Schaffner1">[21]</xref>, to calculate the significance of the deviation from neutrality.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>EHH analysis</title>
        <p>Data on the genotypes of SNPs of chromosome 20 for the individuals that we resequenced for <italic>GDF5</italic> were downloaded from the Harvard HGDP-CEPH Genotypes for Population Genetics Analyses FLAT FILES SUPPLEMENT 10 from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cephb.fr/en/hgdp/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.cephb.fr/en/hgdp/</ext-link>. We merged the SNPs data at <italic>GDF5</italic> to the genotyped data for chromosome 20 and constructed haplotypes for each chromosome using the fastPHASE program <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Scheet1">[41]</xref>. Positively selected alleles or haplotypes will quickly become accumulate, and tend to have strong extended haplotype homozygosity with surrounding loci as recombination would not have time to disrupt it <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Sabeti2">[42]</xref>. Here, the extended haplotype homozygosity (EHH) and REHH (relative EHH) for each haplotype at 300 kb, 500 kb, and 1000 kb upstream and downstream of the core region were calculated by the Sweep program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/mpg/sweep/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.broadinstitute.org/mpg/sweep/</ext-link>). In addition, the world-wide allele frequency distribution of the two GDF5 SNPs rs143384 and rs143383 was downloaded from the hgdp selection browser (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hgdp.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/gbrowse/HGDP/" xlink:type="simple">http://hgdp.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/gbrowse/HGDP/</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Population differentiation analysis</title>
        <p>Population differentiation of the SNPs on chromosome 22 was described in Wu and Zhang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Wu4">[43]</xref>, which employed method from Weir BS and Cockerham <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Weir1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-Akey1">[45]</xref>, and HapMap Phase II (release 24, NCBI36) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0042553-The1">[46]</xref> for the three populations: African (YRI panel including 60 Yoruban individuals from Ibadan), European (CEU panel including 60 individuals of Utah residents with ancestry from northern and western Europe) and East Asian (EA panels including 45 Han Chinese (HCB) and 45 Japanese from Tokyo (JPT)). A sliding window analysis was performed with a window size of 50 kb and a step size of 25 kb.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Prof. David Irwin for improving the writing of the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Varki1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altheide</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Comparing the human and chimpanzee genomes: searching for needles in a haystack</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1746</fpage>–<lpage>1758</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Sabeti1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabeti</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lohmueller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Varilly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Positive natural selection in the human lineage</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>312</volume>: <fpage>1614</fpage>–<lpage>1620</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Wu1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Positive Darwinian selection in human population: A review</article-title>. <source>Chinese Science Bulletin</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>1457</fpage>–<lpage>1467</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Wu2">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Positive selection drives population differentiation in the skeletal genes in modern humans</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2341</fpage>–<lpage>2346</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-He1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>QP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Intriguing balancing selection on the intron 5 region of LMBR1 in humanpopulation</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>2948</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Wu3">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>NLS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name> <article-title>Evidence for Positive Selection on the Osteogenin (BMP3) Gene in Human Populations</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e10959</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Chang1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vukicevic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Cartilage-derived morphogenetic proteins. New members of the transforming growth factor-beta superfamily predominantly expressed in long bones during human embryonic development</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>269</volume>: <fpage>28227</fpage>–<lpage>28234</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Settle1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Settle</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rountree</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thacker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Multiple joint and skeletal patterning defects caused by single and double mutations in the mouse Gdf6 and Gdf5 genes</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source> <volume>254</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Thomas1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nandedkar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cervenka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>A human chondrodysplasia due to a mutation in a TGF-β superfamily member</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Yang1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Novel point mutations in GDF5 associated with two distinct limb malformations in Chinese: brachydactyly type C and proximal symphalangism</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Thomas2">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kilpatrick</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erlacher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lembessis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Disruption of human limb morphogenesis by a dominant negative mutation in CDMP1</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-FaiyazUlHaque1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faiyaz-Ul-Haque</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaidi</surname><given-names>SHE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teebi</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Mutation in the cartilage-derived morphogenetic protein-1 (CDMP1) gene in a kindred affected with fibular hypoplasia and complex brachydactyly (DuPan syndrome)</article-title>. <source>Clin Genet</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>454</fpage>–<lpage>458</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Miyamoto1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mabuchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takatori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A functional polymorphism in the 5′ UTR of GDF5 is associated with susceptibility to osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>533</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Southam1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Southam</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Lopez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pombo-Suarez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snelling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>An SNP in the 5′-UTR of GDF5 is associated with osteoarthritis susceptibility in Europeans and with in vivo differences in allelic expression in articular cartilage</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>2226</fpage>–<lpage>2232</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Chapman1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meulenbelt</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Lopez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A meta-analysis of European and Asian cohorts reveals a global role of a functional SNP in the 5′UTR of GDF5 with osteoarthritis susceptibility</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1497</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Sanna1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagaraja</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Common variants in the GDF5-UQCC region are associated with variation in human height</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Larsen1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Biological changes in human populations with agriculture</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Anthropol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Stephens1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A comparison of bayesian methods for haplotype reconstruction from population genotype data</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>1162</fpage>–<lpage>1169</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Stephens2">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A new statistical method for haplotype reconstruction from population data</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>978</fpage>–<lpage>989</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Bamshad1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bamshad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wooding</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Signatures of natural selection in the human genome</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Schaffner1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Calibrating a coalescent simulation of human genome sequence variation</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1576</fpage>–<lpage>1583</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Slatkin1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slatkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rannala</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Estimating allele age</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>385</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Kimura1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>The age of a neutral mutant persisting in a finite population</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Nei1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Genetic support for the out-of-Africa theory of human evolution</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>6720</fpage>–<lpage>6722</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Voight1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voight</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kudaravalli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A map of recent positive selection in the human genome</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e72</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Egli1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egli</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Southam</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pombo-Suarez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Functional analysis of the osteoarthritis susceptibility-associated GDF5 regulatory polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Arthritis &amp; Rheumatism</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>2055</fpage>–<lpage>2064</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Ruff1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Variation in human body size and shape</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Anthropol</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Hawks1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Selection for smaller brains in Holocene human evolution</article-title>. <volume>arXiv</volume>: <fpage>11025604v1</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Frisancho1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frisancho</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pallardel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yanez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Adaptive significance of small body size under poor socio-economic conditions in southern Peru</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthrop</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Stini1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Stini WA (1975) Adaptive strategies of human populations under nutritional stress. Physiological and Morphological Adaptation and Evolution: The Hague, Netherlands: Mouton. pp. 387–408.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Leppaeluoto1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leppaeluoto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hassi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Human physiological adaptations to the arctic climate</article-title>. <source>Arctic</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Ding1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y-C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grady</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morishima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Evidence of positive selection acting at the human dopamine receptor D4 gene locus</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Harpending1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harpending</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>In our genes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Cann1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cann</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Toma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cazes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Legrand</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A human genome diversity cell line panel</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>296</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Bandelt1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandelt</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rohl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Median-joining networks for inferring intraspecific phylogenies</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Librado1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Librado</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>DnaSP v5: a software for comprehensive analysis of DNA polymorphism data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1451</fpage>–<lpage>1452</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Tajima1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Statistical method for testing the neutral mutation hypothesis by DNA polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Fu1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Statistical tests of neutrality of mutations against population growth, hitchhiking and background selection</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>915</fpage>–<lpage>925</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Fu2">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Statistical tests of neutrality of mutations</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>709</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Fay1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Hitchhiking under positive Darwinian selection</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>155</volume>: <fpage>1405</fpage>–<lpage>1413</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Scheet1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A fast and flexible statistical model for large-scale population genotype data: applications to inferring missing genotypes and haplotypic phase</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>644</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Sabeti2">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabeti</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>HZP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Detecting recent positive selection in the human genome from haplotype structure</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>419</volume>: <fpage>832</fpage>–<lpage>837</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Wu4">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Different level of population differentiation among human genes</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Weir1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cockerham</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Estimating F-statistics for the analysis of population structure</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1358</fpage>–<lpage>1370</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-Akey1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akey</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shriver</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Interrogating a high-density SNP map for signatures of natural selection</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1805</fpage>–<lpage>1814</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0042553-The1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">The International HapMap Consortium</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A second generation human haplotype map of over 3.1 million SNPs</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>449</volume>: <fpage>851</fpage>–<lpage>861</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>