<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-19335</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077815</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mitochondrial and Nuclear Genes-Based Phylogeography of <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic> (Murinae) and Sub-Saharan Open Habitats Pleistocene History</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Phylogeography of the Nile Grass Rat</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobigny</surname><given-names>Gauthier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatard</surname><given-names>Caroline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>Philippe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ba</surname><given-names>Khalilou</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duplantier</surname><given-names>Jean-Marc</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kergoat</surname><given-names>Gael J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>IRD, CBGP (IRD, Inra, CIRAD, Montpellier SupAgro), Campus de Baillarguet, Montferrier-sur-Lez, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Centre Régional Agrhymet, Rive Droite, Niamey, Niger</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Inra, CBGP (IRD, Inra, CIRAD, Montpellier SupAgro), Campus de Baillarguet, Montferrier-sur-Lez, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>IRD, CBGP (IRD, Inra, CIRAD, Montpellier SupAgro), Dakar, Senegal</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanyon</surname><given-names>Roscoe</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Florence, Italy</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">kergoat@supagro.inra.fr</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: GD CT PG. Performed the experiments: GD CT PG. Analyzed the data: GD GJK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: GD CT PG KB JMD LG. Wrote the paper: GD CT JMD LG GJK.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<elocation-id>e77815</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Dobigny et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>A phylogeographic study was conducted on the Nile grass rat, <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic>, a rodent species that is tightly associated with open grasslands from the Sudano-Sahelian regions. Using one mitochondrial (cytochrome b) and one nuclear (intron 7 of Beta Fibrinogen) gene, robust patterns were retrieved that clearly show that (i) the species originated in East Africa concomitantly with expanding grasslands some 2 Ma, and (ii) four parapatric and genetically well-defined lineages differentiated essentially from East to West following Pleistocene bioclimatic cycles. This strongly points towards allopatric genetic divergence within savannah refuges during humid episodes, then dispersal during arid ones; secondary contact zones would have then stabilized around geographic barriers, namely, Niger River and Lake Chad basins. Our results pertinently add to those obtained for several other African rodent as well as non-rodent species that inhabit forests, humid zones, savannahs and deserts, all studies that now allow one to depict a more comprehensive picture of the Pleistocene history of the continent south of the Sahara. In particular, although their precise location remains to be determined, at least three Pleistocene refuges are identified within the West and Central African savannah biome.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>The authors have no support or funding to report.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Current climatic changes and their consequences on the evolution of biodiversity are a hotly debated topic with sometimes highly divergent predictive scenarios <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Parmesan1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Bellard1">[6]</xref>. In most groups, long-term surveys are still lacking to provide robust predictions under various potential scenarios. In such a context, though at a very different scale, the reconstruction of past eco-climatic modifications may provide helpful pieces of information. In particular, when interpreted through available paleo-environmental frameworks, phylogeographic studies of habitat-specialist species can join the cortege of data that is necessary to draw the complete picture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Avise1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Pease1">[8]</xref>. Even more instructive is the comparison of phylogeographic patterns obtained in several species sharing the same biogeographic regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Beaty1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Poelchau1">[11]</xref>.</p>
<p>In Africa, a majority of phylogeographic investigations have been conducted on large mammals (see references below; review in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lorenzen1">[10]</xref>). Yet, the latter are now usually confined to protected areas where recent demographic and genetic effects may mask signatures of more ancient evolutionary events. In contrast, rodents appear as excellent alternative phylogeographic markers owing to their usually strong affinities to particular ecological niches and wide geographic distribution, their short generation time, their weak dispersal abilities as well as their small size that may render them highly sensible to geographic barriers such as mountains or large rivers, thus limiting admixture between allopatrically differentiated lineages. Altogether, these characteristics are expected to greatly facilitate detection of phylogeographic patterns. Moreover, most of rodent species being abundant and non-protected (when not pest organisms), they are relatively easy to sample, thus facilitating the gathering of datasets that are appropriate for phylogeographic/population studies. This may explain why all African species investigated so far led to strong phylogeographic signals, as well as remarkable congruence between sometimes highly divergent taxa. Indeed, data are now available for rodent species inhabiting arid zones (<italic>Jaculus jaculus</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-BenFaleh1">[12]</xref>), steppes, shrub and tree savannahs (<italic>Lemniscomys striatus</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas1">[13]</xref>; <italic>Praomys daltoni</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Bryja1">[14]</xref>; <italic>Mastomys erythroleucus</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Brouat1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny1">[16]</xref>; <italic>Mastomys natalensis</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Colangelo1">[17]</xref>), rocky habitats (<italic>Acomys chudeaui</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas2">[18]</xref>), humid areas (<italic>Mastomys huberti</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Mouline1">[19]</xref>), forest-savannah mosaics [<italic>Mus (Nannomys) minutoides</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Mboumba1">[20]</xref> and forests (<italic>Praomys rostratus</italic> and <italic>P. tullbergi</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas3">[21]</xref>; <italic>P. misonnei</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas4">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas5">[23]</xref>).</p>
<p>As part of this process, we here focused on the Nile grass rat, <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic> (Muridae, Murinae). This species ranges all along the Southern limit of the Sahara desert, throughout the Sahelian and Sudanian regions, from the Atlantic to the Indian Oceans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Musser1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Granjon1">[25]</xref>. As such, <italic>A. niloticus</italic> biogeographic evolution is expected to provide interesting insights on the effects of past eco-climatic changes on sub-Saharan steppes and savannahs. The genus <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> contains seven currently recognized species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Musser1">[24]</xref>, all found south of the Sahara desert, from the Atlantic coast in Senegal to Ethiopia, and down south to Zambia, with the exceptions of populations along the Nile Valley in Egypt, south west of the Arabian Peninsula, and a mention from the Hoggar mountains, south east Algeria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Musser1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Granjon1">[25]</xref>. Many of them represent sibling species whose boundaries and phylogenetic relationships have essentially been resolved thanks to cytogenetic and molecular studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Granjon2">[26]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-AbdelRahman1">[33]</xref>. Nevertheless, systematic investigations are still required, particularly for several East African taxa (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Castiglia2">[32]</xref>, and below) as well as other ambiguous taxonomic units (e.g. ANI-2 and ANI-4; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny2">[34]</xref>).</p>
<p>The Nile grass rat <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic> is a well-defined species characterized by a 2N = 62/number of autosomal arms (NFa) = 62–64 karyotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Granjon2">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz2">[28]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Volobouev1">[30]</xref>). This species exhibits the widest distribution within the genus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Musser1">[24]</xref>. It is rather generalist and inhabits steppes, savannahs as well as humid zones and human-modified biotopes (e.g. villages, gardens, rice fields, sometimes within cities) of the Sahelian and Sudanian bioclimatic zones where it is considered a major agricultural pest <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Granjon1">[25]</xref>. <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic> has also been shown to carry a number of pathogens, such as <italic>Leishmania major</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-ElGithure1">[35]</xref>, <italic>Borrelia</italic> spp. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Trape1">[36]</xref>, <italic>Leptospira</italic> spp. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Sebek1">[37]</xref>, <italic>Rickettsia</italic> spp. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Julvez1">[38]</xref>, <italic>Schistosoma</italic> spp. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Duplantier1">[39]</xref> or <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Mercier1">[40]</xref>. Yet, our understanding of evolutionary patterns in the Nile grass rat still relies on very scarce data, and no wide scale survey has been performed on this species to date. Previous cytogenetic studies have suggested the possible existence of two lineages, a West African one (ANI-1a, <italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Volobouev1">[30]</xref>) and another Central and East African one (ANI-1b) whose karyotypes would differ by a pericentric inversion on pair 30 (NFa = 62 and 64, respectively; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Volobouev1">[30]</xref>). Recently, Abdel Rahman <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-AbdelRahman1">[33]</xref> proposed some preliminary hypotheses about <italic>A. niloticus</italic> phylogeography and demogenetics using only mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) sequence data. Unfortunately, their study was based on only 26 specimens, 23 of which were sampled in Sudan, making their results likely biased and uninformative at a wider scale.</p>
<p>In order to fill this gap, we performed a comprehensive phylogeographic survey of <italic>A. niloticus</italic> based on a sample that covers all the species range. In contrast with previous phylogeographic studies dealing with West and Central African rodents (see above), we used both a mitochondrial (cytochrome b) and a non-translated part of a nuclear (Beta Fibrinogen intron 7) coding genes to infer the evolutionary history of our species of interest. We also implemented more thorough time calibration analyses, by using independent set of constraints based either on fossil data or on secondary calibrations. Finally, our results are discussed in regards to those previously obtained for other rodent as well as non-rodent species in this part of Africa.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Sampling Effort</title>
<p>In total, 105 individuals of <italic>A. niloticus</italic> and two <italic>A. ansorgei</italic> individuals were trapped during various field surveys conducted in seven countries (Burkina-Faso, Cameroon, Chad, Mali, Niger, Mauritania and Senegal; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t001">Table 1</xref>). Organs or hind feet digits were conserved in ethanol until use in the laboratory. In addition, fibroblast cell pellets from one <italic>A. niloticus</italic> specimen from Egypt and two <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> individuals from Kenya were kindly provided by V. Volobouev (Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris, France). Four ethanol-preserved samples of <italic>A. niloticus</italic> from Sudan (courtesy of E. Abdel Rahman, Natural Science Museum, Durban, South Africa) and one <italic>A. ansorgei</italic> from Burkina-Faso (courtesy of M. Deniau) were also available. All these specimens (115 in total) were sequenced for the mitochrondrial cytochrome b gene (cytb), while some representatives were selected among them for the intron 7 of the nuclear gene Beta Fibrinogen (Fib7) sequencing (see details below). In addition, 54 cytb sequences were downloaded from GenBank, among which 34 <italic>A. niloticus</italic> representatives (one from Egypt, one from Senegal, two from Niger, seven from Cameroon and 23 from Sudan), nine representatives of other <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> species as well as 11 representatives of other genera (<italic>Aethomys, Desmomys, Golunda, Mylomys, Otomys, Pelomys</italic>, and <italic>Rhabdomys</italic>). For the fib7 dataset we also used a sequence from a specimen of <italic>Mastomys erythroleucus</italic> that was trapped in Mali. Finally, one <italic>Lemniscomys</italic> cytb sequence was kindly provided by V. Nicolas (Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris, France). The rationale here (see also the <italic>Phylogenetic and dating analyses</italic> section for details) was: (i) to have a dense sampling of <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> species in order to properly enforce the corresponding fossil constraint; (ii) include species used in previous studies within Arvicanthini and Murinae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz4">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lecompte1">[42]</xref> in order to perform secondary calibrations. Associated voucher specimens are deposited in the collections of the Centre de Biologie pour la Gestion des Populations (CBGP, France), Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle (MNHN, France) and Durban Natural Science Museum (DM); they can be recovered using numbers provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0077815-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Samples used in this study, with the individual reference numbers of the different collections where they are registered.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0077815-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individuals and species</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Origin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lat.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cyt b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fib7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Labels</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: AF004568.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethiopia, Koka</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">08°26N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39°02E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eth 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5659, M5678</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burkina-Faso, Niassan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°07N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">03°26W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BF 1,2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: HM635824</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon, Gamnaga</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°57N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°03E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cam 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: HM635825</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon, Kongola</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°37N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°25E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cam 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: HM635826</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon, Kongola</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°37N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°25E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cam 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: HM635827; CBGP: C344, C345, C352, C353</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon, Maga</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°50N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°57E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cam 2, 6–9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: C358, C374; GenBank: HM635835, HM635836</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon, Maga</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°50N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°57E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cam 10–13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: HM635828</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon, Maga</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°50N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°57E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cam 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: VV1998-060</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chad, Farcha</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°06N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°03E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cha 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: VV1998-061, VV1999-213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chad, Farcha</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°06N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°03E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cha 7,8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: 2000-060</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chad, Goz Djerat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°59N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19°55E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cha 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: 2000-061</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chad, Goz Djerat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°59N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19°55E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cha 6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4134</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chad, Zakouma NP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°44N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19°40E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cha 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4159, N3085</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chad, Zakouma NP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°44N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19°40E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cha 2,3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: VV1995-073</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egypt, breeding colony</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egy 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: AF004569</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egypt, breeding colony</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egy 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5240</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Abeibara</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19°01N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">01°45E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KM1039</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Ansongo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°40N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00°30E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5647</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Bintagoungou</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°44N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">03°44W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4060</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Boulou</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°11N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09°31W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4189</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Dialo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°28N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11°30W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5645</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Dianké</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°45N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">04°39W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4260</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Dirimbé</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°01N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°54W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: VV1999-054</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Edjerir</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18°12N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">01°24E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: VV1999-046</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Edjerir</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18°12N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">01°24E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5385</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Emnalhere</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°28N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">04°05W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4605</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Farabougou</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°53N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">06°08W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4675</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Farabougou</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°53N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">06°08W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4680</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Gono</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°03N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°47W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4771</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Gono</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°03N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°47W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5649</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Goubolabo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°54N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">03°59W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4065</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Makana</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°08N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09°26W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: VV1999-076</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Ménaka</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°55N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°25E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5367</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Niono</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°17N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">05°59W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KM1081</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Ouatagouna</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°12N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00°42E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 28</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5639</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, San</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°22N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">04°56W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4209</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Sare Mama</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°53N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">04°02W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4934</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Sare Mama</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°53N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">04°02W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5682</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Tanda</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°46N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">04°38W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: VV1999-049, VV1999-070</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Tararabat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19°24N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">01°14E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 11,12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5265</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Tidermène</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17°01N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°07E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5287</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Tidermène</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17°01N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°07E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4589</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Tirna</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°41N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">04°44W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M4619</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Tirna</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°41N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">04°44W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mal 18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: VV1995-017</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mauritania, Chott Boul</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°37N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°25W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mau 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: VV1995-041</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mauritania, Chott Boul</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°37N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°25W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mau 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N3214</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Agadez</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°58N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">07°59E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N3222</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Agadez</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°58N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">07°59E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N3143</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Bosso</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°41N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°18E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4251</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Boumba</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°25N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°50E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4211</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Boumba</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°25N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°50E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N3266</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Chétimari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°10N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°28E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4078, N4092</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Chétimari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°10N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°28E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 12,13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4094, N4152</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Chétimari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°10N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°28E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 24,25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4096</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Djirataoua</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°24N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">07°08E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4134</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Djirataoua</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°24N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">07°08E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4146</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Gaya</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11°53N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">03°27E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4147</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Gaya</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11°53N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">03°27E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N3267</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Gouré</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°03N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°13E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4135</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Guidimouni</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19°24N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09°30E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N3106, N3107</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Guileyni</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°26N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°42E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 1,2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4271</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Karey Kopto</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°33N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°38E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4273</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Karey Kopto</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°33N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°38E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4093</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Kojimairi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°24N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11°05E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4098, N4109, N4133, N4154, N4159</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Kojimairi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°24N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11°05E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 15, 27–30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: AF004571, AF004570</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Kollo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°21N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°17E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 23,24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N3124</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, N’Guigmi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°15N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°06E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N3144</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Niamey</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°31N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°05E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N4001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Tabelot</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17°36N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">08°56E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N3268</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Tanout</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°57N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">08°53E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5295</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Tiloa</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°09N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°04E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: N3219</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger, Tondibia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°34N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">02°01E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nig 6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB2807, KB2816</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Darou-Wolof</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°00N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°47W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 23,24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: JMD441, JMD447</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Gouniang</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°50N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°26W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 1,2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB932, KB933</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Kaolack</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°10N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°07W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 17,18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB1243</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Lampsar Peuhl</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°05N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°20W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB1244</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Lampsar Peuhl</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°05N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°20W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB924, KB925</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Lindiane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°10N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°09W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 15,16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB3125, KB3126</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Mibess</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°25N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°42W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 25,28</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB2407</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Ndya</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°34N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°45W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB2408</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Ndya</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°34N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°45W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB1191</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Niaga</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°49N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17°16W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB3143</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Pekh Tall</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°27N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°24W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB3150</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Pekh Tall</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°27N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°24W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: AF004572</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Richard Toll</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°28N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°45W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB2765, KB2766</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Saré-Gayo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°51N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°58W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 21,22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB1437</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Savoigne</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°09N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°18W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: JMD645, JMD646</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Sinthiane Doudé</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°25N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°57W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 3,4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB2755</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Sinthiou-Maleme</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°49N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°55W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB2758</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Sinthiou-Maleme</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°49N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°55W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB2441</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Sinthiou-Doudé</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°11N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°45W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB2442</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Sinthiou-Doudé</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°11N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°45W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: KB1335, KB1336</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal, Wouro-Aïb</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°28N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°37W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sen 7,8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: EF128062, 128063, 128064</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan, Dongola</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19°00N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30°29E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud 5–7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: EF128067, EF128068, EF128069</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan, El Sabagola</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17°34N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33°26E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud 3, 10–11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: EF128070, EF128071, EF128072; DM: 9106</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan, El Sabagola</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17°34N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33°26E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud 12–15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM: 8993</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan, El Sabagola</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17°34N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33°26E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM: 9103, 9108</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan, El Suki</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°19N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33°54E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud 1,2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: EF128083, EF128084</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan, El Suki</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13°19N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33°54E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud 26,27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: EF128073, EF128074, EF128075</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan, Khartoum</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°40N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32°35E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud 16–18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: EF128076, EF128077</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan, Khartoum</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°40N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32°35E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud 19,20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: EF128078, EF128079, EF128080</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan, Medani</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°23N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33°29E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud 21–23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: EF128081, EF128082</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan, Medani</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°23N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33°29E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud 24,25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: EF128065, EF128066</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan, Shandi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°42N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33°29E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud 8,9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvicanthis</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">**</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN: VV1996-009, VV1996-010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kenya, Masai Mara NP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">01°49S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35°20E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvicanthis abyssinicus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: AF004567.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethiopia, Menagesha</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09°03N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38°34E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: AF004566.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethiopia, Sululta</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09°11N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38°46E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvicanthis neumanni</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: AF004574<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">****</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tanzania, Berega</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">06°11S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37°09E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: AF004573<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">****</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tanzania, Berega</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">06°11S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37°09E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvicanthis ansorgei</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: Leish NEG 024MS1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burkina-Faso, Pissy</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12°20N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">01°35W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M6068</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burkina-Faso, Toumbani</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11°00N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00°58E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBGP: M5619</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali, Séniéna</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°50N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">05°40W</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvicanthis</italic> sp. (ANI-2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: HM635839</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon, Gamnaga</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°57N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14°03E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANI-2 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: AF004584</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAR, Koumbala</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09°14N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20°42E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANI-2 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvicanthis</italic> cf. <italic>rufinus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: AF004582</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benin, Lokossa</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">06°38N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">01°43E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank: AF004583</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benin, Tanougou</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10°49N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">01°26E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-<italic>Arvicanthis</italic> species</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aethomys chrysophilus</italic> (GenBank: AJ604526.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tanzania</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Desmomys harringtoni</italic> (GenBank: AF141206)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethiopia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Golunda ellioti</italic> (GenBank: AM408338.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lemniscomys striatus</italic> (MNHN: ZM-2008-020)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mastomys erythroleucus</italic> (CBGP: M4136)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mylomys dybowskii</italic> (GenBank: AF141212.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ivory Coast</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pellomys fallax</italic> (GenBank: DQ022382.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tanzania</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Otomys irroratus</italic> (GenBank: EU874434)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Otomys sungae</italic> (GenBank: JF795993)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Otomys tropicalis</italic> (GenBank: JF795995)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rhabdomys pumilio</italic> (GenBank: AF533116)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>“CBGP”, “DM” and “MNHN” stand for Centre de Biologie pour la Gestion des Populations (Montpellier, France), Durban Natural Science Museum (Durban, South Africa) and Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle (Paris, France), respectively. Individuals’ labels corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g001">Figures 1</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g003">3</xref> are also provided.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>*</label><p>referred to as <italic>A. dembeensis</italic> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz3">[29]</xref>;</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>**</label><p>most probably referable to <italic>A. somalicus</italic> (cf. text for details);</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>***</label><p>referred to as <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>abyssinicus</italic> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz3">[29]</xref>;</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>****</label><p>referred to as <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>somalicus</italic> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz3">[29]</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Ethics Statement</title>
<p>Each trapping campaign was validated by national and local authorities. At the French level, all sampling procedures were conducted by biologists from the IRD holding a certificate to carry out experiments on live animals (‘<italic>certificat d’autorisation à expérimenter sur animaux vivants</italic>’; agreement number C34-106, valid until December, 16<sup>th</sup> 2016). The CBGP joint research unit is also holding an agreement to conduct experiments on live animals (‘<italic>établissement agréé pour expérimenter sur animaux vivants’</italic>; agreement number C34-169-1, valid until July, 25<sup>th</sup> 2017). Within each country where sampling was performed, research was systematically made possible thanks to extant conventions between the IRD and local governments (see the regional sections as well as IRD Ethical Guidelines on the IRD website: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ird.fr" xlink:type="simple">www.ird.fr</ext-link>). Additional authorizations were not required because <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> species are considered as pest species (especially <italic>A. niloticus</italic>) and have no protected status (see IUCN and CITES lists). At the local level, traps were systematically set only after the agreement of the village head and the field owner was explicitly obtained. Moreover, in cultivated fields, traps were always posed on the edge of the exploited area, so that no damage could be cause to crops. Nile rats were caught alive in wire-mesh and Sherman traps. All animals were euthanized by cervical dislocation. Animals were treated in a humane manner, and in accordance with guidelines of the American Society of Mammalogists <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Sikes1">[43]</xref>. No ethic country-specific agreement could be obtained since countries where sampling occurred and the IRD have no ethics committee that oversees animal experimentation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>DNA Extraction and Sequencing</title>
<p>Total genomic DNA was extracted using the Puregene DNA Purification Kit (Gentra Systems). The complete cytb mitochondrial gene was then amplified using primers H15915 and L14123 following procedures detailed in Lecompte <italic>et al.</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lecompte2">[44]</xref>. The resulting PCR products were purified and then sequenced in both directions on a MegaBACE 1000 (Amersham Biosciences). Sequences were carefully checked by eye, and aligned using the ClustalW Multiple Alignment option implemented in BioEdit v.7.0.4.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Hall1">[45]</xref>. In total, our cytb dataset includes 169 sequences encompassing 146 <italic>A. niloticus</italic>, two <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic>, 11 other <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> spp. and 10 representatives of other rodent genera (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t001">Table 1</xref>). The complete non translated intron 7 of the Fibrinogen nuclear gene was amplified using primers BFIBR1 and BFIBR2, following Seddon <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Seddon1">[46]</xref>. These PCR products were purified and then sequenced in both directions by Macrogen (Seoul, Korea). In total, our Fib7 dataset groups 67 sequences that represent 60 <italic>A. niloticus</italic>, two <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> from Kenya, four representatives of other <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> species as well as one representative of genus <italic>Mastomys</italic>, to be used as an outgroup (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t001">Table 1</xref>). As stated previously, all individuals sequenced for Fib7 were sequenced for cytb (except for the <italic>A. niloticus</italic> specimen labelled ‘Mal 29′, and the representative of genus <italic>Mastomys</italic>), thus allowing us to build a combined dataset of 1,871 nucleotides (nt) encompassing 171 individuals. Importantly, all 10 countries that are represented for <italic>A. niloticus</italic> or <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> individuals in our cytb dataset are also represented in our Fib7 dataset. Similarly, 57 out of the 72 localities sampled in the <italic>A. niloticus</italic> or <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> cytb dataset were also sampled for Fib7 (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t001">Table 1</xref>), thus providing a very similar and fully overlapping geographic coverage for both genes. All the sequences generated in this study were deposited in GenBank (accession numbers KF478244 to KF478310 for the Fib7 and KF478311 to KF478426 for the cytb).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Phylogenetic and Dating Analyses</title>
<p>Bayesian inference (BI) was used to co-estimate phylogenetic relationships and divergence times using the BEAST v1.7.5 package <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Drummond1">[47]</xref>. BEAST uses Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) procedures to approximate phylogenies and simultaneously infer nodes ages. To infer the time-calibrated phylogeny, we used the Bayesian relaxed clock (BRC) approach <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Drummond2">[48]</xref> implemented in BEAST. This method accounts for rate variation across lineages and assumes that substitution rates are uncorrelated across the tree (there is thus no <italic>a priori</italic> correlation between a lineage rate and that of its ancestor). To maximize the amount of available information, analyses were performed on the combined dataset, using specific sets of parameters for each gene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nylander1">[49]</xref>. Best-fit models of evolution for each gene were selected with jModelTest <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Posada1">[50]</xref> using the Bayesian information criterion (BIC). For the molecular dating analyses, each gene was associated with a specific uncorrelated lognormal relaxed clock (ULRC) model. A coalescent model tree prior with a constant population size was also preferentially used to account for the fact that our trees mostly describe intra-specific relationships <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Heled1">[51]</xref>. BEAST. xml files were also modified to implement the path-sampling (PS) procedure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lartillot1">[52]</xref>, which allows a better approximation of the marginal likelihood of runs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Baele1">[53]</xref>. In a complementary way, we carried out maximum likelihood (ML) analyses with the software RAxML v.7.0.8 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Stamatakis1">[54]</xref> using default settings and 100 random-addition replicates. For the corresponding partitioned analyses, the same best-fit models of evolution (as in BI) were used. Clade support for ML was assessed with non-parametric bootstrap values (BV; 1,000 replicates were used).</p>
<p>Three distinct sets of calibration were used in this study. The first two sets rely on the oldest known fossil occurrence for the genus <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Winkler1">[55]</xref>. This fossil (individual BPRP#76) is a relatively complete specimen found in Kenya, in the Lukeino formation, which was radiometrically dated at 5.9-5.7 million years ago (Ma; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Winkler1">[55]</xref>). We used two distinct parametric distributions (exponential and lognormal) to set a minimum age of 5.7 Ma for the genus <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ho1">[56]</xref>, for more rationale on these settings). The corresponding 5.7 Ma minimum age constraint was enforced as follows: exponentialPrior mean = 5.0, offset = 5.444 (for the exponential distribution), and lognormalPrior mean = 1.0, stdev = 1.0, offset = 5.175 (for the lognormal distribution). For the third set of constraints we used the time-calibrated phylogeny of Lecompte <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lecompte1">[42]</xref> to set a series of secondary calibrations for the nodes that are shared between our respective datasets. Though the use of secondary calibration is not advocated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ho1">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Graur1">[57]</xref>, we conducted these analyses for comparison purpose. The fact that our outgroup choice was based on the result of the study of Lecompte <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lecompte1">[42]</xref> allowed us to identify six shared nodes that were used for secondary calibrations. To do so, we used normal parametric distributions to set minimum and maximum ages for the corresponding nodes. These constraints were enforced as follows: (<italic>i</italic>) most recent common ancestor (MRCA) of <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> and <italic>Aethomys</italic>, normalPrior mean = 6.9 stdev = 1.0; (ii) MRCA of <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> and <italic>Desmomys</italic>, normalPrior mean = 8.4 stdev = 1.0; (iii) MRCA of <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> and <italic>Lemniscomys</italic>, normalPrior mean = 4.8 stdev = 1.0; (iv) MRCA of <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> and <italic>Otomys</italic>, normalPrior mean = 11.0 stdev = 1.0; (v) MRCA of <italic>Desmomys</italic> and <italic>Rhabdomys</italic>, normalPrior mean = 5.1 stdev = 1.0; (vi) MRCA of <italic>Mylomys</italic> and <italic>Pelomys</italic>, normalPrior mean = 3.85 stdev = 1.0.</p>
<p>For each calibration set (‘exponential distribution’; ‘lognormal distribution’; ‘secondary calibrations’), two distinct runs were carried out, each one with 50 million generations, default priors and trees sampled every 5000th generation. After applying a conservative burn-in of 12.5 million generations for each run, convergence of runs was further assessed by examining the effective sample size (ESS) of parameters with Tracer available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/" xlink:type="simple">www.tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/</ext-link>. The resulting log and tree files were then combined using LogCombiner. We then directly estimated both node support (posterior probabilities: PP) and node age (median age estimates and 95% higher posterior densities: 95% HPD) using TreeAnnotator. Only nodes with posterior probabilities (PP) ≥0.95 were considered strongly supported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Erixon1">[58]</xref>. Bayes factor (B<sub>F</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Kass1">[59]</xref>) were then estimated using the log files of the three distinct calibration sets, using scripts detailed in Baele <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Baele1">[53]</xref>. The resulting time-calibrated trees (one per calibration set) were further modified under Mesquite v2.75 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Maddison1">[60]</xref> by pruning the most basal outgroup taxa. For comparison purpose, additional runs (same settings for the MCMC) were also conducted for the cytb dataset (169 taxa; 1,113 nt) and the Fib7 dataset (67 taxa; 758 nt).</p>
<p>Additional phylogenetic-based analyses were also conducted to precise the geographic origin of the various <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic> populations. To do so, we relied on the tree resulting from the analyses of the combined dataset. This tree was further pruned under Mesquite in order to include one specimen for each of the major lineages of <italic>A. niloticus</italic>, and one specimen for each other <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> species. Character optimizations were then performed to infer the ancestral areas of distribution. Three major areas were categorized for this analysis: (i) ‘West Africa’, which includes Benin, Burkina-Faso, Ghana, Mali, Niger, Senegal, Togo; (ii) ‘Central Africa’, which includes Cameroon, Central African Republic, Chad; and (iii) ‘North-East and East Africa’, which here includes Egypt, Ethiopia, Kenya, Somalia, Sudan, Tanzania. We then performed a single state parsimony optimization with Mesquite in order to identify the geographic origin of the MRCA of each <italic>A. niloticus</italic> phylogroups.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Genetic Differentiation, Genetic Diversity and Network Analyses</title>
<p>Analyses at the intraspecific level were performed on datasets that encompass only <italic>A. niloticus</italic> individuals (146 individuals for the cytb dataset and 60 individuals for the Fib7 one). The genetic differentiation between specimens belonging to the major phylogroups inferred by the phylogenetic analyses of the combined dataset was assessed for each gene using DnaSP v.5.1.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Librado1">[61]</xref>. However, the fact that DnaSP does not take into account missing data was problematic for the Fib7 dataset since it led to the exclusion of 113 nucleotide positions. Therefore, we analyzed a subset of the original dataset from which two sequences with a lot of missing data were removed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Gaubert1">[62]</xref>. In order to assess the level of genetic differentiation among the four phylogroups, we used three distinct statistics (F<sub>ST</sub>, K<sub>ST*</sub>, and S<sub>nn</sub>). The F<sub>ST</sub> (fixation index) is a statistic that compares the level of diversity of randomly chosen alleles in a given population with those found in the entire geographical sample; the K<sub>ST*</sub> is a statistic that takes into account the number of nucleotide differences between different haplotypes but does not give much weighting to large numbers of differences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Hudson1">[63]</xref>; the nearest-neighbour statistic (S<sub>nn)</sub> measures how often the nearest neighbours within a matrix of sequences originate from the same population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Hudson2">[64]</xref>. Because these three indices are known to be more or less sensitive to specific dataset features (such as low level of genetic diversity or low sample size), we used them in combination to ensure a more robust detection of genetic differentiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-MoralesHojas1">[65]</xref>. For each statistics, a permutation test of 1,000 replicates was performed to assess the significance of the subdivision parameters. DnaSP was then used to infer the following parameters of genetic diversity: number of segregating sites <italic>(S),</italic> number of haplotypes (<italic>h</italic>), haplotypic (<italic>Hd</italic>) and nucleotide (π) diversities. We also performed neutrality tests for each gene using Tajima’s <italic>D</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Tajima1">[66]</xref> and Fu’s <italic>F</italic> statistics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Fu1">[67]</xref>. For the latter, values close to zero are expected for historically stable populations, whereas negative values would be indicative of recent population expansion.</p>
<p>Finally, networks analyses were conducted on the reduced cytb and fib7 datasets using the reduced median joining method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Bandelt1">[68]</xref>, which has the ability to deal with missing data as well as to infer ancestral haplotypes. This method also performs well against, or outperforms other network approaches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Woolley1">[69]</xref>. It was implemented using the software Network v.4.6.1.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fluxus-engineering.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.fluxus-engineering.com</ext-link>), with ε set to 0 in order to minimize alternative median networks.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Phylogenetic Analyses</title>
<p>The BIC returned a general time reversible (GTR) model+Γ as best-fit model for each gene. For all analyses (combined dataset, or Fib7 and cytb gene alone), convergence was reached as indicated by the high ESS values (&gt;200) recovered for all runs.</p>
<p>Analyses of the combined dataset yield a similar topology whatever the method used (BI or ML; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Overall the corresponding trees are well supported, and most interspecific nodes are supported by PP≥0.95 under BI or bootstrap values ≥70% under ML (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Within the genus <italic>Arvicanthis</italic>, two main plurispecific clades emerge: specimens of <italic>A. ansorgei</italic>, <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>rufinus</italic> and ANI-2 cytotype (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Volobouev1">[30]</xref>) form a well-supported monophyletic group (PP of 1.0/BV of 93%) whose sister assemblage contains (PP of 1.0/BV of 99%) representatives identified as <italic>A. neumanni</italic>, <italic>A. abyssinicus</italic>, <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> (two specimens from Kenya) and <italic>A. niloticus sensu stricto</italic> (i.e. all <italic>A. niloticus</italic> but the two latter Kenyan specimens) here below referred to as <italic>A. niloticus</italic>. Within the former group, <italic>A. ansorgei</italic> forms a first robust monophyletic lineage (PP of 1.0/BV of 100%), while the second one contains <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>rufinus</italic> and ANI-2 individuals (PP of 1.0/BV of 98%). Within the second main <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> assemblage, three lineages were clearly retrieved: lineage A (PP of 0.88/BV ≤50%) is basal and made of two <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> and two <italic>A. neumanni</italic> specimens from Kenya and Tanzania, respectively; then, lineage B (PP of 1.0/BV of 100%) is represented by the two <italic>A. abyssinicus</italic> specimens from Ethiopia; lineage C (PP of 0.71/BV of 84%) groups all <italic>A. niloticus</italic> (from Ethiopia, Sudan, Egypt throughout all other westward countries) specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0077815-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Time-calibrated tree resulting from the partitioned Bayesian analysis of the combined dataset.</title>
<p>Age estimates correspond to the results of the BRC analysis using the fossil constraint with an exponential distribution. Labels on nodes correspond to the nodes listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t002">Table 2</xref>. Posterior probabilities (left) and bootstrap values (right) are also indicated for major nodes (values below&lt;0.50 are not figured). On the bottom left (lower panel), a map is included to figure the localities of almost all sampled <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic> specimens (with the exception of the specimen from Ethiopia and the two specimens from Egypt). Additional information on mountain and hydrogeographic formations of interest is also provided. A red line is also used to figure the distribution limits of the two distinct <italic>A. niloticus</italic> cytotypes (ANI-1a and ANI-1b; see text for details). On the right side, the general origin of <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic> specimens is represented using circles filled with colours corresponding to those used on the map. In addition, vertical sidebars highlight the three major lineages (A, B and C) and the four major clades within the lineage C (C-1, C-2, C-3 and C-4). On the bottom left again (upper panel), the simplified phylogenetic topology of <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> studied here is represented with corresponding geographic origin of extant lineages as well as of MRCA as inferred by the ancestral area optimization under Mesquite (see text for details).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Central to the present study, lineage C splits into four phylogroups (C-1 to C-4), which also correspond to remarkably well-defined and exclusive geographic areas: (i) phylogroup C-1 (PP of 1.0/BV of 99%) contains all <italic>A. niloticus</italic> from Ethiopia, Sudan and Egypt; (ii) phylogroup C-2 (PP of 1.0/BV of 100%) groups all <italic>A. niloticus</italic> from Chad and Northern Cameroon, as well as one specimen from the Western bank of Lake Chad (Bosso) in Niger; (iii) <italic>A. niloticus</italic> individuals from West Mali to Senegal and Mauritania all gather in phylogroup C-3 (PP of 0.48/BV of 57%); (iv) specimens from phylogroup C-4 (PP of 0.48/BV of 60%) are all Nile grass rats originating from Niger, Burkina-Faso, North and East of Mali. In other words, in addition to a perfect match between genetic and geographic structure, a clear differentiation from East (phylogroup C-1 as sister to all remaining group) to West (phylogroups C-3 and C-4 as the most derived ones) is suggested. The latter pattern is also supported by the result of the character optimization of ancestral areas (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g001">Figure 1</xref>), which indicates that the MRCA of all <italic>A. niloticus</italic> phylogroups is of East African origin. On a side note, it is also worthy to notice that individuals from Adrar des Ifoghas massif (specimens 'Mali.10’, ‘Mali.11’, ‘Mali.12’ and ‘Mali.13’) appear genetically very close to each other, while those from Aïr massif (specimens ‘Nig.4’, ‘Nig.5’ and <italic>‘</italic>Nig.9’) do not convincingly do so.</p>
<p>All the aforementioned lineages and phylogroups are recovered by the separate analysis of the cytb gene (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g002">Figure 2</xref>), with moderate (PP of 0.58 for lineage C) to high supports (PP of 0.98 for lineage A, and PP of 1.0 for lineage B and phylogroups C-1, C-2, C-3 and C-4). By contrast, a less resolved and supported topology is inferred by the analysis of the Fib7 gene alone (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g003">Figure 3</xref>), which only identifies two well-supported (PP of 1.0) clades within <italic>A. niloticus</italic>: the first one mixes together individuals that are found in previously mentioned phylogroups C-1 and C-2, while the second one gathers representatives from phylogroups C-3 and C-4. The two Kenyan representatives of <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> were found basal to all other <italic>A. niloticus</italic>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0077815-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Haplotype network and phylogenetic tree resulting from the analysis of the cytb dataset.</title>
<p>The haplotype network reconstruction takes into account missing data and gap so the inferred number of haplotype I higher than the one presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t004">Table 4</xref>. Red values on nodes indicate the inferred number of mutation steps between haplotypes or ancestral haplotypes (symbolized by a red node). The absence of value means that the number of steps is inferior to 10. The phylogenetic tree corresponds to the results of a Bayesian inference analysis (see text for details); posterior probabilities (PP) are indicated for major nodes (values below&lt;0.50 are not figured). On the right side, the general origin of <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic> specimens is figured using circles filled with different colours that directly refer to the map presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g001">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0077815-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Haplotype network and phylogenetic tree resulting from the analysis of the Fib7 dataset.</title>
<p>The haplotype network reconstruction takes into account missing data and gaps, so that the inferred number of haplotypes is higher than the one presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t004">Table 4</xref>. Red values on nodes indicate the inferred number of mutation steps between haplotypes or ancestral haplotypes (symbolized by a red node). The absence of value means that the number of step is equal to 1. The phylogenetic tree corresponds to the results of a Bayesian inference analysis (see text for details); posterior probabilities (PP) are indicated for major nodes (values below&lt;0.50 are not figured). On the right side, the general origin of <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic> specimens is figured using circles filled with different colours that directly refer to the map presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g001">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Divergence Time Estimates</title>
<p>Regarding dating analyses, the ‘secondary calibrations’ set yields younger age estimates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t002">Table 2</xref>). The latter is problematic since the age of the oldest known <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> fossil (5.7–5.9 Ma) significantly predates the median age resulting from the ‘secondary calibrations’ calibration set (4.71 Ma). The two other calibration sets recover very similar median ages, which never differ from more than 1 Ma when considering Arvicanthini lineages. Because the ‘exponential distribution’ calibration set is significantly favoured by the corresponding B<sub>F</sub> comparison (Ln B<sub>F</sub> = −10881.60+11332.01 = 450.41), we chose to preferentially present the corresponding age estimates in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g001">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0077815-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Bayesian relaxed clock age estimates (Ma) based on three distinct calibration sets (fossil constraint with an ‘exponential distribution’, fossil constraint with a ‘lognormal distribution’, ‘secondary calibrations’).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0077815-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Node</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ancestor of</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clade of interest</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Fossil constr. (expon.)</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Fossil constr. (lognormal)</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Secondary calibrations</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% HPD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% HPD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% HPD</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Otomys tropicalis</italic> - <italic>Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sen.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.08</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.87–30.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.52–25.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.02–12.60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Golunda ellioti</italic> - <italic>Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sen.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Arvicanthini</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.04–22.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70–19.30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.19–11.14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lemniscomys striatus - Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sen.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.68–14.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.83</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.67–12.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.65–7.56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. ansorgei</italic> 1 <italic>- Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sen.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Arvicanthis</italic></bold><bold> spp.</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.44 –11.41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.27–10.24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40–6.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. ansorgei</italic> 1 <italic>- Arvi. rufinus</italic> 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67–7.85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89–7.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75–4.36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. ansorgei</italic> 1 <italic>- Arvi. ansorgei</italic> 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03–0.43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05–0.72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06–0.47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. rufinus</italic> 1 <italic>- Arvi.</italic> ANI2-1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65–3.71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65–3.36</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62–2.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. rufinus</italic> 1 <italic>- Arvi. rufinus</italic> 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06–0.96</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06–0.80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06–0.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi.</italic> ANI-2 1 <italic>- Arvi.</italic> ANI-2 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40–2.66</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36–2.33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31–1.51</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> 1 <italic>- Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sen.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.67</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.46–8.30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42–7.16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09–4.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> 1 <italic>- Arvi. neumanni</italic> 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>lineage A</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20–5.89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15–5.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04–3.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> 1 <italic>- Arvi.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15–2.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11–1.56</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12–1.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. neumanni</italic> 1 <italic>- Arvi. neumanni</italic> 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07–1.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06–1.13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06–0.73</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. abyssinicus</italic> 1 <italic>- Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sen.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67–6.46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59–5.46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49–3.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. abyssinicus</italic> 1 <italic>- Arvi. abyssinicus</italic> 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>lineage B</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05–1.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05–0.89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04–0.59</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. niloticus</italic> Eth.1 <italic>- Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sen.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>lineage C</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42–5.42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59–5.46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25–2.82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. niloticus</italic> Eth.1 <italic>- Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sud.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>phylogroup C-1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50–2.72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56–2.41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50–1.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. niloticus</italic> Cha.5 <italic>- Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sen.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93–3.71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86–3.29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84–2.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. niloticus</italic> Cha.5 <italic>- Arvi. niloticus</italic> Cam.13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>phylogroup C-2</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16–1.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17–0.64</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14–0.63</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. niloticus</italic> Nig.30 <italic>- Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sen.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66–2.76</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54–2.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55–1.38</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sen.3 <italic>- Arvi. niloticus</italic> Sen.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>phylogroup C-3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35–1.49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20–0.97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19–0.57</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvi. niloticus</italic> Nig.24 <italic>- Arvi. niloticus</italic> Nig.30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>phylogroup C-4</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22–1.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31–1.19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27–0.71</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt106"><label/><p>The median age and 95% HPD of major nodes are reported for each calibration set. Clades of interest are highlighted using bold characters.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>With respect to the age of Arvicanthini, a mid-Miocene origin was inferred with ages ranging from 11.29 Ma (95% HPD: 6.7–19.3; ‘lognormal distribution’ calibration) to 12.13 Ma (95% HPD: 7.04–10.924; ‘exponential distribution’ calibration). A Late Miocene origin was recovered for the genus <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> with ages ranging from 6.52 Ma (95% HPD: 5.27–10.24; ‘lognormal distribution’ calibration) to 6.6 Ma (95% HPD: 5.44–11.41; ‘exponential distribution’ calibration). The lineage encompassing all <italic>A. niloticus</italic> specimens (lineage C) appeared in the Late Pleistocene approximately 2.72–2.92 Ma. Several major splits then occurred in the Pleistocene (1.85–1.92 Ma, 1.16–1.43 Ma), leading to <italic>A. niloticus</italic> phylogroups C-1 to C-4.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Genetic Differentiation, Genetic Diversity and Network Analyses</title>
<p>For the cytb gene, all statistics (F<sub>ST</sub>, K<sub>ST*</sub>, and S<sub>nn</sub>) recovered a significant level of genetic differentiation among the four major phylogroups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t003">Table 3</xref>). By contrast, the level of genetic structure was lower for the Fib7 gene since no significant genetic structure was evidenced between C-1 and C-2, or between C-3 and C-4. For the latter, the statistics were not even computable because of the absence of genetic variation (when excluding gaps and positions with missing data) between the 50 sampled specimens of the two groups.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0077815-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Parameters describing genetic differentiation among phylogroups.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0077815-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groups</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F<sub>ST</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref><italic><sub>ST</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S<sub>nn</sub></italic></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytb</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-1 <italic>vs</italic> C-2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.870<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.344<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-1 <italic>vs</italic> C-3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.888<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.389<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-1 <italic>vs</italic> C-4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.303<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-2 <italic>vs</italic> C-3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.877<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.400<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-2 <italic>vs</italic> C-4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.825<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.309<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-3 <italic>vs</italic> C-4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.775<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fib7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-1 <italic>vs</italic> C-2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.272 (ns)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.247 (ns)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.619 (ns)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-1 <italic>vs</italic> C-3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.941<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">**</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">**</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-1 <italic>vs</italic> C-4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.933<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">**</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">**</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-2 <italic>vs</italic> C-3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.964<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.915<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-2 <italic>vs</italic> C-4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.960<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-3 <italic>vs</italic> C-4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><label/><p>The following abbreviations were used:</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label>*</label><p>significant with <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05;</p></fn><fn id="nt109"><label>**</label><p>significant with P&lt;0.01;</p></fn><fn id="nt110"><label>***</label><p>significant with P&lt;0.001. “n/a” indicates that it was impossible to compute the corresponding test statistic because of the lack of relevant data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>In contrast with the cytb gene (S = 182, h = 79, Hd = 0.985), genetic diversity was extremely low for the Fib7 gene (S = 9, h = 4, Hd = 0.253) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t004">Table 4</xref>). For both genes, the highest levels of genetic diversity were found in the phylogroup C-1. Interestingly, this result was recovered despite the fact that the number of sampled individuals for phylogroup C-1 is lower than those of phylogroups C-3 and C-4 (and even C-2 when considering the Fib7 dataset). The results of the neutrality tests for the two genes showed that <italic>A. niloticus</italic> populations were stable over time. We only find evidence for expansion of populations’ size for the phylogroup C-1 (both Tajima’s <italic>D</italic> and Fu’s <italic>F</italic> statistics) and in the phylogroup C-3 (Fu’s <italic>F</italic> statistics).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0077815-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>Parameters describing genetic diversity and genetic differentiation.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0077815-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phylogroup (n)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>h</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hd</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">π</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytb</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(All) (146)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.985</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0465</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078 (ns)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.008 (ns)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-1 (30)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.983</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0151</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.897*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.536*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-2 (22)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.870</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0055</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.318 (ns)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.695 (ns)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-3 (47)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.946</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0043</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.713 (ns)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14.579*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-4 (47)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.946</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0107</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.863 (ns)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.781 (ns)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fib7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(All) (58)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0026</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.162 (ns)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.101 (ns)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-1 (2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0014</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-2 (6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.600</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.445 (ns)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.795 (ns)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-3 (24)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-4 (26)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt111"><label/><p>The following abbreviations were used: number of sequences per phylogroup (n); number of polymorphic sites (<italic>S</italic>); number of haplotypes (<italic>h</italic>); haplotypic diversity (<italic>Hd</italic>); nucleotide diversity (π); Tajima’s <italic>D</italic> statistic (<italic>D</italic>); Fu’s <italic>F</italic> statistic (<italic>F</italic>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Network analyses recovered a relatively congruent pattern for both genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g002">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g003">Figure 3</xref>), in which the haplotypes from East Africa (phylogroup C-1) are connected with haplotypes from Central Africa (phylogroup C-2), which are further connected with haplotypes from West Africa (phylogroups C-3 and C-4), thus indicating a clear East to West pattern of colonization. Furthermore, the cytb dataset suggests that the genetic pool that is now present in the eastern part of West Africa (phylogroup C-4) originated from the haplotypic population that currently lies in the western part of West Africa (phylogroup C-3).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>All <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> individuals cluster in a monophyletic clade, whose sister group is <italic>Lemniscomys striatus</italic>, in agreement with Lecompte <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lecompte1">[42]</xref>. Within <italic>Arvicanthis</italic>, three distinct clades are retrieved. A first one, that would be the sister group of all other <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> specimens studied here, comprises two subgroups of specimens: one includes individuals of <italic>A. ansorgei</italic> and the other contains individuals of <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>rufinus</italic> as well as those referred to as ANI-2. Such an association was already retrieved and discussed by Ducroz <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz3">[29]</xref>, Volobouev <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Volobouev2">[70]</xref>, and Dobigny <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny2">[34]</xref>, and it will thus not be commented further here.</p>
<p>A second clade comprises two specimens of <italic>A. neumanni</italic> and two <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> specimens from Kenya. The two specimens labelled <italic>A. neumanni</italic> (from Tanzania) are those studied under the name <italic>A. somalicus</italic> by Ducroz <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz3">[29]</xref> who found them to be characterized by a 2N = 54/NFa = 62 karyotype. Ducroz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz1">[27]</xref> further proposed that they correspond to <italic>A. neumanni</italic>, as acknowledged by Castiglia <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Castiglia2">[32]</xref> to distinguish them from the true <italic>A. somalicus</italic> that they considered as having a karyotype with 2N = 62 and NFa = 62–63. As in Ducroz <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz3">[29]</xref>, these two <italic>A. neumanni</italic> specimens have a sister-group relationship with the <italic>A. niloticus</italic>/<italic>A. abyssinicus</italic> clade. Yet, they here share this position with two <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> from Kenya, that were also karyotyped by Ducroz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz1">[27]</xref> as 2N = 62/NFa = 62. The clear distinctness of these two <italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic> from the remaining <italic>A. niloticus</italic> specimens on molecular grounds strongly suggests that another name should be given to them. The latter may well be <italic>A. somalicus</italic> since their karyotypes seem to match quite well the one proposed by Baskevich &amp; Lavrenchenko <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Baskevich1">[71]</xref> for this species (for further comments, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Castiglia2">[32]</xref>).</p>
<p>The third main clade is characterized by the two individuals of <italic>A. abyssinicus</italic> that lie in a basal position relative to all other <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic>. This result, also found using a much smaller sample of <italic>A. niloticus</italic> specimens by Ducroz <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz3">[29]</xref>, tends to consolidate the sister status of <italic>A. abyssinicus</italic> and <italic>A. niloticus</italic>. The two species are sympatric, but apparently not syntopic, in Ethiopia where the former is considered an endemic of the High Plateaus, whereas the latter would range at lower altitudes, west of the Rift Valley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Musser1">[24]</xref>. The remaining part of this clade corresponds to <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic>, whose phylogeography is discussed in detail below, thanks to a large and wide-ranging sample.</p>
<p>It was previously shown that <italic>A. niloticus</italic> may display two distinct karyomorphs differing by an inversion: ANI-1a with 2N = 62/NFa = 62 and ANI-1b with 2N = 62/NFa = 64 on the Eastern and Western parts of the species range, respectively, with no geographic overlap ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Volobouev1">[30]</xref>; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Nevertheless, the two chromosomal lineages were also found paraphyletic on DNA grounds, and the taxonomic significance of this chromosomal mutation has already been questioned <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Volobouev1">[30]</xref>. Since then, reasonably large series of animals were karyotyped on the Eastern part of <italic>A. niloticus</italic>’ range (Sudan: 33; Northern Cameroon: 34) and, accordingly, they were found with the ANI-1a karyotype. Moreover, the geographic distributions of ANI-1a and ANI-1b (see Fig. 7 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Volobouev1">[30]</xref>) resemble that of the genetic clades retrieved here, with C-3 range (this study) widely overlapping ANI-1b’s one <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Volobouev1">[30]</xref>. However, this geographic match is imperfect since C-3 does not extend beyond the Bani River, while ANI-1b reaches the Adrar des Ifoghas massif (Northern Mali) and South-Western Niger (i.e., Anderamboukane). More precisely, several localities were included in both the cytogenetic and the molecular studies (e.g., Menaka, Ouatagouna and Tararabat, all in North-Eastern Mali) and provided animals with the ANI-1b karyotype but belonging to the C-4 (and not C-3) mtDNA clade. In addition, the two cytotypes were found sympatric in Sare Mama (Central Mali; Granjon, unpubl. data), and one heterozygous individual (2N = 62/NFa = 63) was trapped in Gaya (Southern Niger; Dobigny, unpubl. data). Taking into account the strict geographic exclusion of the C-3/C-4 mtDNA clades observed here, such an imperfect geographic match between chromosomal and molecular patterns may be due to asymmetric introgression between the nuclear (here the karyotype) and mitochondrial genomes following secondary contact of clades C-3 and C-4. Unfortunately, the resolution power offered by the Fib7 gene is too weak here to test for this hypothesis. Karyotypic vs. mtDNA profiles mismatch could also be due to incomplete lineage sorting of a long-standing inversion polymorphism, as already observed in another murid rodent genus, namely <italic>Mastomys</italic>, within the same regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny1">[16]</xref>. If true, this would imply that this inversion polymorphism has been segregating in <italic>A. niloticus</italic> since at least the C-3/C-4 divergence, ∼1.16–1.43 Ma ago, hence is hemiplasic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Avise2">[72]</xref>. These two explanations (introgression and incomplete lineage sorting) are not mutually exclusive. Moreover, the detection of animals with heterozygous karyotypes (i.e., ANI-1a×ANI-1b) within the range of both C-3 and C-4 mtDNA clades suggest at least persisting nuclear gene flows between these two lineages.</p>
<p>The present work is the first one to include both mitochondrial and nuclear DNA sequences for phylogeographic purposes in African rodents. These two genes led to rather congruent patterns, although the nuclear dataset was much less phylogenetically informative. This is expected since nuclear DNA in coding regions usually evolves under slower mutation rates. Nevertheless, the use of Fib7 appeared informative here, and insures the absence of no sex-associated bias (such as male-biased dispersal) in our study.</p>
<p>The first striking result that was obtained here is that the TMRCA for all <italic>A. niloticus</italic> lineages (2.72–2.92 Ma) is markedly older than those of all nine other African rodent species that were investigated so far (all between 1.25 Ma in <italic>Acomys chudeaui</italic> and 0.31 Ma in <italic>Praomys tullbergi</italic>; see references above). This may be attributable to possible biases in previous dating analyses, which likely result from the overuse of questionable secondary calibrations such as the classical <italic>Mus/Rattus</italic> split at 12 Ma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Jacobs1">[73]</xref>, in association with the use of methods that do not always account for rate variation across lineages. It could also be due to the existence of non-sampled lineages in the other species (for instance due to either true sampling bias or basal lineages’ extinction), or to a higher mutation rate in the <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> mitochondrial genome. Yet, geographic coverage appears really comparable in most investigations, with several of the previous studies also considering numerous localities all along from Western to Eastern Africa (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Brouat1">[15]</xref>). In addition, mtDNA-based analyses of higher-systematic levels within murids never detected any atypical molecular features or particularly long branches in <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Ducroz4">[41]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lecompte1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lecompte2">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Steppan1">[74]</xref>). As a consequence, and waiting for further proper comparisons between species, we suggest that <italic>A. niloticus</italic> can reasonably be considered as a truly rather ‘old’ species, already following its own trajectory with a first major split ∼2 Ma ago. Our results are significantly older than those inferred by Abdel Rahman and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-AbdelRahman1">[33]</xref>. While taxonomic and geographic coverage as well as calibration and inference methods are quite different in both studies, thus making a proper comparison difficult, such a discrepancy is probably due to their use of a younger <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> fossil supposed to be 5-4 Myr old <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-AbdelRahman1">[33]</xref>, whereas we relied on a 5.9-5.7 Myr old one <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Baele1">[53]</xref>. Interestingly, our dates fit perfectly well with one of the major faunal turnover that was associated with grasslands expansion and increased adaptation to open habitats (2-1.8 Ma; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Bobe1">[75]</xref>).</p>
<p>Furthermore, there is little doubt from our results that <italic>A. niloticus</italic> centre of origin is Eastern Africa. Indeed, the lineages that are the most closely related to unambiguously identified <italic>A. niloticus</italic> phylogroups (i.e. C-1 to C-4) all originate from this region (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0077815-t001">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g001">Fig. 1</xref>): <italic>A. abyssinicus</italic> (Ethiopia), <italic>A. somalicus</italic> (represented here by the two ‘<italic>A.</italic> cf. <italic>niloticus</italic>’ specimens from Kenya; see above) and <italic>A. neumanni</italic> (Tanzania). The corresponding character optimization of ancestral areas also supports this hypothesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). At some point, it is also the case of the results of the genetic diversity analyses, which recovers a higher level of genetic diversity for the phylogroup C-1. Thanks to the results of the network analyses, we can also infer a more precise pattern for <italic>A. niloticus</italic> phylogroups. Overall, there is a clear East to West differentiation of populations, with Egyptian and Sudanese individuals (phylogroup C-1) being connected to Chadian or Northern Cameroonese (phylogroup C-2) populations. Unfortunately, a wide sampling gap exists between Sudanese (phylogroup C-1) and Chadian (phylogroups C-2) samples which precludes any precise localization of the contact zone between these two lineages. Surprisingly, the clade from Central Africa (phylogroup C-2) is genetically more related to a lineage that is not in direct contact (phylogroup C-3), thus suggesting that the ancestors of these lineages were likely isolated during a past episode. After this episode, the eastern part of West Africa was recolonized by another population (phylogroup C-4), which is in contact with phylogroup C-3 in Central Mali (more precisely along the Eastern side of the Niger River valley) and in contact with phylogroup C-2 in the Lake Chad surroundings.</p>
<p>As already suggested for many other rodent as well as non-rodent African organisms (see below, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0077815.s001">Table S1</xref>), such a pattern, which is referable to phylogeographic category I of Avise <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Avise3">[76]</xref>, strongly suggests that extant genetic structure in <italic>A. niloticus</italic> results from the divergence of allopatric populations, either through ecological local adaptation, through vicariance (i.e. on each side of persisting geographic barriers) or through isolation in refuges and subsequent dispersal until secondary contact. West African steppes and savannas represent a rather homogenous habitat from Senegal to the Red Sea. This is why the East-West differentiation of <italic>A. niloticus</italic> lineages can hardly being accounted for by ecology-driven local adaptive processes. Furthermore, the numerous individuals that were trapped in very close localities but that yet belong to different genetic clades (e.g., in Central Mali and around Lake Chad) poorly support the local adaptation hypothesis. In the same manner, although putative geographic barriers that currently delimit <italic>A. niloticus</italic> intraspecific clades (Niger River, Lake Chad basin) were identified, vicariance appears as an inaccurate explanation here since no admixture at all was detected in our dataset. Indeed, this would imply that propagules crossed each of those barriers only ‘once’ and then remained reproductively isolated for hundreds thousand years, something that sounds highly improbable.</p>
<p>On the contrary, the refuge theory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Haffer1">[77]</xref> fits well to the phylogeographic pattern observed in the Nile grass rats: lineages’ splits all occurred during the Pleistocene which is characterised by deep climatic variations that induced extensive modifications of the open grasslands habitat range in Sub-Saharan Africa. Indeed, some 3 million years ago, the African climate started to get generally cooler and drier, along with successive arid-pluvial cycles, more or less following glacial-interglacial ones at higher latitudes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-DeMenocal1">[78]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dupont1">[81]</xref>. Whatever sudden <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-DeMenocal1">[78]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-DeMenocal2">[79]</xref> or progressive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Trauth1">[80]</xref>, these recurrent aridification events have led to cyclic contractions of the moistest habitats (i.e., riverine and tropical forests, swampy areas), which were reduced to refugial patches in several instances during the Plio-Pleistocene surrounded by savannah-forest mosaic landscapes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Cowling1">[82]</xref>. In parallel, arid phases induced wide-scale expansion of more xeric and open habitats. These climatic oscillations translated into deep modifications of all major biomes distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-DeMenocal2">[79]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dupont1">[81]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Maley1">[83]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-LeHourou1">[85]</xref>; among many others). In particular, C4 grasses, which are considered as valuable biomarkers of open grassland habitats, emerged during the Upper Miocene but became a major component of African biomes only from the Plio-Pleistocene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Sgalen1">[86]</xref>. Recurrent phases of grassland expansion following Pleistocene climatic cycles were accompanied by major turnovers of mammalian faunas towards more numerous and more abundant open habitat-adapted species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-LeHourou1">[85]</xref>. Conversely, phases of savannah fragmentation have triggered intra- and inter-specific diversification ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lorenzen1">[10]</xref>, and references below). These variations in grassland habitats of the Sahelian region during the Pleistocene have probably had major consequences on <italic>A. niloticus</italic> evolution since this species is highly specialized in this habitat type: its diet is mainly herbivorous, and it also forages along runways through matted grass around its nests which are mainly made of intermingled blades of grass themselves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Granjon1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Granjon3">[87]</xref>.</p>
<p>The refuge theory is also strongly supported by an increasing number of studies dealing with other Sub-Saharan rodent species (see below as well as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0077815.s001">Table S1</xref>), and where geographic distributions perfectly or almost perfectly match with genetic assemblages. All these studies similarly point towards isolation and genetic differentiation within refuges during unfavourable periods, with subsequent dispersion phases during favourable ones. Secondary contacts then tend to stabilize around strict (or even partial) geographic barriers that stop (or slow down) dispersal and gene flow –the so-called suture zones <italic>sensu</italic> Hewitt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Hewitt1">[88]</xref>. Of course, the nature of refuges, favourable/unfavourable periods and/or barriers depend on species-specific characteristics.</p>
<p>For instance, the Sahelo-Saharan spiny mouse <italic>Acomys chudeaui</italic> was most probably restricted to rocky areas that were surrounded by sand deserts during arid episodes, but may have dispersed through steppe-like environments during less arid periods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas2">[18]</xref>. The humid habitat-adapted <italic>Mastomys huberti</italic> underwent isolation around water-body relics during arid phases, while it colonized hydrographic basins of Senegal, Mali and Guinea during humid ones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Mouline1">[19]</xref>. As far as forest-dwelling rodent species are concerned, they are expected to be trapped in forest relic patches during arid episodes but to extend during forest expansions associated with humid periods (e.g., <italic>Praomys tullbergi</italic> and <italic>Praomys rostratus</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas3">[21]</xref>; <italic>Praomys misonnei</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas4">[22]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas5">[23]</xref>). Similarly, populations of open tree savannah species would diverge allopatrically during moist episodes, when fragmented throughout extended savannah-forest mosaic landscapes (e.g., <italic>Praomys daltoni</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Bryja1">[14]</xref>). On the contrary, species from the drier scrub savannah and steppes are thought to be isolated when surrounded by forests during the moistest phases, and then to disperse widely with expanding open grasslands (<italic>Mastomys erythroleucus</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Brouat1">[15]</xref>; <italic>Lemniscomys striatus</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas1">[13]</xref>). <italic>A. niloticus</italic> is to be considered as belonging to the latter category.</p>
<p>Geographic barriers to dispersal were also identified in most of African rodent phylogeographic investigations. Once again, many similarities appear between species-specific case studies. The tectonic complex of the Rift Valley was identified as a contact zone between parapatric phylogroups in <italic>L. striatus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas1">[13]</xref> and <italic>Mastomys natalensis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Colangelo1">[17]</xref>. Similarly, the relationships between some hydrographic features and genetic structure have been documented in several Sub-Saharan rodent species (e.g., <italic>Taterillus</italic> spp.: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny3">[89]</xref>; <italic>M. erythroleucus</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Brouat1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny1">[16]</xref>; <italic>L. striatus</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas1">[13]</xref>; <italic>P. tullbergi</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas3">[21]</xref>; <italic>P. misonnei</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas4">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas5">[23]</xref>; <italic>P. daltoni</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Bryja1">[14]</xref>). In particular, it is striking to see how the same rivers and/or lakes have been pointed out as putative barriers in several taxa. In regards to the present study, this is notably the case for the Niger River valley that tends to separate clades C-3 and C-4 of <italic>A. niloticus</italic>, as well as several parapatric clades within (<italic>L. striatus</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas1">[13]</xref>; <italic>M. erythroleucus</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Brouat1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny1">[16]</xref>; <italic>P. daltoni</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Bryja1">[14]</xref>) and between (<italic>Taterillus</italic> spp.: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny3">[89]</xref>) other unrelated rodent species. In the same manner, Lake Chad and its surroundings coincide with the contact zone between <italic>A. niloticus</italic> clades C-2 and C-3, while this area also signs genetic hiatus in <italic>Mastomys erythroleucus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Brouat1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny1">[16]</xref>, <italic>Gerbillus nigeriae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Hima1">[90]</xref> and <italic>Taterillus</italic> spp. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny3">[89]</xref>. Besides, it has already been suggested that the latter region constitutes a ‘phylogeographic crossroad’, i.e. a centre of diversification where faunas may have diversified following the recurrent Plio-Pleistocene cycles of transgression/regression of the Palaeolake Chad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny2">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Granjon4">[91]</xref>.</p>
<p>So, in essence, ancestral <italic>A. niloticus</italic> populations would have diverged allopatrically during humid periods within at least four different Pleistocene refuges of open habitat. They would have dispersed during more arid ones until secondary contacts around geographic barriers such as the Niger River and the Lake Chad basins. The precise timing of isolation within Pleistocene refuges and of dispersal outside these refuges is not feasible here since molecular inferences of dates for such events are associated with confidence intervals that are usually of the same magnitude -when not larger- than Pleistocene climatic cycles themselves, thus precluding any robust conclusion. Also, the putative existence of a third barrier eastwards will require further sampling in Eastern Chad and Sudan in order to identify the precise geographic range of clades C-1 and C-2.</p>
<p>Finally, although we did not attempt to investigate formally sub-structure within each clade, we clearly retrieve a well-supported group of individuals that all originate from Adrar des Ifoghas in Mali (4 specimens from 2 different localities). No such signal could be obtained for individuals from Aïr in Niger (3 specimens from 2 different localities), thus supporting a previous hypothesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny4">[92]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Dobigny5">[93]</xref> that the Malian Adrar may represent a more isolated Sahelian refuge within the Sahara desert than the Aïr.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the picture drawn from studies on rodents often resembles those obtained on other mammals that we are aware of: refuges and allopatry during successive climatic cycles in the past were advocated to explain the differentiation of genetic lineages in cercopithecine monkeys (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Colyn1">[94]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Tosi1">[95]</xref>), baboons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Zinner1">[96]</xref>, hyenas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Rohland1">[97]</xref>, wild dog <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Mardsen1">[98]</xref>, common warthog <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Muwanika1">[99]</xref>, giraffe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Brown1">[100]</xref>, buffalo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Smitz1">[101]</xref> and many large antelopes like topi, hartebeest <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Arctander1">[102]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Flagstad1">[103]</xref>, impala, kudu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nersting1">[104]</xref>, waterbuck <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lorenzen2">[105]</xref>, kob <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lorenzen3">[106]</xref>, African bushbuck <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Moodley1">[107]</xref>, common eland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lorenzen4">[108]</xref> and roan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Alpers1">[109]</xref>. Similar conclusions were also reached in plants (e.g., shea tree: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Fontaine1">[110]</xref>; giant lobelia: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Kebede1">[111]</xref>; coffee tree: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Gomez1">[112]</xref>), insects (e.g., maize stalk borer: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Sezonlin1">[113]</xref>), reptiles (e.g., puff adder: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Barlow1">[114]</xref>; Southern rock agama: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Matthee1">[115]</xref>) and birds (e.g., starred robin: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Bowie1">[116]</xref>; ostrich: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Miller1">[117]</xref>). Zoogeographic barriers to dispersal have also been pointed out in several species, including the Rift Valley (e.g., lion: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Barnett1">[118]</xref>; giraffe: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Brown1">[100]</xref>; wildebeest: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Arctander1">[102]</xref>; waterbuck: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lorenzen2">[105]</xref>; bushbuck: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Moodley1">[107]</xref>; maize stalk borer: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Sezonlin1">[113]</xref>; giant lobelia: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Kebede1">[111]</xref>) and great rivers (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Tosi1">[95]</xref>).</p>
<p>As a whole, this reaches what was inferred for other continents, especially the well-studied Europe and North America <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Hewitt2">[119]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Emerson1">[121]</xref>. Sub-Saharan Africa was once claimed to be understudied <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Hewitt2">[119]</xref>, but data have accumulated during the last decade (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lorenzen1">[10]</xref>, and references hereabove). Among studies that have concerned ungulates, a clear sampling bias towards Eastern and Southern Africa is obvious. West African megafauna’s phylogeography remains very poorly documented and this part of the continent is usually dramatically absent from most datasets: Lorenzen and colleagues’ recent review <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lorenzen1">[10]</xref> clearly illustrates such a gap of knowledge, with several highly differentiated ungulate lineages west of the Rift Valley (see their <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077815-g003">Figure 3</xref>) that, unfortunately, are documented through extremely reduced number of localities (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Smitz1">[101]</xref>, for a slightly higher number of sampling sites in buffaloes). This emphasizes the importance of studies conducted on rodents that, in the contrary, have mainly focused on West and Central African deserts, grasslands and forests. In particular, the present study adds to the three other available ones that are typical of open grasslands in West and Central Africa, namely <italic>Mastomys natalensis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Colangelo1">[17]</xref>, <italic>M. erythroleucus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Brouat1">[15]</xref> and <italic>Lemniscomys striatus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Nicolas1">[13]</xref>. Together, these latter works allow us to draw an integrative picture of West and Central African open habitats history during the Pleistocene, something that could not be reached with ungulates models. In particular, one refuge was hypothesised in West Africa (i.e., between Senegal and the Rift Valley) on the basis of large mammals data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0077815-Lorenzen1">[10]</xref>, while at least three and potentially four major ones can be speculated from patterns obtained in these four rodent species: one most probably westward of the Niger River, one somewhere between the Niger River and the Lake Chad, and one or two between the Lake Chad and the Nile River. Nevertheless, the precise locations of these Pleistocene refuges for open habitat species are still to be precisely assessed.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0077815.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0077815.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Summary of previous phylogeographic studies conducted on Sub-Saharan African rodents.</bold> The species, their preferred habitat, the molecular marker used, the sample size, the methods for date inference, the major evolutionary events as well as putative corresponding geographic aspects are indicated. References can be found in the main text.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank the associate editor Dr. Roscoe Stanyon and four anonymous reviewers for their constructive comments on the present manuscript. We are grateful to Drs C. Brouat and F.L. Condamine for useful advices on a preliminary version of the manuscript. We also thank the numerous collectors and providers of samples that helped us with the sampling. Some of the molecular data used in this work were produced through technical facilities of the “Laboratoire d’Excellence - Centre Méditerranéen de l’Environnement et de la Biodiversité” (LabEx - CeMEB), Montpellier, France.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Parmesan1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parmesan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Ecological and evolutionary response to recent climate change</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>637</fpage>–<lpage>669</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Willis1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhagwat</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Biodiversity and climate change</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>326</volume>: <fpage>806</fpage>–<lpage>807</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Pereira1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leadley</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Proenca</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alkemade</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scharlemann</surname><given-names>JPW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Scenarios for global biodiversity in the 21st century</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>330</volume>: <fpage>1496</fpage>–<lpage>1501</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Dawson1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>House</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Beyond predictions: biodiversity conservation in a changing climate</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>332</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-McMahon1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armbruster</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlein</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beale</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Improving assessment and modelling of climate change impacts on global terrestrial biodiversity</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Bellard1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertelsmeier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leadley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thuiller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Courchamp</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Impacts of climate change on the future of biodiversity</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>377</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Avise1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Avise</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The history and purview of phylogeography: a personal reflection</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>379</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Pease1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pease</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollinger</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buermann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Landscape genetics of California mule deer (<italic>Odocoileus hemionus</italic>): the roles of ecological and historical factors in generating differentiation</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1848</fpage>–<lpage>1862</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Beaty1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaty</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Provan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Comparative phylogeography of two related plant species with overlapping ranges in Europe, and the potential effects of climate change on their intraspecific genetic diversity</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Lorenzen1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzen</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegismund</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Comparative phylogeography of African savannah ungulates</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>3656</fpage>–<lpage>3670</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Poelchau1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poelchau</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamrick</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Comparative phylogeography of three common Neotropical tree species</article-title>. <source>J Biogeog</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>618</fpage>–<lpage>631</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-BenFaleh1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Faleh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duplantier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobigny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography of two cryptic species of African desert jerboas (Dipodidae: <italic>Jaculus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Biol J Linnean Soc</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Nicolas1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mboumba</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verheyen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denys</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lecompte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008b</year>) <article-title>Phylogeographic structure and regional history of <italic>Lemniscomys striatus</italic> (Rodentia, Muridae) in tropical Africa</article-title>. <source>J Biogeog</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>2074</fpage>–<lpage>2089</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Bryja1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryja</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobigny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patzenhauerova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Konecny</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Plio-Pleistocene history of West African Sudanian savanna and the phylogeography of the <italic>Praomys daltoni</italic> complex (Rodentia): the environment/geography/genetic interplay</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>4783</fpage>–<lpage>4799</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Brouat1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brouat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bâ</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cosson</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobigny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography of the Guinea multimammate mouse (<italic>Mastomys erythroleucus</italic>) : a case study for Sahelian species in West Africa</article-title>. <source>J Biogeog</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>2237</fpage>–<lpage>2250</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Dobigny1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobigny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Catalan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>PCM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brouat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Geographic patterns of inversion polymorphisms in a wild African rodent, <italic>Mastomys erythroleucus</italic></article-title>. <source>Heredity</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>378</fpage>–<lpage>386</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Colangelo1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colangelo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verheyen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leirs</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denys</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A mitochondrial phylogeographic scenario for the most widespread African rodent, <italic>Mastomys natalensis</italic></article-title>. <source>Biol J Linnean Soc</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>901</fpage>–<lpage>916</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Nicolas2"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duplantier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cruaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobigny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography of spiny mice (genus <italic>Acomys</italic>, Rodentia: Muridae) from the south-Western margin of the Sahara with taxonomic implications</article-title>. <source>Biol J Linnean Soc</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Mouline1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mouline</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdoullaye</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography of a Sahelian rodent species <italic>Mastomys huberti</italic>: a Plio-Pleistocene story of emergence and colonization of humid habitats</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1036</fpage>–<lpage>1053</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Mboumba1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mboumba</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deleporte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography of <italic>Mus (Nannomys) minutoides</italic> (Rodentia, Muridae) in West Central African savannas: singular vicariance in neighbouring populations</article-title>. <source>J Zool Syst Evol Res</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Nicolas3"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bryja</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akpatou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Konecny</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lecompte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008a</year>) <article-title>Comparative phylogeography of two sibling species of forest-dwelling rodent (<italic>Praomys rostratus</italic> and <italic>P. tullbergi</italic>) in West Africa: different reactions to past fragmentation</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>5118</fpage>–<lpage>5134</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Nicolas4"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Missoup</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denys</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerbis Peterhans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katuala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The roles of rivers and Pleistocene refugia in shaping genetic diversity in <italic>Praomys misonnei</italic> in tropical Africa</article-title>. <source>J Biogeog</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Nicolas5"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Missoup</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cruaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denys</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>West-Central African Pleistocene lowland forest evolution revealed by the phylogeography of Misonne’s soft-furred mouse</article-title>. <source>African Zool</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Musser1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Musser GG, Carleton MD (2005) <italic>Arvicanthis</italic>. In: Wilson DE, Reeder DAM, editors. Mammals of the World: a taxonomic and geographic reference, 3<sup>rd</sup> edition, volume 2. Baltimore, USA: The Johns Hopkins University Press. pp. 1285–1292.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Granjon1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Granjon L, Duplantier JM (2009) Les rongeurs de l’Afrique sahélo-soudanienne. Marseille, France : Editions IRD, Publications Scientifiques du MNHN. 215 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Granjon2"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duplantier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Catalan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Britton-Davidian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Karyotypic data on rodents from Senegal</article-title>. <source>Israel J Zool</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Ducroz1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ducroz JF (1998) Contribution des approches cytogénétique et moléculaire à l’étude systématique et évolutive des genres de rongeurs Murinae de la division « <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> ». PhD thesis, Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris, France. 250 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Ducroz2"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ducroz</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chevret</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duplantier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lombard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Characterization of two distinct species of <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> (Rodentia, Muridae) in West Africa: cytogenetic, molecular and reproductive evidence</article-title>. <source>J Zool</source> <volume>214</volume>: <fpage>709</fpage>–<lpage>723</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Ducroz3"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ducroz</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Volobouev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A molecular perspective on the systematics and evolution of the genus <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> (Rodentia, Muridae): inferences from complete cytochrome b sequences</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Volobouev1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volobouev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ducroz</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aniskin</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Britton-Davidian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castiglia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002a</year>) <article-title>Chromosomal characterization of <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> species (Rodentia, Murinae) from Western and Central Africa: implications for taxonomy</article-title>. <source>Cytogenet Genome Res</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>250</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Castiglia1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castiglia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tesha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scanzani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fadda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Cytogenetics of the genus <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> (Rodentia, Murinae): 3. Comparative cytogenetics of <italic>A. neumanni</italic> and <italic>A. nairobae</italic> from Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Genetica</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Castiglia2"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castiglia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bekele</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Makundi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oguge</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Chromosomal diversity in the genus <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> (Rodentia, Muridae) from East Africa: a taxonomic and phylogenetic evaluation</article-title>. <source>J Syst Evol Res</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-AbdelRahman1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel Rahman</surname><given-names>AEH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ducroz</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Contrafatto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny and historical demography of economically important rodents of the genus <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> (Mammalia, Muridae) from the Nile Valley: of mice and men</article-title>. <source>Biol J Linnean Soc</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>641</fpage>–<lpage>655</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Dobigny2"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobigny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brouat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A cytotaxonomic and DNA-based survey of rodents from Northern Cameroon and Western Chad</article-title>. <source>Mammal Biol</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-ElGithure1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Githure</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schnur</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Blancq</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendricks</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Characterization of Kenyan <italic>Leishmania</italic> spp. and identification of <italic>Mastomys natalensis</italic>, <italic>Taterillus emini</italic> and <italic>Aethomys kaiseri</italic> as new hosts of <italic>Leishmania major</italic></article-title>. <source>Ann Trop Med Parasitol</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Trape1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trape</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Godeluck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diatta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Legros</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The spread of tick-borne borreliosis in West Africa and its relationship to sub-Saharan drought</article-title>. <source>Ann J Trop Med Hyg</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Sebek1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sebek</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sixl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reinthaler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneeweiss</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Results of serological examination for leptospirosis of domestic and wild animals in the Upper Nile province (Sudan)</article-title>. <source>J Hyg Epid Microbiol Immunol</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Julvez1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Julvez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michault</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerdelhue</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Etude sérologique des rickettsioses à Niamey, Niger</article-title>. <source>Méd Trop</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Duplantier1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Duplantier JM, Sene M (2006) Rodents as definitive hosts of <italic>Schistosoma</italic> with special reference to <italic>S. mansoni</italic> transmission. In: Morand S, Krasnov BR, Poulin R, editors. Micromammals and Macroparasites. Springer-Verlag, Tokyo, Japan. pp. 527–543.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Mercier1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnabau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Toxoplasmosis seroprevalence in urban rodents: a survey in Niamey, Niger</article-title>. <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Ducroz4"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ducroz</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Volobouev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>An assessment of systematics of Arvicanthine rodents using mitochondrial DNA sequences: evolutionary and biogeographical implications</article-title>. <source>Mammal Evol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Lecompte1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lecompte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aplin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denys</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Catzeflis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chades</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny and biogeography of African Murinae based on mitochondrial and nuclear gene sequences, with a new tribal classification of the subfamily</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Sikes1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sikes</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gannon</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <collab xlink:type="simple">Animal Care and Use Committee of the American Society of Mammalogists</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Guidelines of the American Society of Mammalogists for the use of wild mammals in research. J. Mammal</article-title>. <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Lecompte2"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lecompte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denys</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The phylogeny of the <italic>Praomys</italic> complex (Rodentia, Mammalia) and its phylogeographic implications</article-title>. <source>J Zool Syst Evol Res</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Hall1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT</article-title>. <source>Nucl Acids Symp Ser</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Seddon1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seddon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santucci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reeve</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>DNA footprints of European hedgehogs, <italic>Erinaceus europaeus</italic> and <italic>E. concolor</italic>: Pleistocene refugia, postglacial expansion and colonization routes</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>2187</fpage>–<lpage>2198</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Drummond1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Bayesian phylogenetics with BEAUti and the BEAST 1.7</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1969</fpage>–<lpage>1973</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Drummond2"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Relaxed phylogenetics and dating with confidence</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e88</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Nylander1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nylander</surname><given-names>JAA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieves-Aldrey</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Bayesian phylogenetic analysis of combined data</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Posada1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>jModeltest: phylogenetic model averaging</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1253</fpage>–<lpage>1256</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Heled1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heled</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Bayesian inference of species trees from multilocus data</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>570</fpage>–<lpage>580</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Lartillot1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lartillot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Computing Bayes factors using thermodynamic integration</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Baele1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baele</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WLS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Accurate model selection of relaxed molecular clocks in Bayesian phylogenetics</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Stamatakis1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>RaxML-III: a fast program for maximum likelihood-based inference of large phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Winkler1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Neogene paleobiogeography and East African paleoenvironments: contributions from the Tugen Hills rodents and lagomorphs</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Ho1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Accounting for calibration uncertainties in phylogenetic estimation of evolutionary divergence times</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Graur1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graur</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Reading the entrails of chickens: molecular timescales of evolution and the illusion of precision</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Erixon1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erixon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Svennblad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oxelman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Reliability of Bayesian posterior probabilities and bootstrap frequencies in phylogenetics</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>673</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Kass1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kass</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raftery</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Bayes factors</article-title>. <source>J Am Stat Assoc</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>773</fpage>–<lpage>795</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Maddison1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Maddison WP, Maddison DR (2011) Mesquite: a modular system for evolutionary analysis. Version 2.75. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mesquiteproject.org" xlink:type="simple">http://mesquiteproject.org</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Librado1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Librado</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>DnaSP v5: a software for comprehensive analysis of DNA polymorphism data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1451</fpage>–<lpage>1452</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Gaubert1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaubert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benyacoub</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelhamid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Reviving the African wolf <italic>Canis lupus lupaster</italic> in North West Africa: a mitochondrial lineage ranging more than 6,000 km wide</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e42740</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Hudson1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boos</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>A statistical test for detecting geographic subdivision. Mol. Biol. Evol</article-title>. <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Hudson2"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A new statistic for detecting genetic differentiation</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>155</volume>: <fpage>2011</fpage>–<lpage>2014</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-MoralesHojas1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morales-Hojas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Inferring the evolutionary history of <italic>Drosophila Americana</italic> and <italic>Drosophila novamexicana</italic> using a multilocus approach and the influence of chromosomal rearrangements in single gene analyses</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>2910</fpage>–<lpage>2926</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Tajima1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Statistical-method for testing the neutral mutation hypothesis by DNA polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Fu1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Statistical tests of neutrality of mutations against population growth, hitchhiking and background selection</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>915</fpage>–<lpage>925</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Bandelt1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandelt</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Röhl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Median-joining networks for inferring intraspecific phylogenies. Mol. Biol. Evol</article-title>. <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Woolley1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woolley</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crandall</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A comparison of phylogenetic network methods using computer simulation</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e1913</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Volobouev2"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volobouev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aniskin</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lecompte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ducroz</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2002b</year>) <article-title>Patterns of karyotype evolution in complexes of sibling species within three genera of African murid rodents inferred from the comparison of cytogenetic and molecular data</article-title>. <source>Cytogenet Genome Res</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Baskevich1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baskevich</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lavrenchenko</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Review of karyological studies and the problems of systematics of Ethiopian <italic>Arvicanthis</italic> Lesson, 1842 (Rodentia: Muridae)</article-title>. <source>Bönner Zool Monogr</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Avise2"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Avise</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Hemiplasy: a new term in the lexicon of phylogenetics</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Jacobs1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Jacobs LL, Downs WR (1994) The evolution of murine rodents in Asia. In: Tomida Y, Li C, Setoguchi T, editors. Rodent and Lagomorph Families of Asian origin and diversification. Tokyo, Japan: National Science Museum Monograph. pp. 149–156.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Steppan1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steppan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adkins</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny and divergence-date estimates of rapid radiations in Muroid rodents based on multiple nuclear genes</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Bobe1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bobe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Behrensmeyer</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The expansion of grass land ecosystem in Africa in relation to mammalian evolution and the origin of the genus <italic>Homo</italic></article-title>. <source>Pal Pal Pal</source> <volume>207</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Avise3"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Avise JC (2000) Phylogeography: the history and formation of species. Cambridge, UK: Harvard University Press. 447 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Haffer1"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haffer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1969</year>) <article-title>Speciation in Amazonian forest birds</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>165</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-DeMenocal1"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Menocal</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Plio-Pleistocene African climate</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-DeMenocal2"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Menocal</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>African climate change and faunal evolution during the Plio-Pleistocene</article-title>. <source>Earth Planet Sc Lett</source> <volume>220</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Trauth1"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trauth</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larrasoana</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mudelsee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Trends, rhythms and events in Plio-Pleistocene African climate</article-title>. <source>Quaternary Sc Rev</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Dupont1"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Orbital scale vegetation change in Africa</article-title>. <source>Quaternary Sc Rev</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>3589</fpage>–<lpage>3602</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Cowling1"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maslin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Simulated glacial and interglacial vegetation across Africa: implications for species phylogenies and trans-African migration of plants and animals</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>827</fpage>–<lpage>840</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Maley1"><label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Maley J (1980) Les changements climatiques de la fin du Tertiaire en Afrique : leur conséquence sur l’apparition du Sahara et de sa végétation. In: Williams MAJ, Faure H, editors. The Sahara and the Nile: quaternary environments and prehistoric occupation in Northern Africa. Rotterdam, Netherlands: Balkerma. pp. 63–86.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Maley2"><label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Maley J (2001) The impact of arid phases on the African rain forest through geological history. In: Weber W, Vedder A, Naughton-Treves L, editors. <italic>African</italic> rain forest ecology and conservation: an interdisciplinary perspective. Yale, USA: Yale University Press. pp. 68–87.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-LeHourou1"><label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Houérou</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Outline of the biological history of the Sahara</article-title>. <source>J Arid Env</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Sgalen1"><label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ségalen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee-Thorp</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cerling</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Timing of C4 grass expansion across sub-Saharan Africa</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>459</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Granjon3"><label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Granjon L, Bekele A, Ducroz JF (2013) <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus.</italic> In: Happold DCD, editor. Mammals of Africa, Volume III: Rodents, Hares and Rabbits. London, UK: Bloomsbury Publishing. pp. 387–388.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Hewitt1"><label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The genetic legacy of the Quaternary ice ages</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>405</volume>: <fpage>907</fpage>–<lpage>913</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Dobigny3"><label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobigny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aniskin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornette</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Volobouev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Recent radiation in West African <italic>Taterillus</italic> (Rodentia, Gerbillinae): the concerted role of climatic and chromosome changes</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>358</fpage>–<lpage>368</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Hima1"><label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thiam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Catalan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duplantier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Extensive Robertsonian polymorphism in the African rodent <italic>Gerbillus nigeriae</italic>: geographic aspects and meiotic data</article-title>. <source>J Zool Lond</source> <volume>284</volume>: <fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Granjon4"><label>91</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Granjon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobigny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The importance of cytotaxonomy in understanding the biogeography of African rodents: Lake Chad murids as an example</article-title>. <source>Mammal Rev</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Dobigny4"><label>92</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Dobigny G, Cornette R, Moulin S, Ag Sidiyène E (2001) The mammals of Adrar des Iforas, Mali, with special emphasis on small mammals: systematic and biogeographical implications. In: Denys C, Granjon L, Poulet A editors. Proceedings of African Small Mammals Symposium. Editions IRD, Paris, France. pp. 445–458.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Dobigny5"><label>93</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobigny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nomao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gautun</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Rodents from Niger: implications for systematics, biodiversity and biogeography</article-title>. <source>Mammalia</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>523</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Colyn1"><label>94</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gautier-Hion</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verheyen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>A re-appraisal of palaeoenvironmental history in Central Africa: evidence for a major fluvial refuge in the Zaire Basin</article-title>. <source>J Biogeog</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Tosi1"><label>95</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tosi</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Forest monkeys and Pleistocene refugia: a phylogeographic window onto the disjunct distribution of the <italic>Chlorocebus lhoesti</italic> species group</article-title>. <source>Zool J Linnean Soc</source> <volume>154</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Zinner1"><label>96</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zinner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Groeneveld</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial phylogeography of baboons (<italic>Papio</italic> spp.): indication for introgressive hybridization?</article-title> <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e83</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Rohland1"><label>97</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohland</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beauval</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Airvaux</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The population history of extant and extinct hyenas</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2435</fpage>–<lpage>2443</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Mardsen1"><label>98</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mardsen</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woodroffe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milss</surname><given-names>MGL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McNutt</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Creel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Spatial and temporal patterns of neutral and adaptive variation in the endangered African wild dog (<italic>Lycaon pictus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1379</fpage>–<lpage>1393</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Muwanika1"><label>99</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muwanika</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nyakaana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegismund</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arctander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography and population structure of the common warthog (<italic>Phacochoerus africanus</italic>) inferred from variation in mitochondrial DNA sequences and microsatellite loci</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Brown1"><label>100</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brenneman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koepfli</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollinger</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mila</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Extensive population genetic structure in the giraffe</article-title>. <source>BMC Biol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e57</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Smitz1"><label>101</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smitz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berthouly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornélis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Hooft</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Pan-African genetic structure in the African Buffalo (<italic>Syncerus caffer</italic>): investigating intraspecific divergence</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e56235</fpage>–<lpage>56241</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Arctander1"><label>102</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arctander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coutellec-Vreto</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography of three closely related African bovids (tribe Alcelaphini)</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1724</fpage>–<lpage>1739</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Flagstad1"><label>103</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flagstad</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Syvertsen</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stenseth</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jakobsen</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Environmental change and rates of evolution: the phylogeographic pattern within the hartebeest complex as related to climatic variation</article-title>. <source>Proc Roy Soc B</source> <volume>268</volume>: <fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>677</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Nersting1"><label>104</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nersting</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arctander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography and conservation of impala and greater kudu</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>711</fpage>–<lpage>719</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Lorenzen2"><label>105</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzen</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simonsen</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kat</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arctander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegismund</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Hybridization between subspecies of waterbuck (<italic>Kobus ellipsiprymnus</italic>) in zones of overlap with limited introgression</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>3787</fpage>–<lpage>3799</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Lorenzen3"><label>106</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzen</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Neergaard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arctander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegismund</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography, hybridization and Pleistocene refugia of the kob antelope (<italic>Kobus kob</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>3241</fpage>–<lpage>3252</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Moodley1"><label>107</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moodley</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruford</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular biogeography: towards an integrated framework for conserving pan-African biodiversity</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e454</fpage>–<lpage>462</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Lorenzen4"><label>108</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzen</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masembe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arctander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegismund</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A long-standing Pleistocene refugium in Southern Africa and a mosaic of refugia in East Africa: insights from mtDNA and the common eland antelope</article-title>. <source>J Biogeog</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>571</fpage>–<lpage>581</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Alpers1"><label>109</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alpers</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Vuuren</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arctander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Population genetics of the roan antelope (<italic>Hippotragus equinus</italic>) with suggestions for conservation</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1771</fpage>–<lpage>1784</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Fontaine1"><label>110</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontaine</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovett</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouvet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Genetic diversity of the shea tree (<italic>Vitellaria paradoxa</italic> C. F. Gaertn) detected by RAPD and chloroplast microsatellite markers</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>–<lpage>648</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Kebede1"><label>111</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kebede</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taberlet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nemomissa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brochmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography and conservation genetics of a giant lobelia (<italic>Lobelia giberroa</italic>) in Ethiopian and Tropical East African mountains</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1233</fpage>–<lpage>1243</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Gomez1"><label>112</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dussert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Kochko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Current genetic differentiation of <italic>Coffea canephora</italic> Pierre ex A. Froehn in the Guineo-Congolian African zone: cumulative impact of ancient climatic changes and recent human activities</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e167</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Sezonlin1"><label>113</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sezonlin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dupas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Rü</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Gall</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moyal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography and population genetics of the maize stalk borer <italic>Busseola fusca</italic> (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae) in sub-Saharan Africa</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>420</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Barlow1"><label>114</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendry</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peppin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phelps</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography of the widespread African puff adder (<italic>Bitis arietans</italic>) reveals multiple Pleistocene refugia in Southern Africa</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1134</fpage>–<lpage>1157</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Matthee1"><label>115</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matthee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flemming</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Population fragmentation in the Southern rock agama, <italic>Agama atra</italic>: more evidence for vicariance in Southern Africa</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>471</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Bowie1"><label>116</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowie</surname><given-names>RCK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fjeldsa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Coalescent models reveal the relative roles of ancestral polymorphism, vicariance, and dispersal in shaping phylogeographical structure of an African montane forest robin</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Miller1"><label>117</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hallager</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monfort</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Phylogeographic analysis of nuclear and mtDNA supports subspecies designations in the ostrich (<italic>Struthio camelus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Conserv Genet</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>423</fpage>–<lpage>431</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Barnett1"><label>118</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The origin, current diversity and future conservation of the modern lion (<italic>Panthera leo</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Proc Roy Soc B</source> <volume>273</volume>: <fpage>2119</fpage>–<lpage>2125</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Hewitt2"><label>119</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Speciation, hybrid zones and phylogeography –or seeing genes in space and time</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>549</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Hewitt3"><label>120</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A climate for colonization</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0077815-Emerson1"><label>121</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>