<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-08652</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065576</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Emergence</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary systematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Phylogenetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Organismal evolution</subject><subj-group><subject>Eukaryotic evolution</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Paleontology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleobotany</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Mycology</subject><subj-group><subject>Fungi</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Paleontology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleobotany</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant science</subject><subj-group><subject>Botany</subject><subj-group><subject>Mycology</subject><subj-group><subject>Fungi</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Paleobotany</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Earth sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleontology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleobotany</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Dating the Diversification of the Major Lineages of Ascomycota (Fungi)</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Molecular Dating in Ascomycota</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>María</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wedin</surname><given-names>Mats</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Botany, Swedish Museum of Natural History, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Departamento de Biología y Geología, Universidad Rey Juan Carlos, Móstoles, Madrid, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Sydney, Australia</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">maria.prieto@nrm.se</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MP MW. Performed the experiments: MP. Analyzed the data: MP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MP MW. Wrote the paper: MP MW. Contributed to analyses and discussion: MW MP.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>e65576</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Prieto, Wedin</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Establishing the dates for the origin and main diversification events in the phylogeny of Ascomycota is among the most crucial remaining goals in understanding the evolution of Fungi. There have been several analyses of divergence times in the fungal tree of life in the last two decades, but most have yielded contrasting results for the origin of the major lineages. Moreover, very few studies have provided temporal estimates for a large set of clades within Ascomycota. We performed molecular dating to estimate the divergence times of most of the major groups of Ascomycota. To account for paleontological uncertainty, we included alternative fossil constraints as different scenarios to enable a discussion of the effect of selection of fossils. We used data from 6 molecular markers and 121 extant taxa within Ascomycota. Our various ‘relaxed clock’ scenarios suggest that the origin and diversification of the Pezizomycotina occurred in the Cambrian. The main lineages of lichen–forming Ascomycota originated at least as early as the Carboniferous, with successive radiations in the Jurassic and Cretaceous generating the diversity of the main modern groups. Our study provides new information about the timing of the main diversification events in Ascomycota, including estimates for classes, orders and families of both lichenized and non–lichenized Ascomycota, many of which had not been previously dated.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This project was funded by the Swedish Research Council (grant VR 621–2009–5372 to MW). The authors thank the Swedish Museum of Natural History for providing complementary facilities. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Molecular dating, or the use of DNA sequences to estimate divergence times in phylogenetic trees, is rapidly developing into one of the most exciting applications of phylogenetic systematics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Bromham1">[1]</xref>. Common tools for estimating evolutionary timescales are often based on the molecular clock hypothesis, which assumes a constant evolutionary rate over time <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Zuckerkandl1">[2]</xref>. Unsurprisingly, however, deviations from a clocklike evolution are found in many cases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Britten1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Hasegawa2">[6]</xref>. Different methods have been developed to handle rate heterogeneity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Rutschmann1">[7]</xref>, some of which attempt to relax the molecular clock assumption by allowing the rate to vary across the tree <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Sanderson1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Drummond1">[11]</xref>. These relaxed–clock methods offer greater flexibility in modelling evolutionary events and in incorporating calibrations, which has resulted in a recent discussion about how to calibrate divergence time estimates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Drummond1">[11]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Ho2">[16]</xref>. Calibrations play a crucial role in studies of divergence times <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Graur1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Ho2">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Near1">[17]</xref> and incorrect calibrations can introduce error into an analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Parham1">[18]</xref>. Sources of error in the calibration process include the incompleteness of the fossil record, erroneous fossil age estimates, and erroneous placements of fossils on phylogenetic trees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Forest1">[19]</xref>. Different methods deal with uncertainty associated with the phylogenetic position of fossil calibration points <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Lee1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Near2">[22]</xref>. The method implemented in the Bayesian phylogenetic software BEAST <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Drummond2">[23]</xref> allows the user to account for uncertainty in the age of a given fossil, in the form of a prior distribution. By allowing calibrating information to be represented in the form of parametric distributions, this approach offers a high degree of flexibility to incorporate a time scale into a phylogenetic analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Ho2">[16]</xref>.</p>
<p>Several estimates for divergence times in Fungi have been published during the last two decades (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Berbee1">[24]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Taylor1">[27]</xref>). Many of these studies obtained radically different age estimates for the same divergence events, with analyses based on different methods (e.g. single rate, strict clock), datasets (based on a single gene, or more), taxon sampling, and fossil constraints, including external divergences (e.g. the split between eudicots and monocots, or extrapolations from animal divergences) or secondary calibrations (i.e. a point derived from a previous study). The fossil record in Fungi is very limited compared with plants and animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Taylor2">[28]</xref>. This is due to a combination of the often microscopic nature of fungi, the very poor preservation potential <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Blair1">[29]</xref> and probably, the relative difficulty in recognizing them in the fossil record <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Taylor3">[30]</xref>. Many, probably most, major lineages of fungi thus currently lack fossil data.</p>
<p>As the fossil record is fragmentary, a given fossil will very rarely possess features that place it in the crown group rather than along the stem lineage leading to the crown group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Forest1">[19]</xref>. Donoghue &amp; Purnell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Donoghue1">[31]</xref> point out that the most conservative and secure interpretation of the fossils is to avoid trying to resolve equivocal interpretations of stem or crown group classifications and instead to accept their classification as part of the total group. In Fungi, one of the most noteworthy examples is <italic>Paleopyrenomycites devonicus</italic>, the oldest unequivocal euascomycete fossil from the lower Devonian (ca 400 million years ago [Mya]), the systematic position of which has been widely disputed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Padovan1">[26]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Taylor1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Lcking1">[32]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Berbee2">[34]</xref>. Lücking et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Lcking1">[32]</xref> placed this fossil at three different positions in the Ascomycota (i.e. at the origin of Sordariomycetes, at the divergence of Pezizomycotina, and at the origin of Pezizomycotina) and re–estimated the divergence times for main fungal groups. This was done through a graphical recalibration of nodes from a number of fungal molecular clock trees, by fixing the age of the Ascomycota-Basidiomycota origin to 1 and calculating the relative ages of major nodes in the tree (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Lcking1">[32]</xref>, pp 814–815). The fossil is morphologically complex and does not fit within any extant taxonomic group. The presence of an ascoma opening similar to an operculum has resulted in different interpretations about its affinities, although it is clear that this structure is not homologous with the operculum in modern Pezizomycotina. Consequently, a conservative approach is to treat this fossil as a member of the stem lineage of the Ascomycota subphylum Pezizomycotina (the “Euascomycetes”).</p>
<p>Other remarkable Ascomycota fossils found in amber include an <italic>Aspergillus</italic> species growing on a springtail from the Eocene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Drfelt1">[35]</xref>, a species related to the extant anamorphic ascomycete genus <italic>Curvularia</italic> from the Cretaceous <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Schmidt1">[36]</xref> and a <italic>Xylaria</italic> species from Dominican amber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Poinar1">[37]</xref>. The resinicolous mazaediate fungus <italic>Chaenothecopsis bitterfeldensis</italic> was found in Bitterfeld amber from around 22 million years ago, near the Miocene–Oligocene boundary <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Rikkinen1">[38]</xref> and recently, two <italic>Chaenothecopsis</italic> fossils were described from Eocene Baltic and Oligocene Bitterfeld amber dating back to at least 35 and 24 Ma ago, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Tuovila1">[39]</xref>.</p>
<p>Well–preserved lichen fossils are found in Baltic (35–55 Mya) and Dominican amber (with estimates ranging from 15–20 to 30–45 Mya). Among these fossils, there is an alectorioid lichen and two specimens of <italic>Anzia</italic> from Baltic amber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Mgdefrau1">[40]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Rikkinen2">[41]</xref>, two species of <italic>Parmelia</italic> s.l. and one <italic>Phyllopsora</italic> described from Dominican amber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Poinar2">[42]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Rikkinen3">[43]</xref>. Crustose lichen fossils belonging to both mazaediate genera <italic>Calicium</italic> and <italic>Chaenotheca</italic> were also found in Baltic amber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Rikkinen4">[44]</xref>. Finally, an impression of a foliose macrolichen belonging to Lobariaceae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Peterson1">[45]</xref> was found from Miocene deposits.</p>
<p>Until now, very few studies have included these fossils to calibrate phylogenetic trees and even fewer have used them to estimate the timing of the main divergence events within Ascomycota. Most of the existing dating studies provide hypotheses on divergence times for major events in fungal evolution (e.g., the time for the origin of Fungi, Basidiomycota or Ascomycota), but not on the details of the radiation within a major group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Padovan1">[26]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Taylor1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Lcking1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Hedges2">[46]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Peterson2">[47]</xref>. Most of these studies are also not focused on Fungi, but have a wider scope, including plants and animals, and the taxon sampling may not be optimal for calculating the origin and divergence times of lineages within Ascomycota or Basidiomycota <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Heckman1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Douzery1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Wang1">[49]</xref>. One exception is the study of Gueidan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Gueidan1">[50]</xref> in which several groups of Ascomycota, including lichen–forming fungi, were included with a broad taxon sampling. Gueidan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Gueidan1">[50]</xref> still highlighted the need to improve the gene and taxon sampling, to achieve more accurate date estimates for fungal groups.</p>
<p>Several fossils related to extant mazaediate genera have been found in amber, but these have not been used for calibrating phylogenetic trees. We have recently produced a phylogeny of the Ascomycota with the aim of placing mazaedia–producing groups with previously unknown relationships <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Prieto1">[51]</xref>. This phylogeny contains representatives of several groups in which amber–preserved fossils occur, which can now be utilized for dating. Here, we want to take advantage of this recent phylogeny and use it to date the main diversification events within Ascomycota. To achieve this, we include all the dateable mazaediate fossils known, together with other Ascomycota fossils, to investigate the origin and divergence times of a number of major groups within Ascomycota, including lichenized fungi. We include a total of 6 fossils attributable to extant groups of Ascomycota. To account for the paleontological uncertainty, we also investigate the impact of various calibration scenarios on age estimates.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Taxon Sampling, Molecular Data and Phylogenetic Analysis</title>
<p>We included representatives of most lineages of Ascomycota, with a total of 118 species belonging to 10 classes of Pezizomycotina (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065576.s001">Table S1</xref>) and three members of Saccharomycotina and Taphrinomycotina as the outgroup. Six loci were used for this analysis (nuLSU and nuSSU rDNA, the 5.8S nuclear rDNA, mtSSU rDNA, and the nuclear protein–coding genes RPB1, and MCM7) with a total of 4112 characters included. The alignments from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Prieto1">[51]</xref> were utilized, with some additional sequences retrieved from GenBank (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065576.s001">Table S1</xref>). All the alignments are available upon request. Substitution models for each partition were selected using the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) implemented in jMODELTEST <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Posada1">[52]</xref>. The GTR model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Rodriguez1">[53]</xref> with an estimated proportion of invariable sites and with gamma-distributed rates among sites was selected for each of the six loci.</p>
<p>Phylogenetic relationships between taxa were estimated by maximum-likelihood analysis with the software RAxML VI–HPC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Stamatakis1">[54]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Stamatakis2">[55]</xref> on the CIPRES Science Gateway v. 3.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Miller1">[56]</xref>, using a GTR+I+G model of molecular evolution for six partitions (nuSSU, nuLSU, 5.8S, mtSSU, RPB1 and MCM7), rate heterogeneity with unlinked parameters and 1000 ML bootstrap replicates.</p>
<p>We performed the RAxML analysis with 6 and with 10 partitions (i.e. dividing the three codon positions for each of the two protein coding genes), but since the topologies were identical, we only present and discuss the RAxML tree obtained with 6 partitions. The best tree with bootstrap support values is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0065576-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Best tree from the maximum-likelihood analysis.</title>
<p>Numbers in circles indicate the nodes used for fossil calibration: (1) <italic>Paleopyrenomycites devonicus</italic>; (2) <italic>Chaenotheca</italic> sp.; (3) <italic>Calicium</italic> sp.; (4) <italic>Alectoria succinica</italic> or <italic>Parmelia ambra</italic>; and (5) <italic>Chaenothecopsis</italic> sp. Numbers above branches correspond to bootstrap support values and thicker branches show bootstrap support &gt;70%.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Molecular Clock Analysis</title>
<p>We implemented a Bayesian Markov chain Monte Carlo algorithm for estimating divergence times using data from multiple gene loci and accommodating multiple fossil calibration nodes. These analyses were performed using the BEAST v1.6.2 software package <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Drummond2">[23]</xref>. The tree topology and divergence times were estimated simultaneously. To provide an empirical test for the impact of various approaches to calibration, we investigated four different scenarios using several combinations of fossil constraints (see below, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t001">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). In all cases, we partitioned the data by gene, with unlinked partitions with the GTR+I+G substitution model for each partition. We also explored one of the BEAST scenarios with 10 partitions, and the divergence times estimated were very similar to the same scenario with 6 partitions, so we used the latter partitioning scheme for all of the analyses. We used the uncorrelated lognormal relaxed clock model, which allows rates of molecular evolution to be uncorrelated across the tree. We implemented a birth–death tree prior. BEAST analyses were run for 50 million generations, logging parameters and trees every 1000 generations. Convergence, mixing and effective sample sizes (ESS) of parameters were checked using Tracer v1.5.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Rambaut2">[57]</xref>. A burn–in of 500 trees was removed from each analysis. The remaining trees were used to generate a maximum clade credibility tree with TreeAnnotator v1.6.2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Drummond2">[23]</xref>. The performance for each scenario was compared through a Bayes Factors analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Kass1">[58]</xref>, carried out in Tracer v1.5.0, using the harmonic mean as an approximation of the marginal likelihood of each scenario, with 1000 bootstrap replicates to measure the error in the estimate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0065576-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Different scenarios investigated, fossils used, ages for each fossil and distributions associated with the selected fossils.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0065576-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (My)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 4</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alectoria succinica</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Mgdefrau1">[40]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 33*)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 33*)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Calicium</italic> sp.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Rikkinen4">[44]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 33*)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 33*)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 33*)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 33*)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Chaenotheca</italic> sp.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Rikkinen4">[44]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 98.9<sup>†</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 98.9<sup>†</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 98.9<sup>†</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 98.9<sup>†</sup>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Chaenothecopsis</italic> sp.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Tuovila1">[39]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–47</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 98.9<sup>†</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (35, 98.9<sup>†</sup>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Paleopyrenomycites devonicus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Taylor4">[33]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (400, 67.8<sup>‡</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (400, 67.8<sup>‡</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (400, 67.8<sup>‡</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (400, 67.8<sup>‡</sup>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Parmelia ambra</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Poinar2">[42]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15–45</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (15, 39.4*)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (15, 39.4*)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>Exponential distribution = Exp (offset, mean). The means were selected so that 97.5% of the prior probability for each fossil date would fall below the age of the major group the fossil belongs to, i.e. 400 Mya which is the age for the †Pezizomycotina crown and 650 Mya for the ‡ Ascomycota base, both according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Lcking1">[32]</xref> and 160 Mya which is the age of the * Lecanorales based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-AmodePaz1">[59]</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0065576-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Natural logarithm (x2) of Bayes Factors obtained in Tracer for the 4 molecular clock Scenarios.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0065576-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marginal likelihood</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S.E.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 4</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−97269,904</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/−0,237</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1,69</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1,59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1,12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−97269,059</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/−0,217</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,69</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,57</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−97269,109</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/−0,246</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0,1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−97269,344</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/−0,216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0,57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0,47</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><p>Marginal likelihood estimated as the ln harmonic mean likelihoods of the data. S.E.: Standard error of the marginal likelihood.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Fossil Calibration</title>
<p>For this study we selected the six fossils we considered most reliable in age and identification, including lichenized and non–lichenized Ascomycota (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). To incorporate uncertainty surrounding fossil calibrations, we specified prior probability distributions with a hard minimum bound, i.e. the estimated divergence date cannot be younger than the earliest known fossil. The correct use of fossils to calibrate phylogenetic trees is much debated (e.g. a summary in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Parham1">[18]</xref>). Several parametric distributions are available as priors on nodal ages in a Bayesian phylogenetic framework <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Ho2">[16]</xref>. In the present study we carried out several analyses, hereafter called “scenarios”, including different combinations of fossils (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t001">Table 1</xref>). All our scenarios share <italic>Paleopyrenomycites devonicus</italic> from the lower Devonian (400 Mya) as the oldest calibration point. Scenario 1 included the calibration points <italic>Calicium sp.</italic>, <italic>Chaenotheca sp.</italic> and <italic>Parmelia ambra</italic> with exponential distributions associated with their priors. In Scenario 2 we added <italic>Chaenothecopsis</italic> as another calibration point to the previous scenario. Scenario 3 includes <italic>Alectoria succinica</italic>, <italic>Calicium sp.</italic> and <italic>Chaenotheca sp.</italic> with exponential distributions. In Scenario 4 we added the <italic>Chaenothecopsis</italic> calibration point to Scenario 3.</p>
<p><italic>Paleopyrenomycites devonicus</italic> was placed at the base of the stem group, corresponding to the Pezizomycotina–Saccharomycotina divergence (the “Pezizomycotina origin”, constraint 1 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). <italic>Chaenotheca sp.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Rikkinen4">[44]</xref> was placed at the base of the family Coniocybaceae (constraint 2 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) and <italic>Calicium sp.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Rikkinen4">[44]</xref> was used to calibrate the <italic>Calicium</italic>–<italic>Cyphelium</italic> clade (constraint 3 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Amo de Paz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-AmodePaz1">[59]</xref> used <italic>Alectoria succinica</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Mgdefrau1">[40]</xref> as a calibration point either for the <italic>Alectoria</italic> clade or the whole alectorioid clade. As there is an uncertainty in this assignment, we decided to use it to calibrate the stem group (i.e. the <italic>Parmelia</italic>–<italic>Alectoria</italic> clade, constraint 4 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) to be more conservative. <italic>Parmelia ambra</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Poinar2">[42]</xref> was used by Amo de Paz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-AmodePaz1">[59]</xref> to calibrate the crown of <italic>Parmelia</italic> sensu stricto. Poinar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Poinar2">[42]</xref> pointed out that <italic>Parmelia ambra</italic> appears very similar to extant members of <italic>Parmelia</italic> and it is tempting to speculate on its resemblance to <italic>P. saxatilis</italic> and similar species. However, the small specimen studied lacks necessary characters to ensure that it belongs to <italic>Parmelia</italic>. Taking this uncertainty into account, we took a conservative approach and used this fossil to calibrate the stem of this group (i.e. the <italic>Parmelia–Alectoria</italic> clade, constraint 4 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), which is beyond doubt. Given that we cannot use two different fossils to calibrate the same node, we use both mutually exclusive scenarios, with either <italic>Parmelia</italic> or <italic>Alectoria</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t001">Table 1</xref>, Scenarios 1, 2, 3, 4 and constraint 4 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). We also incorporated <italic>Chaenothecopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t001">Table 1</xref>, Scenarios 2 and 4), from Eocene Baltic and Oligocene Bitterfeld ambers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Tuovila1">[39]</xref>, to calibrate the Mycocaliciales clade (constraint 5, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
<p>For nodes with less precise ages (e.g. known from one or a small number of fossils) Brown &amp; Sorhannus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Brown1">[60]</xref> suggested using two distinct calibration procedures, exponential and lognormal. The lognormal distribution is considered appropriate for use as a prior on calibrated nodes because it places the highest probability on ages somewhat older than the fossil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Ho2">[16]</xref>. However, the exponential distribution (with the highest probability similar to fossil age) can be a good alternative to a lognormal when there is insufficient paleontological information, as this distribution requires one fewer parameter. Hence, we chose an exponential distribution to minimize the number of additional parameters estimated from the data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t001">Table 1</xref>, scenarios 1, 2, 3 and 4).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<p>The best tree identified in the maximum-likelihood analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) is congruent with recent larger phylogenetic studies of the Ascomycota <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Prieto1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Spatafora1">[61]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Gazis1">[63]</xref>. The 11 Pezizomycotina classes included in the study were recovered as monophyletic. A discussion of the detailed relationships among euascomycete classes can be found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Prieto1">[51]</xref>.</p>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Comparing Scenarios</title>
<p>To assess the fit of the different calibration scenarios we compared the Bayes Factors of the –log likelihood between each scenario (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t002">Table 2</xref>, expressed as twice the natural logarithm of the Bayes factor). Age estimates with means and 95% confidence intervals for some of the major Ascomycota splits from the 4 scenarios are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t003">Table 3</xref> and the chronogram from Scenario 4 is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g002">Fig. 2</xref>. The Bayes factors analysis does not favour any particular scenario according to the criteria by Kass &amp; Raftery <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Kass1">[58]</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t002">Table 2</xref>). The four scenarios yield date estimates with overlapping credibility intervals, but the means and range of the age estimates vary with the different fossil constraints used (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g003">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t003">Table 3</xref>). Mean estimates are younger and the credibility intervals are narrower in Scenario 3 than in Scenario 1 (with <italic>Alectoria</italic> or <italic>Parmelia</italic>, respectively, as constraints) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g003">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t003">Table 3</xref>). Scenario 2 differs very little from Scenario 4 (<italic>Parmelia</italic> or <italic>Alectoria</italic>, plus <italic>Chaenothecopsis</italic>, respectively, as constraints) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g003">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t003">Table 3</xref>). Scenario 2 has narrower credibility intervals than Scenario 1, both at basal nodes and nodes towards the tips, but Scenario 4 has wider credibility intervals (especially in some basal nodes) and older means than in scenario 3. We interpret this as meaning that the inclusion of a more accurately dated fossil (<italic>Alectoria</italic>) affects the dating estimates differently depending on the number of fossils included, and that the effect is reduced when an additional fossil (<italic>Chaenothecopsis</italic>) is included. The effect also depends on the node being considered, as nodes closer to the tips are less affected than nodes further down the tree. We can conclude as a general rule that it is important to select as accurately dated fossils, and to include as many fossils, as possible.</p>
<fig id="pone-0065576-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Maximum clade credibility chronogram for the major groups of Ascomycota.</title>
<p>The chronogram is the result from the BEAST analysis of Scenario 4. Each node represents the mean divergence time estimate and bars show their associated 95% credibility interval. Numbers corresponding to dated groups shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065576-t003">Table 3</xref> are written above the nodes.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0065576-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Comparison of divergence ages in several Ascomycota clades.</title>
<p>The mean divergence time estimates and their associated 95% credibility intervals (y–axis) for selected nodes within Ascomycota for the 4 scenarios studied (x–axis) are represented. A: node 1, Ascomycota crown; B: node 2, Pezizomycotina crown; C: node 3, Pezizomycetes–“Leotiomyceta”; D: node 9, Lichinomycetes–Coniocybomycetes; E: node 10, Coniocybomycetes crown; F: node 19, Lecanoromycetes crown; G: node 20, Eurotiomycetes crown; H: node 33, Ostropomycetidae; I: node 43, Ostropales; J: node 46, Lecanoromycetidae crown; K: node 47, Lecanorales crown; L: node 41, Arctomiaceae.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0065576-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Mean and range (95% credibility intervals) divergence time estimations (Mya) among the major Ascomycota lineages for the 4 molecular clock scenarios studied.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0065576-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenarios</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Scenario 1</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Scenario 2</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Scenario 3</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Scenario 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Node label</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clade name</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascomycota crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">408–715</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">539</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">419–660</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">533</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">408–633</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410–671</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">531</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pezizomycotina crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">417–614</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">498</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">421–555</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">485</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">420–532</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">471</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">422–558</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">485</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pezizomycetes–Leotiomyceta</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400–539</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">445</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400–485</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">435</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400–466</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">424</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400–487</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">435</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orbiliomycetes crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32–201</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41–197</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39–191</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39–188</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leotiomyceta crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">306–490</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">388</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">338–434</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">383</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">325–413</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">370</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">338–434</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">383</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pezizomycetes crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192–448</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">322</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203–425</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">322</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213–407</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">317</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203–425</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">322</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">274–444</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">353</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">308–385</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">348</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">298–373</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">335</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">310–394</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">350</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>8</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geoglossomycetes crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27–145</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26–127</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29–142</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26–127</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>9</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lichinomycetes–Coniocybomycetes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190–363</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">273</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204–328</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">267</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194–319</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204–328</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">267</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coniocybomycetes crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66–150</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73–141</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73–137</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72–141</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>11</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lichinomycetes crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107–260</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114–238</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112–228</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114–238</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Candelariales crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30–196</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36–178</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40–164</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36–178</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inoperculate Fungi+Arthoniomycetes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224–386</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">302</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">255–346</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243–331</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">288</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251–348</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">302</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>14</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sordariomycetes–Leotiomycetes split</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166–320</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197–296</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190–285</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193–299</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>15</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sordariomycetes crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64–194</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81–189</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71–170</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77–181</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leotiomycetes crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61–209</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67–191</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69–197</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62–199</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>17</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arthoniomycetes crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88–232</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96–228</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95–214</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100–219</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>18</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dothideomycetes crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93–252</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105–245</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103–226</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107–245</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>19</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lecanoromycetes crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233–388</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">306</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265–342</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">304</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256–326</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">291</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">267–344</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurotiomycetes crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">231–386</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">307</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265–344</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">304</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">254–329</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">292</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266–347</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">306</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>21</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204–354</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">276</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233–314</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">273</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224–305</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">234–314</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">273</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>22</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165–303</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186–272</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179–261</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184–270</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>23</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155–292</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173–262</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167–253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171–263</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>24</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121–233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137–215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129–207</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134–214</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>25</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurotiales</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73–169</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84–163</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80–154</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81–159</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>26</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Onygenales</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89–193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102–183</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95–176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100–181</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>27</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107–228</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120–208</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114–204</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116–208</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>28</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chaetothyriales</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33–121</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38–114</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32–106</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–110</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>29</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verrucariales</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–124</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37–112</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36–107</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33–116</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>30</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyrenulales</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58–185</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65–172</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63–167</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66–173</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>31</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mycocaliciales</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84–239</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82–232</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79–218</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87–226</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>32</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acarosporomycetidae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49–146</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55–132</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52–134</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53–134</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>33</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ostropomycetidae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184–309</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211–275</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202–261</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211–275</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>34</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Umbilicariales crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94–280</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102–266</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106–253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105–269</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>35</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lecanoromycetidae<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref> crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175–302</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202–269</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">234</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193–257</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203–269</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>36</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variolaria</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75–167</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82–155</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82–150</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83–154</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>37</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ochrolechiaceae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22–99</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22–99</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25–95</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25–99</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Megasporaceae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37–132</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42–132</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41–122</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39–121</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>39</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Varicellaria</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36–122</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–115</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33–113</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37–112</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>40</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microcaliciales</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31–98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34–92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32–88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34–89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>41</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arctomiaceae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>42</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Icmadophilaceae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45–145</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51–136</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47–125</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50–135</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>43</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ostropales</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138–248</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158–229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150–212</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155–221</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>44</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coccotremataceae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66–163</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72–159</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69–154</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70–156</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>45</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agyriaceae–Pertusaria s.str.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91–205</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99–196</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95–189</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106–199</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>46</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lecanoromycetidae<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">**</xref> crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160–279</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182–250</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176–240</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185–248</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>47</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lecanorales crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104–210</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119–195</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115–188</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120–196</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>48</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peltigerales crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95–201</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104–193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101–189</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109–192</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>49</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lecideales crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16–79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16–73</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15–71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15–79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>50</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caliciales crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118–222</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132–199</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128–193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135–202</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>51</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhizocarpales crown</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66–239</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84–224</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87–217</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90–230</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><p>Node labels correspond to nodes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g002">Fig. 2</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>*</label><p>Excluding Umbilicariales;</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>**</label><p>Excluding Umbilicariales and Rhizocarpales.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Divergence Times of Major Ascomycota Groups</title>
<p>The maximum clade credibility trees obtained for all the BEAST analyses are topologically identical to the best tree obtained with maximum likelihood. As scenario 4 includes most fossils, and the most accurate dated fossil (<italic>Alectoria</italic>), we will base our discussion below on the dates obtained from scenario 4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g002">Fig. 2</xref>; chronogram).</p>
<p>For all scenarios, the first divergence in Ascomycota (the split between [Saccharomycotina+Taphrinomycotina] and Pezizomycotina) took place in the Early Cambrian (node 1; 531 Mya; 410–671 Mya credibility interval [CI]), which corresponds to the origin of the Pezizomycotina (the euascomycetes, or the Ascomycota crown). In previous studies, various dates have been proposed for this divergence, ranging from ca. 325 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Berbee1">[24]</xref> to 1316 Mya <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Taylor1">[27]</xref>. Lücking et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Lcking1">[32]</xref> estimated that this split happened ca. 400–520 Mya (Pezizomycotina stem base), and Gueidan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Gueidan1">[50]</xref>, using relaxed clock methods, estimated this date to be 538 Mya, which are very close to the estimates obtained here. These results place the origin of the Pezizomycotina in the Cambrian, which is earlier than the origin and diversification of the land plants. As the first groups to diverge, Taphrinomycotina and Saccharomycotina, include both saprotrophs and parasites, this dating is consistent with the hypothesis that the ancestors of the Pezizomycotina would have been saprotrophs on algae or invertebrates. But whether the origin of the ancestors of Ascomycota and Pezizomycotina was marine or terrestrial is an open question. Some propose a terrestrial origin of the Ascomycota (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Spatafora2">[64]</xref>), but this hypothesis has never been tested with adequate methodology to confidently resolve the ancestry for Ascomycota. Marine fungi have been reported from oceanic areas in different parts of the world, living as saprophytes and parasites, contributing to the decay of algae or other plant remains and the infection of marine plants and animals. As the dating obtained here for the Pezizomycotina is earlier than the appearance of land plants, this suggests the possibility of a marine origin for the group. Further work is needed to properly test the possible marine–terrestrial transition within the early evolution of the Ascomycota.</p>
<p>The earliest splits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g002">Fig. 2</xref>) within Pezizomycotina took place in the Ordovician, resulting in the Orbiliomycetes and the Pezizomycotina crown group (node 2; 485 Mya, 422–558 CI); in the Silurian (node 3; 435 Mya, 400–487 CI), resulting in the Pezizomycetes and the “Leotiomyceta”; and in the Upper Devonian (node 5, 383 Mya; 338–434 Mya CI) giving rise to the Geoglossomycetes. A recent date estimation of the origin of the Pezizomycetes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Gueidan1">[50]</xref> was very similar to ours (441 Mya, 386–498 Mya CI), but the divergence between Orbiliomycetes and the Pezizomycotina crown group was slightly younger (455 Mya, 396–516 Mya).</p>
<p>Character state reconstruction supports a saprobic nutritional mode for ancestors of “Leotiomyceta” and Pezizomycetes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Schoch1">[62]</xref>. At the time we estimate that they appeared (i.e. Silurian) there is direct fossil evidence of vascular plants and terrestrial arthropods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Kenrick1">[65]</xref> with which these fungi could have established biotic interactions, thus also supporting that both these groups had saprophytic ancestors.</p>
<p>The lineage including, among others, all lichenized lineages in the tree (node 7) is dated to 350 Mya, 310–394 CI, in the early Carboniferous. This lineage also includes non-lichenized fungi and the ancestor is considered to have been non–lichenized <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Schoch1">[62]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Gueidan2">[66]</xref>. The stem leading to most members of inoperculate fungi (i.e. Dothideomycetes, Leotiomycetes and Sordariomycetes), and the lichenized class Arthoniomycetes, dates from the Upper Carboniferous (node 13, 302 Mya). The most recent common ancestor for the lichen classes Lichinomycetes and Coniocybomycetes dates from the Permian (node 9; 267 Mya, 204–328 CI). The diversification of Eurotiomycetes and Lecanoromycetes took place in the Upper Carboniferous (nodes 20 and 19, 306 and 305 Mya respectively). The Lecanoromycetes include most lichenized Ascomycota, and the ancestor has been reconstructed as lichenized <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Gueidan2">[66]</xref>, suggesting that the main lineages of lichen–forming Ascomycota originated in the Upper Carboniferous. During this period, the uplift of the continents caused a transition to a more terrestrial environment, and a trend towards aridity. The lycopods underwent a major extinction event and ferns became more important with an increase in the number of trees. By the end of the Carboniferous, all five of the major extant fern lineages were present <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Pryer1">[67]</xref>, and gymnosperms had appeared <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Renner1">[68]</xref>, which resulted in a wide range of substrates to colonize and thus could explain the rapid diversification of the Lecanoromycetes at this time.</p>
<p>Although node 35 is not fully supported (69% bootstrap support in the likelihood analysis, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), lineages leading to Lecanoromycetidae (excluding the Umbilicariales but including Rhizocarpales) originated during the Triassic, after the P–T mass extinction (node 35, 236 Mya), as well as the diversification of Ostropomycetidae (node 33, 243 Mya) and the diversification of Lecanoromycetidae (excluding Rhizocarpales, node 46, 217 Mya).</p>
<p>Within the Eurotiomycetes, all orders diversified during the Cretaceous (nodes 24, 25, 27, 28, 29 and 30). The main orders within the Lecanoromycetidae (47, 48 and 50 dated from 158, 150 and 169 Mya respectively) diversified in the Jurassic, except the Lecideales (node 49, 42 mya) which diversified in the Eocene. The relationships within Ostropomycetidae are not fully resolved, as in other studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Lumbsch1">[69]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Baloch1">[71]</xref>, and divergence times have been obtained mainly at the family level. Our results indicate that most of the families diverged already in the Cretaceous–Paleocene (nodes 36 to 40), except the Arctomiaceae which diverged in the Miocene (node 41, 9 Mya).</p>
<p>Although all major lichenized lineages had their origins in the Upper Carboniferous (Table and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065576-g003">Fig. 3</xref>), it was successive radiations in the Jurassic and Cretaceous that generated the diversity in the main modern groups. Recent estimates suggest that the origin of angiosperms was either in the lower Jurassic to Lower Cretaceous <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Bell1">[72]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Soltis1">[74]</xref>, or in the Triassic–early Jurassic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Clarke1">[75]</xref>. This could explain the main diversification events within Lecanoromycetidae and Ostropomycetidae, in which many taxa grow as epiphytes. The high levels of diversity in lichenized groups in the Jurassic and Cretaceous could thus be potentially explained by the many new environments dominated by the new diversity of angiosperms, which could be inhabited by these lichens.</p>
<p>In our analysis, Acarosporomycetideae and Candelariales are two of the oldest groups of lichenized fungi, but their crown diversification dates are among the most recent (nodes 11 and 31, Upper Cretaceous). Whether these two clades have experienced a recent speciation or suffered a high number of extinctions is unknown and further studies are necessary to answer this question.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Despite the increasing interest in dating the origin and diversification of different groups in Fungi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-AmodePaz1">[59]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Divakar1">[76]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0065576-Yang2">[79]</xref>, we still lack detailed information to provide hypotheses on the evolutionary history of Ascomycota. This includes the lichenized euascomycetes, a clade that is key to understanding the evolution of symbiosis in Fungi. In this study we provide three important observations that can further our knowledge of the evolutionary rate and dates in Ascomycota. First, our analysis suggests an ancient origin of Pezizomycotina, ca 530 Mya, in the Cambrian period. Second, the main lichenized Ascomycota lineages appeared at least as early as the Carboniferous, with successive radiations in the Jurassic and Cretaceous that generated the diversity in the main modern groups. Third, we provide estimates for the origin and diversification dates for many clades in the Pezizomycotina, which previously had not been dated, including the current major classes and orders, as well as some families of both lichenized and non–lichenized groups. Such dates, even if tentative, set a promising foundation for future hypotheses on the evolution of this fascinating group of Fungi.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0065576.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0065576.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Specimens used in this study with GenBank accession numbers.</bold></p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank M. Méndez and I. Olariaga for discussions and comments on the manuscript, S. Nylinder for advice on the divergence time analysis and S. Ho, S. Leavitt and an anonymous reviewer for their constructive comments.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Bromham1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bromham</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The modern molecular clock</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Zuckerkandl1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zuckerkandl E, Pauling L (1965) Evolutionary divergence and convergence in proteins. In: Bryson V, Vogel H, editors. Evolving genes and proteins. New York: Academic Press. 97–166.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Britten1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Britten</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Rates of DNA sequence evolution differ between taxonomic groups</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>231</volume>: <fpage>1393</fpage>–<lpage>1398</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Hasegawa1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kishino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Heterogeneity of tempo and mode of mitochondrial DNA evolution among mammalian orders</article-title>. <source>Jpn J Genet</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Ayala1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayala</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Vagaries of the molecular clock</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>7776</fpage>–<lpage>7783</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Hasegawa2"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kishino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Time scale of eutherian evolution estimated without assuming a constant rate of molecular evolution</article-title>. <source>Genes Genet Syst</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Rutschmann1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutschmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Molecular dating of phylogenetic trees: A brief review of current methods that estimate divergence times</article-title>. <source>Divers Distrib</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Sanderson1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A nonparameteric approach to estimating divergence times in the absence of rate constancy</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1218</fpage>–<lpage>1231</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Rambaut1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bromham</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Estimating divergence dates from molecular sequences</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>442</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Thorne1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kishino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Painter</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Estimating the rate of evolution of the rate of molecular evolution</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1647</fpage>–<lpage>1657</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Drummond1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Relaxed phylogenetics and dating with confidence</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e88</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Graur1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graur</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Reading the entrails of chickens: molecular timescales of evolution and the illusion of precision</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Hedges1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Precision of molecular time estimates</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>242</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Yang1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rannala</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Bayesian estimation of species divergence times under a molecular clock using multiple fossil calibrations with soft bounds</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Ho1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Calibrating molecular estimates of substitution rates and divergence times in birds</article-title>. <source>J Avian Biol</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>409</fpage>–<lpage>414</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Ho2"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Accounting for calibration uncertainty in phylogenetic estimation of evolutionary divergence times</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Near1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Near</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Assessing the quality of molecular divergence time estimates by fossil calibrations and fossil–based model selection</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans R Soc London</source> <volume>359</volume>: <fpage>1477</fpage>–<lpage>1483</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Parham1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parham</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>PCJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calway</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Head</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Best Practices for Justifying Fossil Calibrations</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>346</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Forest1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forest</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Calibrating the Tree of Life: fossils, molecules and evolutionary timescales</article-title>. <source>Ann Bot</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>789</fpage>–<lpage>794</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Lee1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MSY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetic uncertainty and molecular clock calibrations in legless lizards (Pygopodidae, Gekkota)</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>661</fpage>–<lpage>666</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Rutschmann2"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutschmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salim</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Assessing calibration uncertainty in molecular dating: the assignment of fossils to alternative calibration points</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>591</fpage>–<lpage>608</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Near2"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Near</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meylan</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Assessing concordance of fossil calibration points in molecular clock studies: an example using turtles</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>165</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Drummond2"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>BEAST: Bayesian evolutionary analysis by sampling trees</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>214</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Berbee1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berbee</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Dating the evolutionary radiations of the true fungi</article-title>. <source>Can J Bot</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1114</fpage>–<lpage>1127</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Heckman1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heckman</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geiser</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eidell</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stauffer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kardos</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Molecular evidence for the early colonization of land by fungi and plants</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>293</volume>: <fpage>1129</fpage>–<lpage>1133</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Padovan1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Padovan</surname><given-names>ACB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanson</surname><given-names>GFO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunstein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Briones</surname><given-names>MRS</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Fungi evolution revisited: application of the penalized likelihood method to a Bayesian fungal phylogeny provides a new perspective on phylogenetic relationships and divergence dates of Ascomycota groups</article-title>. <source>J Mol Evol</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>726</fpage>–<lpage>735</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Taylor1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berbee</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Dating divergences in the fungal tree of life: review and new analyses</article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>838</fpage>–<lpage>849</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Taylor2"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Taylor PD (2004) Extinction and the fossil record. In: Taylor PD, editor. Extinctions in the History of Life. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 1–34.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Blair1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Blair JE (2009) Fungi. In: Hedges SB, Kumar S, editors. The Timetree of Life. New York: Oxford University Press. 213–220.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Taylor3"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The importance of fungi in zapping the paleoecosystem</article-title>. <source>Rev Palaeobot Palyno</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Donoghue1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>PCJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Purnell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Distinguishing heat from light in debate over controversial fossils</article-title>. <source>BioEssays</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Lcking1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lücking</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huhndorf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rivas Platas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lumbsch</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Fungi evolved right on track</article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>810</fpage>–<lpage>822</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Taylor4"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hass</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerp</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krings</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanlin</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Perithecial ascomycetes from the 400 million year old Rhynie chert: an example of ancestral polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Berbee2"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berbee</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Dating the molecular clock in fungi–how close are we?</article-title> <source>Fungal Biol Rev</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Drfelt1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dörfelt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A fossil <italic>Aspergillu</italic>s from Baltic amber</article-title>. <source>Mycol Res</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>956</fpage>–<lpage>960</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Schmidt1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perrichot</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Svojtka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belete</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Cretaceous African life captured in amber</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>7329</fpage>–<lpage>7334</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Poinar1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Poinar GO Jr (1992) Life in Amber. California: Stanford University Press. 350 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Rikkinen1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rikkinen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A new species of resinicolous <italic>Chaenothecopsis</italic> (Mycocaliciaceae, Ascomycota) from 20 million year old Bitterfeld amber, with remarks on the biology of resinicolous fungi</article-title>. <source>Mycol Res</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Tuovila1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuovila</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beimforde, Dörfelt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grabenhorst</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Stuck in time – a new <italic>Chaenothecopsis</italic> species with proliferating ascomata from <italic>Cunninghamia</italic> resin and its fossil ancestors in European amber</article-title>. <source>Fungal Divers</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Mgdefrau1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mägdefrau</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1957</year>) <article-title>Flechten und Moose in baltischen Bernstein</article-title>. <source>Ber Deut Bot Ges</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Rikkinen2"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rikkinen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Yeast-like fungi in Dominican amber</article-title>. <source>Karstenia</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Poinar2"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>GO</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Fossil <italic>Parmelia</italic> in new world amber</article-title>. <source>Lichenologist</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Rikkinen3"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rikkinen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>GO</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A new species of <italic>Phyllopsora</italic> (Lecanorales, lichen–forming Ascomycota) from Dominican amber, with remarks on the fossil history of lichens</article-title>. <source>Journal Exp Bot</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>1007</fpage>–<lpage>1011</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Rikkinen4"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rikkinen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Calicioid lichens from European Tertiary amber</article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>1032</fpage>–<lpage>1036</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Peterson1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>An overlooked fossil lichen (Lobariaceae)</article-title>. <source>Lichenologist</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Hedges2"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Venturi</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shoe</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A molecular timescale of eukaryote evolution and the rise of complex multicellular life</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Peterson2"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurogi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny and biogeography of <italic>Chorioactis geaster</italic> (Pezizales, Ascomycota) inferred from nuclear ribosomal DNA sequences</article-title>. <source>Harvard Pap Bot</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Douzery1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Douzery</surname><given-names>EJP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snell</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bapteste</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The timing of eukaryotic evolution: Does a relaxed molecular clock reconcile proteins and fossils?</article-title> <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>15386</fpage>–<lpage>15391</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Wang1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DYC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Divergence time estimates for the early history of animal phyla and the origin of plants, animals and fungi</article-title>. <source>P Roy Soc Lond B Bio</source> <volume>266</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Gueidan1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gueidan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruibal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Hoog</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Rock–inhabiting fungi originated during periods of dry climate in the late Devonian and middle Triassic</article-title>. <source>Fungal Biology</source> <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>–<lpage>996</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Prieto1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Prieto M, Baloch E, Tehler A, Wedin M (2013) Mazaedium evolution in the Ascomycota (Fungi) and the classification of mazaediate groups of formerly unclear relationship. Cladistics. doi: 10.1111/j.1096-0031.2012.00429.x.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Posada1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>jModelTest: Phylogenetic Model Averaging</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1253</fpage>–<lpage>1256</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Rodriguez1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>The general stochastic model of nucleotide substitution</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source> <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Stamatakis1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>RAxML-VI-HPC: maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic analyses with thousands of taxa and mixed models</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2688</fpage>–<lpage>2690</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Stamatakis2"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rougemont</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A fast bootstrapping algorithm for the RAxML Web-Servers</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>758</fpage>–<lpage>771</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Miller1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Miller MA, Pfeiffer W, Schwartz T (2010) Creating the CIPRES Science Gateway for inference of large phylogenetic trees. In: Proceedings of the Gateway Computing Environments Workshop (GCE), New Orleans, LA. 1–8.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Rambaut2"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rambaut A, Drummond AJ (2007) Tracer v1.4. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer" xlink:type="simple">http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer</ext-link>. Accessed 2011 May.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Kass1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kass</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raftery</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Bayes factors</article-title>. <source>J Am Stat Assoc</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>773</fpage>–<lpage>795</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-AmodePaz1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amo de Paz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cubas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Divakar</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lumbsch</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crespo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Origin and diversification of major clades in Parmelioid lichens (Parmeliaceae, Ascomycota) during the Paleogene inferred by bayesian analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e28161</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Brown1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sorhannus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A molecular genetic timescale for the diversification of autotrophic Stramenopiles (Ochrophyta): substantive underestimation of putative fossil ages</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e12759</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Spatafora1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spatafora</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Rourke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A five-gene phylogenetic analysis of the Pezizomycotina</article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>1018</fpage>–<lpage>1028</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Schoch1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoch</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>G–H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>López–Giráldez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miadlikowska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Ascomycota tree of life: a phylum wide phylogeny clarifies the origin and evolution of fundamental reproductive and ecological traits</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Gazis1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gazis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miadlikowska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lutzoni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaverri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Culture–based study of endophytes associated with rubber trees in Peru reveals a new class of Pezizomycotina: Xylonomycetes</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>294</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Spatafora2"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spatafora</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Volkmann-Kohlmeyer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohlmeyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Independent terrestrial origins of the Halosphaeriales (marine Ascomycota)</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>1569</fpage>–<lpage>1580</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Kenrick1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenrick</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wellman</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edgecombe</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A timeline for terrestrialization: consequences for the carbon cycle in the Palaeozoic</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>367</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>536</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Gueidan2"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gueidan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruibal Villaseñor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Hoog</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gorbushina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Untereiner</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A rock–inhabiting ancestor for mutualistic and pathogen–rich fungal lineages</article-title>. <source>Stud Mycol</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Pryer1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pryer KM, Schuettpelz E (2009) Ferns. In: Hedges SB, Kumar S, editors. The Timetree of Life, New York: Oxford University Press. 153–156.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Renner1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Renner S (2009) Gymnosperms. In: Hedges SB, Kumar S, editors. The Timetree of Life, New York: Oxford University Press. 157–160.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Lumbsch1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumbsch</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mangold</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wedin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Ascus types are phylogenetically misleading in <italic>Trapeliaceae</italic> and <italic>Agyriaceae</italic> (Ostropomycetidae, Ascomycota)</article-title>. <source>Mycol Res</source> <volume>111</volume>: <fpage>1133</fpage>–<lpage>1141</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Schmitt1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frankhauser</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spribille</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kalb</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Gyalectoid <italic>Pertusaria</italic> species from a sister clade to <italic>Coccotrema</italic> (Ostropomycetidae, Ascomycota) and comprise the new lichen genus <italic>Gyalectaria</italic></article-title>. <source>Mycology</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Baloch1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baloch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lücking</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lumbsch</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wedin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Major clades and phylogenetic relationships between lichenized and non–lichenized lineages in Ostropales</article-title>. <source>Taxon</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>1483</fpage>–<lpage>1494</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Bell1"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The age and diversification of the angiosperms re–revisited</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>1296</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Bell2"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The age and diversification of the angiosperms: A molecular timescale without a clock</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>1245</fpage>–<lpage>1258</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Soltis1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The origin and early evolution of angiosperms</article-title>. <source>Ann New York Acad Sci</source> <volume>1133</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Clarke1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warnock</surname><given-names>RCM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>PCJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Establishing a time–scale for plant evolution</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>192</volume>: <fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Divakar1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Divakar</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>del Prado</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lumbsch</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wedin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esslinger</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Diversification of the newly recognized lichen-forming fungal lineage <italic>Montanelia</italic> (Parmeliaceae, Ascomycota) and its relation to key geological and climatic events</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>2014</fpage>–<lpage>2026</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-AmodePaz2"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Amo de Paz G, Cubas P, Crespo A, Elix JA, Lumbsch HT (2012) Transoceanic Dispersal and Subsequent Diversification on Separate Continents Shaped Diversity of the <italic>Xanthoparmelia pulla</italic> Group (Ascomycota). PLoS ONE: e39683.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Leavitt1"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leavitt</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esslinger</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Divakar</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lumbsch</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Miocene and Pliocene dominated diversification of the lichen–forming fungal genus <italic>Melanohalea</italic> (Parmeliaceae, Ascomycota) and Pleistocene population expansions</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>176</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0065576-Yang2"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Origin and evolution of carnivorism in the Ascomycota (fungi)</article-title>. <source>P Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>10960</fpage>–<lpage>10965</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>