<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-15114</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061827</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecological environments</subject><subj-group><subject>Freshwater environments</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Ecological metrics</subject><subj-group><subject>Relative abundance distribution</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biogeography</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Natural selection</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Systems biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal phylogenetics</subject><subject>Animal taxonomy</subject><subject>Ichthyology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Molecular Phylogeny and Biogeography of <italic>Percocypris</italic> (Cyprinidae, Teleostei)</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>Percocypris</italic> Molecular Phylogeny and Biogeography</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Mo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Jun-Xing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xiao-Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Resources and Evolution, Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, Yunnan, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salzburger</surname><given-names>Walter</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Basel, Switzerland</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">chenxy@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email> (XYC); <email xlink:type="simple">yangjx@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email> (JXY)</corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: XYC JXY. Performed the experiments: MW. Analyzed the data: MW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: XYC JXY. Wrote the paper: MW XYC JXY.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>e61827</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Wang et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Fierce predatory freshwater fishes, the species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> (Cyprinidae, Teleostei) inhabit large rivers or lakes, and have a specific distribution pattern. Only a single species or subspecies occurs in each large-scale drainage basin of the Southeastern Tibetan Plateau. In this study, the molecular phylogenetic relationships for all but one of the described subspecies/species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> were investigated based on three mitochondrial genes (16S; COI; Cyt <italic>b</italic>) and one nuclear marker (Rag2). The results of Maximum Likelihood and Bayesian Inference analyses show that <italic>Percocypris</italic> is a strongly supported monophyletic group and that it is the sister group of <italic>Schizothorax</italic>. Combined with analyses of morphological characters, our results suggest that <italic>Percocypris</italic> needs to be reclassified, and we propose that six species be recognized, with corresponding distributions in five main drainages (including one lake). In addition, based on the results of the estimation of divergence times and ancestral drainages, we hypothesize that <italic>Percocypris</italic> likely originated in the early Miocene from a paleo-connected drainage system containing the contemporary main drainages of the Southeastern Tibetan Plateau. This study suggests that vicariance (due to the uplift of the Tibetan Plateau modifying the large-scale morphologies of drainage basins in the Southeastern Tibetan Plateau) has played an important role in the speciation of the genus. Furthermore, external morphological characters (such as the length of the fins) and an internal trait (the position of pterygiophore) appear to be correlated with different habitats in rivers and the lake.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 30870288, No. 30730017). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> (Cyprinidae, Teleostei) are fierce predatory freshwater fishes inhabiting large rivers or lakes, in southwestern China and northern Vietnam. Members of the genus have a specific distribution pattern, that is, there is only one species or subspecies in each drainage as follows (Chinese names in brackets): Upper Yangtze River (Jinsha Jiang), Mekong River (Lancang Jiang), Salween River (Nu Jiang), Upper Pearl River (Nanpan Jiang), Red River (Yuan Jiang). The genus thus appears to be an ideal system to study how historical geologic or geographic events of the relevant drainages including the famous Three Parallel Rivers of Yunnan Protected Areas (Salween, Mekong and Upper Yangtze rivers) influenced the biogeography of freshwater fishes.</p>
<p>However, even the basic taxonomy of how many species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> exist has not been resolved. Chu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Chu1">[1]</xref> erected <italic>Percocypris</italic> for <italic>Leptobarbus pingi</italic> Tchang (1930) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Tchang1">[2]</xref>. In the same year, Tchang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Tchang2">[3]</xref> described <italic>Barbus regani</italic> (subsequently treated as <italic>P. pingi regani</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Wu1">[4]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Shan1">[7]</xref>) from Fuxian Lake. Cui &amp; Chu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Cui1">[6]</xref> described <italic>P. pingi retrodorslis</italic> from Mekong and Salween rivers, and presented a classification system of one species with three subspecies that was adopted by other Chinese researchers (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Shan1">[7]</xref>). Nevertheless, Kottelat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Kottelat1">[8]</xref> regarded the three subspecies as three species with the scientific names of <italic>P. pingi</italic>, <italic>P. regani</italic> and <italic>P. tchangi</italic> (<italic>P. pingi retrodorslis</italic> treated as a synonym of <italic>P. tchang</italic>), and pointed out that the species <italic>P. tchangi</italic> Pellegrin &amp; Chevey 1936 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Pellegrin1">[9]</xref> (described from Red River) was apparently overlooked. The basic disagreement over the classification of <italic>Percocypris</italic> – of whether it consists of one species with three subspecies (<italic>P. pingi pingi</italic>, <italic>P. pingi regani</italic> and <italic>P. pingi retrodorslis</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Cui1">[6]</xref>) or three species (<italic>P. pingi</italic>, <italic>P. regani</italic> and <italic>P. tchangi</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Kottelat1">[8]</xref>) – needs to be resolved. In this study, we provisionally follow the classification system of Cui &amp; Chu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Cui1">[6]</xref>, that is, <italic>P. pingi pingi</italic> (Upper Yangtze River), <italic>P. pingi regani</italic> (Fuxian Lake, Upper Pearl River) and <italic>P. pingi retrodorslis</italic> (Mekong and Salween rivers).</p>
<p>The studies cited above on the taxonomy of <italic>Percocypris</italic> relied entirely on morphological characters. However, molecular studies on <italic>Percocypris</italic> to date have utilized only collections of <italic>P. pingi pingi</italic> from one locality (Hejiang, Sichuan Prov.) and <italic>P. pingi retrodorslis</italic> from one locality (Baoshan, Yunnan Prov.). The sample of <italic>P. pingi pingi</italic> was used in the molecular phylogenetic analyses of Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Wang1">[10]</xref>, Kong et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Kong1">[11]</xref> and Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Li1">[12]</xref>, which were based on the Rag2 [recombinant activation gene 2], <italic>S6K1</italic> [ribosomal protein S6 kinase 1] and 16S [16S ribosomal small subunit] genes, respectively. In addition to <italic>P. pingi pingi</italic>, one sample of <italic>P. pingi retrodorslis</italic> (IHBCY0505008; Baoshan, Yunnan Prov.) was also included in the study of Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Li1">[12]</xref>. The results of all the three studies suggested that <italic>Schizothorax</italic> may be the sister group of <italic>Percocypris</italic>. In addition, the monophyly of <italic>Percocypris</italic> was not firmly established by Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Li1">[12]</xref>, due to the particularly weak nodal supports of the clade of <italic>P. pingi pingi</italic> and <italic>P. pingi retrodorslis</italic> (Maximum parsimony bootstrap values  = 56; Bayesian posterior probability  = 0.80/0.82). These studies suffered from incomplete taxon sampling, with only two samples, at most, included. Moreover, only a single gene was used in these analyses; no combined molecular data set was compiled. Thus, there are ambiguities regarding the relationships within this genus, and the monophyly of <italic>Percocypris</italic> has not been convincingly demonstrated.</p>
<p>The potential impact of paleo-drainage basin morphologies on biogeographic patterns of the Tibetan Plateau and East Himalayas has been attracting increasing attention in recent studies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-He1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-He3">[18]</xref>). Although <italic>Percocypris</italic> is likely an ideal system for testing the biogeographical hypotheses, the evolutionary history and even the classification of this group were not well understood because of the difficulty of collecting relevant specimens. To the best of our knowledge, there have been few, if any, studies using a fish genus with the particular distribution pattern found in <italic>Percocypris</italic> to investigate biogeographic issues of the Southeastern Tibetan Plateau.</p>
<p>In this paper, a molecular phylogeny was reconstructed including all but one of the putative species of <italic>Percocypris</italic>, based on a combined dataset of three mitochondrial DNA genes and one nuclear gene. The divergence times and ancestral drainage of this group were also inferred using the Bayesian relaxed molecular clock and primary Brooks Parsimony Analysis (BPA) methods, respectively. The objective of this study was to clarify the relationships within <italic>Percocypris</italic> based on the results of multiple molecular phylogenetic methods and the analysis of morphological traits. Furthermore, we attempted to analyze the potential relationship between the evolutionary history of the genus and the change of paleo-drainages surrounding the Southeastern Tibetan Plateau. On the basis of the results of molecular and morphological analyses, we suggest that the species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> should be reassigned to six species, the distributions of which coincide with five river drainages and one lake basin (connective with one of the five river drainages). In addition, our results suggest that the genus originated during a time when the present-day drainages inhabited by <italic>Percocypris</italic> were connected to each other. We hypothesize that the changes in the large-scale morphologies of paleo-drainages basins of the Southeastern Tibetan Plateau played a significant role in the speciation of <italic>Percocypris</italic>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Ethics statement</title>
<p>All the animal samples were obtained in compliance with “Law of People's Republic of China on the Protection of Wildlife” and “Regulations for the Implementation of the People's Republic of China on the Protection of Aquatic Wildlife”. The samples were processed with the approval of the ethics committee of the Institutional Review Board of Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences. All specimens are stored in Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences (KIZ) and were used with the permission of KIZ.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Taxon sampling</title>
<p>Thirty eight individuals of <italic>Percocypris</italic> were measured in the morphometric study and forty three specimens of <italic>Percocypris</italic> were examined for the osteological features. Thirty four specimens of <italic>Percocypris</italic> were used in the molecular analysis, representing three subspecies of the nominal <italic>P. pingi</italic> from Fuxian Lake, Upper Pearl River, Upper Yangtze River, Mekong River and Salween River (the collection sites are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g001">Figure 1</xref>). The specimens were collected by electro-fishing and/or seining mainly from 2003 to 2011, and were subsequently deposited in KIZ. Although many localities including the type locality (the city of Laocai in Vietnam) of Red River basin were sampled numerous times at different seasons every year, we failed to acquire any specimens of <italic>P. tchangi</italic>. Following recent studies involving <italic>Percocypris</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Wang1">[10]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Li1">[12]</xref>, <italic>Schizothorax meridionalis</italic>, <italic>S. waltoni</italic>, <italic>Onychostoma simum</italic>, <italic>Spinibarbus denticulatus</italic>, <italic>Barbonymus schwanenfeldii</italic>, <italic>Sinocyclocheilus tingi</italic>, <italic>Cyprinus pellegrini</italic>, <italic>Carassius auratus</italic>, <italic>Tor douronensis</italic>, <italic>Labeo stoliczkae</italic> and <italic>Danio rerio</italic> were included as outgroup taxa. All of the ingroup members (except <italic>P. tchangi</italic>) and three outgroup taxa (<italic>Spinibarbus denticulatus</italic>, <italic>Cyprinus pellegrini</italic>, <italic>Labeo stoliczkae</italic>) were sequenced in this study, and the sequences deposited in GenBank (Listed in  <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s003">Table S1</xref> along with sequences of other outgroup taxa obtained from GenBank).</p>
<fig id="pone-0061827-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Distributions of <italic>Percocypris</italic> and molecular samples.</title>
<p>Red lines indicate major river basins; blue arrows denote general direction of water flow; green lines indicate boundaries. (Right map) Extant distributions of <italic>Percocypris</italic> based on literature records and localities of specimens: dots – Upper Yangtze River, five-pointed star – Fuxian Lake, diamonds – Upper Pearl River, triangles – Mekong River, squares – Salween River, cross – Red River; (Left map) Geographic distribution of molecular samples of <italic>Percocypris</italic> used in this study: orange dots – Upper Yangtze River, red five-pointed star – Fuxian Lake, purple diamond – Upper Pearl River, pink triangles – Mekong River, green square – Salween River.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Morphological analyses</title>
<p>In order to explore the morphological variation among the different species and the various habitat types of <italic>Percocypris</italic>, the morphological analyses included both external morphological measurements and aspects of the skeletal system.</p>
<p>For the external morphological analysis, 38 individuals of <italic>Percocypris</italic> were measured for 34 morphological variables. These were recorded to the nearest 0.1 mm using digital calipers following the methods of Chu &amp; Cui <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Chu2">[5]</xref> and Zhao &amp; Zhang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Zhao1">[19]</xref>. The 34 morphological measurements are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g002">Figure 2</xref>. Summary statistics for all the morphological characters were calculated with the statistical program SPSS 17.0 (SPSS for Windows, Chicago, IL, USA) for the Principal Component Analysis (PCA) after scaling according to standard length.</p>
<fig id="pone-0061827-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>External morphological measurements and internal skeletal traits.</title>
<p>(A) External morphological measurements used for morphometric analysis in this study: 1, standard length (SL); 2, head length (HL); 3, snout length (SNL); 4, eye diameter (ED); 5, prenaris length (IPNW); 6, eye-ball diameter (EBD); 7, caudal peduncle length (CPL); AD, predorsal length (PL); DE, dorsal-fin base length (DBL); DF, dorsal fin length (DFL); AW, prepectoral length (PPTL); WV, pectoral-fin base length (PTBL); WU, pectoral fin length (PTFL); AT, prepelvic length (PPVL); TS, pelvic-fin base length (PVBL); TR, pelvic fin length (PVFL); AQ, preanal length (PAL); QP, anal-fin base length (ABL); QO, anal fin length (AFL); HN, caudal peduncle depth (CPD); IK, upper lobe of caudal fin length (UICL); ML, lower lobe of caudal fin length (LLCL); CX, head depth (HD); BY, upper jaw length (UJL); AY, lower jaw length (LJL); the other measurements followed Chu &amp; Cui <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Chu2">[5]</xref> and Zhao &amp; Zhang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Zhao1">[19]</xref>: body depth(BD); caudal peduncle depth at the terminal of Anal fin base (CPDTA); middle caudal fin length (MCL); head width (HW); interorbital width (IOW); width between posterior naris (IPONW); mouth width (MW); maxilla barbel length (MBL); rictal barbel length (RBL). (B) Internal skeletal traits analyzed in this study: Ns, neural spine; Tv, trunk vertebrae; Cv, caudal vertebrae; Pt1, 1<sup>st</sup> dorsal pterygiophore; Pt2, 2<sup>nd</sup> dorsal pterygiophore.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>As a significant diagnostic morphological characteristic for species/subspecies of <italic>Percocypris</italic>, skeletal system images of 43 specimens of <italic>Percocypris</italic> were obtained and the osteological features (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g002">Figure 2</xref>) were observed and counted on a radiograph (X-ray film) taken by molybdenum target radiography.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Molecular methods</title>
<p>Fin tissue samples were frozen in 95% ethanol at −80°C until used. Total genomic DNA was extracted from the alcohol-preserved tissue with the proteinase K digestion and sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) extraction, high salt or phenol isolation and isopropanol precipitation procedure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Sambrook1">[20]</xref>. Three mitochondrial genes (16S, COI [cytochrome oxidase gene subunit I] and the complete Cyt <italic>b</italic> [cytochrome <italic>b</italic>],) and one nuclear protein-coding gene (Rag2) were amplified using polymerase chain reaction (PCR) with primer sequences given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s004">Table S2</xref>.</p>
<p>All the mitochondrial and nuclear DNA PCR-amplifications, performed in 50 μl volume (37 μl of double distilled water, 5 μl of 10× PCR reaction buffer, 3 μl of 2.5mM dNTPs, 2 μl of BSA [bovine serum albumin], 1 μ of a 10 μM solution of each primer, 2.0 U <italic>Taq</italic> DNA polymerase [Sangon Inc., Shanghai, China] and about 100 ng of DNA template), were carried out using the following procedures: an initial denaturing step of 5 min at 94°C, followed by 35 cycles with denaturing 30 s at 94°C, annealing 60 s at 55°C, 50°C, 50°C and 55°C (for 16S, COI, Cyt <italic>b</italic> and Rag2, respectively), extending 60 s at 72°C and a final extension step of 10 min conducted at 72°C. After electrophoresis through a 1.5% agarose gel, all amplified DNA fragments were purified using UNIQ-10 spin column DNA gel extraction kit (Sangon Inc., Shanghai, China) according to manufacturers' instructions. Using the corresponding primers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s004">Table S2</xref>), each fragment was sequenced in both directions with the BigDye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems) on an ABI 3730 automated sequencer.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Sequence alignment, data partitioning and model selection</title>
<p>Sequences of all genes were proofread and assembled with the DNA analysis package DNASTAR Lasergene Seqman and EditSeq version 7.1 (DNAStar Inc., Madison, WI). Alignment of protein-coding sequences (COI, Cyt <italic>b</italic> and Rag2) was conducted using Clustal X 1.83 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Thompson1">[21]</xref> with default settings, after which the DNA sequences were translated to amino acids residues with the software MEGA 5.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Tamura1">[22]</xref> to test for the absence of premature stop codons or indels, and subsequently checked by eye to maximize positional homology. For 16S ribosomal genes, the alignment was initially performed using the program MUSCLE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Edgar1">[23]</xref> with default parameters and also further revised by eye. All sequences obtained in this study were deposited in GenBank database (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s003">Table S1</xref> for accession numbers). For each fragment, after alignment, basic compositional information was estimated with the software MEGA 5.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Tamura1">[22]</xref>.</p>
<p>We partitioned the dataset into two, three, four, five, six, seven or ten partitions based on multiple partitioning strategies (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061827-t001">Table 1</xref> for partition identities). The best fitting evolutionary model of each partition in all data partitioning strategies using Bayesian information criteria (BIC; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Schwarz1">[24]</xref>) was determined with the software jModeltest version 2.1.2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Darriba1">[25]</xref> (selection of the 88 candidate substitution models) and Kakusan4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Tanabe1">[26]</xref> (selection of the 56 candidate substitution models). BIC was chosen to select a model because of its high accuracy and precision <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Luo1">[27]</xref> and its tendency to select simpler models than AIC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Abdo1">[28]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Ripplinger1">[30]</xref>. We also compared the nonpartitioned, proportional and separate models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Yang1">[31]</xref> on each partition using Treefinder <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Jobb1">[32]</xref> in Kakusan4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Tanabe1">[26]</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0061827-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>List of partitioning strategies used in the partitioned Bayesian analyses.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0061827-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partition strategy</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partition identity</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">By mitochondrial and nuclear gene</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16S+COI+Cyt <italic>b</italic>; Rag2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>3</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">By non-coding mitochondrial, protein-coding mitochondrial and nuclear gene</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16S; COI+Cyt <italic>b</italic>; Rag2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>4</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">By gene</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16S; COI; Cyt <italic>b</italic>; Rag2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>5</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Based on the proposed method of Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Li2">[98]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16S; COI_12+Cyt <italic>b</italic>-12; COI_3+Cyt <italic>b</italic>_3; Rag2_12; Rag2_3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>6</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Based on the analysis of our combined dataset using PartitionFinder <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Lanfear1">[99]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16S+Cyt <italic>b</italic>_1; COI_1; COI_2+Cyt <italic>b</italic>_2; COI_3+Cyt <italic>b</italic>_3; Rag2_12; Rag2_3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>7</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">By gene and separating codon positions 1 &amp; 2 and codon position 3 of protein-coding gene</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16S; COI_12; COI_3; Cyt <italic>b</italic>_12; Cyt <italic>b</italic>_3; Rag2_12; Rag2_3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>10</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">By gene and codon position of protein-coding gene</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16S; COI_1; COI_2; COI_3; Cyt <italic>b</italic>_1; Cyt <italic>b</italic>_2; Cyt <italic>b</italic>_3; Rag2_1; Rag2_2; Rag2_3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>The numerical subscripts next to the capital P mean the number of data partitions. The number after COI, Cyt <italic>b</italic> and Rag2 (1 2 3) mean the first, second and third codon position, respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Phylogenetic analyses</title>
<p>We performed phylogenetic analyses using maximum likelihood (ML) and Bayesian inference (BI) methods. Fourteen (seven [partitioning strategies] * two [selected substitution models]) partitioned BI analyses were performed using the settings below. Bayes Factor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Nylander1">[33]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Brown1">[35]</xref> was used to choose alternative partitioning strategies and model selections with jModeltest2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Darriba1">[25]</xref> and Kakusan4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Tanabe1">[26]</xref>. We calculated Bayes Factors by computing the marginal likelihood of log-transformed harmonic means for each BI run (estimated in MrBayes using the “sump” command) in Tracer v. 1.5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Rambaut1">[36]</xref>. The value of 2 ln Bayes factors ≥10 are considered to be very strong evidence supporting the alternative strategy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Kass1">[37]</xref>. The same partitioning scheme and evolutionary models chosen by Bayes Factors were used in both ML and BI analyses. Gaps in the 16S dataset were treated as missing data.</p>
<p>BI analyses were conducted using MrBayes v3.2.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Huelsenbeck1">[38]</xref>, with following settings: two Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) runs of four chains each for 3 million generations, a sampling frequency of 100, and a diagnosing frequency of 1,000. All parameters between partitions except topology and branch lengths were unlinked. The appropriate burn-in fraction and convergence of the MCMC chains were graphically assessed by evaluating the stationary phase of the chains using Tracer v. 1.5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Rambaut1">[36]</xref> and the web-based program AWTY <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Nylander2">[39]</xref>. The final consensus tree and Bayesian posterior probabilities (PP) were generated with the remaining tree samples after discarding the first 60% of samples as burn-in.</p>
<p>For the ML method, we conducted partitioned analyses with the software GARLI 2.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Zwickl1">[40]</xref> using the optimal model of evolution for the five partitions with the models and substitution rates unlinked between partitions. To estimate the best tree, five replicate searches were run with each replicate run for five million generations (stopgen  = “5000000”). 100 nonparametric bootstrap pseudoreplications were performed with the software GARLI and a strict consensus tree was generated from the resulting bootstrap trees with the software PAUP 4.0b 10 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Swofford1">[41]</xref>. The ML bootstrap probability values (BP) were calculated in PAUP.</p>
<p>The average genetic distances between the clades inferred by phylogenetic analyses were computed by Kimura's two-parameter method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Kimura1">[42]</xref> with the program MEGA 5.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Tamura1">[22]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Divergence time and ancestral drainage estimation</title>
<p>To estimate divergence time within <italic>Percocypris</italic>, the Bayesian relaxed clock method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Drummond1">[43]</xref> was used in the program BEAST v. 1.7.4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Drummond2">[44]</xref>. In order to use the reliable fossils of Cypriniformes, we included an additional 70 taxa for the molecular dating analyses (totally 127 samples; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s003">Table S1</xref>). <italic>Corydoras rabauti</italic> was used as outgroup. The 16S, COI and Cyt <italic>b</italic> genes were used for our divergence time estimation because these genes have been extensively used in studies of phylogeny in Cypriniformes and have been more widely sampled than the Rag2 gene. We partitioned the dataset into five partitions as we did in the phylogenetic analyses and chose the models selected by BIC for each partition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s005">Table S3</xref>) after Kakusan4 analyses. BEAUti v. 1.7.4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Drummond2">[44]</xref> was used to generate the input files for the analysis. Analysis was conducted with uncorrelated lognormal relaxed molecular clock model, with partition-specific substitution models, a Yule speciation process for the tree prior, random starting tree but constraining the ingroup to be monophyletic, the prior of mean substitution rate (ucld.mean) fixed to CTMC Rate Reference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Ferreira1">[45]</xref>, and with the most recent common ancestor (MRCA) of the four clades associated with fossil calibration points (see below) treated as lognormal distributions.</p>
<p>We chose the oldest and most unambiguous fossil records for constraints of the age of the root node, setting the latest date of the fossil record as minimum and a soft maximum with lognormal distribution: (1) <italic>Barbus bohemicus</italic> and <italic>Barbus sp</italic>. were reported from Czech Republic and dated as 18–19 million years ago (Mya) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Bhme1">[46]</xref>. Thus, the split between <italic>Barbus</italic> and its sister group (<italic>Luciobarbus</italic> and <italic>Capoeta</italic>; e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Tsigenopoulos1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Levin1">[48]</xref>) was at least 18 Mya and was constrained to a minimum of 18 Mya (log (mean)  =  “0.35” log (stdev)  =  “1.0” offset  = “18.0”). (2) Four fossils of <italic>Mylocheilus inflexus</italic> and five fossils of <italic>Mylocheilus robustus</italic> were recorded from Tortonian (10.5–11.5 Mya; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Bhme1">[46]</xref>) in U.S.A. Therefore, we assumed that the split between <italic>Mylocheilus</italic> and its sister group (<italic>Pogonichthys</italic>; see Schönhuth et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Schnhuth1">[49]</xref>) occurred at least 10.5 Mya (log (mean)  =  “0.5” log (stdev)  =  “1.0” offset  = “10.5”). (3) The oldest known <italic>Mylopharyngodon</italic> fossil (<italic>Mylopharyngodon wui</italic>), paleomagnetically dated to 12.5 Mya <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Chen1">[50]</xref>, is known from the middle Miocene of China. <italic>Ctenopharyngodon idella</italic> is the sister group of <italic>Mylopharyngodon piceusi</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Tao1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-He4">[52]</xref>, and we assumed that the MRCA of <italic>Mylopharyngodon</italic> and its sister group was at least 12.5 Mya (log (mean)  =  “0.5” log (stdev)  =  “1.0” offset  = “12.5”). (4) The oldest fossil similar to <italic>Myxocyprinus asiaticus</italic> (<italic>Plesiomyxocyprinus arratiae</italic>) was recorded from the early to middle Eocene in China (37.2–40.4 Mya; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Bhme1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Liu1">[53]</xref>). The split between <italic>Myxocyprinus</italic> and its sister group (<italic>Carpiodes</italic>, <italic>Ictiobus</italic>, <italic>Cycleptus</italic>, <italic>Catostomus, Minytrema, Moxostoma</italic> and <italic>Hypenteliums</italic>; e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Mayden1">[54]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Bart1">[56]</xref>) was set to be not later than 37.2 Mya (log (mean)  =  “1.1” log (stdev)  =  “1.0” offset  = “37.2”). In addition, a secondary calibration point was used on the root age of the tree. The root age was set using a normal distribution (mean  = “170.5” stdev  = “10.6”) based on the divergence time of Otophysi (the split between ingroup and outgroup [<italic>Corydoras rabauti</italic>]; 170.5 Mya; HPD [Highest Posterior Density] 153.1–187.9) estimated by Near et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Near1">[57]</xref>.</p>
<p>Two independent MCMC chains with a total of 50 million generations, sampled every 5000 generations were run using the corresponding substitution model for each partition. Convergence to the stationary distribution was assessed by inspection of log output files using Tracer and plots of tree files using AWTY. After discarding the burn-in of 25 million generations, the remaining tree samples of the four converged runs were combined using LogCombiner. The maximum clade credibility tree was calculated using TreeAnnotator and visualized with the software FigTree v.1.3.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Rambaut2">[58]</xref>.</p>
<p>We used BPA method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Brooks1">[59]</xref> to estimate the ancestral distribution area and investigate the evolutionary history of <italic>Percocypris</italic>. Based on the present-day drainage distributions of <italic>Percocypris</italic>, five units (Upper Yangtze River, A; Upper Pearl River, B; Fuxian Lake, C; Mekong River, D; and Salween River, E) were defined. The optimized phylogeny (derived from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g003">Figure 3</xref>) was converted into drainage cladogram. Data matrix to the primary BPA was prepared from the cladogram.</p>
<fig id="pone-0061827-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>The topology generated by the partitioned Bayesian analysis inferred from the combined data set.</title>
<p>The nodal numbers or symbol are Bayesian posterior probability and ML bootstrap values as node supports. The asterisk (*) indicates posterior probability ≧0.95 and ML bootstrap values ≧70%. JS, NP, LC, NJ and FX in the name of sample (e.g. m12_JS) stand for Jishan River, Nanpan River, Lancang River, Nujiang River and Fuxian Lake, respectively.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Variation in external morphological measurements and internal skeletal system</title>
<p>The results of the PCA of external morphological measurements are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061827-t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g004">Figure 4</xref>. The first three principal components explained a cumulative 75.627% of total observed variance with 56.743%, 12.328% and 6.556% explained by the first principal component (PC1), the second principal component (PC2) and the third principal component (PC3), respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061827-t002">Table 2</xref>). Furthermore, the length of fins, the distance between the snout and each fin, the length of barbels (maxilla barbel and rictal barbel), the width between posterior nares and the scale of the head (PL, DFL, PPTL, PTFL, PPVL, PVFL, AFL, MCL, UICL, LLCL, HD, HW, IPONW, MBL and RBL; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061827-t002">Table 2</xref>) contributed most to PC1. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g004">Figure 4</xref>, the PCA indicated five distinct clusters corresponding to species from four river basins (Upper Pearl, Upper Yangtze, Mekong and Salween rivers) and Fuxian Lake.</p>
<fig id="pone-0061827-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Scatter plot of the first principal component (PC1) vs. the second principal component (PC2).</title>
<p>The species from Fuxian Lake (red pentagons), Upper Pearl River (blue diamonds), Upper Yangtze River (orange dots), Mekong River (black triangles) and Salween River (green squares).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0061827-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Variance loadings on the first three principal components (PC1, PC2 and PC3) in the analysis of variation in external morphology for species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> among the main clades.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0061827-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characters</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC3</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.341</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.341</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.777</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPDTA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.212</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.373</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.662</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.833</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.268</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.275</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.786</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.332</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPTL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.785</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.239</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.299</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTBL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTFL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.873</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.325</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPVL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.768</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.515</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PVBL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.367</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.335</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PVFL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.909</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.249</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.473</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.758</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.253</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.594</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.071</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.108</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.884</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.191</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.554</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.557</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.842</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.159</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UICL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.825</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.142</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LLCL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.898</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.161</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.664</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.301</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HW</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.813</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.343</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.119</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.235</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.534</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.127</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.126</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IOW</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.743</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.306</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPNW</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.311</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.216</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPONW</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.764</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.118</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.269</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.289</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MW</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.626</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.048</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.309</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UJL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.742</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.196</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LJL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.673</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.236</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.841</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.236</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.885</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.287</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.043</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variance (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.743</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.328</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.556</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumulative (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.743</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.071</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.627</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><p>The boldface values represent the variances that have the high contribution to PC1.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>The number of neural spines before the first pterygiophore was found to differ among the clades of <italic>Percocypris</italic> after the examination on the X-ray film of skeletal system, as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s006">Table S4</xref> (in which the counts of meristic characters of forty five specimens are given as well). An additional two-tailed Pearson's bivariate correlation was performed to examine the relationship between the position of pterygiophore and the external position of dorsal fin using the software SPSS 17.0. A significant positive bivariate relationship (Pearson's correlation  = 0.806) was found.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Sequence characteristics, data partitioning and tree statistics</title>
<p>Including the sequences of eight outgroup species downloaded from the Genbank (24 mtDNA and 8 nuDNA sequences), a total of 1122 bp (base pairs) of 16S, 847 bp of COI, 1140 bp of Cyt <italic>b</italic> and 1236 bp of Rag2 (entirety 4345 bp) were resolved after alignment. For the three protein-coding genes (COI, Cyt <italic>b</italic> and Rag2), no premature stop codons or indels were observed after translation. In addition, no ambiguously aligned regions were found in 16S sequences.</p>
<p>The mean ln likelihood (ln <italic>L</italic>) and Bayes factor comparisons are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061827-t003">Table 3</xref>. The best partition_model strategy was the most partitioned scheme separated by gene and codon position, with the model selected by Kakusan4 (P<sub>10</sub>_K; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061827-t003">Table 3</xref>). For the BI and ML analyses, the best-fit substitution models for each partion selected by BIC in Kakusan4 are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s005">Table S3</xref>. The BI runs in MrBayes produced a posterior distribution with ln <italic>L</italic> = −17341.22. The ML analysis generated the most likely tree with ln <italic>L</italic> = −17237.64753.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0061827-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Comparisons of alternative partitioning strategies and model selections.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0061827-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partition_Model</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ln <italic>L</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>2</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>2</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>3</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>3</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>4</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>4</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>5</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>5</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>6</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>6</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>7</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>7</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>10</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>10</sub>_K</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>2</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18833.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−583.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−736.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−774.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2488.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2697.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2752.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2715.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2586.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2562.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2788.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2867.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>2</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18541.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">583.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">670.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−152.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">578.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−190.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1904.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2113.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2168.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2131.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2002.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1978.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2204.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2283.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>3</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18876.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−87.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−670.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−823.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−92.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−861.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2575.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2784.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2839.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2802.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2673.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2649.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2875.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2954.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>3</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18465.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">736.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">823.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">731.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−37.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1752.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1960.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2015.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1978.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1850.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1826.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2051.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2130.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>4</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18830.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−578.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−731.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−769.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2483.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2691.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2746.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2709.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2581.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2557.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2783.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2861.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>4</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18446.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">774.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">861.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">769.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1714.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1922.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1977.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1940.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1812.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1788.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2013.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2092.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>5</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17589.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2488.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1904.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2575.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1752.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2483.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1714.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−208.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−263.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−226.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−98.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−74.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−299.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−378.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>5</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17484.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2697.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2113.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2784.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1960.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2691.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1922.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−55.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−91.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−170.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>6</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17457.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2752.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2168.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2839.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2746.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1977.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−36.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−114.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>6</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17475.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2715.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2131.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2802.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1978.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2709.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1940.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−37.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−73.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−152.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>7</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17540.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2586.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2673.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1850.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2581.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1812.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−110.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−165.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−128.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−201.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−280.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>7</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17552.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2562.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1978.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2649.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1826.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2557.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1788.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−134.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−189.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−152.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−225.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−304.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>10</sub>_j</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17439.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2788.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2204.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2875.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2051.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2783.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">299.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−78.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>10</sub>_K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17399.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2867.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2283.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2954.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2130.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2861.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2092.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">378.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">304.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><p>ln <italic>L</italic> of each partition_model strategy and 2 ln Bayes factor results of comparisons between each partition_model strategy are given. The numerical subscripts next to the capital P mean the number of data partitions. The letter “j” and “K” mean the selected substitution model with jModeltest2 and Kakusan4, respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Phylogenetic relationships</title>
<p>Phylogenetic analyses employing BI and ML methods yielded identical topologies for the main clades and only minor differences at the terminals (shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g003">Figure 3</xref>). The monophyly of <italic>Percocypris</italic> was strongly supported in the results of all analyses. In addition, <italic>Schizothorax</italic> was recovered as the sister group of <italic>Percocypris</italic> in all our analyses. According to the topology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g003">Figure 3</xref>) generated in this study, four deeply divergent major clades were identified as follows:</p>
<p>Clade A contained individuals that occur in Upper Yangtze River and formed a monophyletic clade with strong support (PP  = 1.00, BP  = 100%). This clade was recovered as the sister group of Clade B (PP  = 1.00, BP  = 100%).</p>
<p>In Clade B, all the individuals of <italic>Percocypris regani</italic> collected from Fuxian Lake clustered together with strong support (1.00 nodal support of PP and 100% of BP, respectively). The sample identified as “m36_NP” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g003">Figure 3</xref>) collected from Upper Pearl River was recovered as the sister taxon of those from Fuxian Lake (PP  = 1.00, BP  = 100%).</p>
<p>All specimens collected from Mekong River constituted Clade C, which was a well supported monophyletic clade (PP  = 1.00, BP  = 100%).</p>
<p>Clade D included all individuals collected from Salween River and was well supported (PP  = 1.00, BP  = 100%). This clade was recovered as the sister group of clade C (PP  = 1.00, BP  = 100%).</p>
<p>In all cases, individuals from the same drainage clustered together with strong support. All of the analyses recovered the A + B clade as the sister group of the C + D clade with strong support, that is, the dichotomy between the two major clades was obvious in all the tree topologies.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Divergence time and ancestral drainage</title>
<p>The combined result of the two independent chains showed effective sample size (ESS) value of posterior &gt;200 (249.012) and ESS value of likelihood &gt;4000 (4216.872). Large degrees of overlap in HPD interval were found between estimates of divergence times (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s001">Figure S1</xref>). <italic>Percocypris</italic> split from its sister group (<italic>Schizothorax</italic>) about 17.56 Mya (HPD 12.76–23.18) in the early Miocene. A little later, the split between Clade A + B and Clade C + D took place nearly in the same period (13.73 Mya; HPD 9.03–18.53). Subsequently, divergences within Clade A + B and within Clade C + D occurred at 5.1 Mya (HPD 2.82–7.92; the late Miocene/Pliocene) and 5.93 Mya (HPD 2.91–9.62; the Late Miocene/Pliocene), respectively. The apparent speciation event between populations of <italic>Percocypris</italic> from Fuxian Lake and those from Upper Pearl River took place about 2.16 Mya (HPD 1.03–3.71).</p>
<p>The result of ancestral drainage estimation carried out with primary BPA analysis is given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s007">Table S5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s002">Figure S2</xref>. The area/species matrix for <italic>Percocypris</italic> is found in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s007">Table S5</xref> and the primary most parsimonious taxon/area cladogram in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s002">Figure S2</xref>. The MRCA of the extant species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> probably inhabited a single paleo-drainage involving all the present-day drainages in which it is found. This hypothetical ancestor evolved into two major clades which were distributed in the paleo-drainages of contemporary Upper Yangtze River + Upper Pearl River and Mekong River + Salween River (for the MRCA of Clade A + B and Clade C + D, respectively). Furthermore, vicariance is the most parsimonious distribution hypothesis for the historical evolution of <italic>Percocypris</italic> suggested by primary BPA analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s002">Figure S2</xref>); that is, the three MRCAs on the corresponding nodes probably evolved as a result of vicariant events (see the discussion section below).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This study represents the first phylogenetic hypothesis of the relationships of the species of <italic>Percocypris</italic>, including all taxa except for <italic>P. tchangi</italic> from Vietnam. The monophyly of the genus is strongly supported in this study; the placement of <italic>Percocypris</italic> as the sister group of <italic>Schizothorax</italic> is tested and supported, and the intrarelationships within <italic>Percocypris</italic> are assessed.</p>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Phylogenetic relationships and systematic implications for <italic>Percocypris</italic></title>
<p>In our phylogenetic topology, the nominal <italic>P. pingi</italic> and <italic>P. regani</italic> clustered together as sister taxa with strong support. The average genetic distance between these two clades was 0.055 in Cyt <italic>b</italic> dataset and 0.026 in the combined dataset; this distance is equivalent to that between some recognized species of <italic>Schizothorax</italic>. In addition, the plots of these two clades in the PCA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g004">Figure 4</xref>) resulted in non-overlapping, although adjacent, clusters. Considering the results of the average genetic distance and the PCA scatter plots, we support Kottelat's <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Kottelat1">[8]</xref> suggestion that these two clades be raised to the species-level.</p>
<p>The PCA analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g004">Figure 4</xref>) indicates that the specimens from Fuxian Lake and Upper Pearl River were clearly assignable to two distinct clusters. The divergence in topology and the distinct differences in morphological characters suggest that these two populations should be recognized as two distinct species (<italic>P. regani</italic> and a putative new species <italic>P.</italic> sp1), despite the fact that the genetic mean distance between these two clades is small (0.017 in Cyt <italic>b</italic> dataset and 0.008 in combined gene dataset).</p>
<p>For the nominal <italic>P. retrodorslis</italic> (Clades C and D), the samples are divided into two well-supported clades (i.e., Clade C from Mekong River and Clade D from Salween River). There is an average genetic distance of 0.063 in the Cyt <italic>b</italic> dataset and 0.029 in the combined gene dataset between these two clades, which is greater than the average genetic distances between some recognized species of <italic>Schizothorax</italic>. This suggests that the two clades should be treated as separate species. In addition, two distinct groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g004">Figure 4</xref>) were recognizable morphologically, which corresponded to the specimens from Mekong (Clade C) and Salween (Clade D) rivers. We found differences between these two clades in the skeletal system as follows: The insertion position of the first proximal pterygiophore of the dorsal fin is between the neural spines of the eighteenth and the nineteenth vertebral column in the individuals from Salween River, whereas for the individuals from Mekong River the position is between the neural spines of the seventeenth and eighteenth, or sixteenth and seventeenth vertebral column. Therefore, we conclude that there are two distinct species present, one in each river. We again follow Kottelat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Kottelat1">[8]</xref> in according <italic>P. retrodorslis</italic> specific status, and regard the Salween population as a putative new species (<italic>P</italic>. sp2).</p>
<p>In this study, we failed to obtain samples of <italic>P. tchangi</italic>, although we have sampled Red River in both Yunnan and Laocai (the type locality in Vietnam) on numerous occasions since 2003. In fact, there are no records of <italic>P. tchangi</italic> since the original description by Pellegrin and Chevey <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Pellegrin1">[9]</xref> in 1936. According to the description of the type specimen of <italic>P. tchangi</italic>, the position of dorsal fin is posteriorly situated, and a lateral stripe and scattered spots are present on the sides of the body. Further differences between <italic>P. tchangi</italic> and the other species of the genus are the number of lateral line scales and the body colour. The former is recorded as 60 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Pellegrin1">[9]</xref>, which is more than has been found in the other species (51–58). Furthermore, the upper body is brown and reddish, the lower body, upper head and the back are also reddish, and the fins are greyish and reddish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Pellegrin1">[9]</xref>. The coloration of other species of the genus differs from <italic>P. tchangi</italic> in having a dark (black to brown) back and a blackish head; fins are blackish or orangish, and the lower body is yellowish (in formalin-fixed specimens). However, the original description of the type specimen of <italic>P. tchangi</italic> is not detailed enough, and the morphometric data is not accurate enough, to allow us to confidently place this species. There is no definitive evidence indicating that <italic>P. retrodorslis</italic> is a junior synonym of <italic>P. tchangi</italic> as suggested by Kottelat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Kottelat1">[8]</xref>. We provisionally regard both <italic>P. retrodorslis</italic> and <italic>P. tchangi</italic> as valid species. To confirm the placement of <italic>P. tchangi</italic>, the sample of this species should be included in future research.</p>
<p>In conclusion, our results support the discovery of two putative new species that need to be formally described. Therefore, we suggest that <italic>Percocypris</italic>, which should be reclassified as we propose above, appears to be a monophyletic group of six species: (1) <italic>P. pingi</italic> from Upper Yangtze River; (2) <italic>P. regani</italic> from Fuxian Lake; (3) <italic>P.</italic> sp1 (putative new species) from Upper Pearl River; (4) <italic>P. retrodorslis</italic> from Mekong River; (5) <italic>P</italic>. sp2 (putative new species) from Salween River; and (6) <italic>P. tchangi</italic> from Red River.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>The origin and evolutionary scenario of <italic>Percocypris</italic></title>
<p>As shown below, <italic>Percocypris</italic> offers an excellent system for testing the hypotheses of the morphologies of the paleo-drainage basins of the Southeastern Tibetan Plateau, and the concomitant influences on the speciation of organisms living there.</p>
<p>The results of divergence time and ancestral drainage estimations indicate that <italic>Percocypris</italic> probably originated in the early Miocene (17.56 Mya; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g005">Figure 5</xref>) from a single paleo-drainage that included current Upper Yangtze, Mekong, Salween, Upper Pearl, and probably Red rivers; this supports the hypothesis that original Upper Yangtze, Middle Yangtze, Upper Mekong and Upper Salween rivers drained together as major tributaries of the paleo-Red River drainage system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Clark1">[60]</xref>. Regarding the origin of <italic>Percocypris</italic>, it is noteworthy that our results strongly suggest that it may originate from a common ancestor with <italic>Schizothorax</italic>. This result is compatible with the hypothesis that <italic>Percocypris</italic> originated from a common ancestor with certain species of the Barbinae (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Wu1">[4]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Shan1">[7]</xref>). The estimated divergence time of <italic>Percocypris</italic> and <italic>Schizothorax</italic> falls within the time range of the second uplift of the Tibetan Plateau (25–17 Mya; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Fang1">[61]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Shi1">[64]</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0061827-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>The origin and evolutionary scenario of <italic>Percocypris</italic>.</title>
<p>Map (A) shows the time tree mapped on to the geography of southeast Qinhai-Tibetan Plateau. The nodal numbers are divergence times; the node circles show the ancestral drainages. Map (B) from Rüber et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Rber1">[14]</xref> show the hypothesized paleo-Red River drainage system of Clark et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Clark1">[60]</xref>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Subsequently, the first diversification in <italic>Percocypris</italic> was the splitting into two main clades (“Clade A + Clade B” and “Clade C + Clade D”). We estimate this event to have occurred about 13.73 Mya (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g005">Figure 5</xref>), which is compatible with the earliest initiation age of rapid fluvial erosion in eastern Tibetan Plateau (13 Mya; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Clark2">[65]</xref>), presumably in response to the uplift of the Eastern Tibeten Plateau <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Clark2">[65]</xref>. The results of primary BPA analysis show that the common ancestor of <italic>P. retrodorslis</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. sp2 occurred in a paleo-drainage of current Mekong and Salween rivers, and this inference is compatible with the hypothesis that these two rivers were once connected, with Salween River as a tributary of Mekong River <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Clark1">[60]</xref>. Additionally, our estimated divergence time of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>retrodorslis</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. sp2 (5.93 Mya; “Clade C + D”) occurred during the Late Miocene/Early Pliocene. This timing supports the hypothesis that Salween River started to form since the Middle and Late Miocene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Zhao2">[66]</xref>. Furthermore, the hypothesis of an ancestral drainage of connecting contemporary Upper Yangtze and Upper Pearl rivers, where the common ancestor of <italic>P. pingi</italic>, <italic>P. regani</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. sp1 is hypothesized to have occurred, may imply that these two drainages were joined for some time. The separations of these species are consistent with the changes in river patterns <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Clark1">[60]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Ming1">[67]</xref>. According to the divergence time estimation of the node of <italic>P. regani</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. sp1, the split between these two species (2.16 Mya; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g005">Figure 5</xref>) seems to be in approximate agreement with the time of formation of Fuxian Lake during the Pliocene (3.0–3.4 Mya; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Nanjing1">[68]</xref>).</p>
<p>Thus, based on primary BPA analysis, the paleo-drainage of all current drainage basins split initially into two paleo-drainages (i.e., one containing Upper Yangtze River and Upper Pearl River; the other containing Mekong and Salween rivers). This could be considered as vicariant events (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s002">Figure S2</xref>). The primary BPA analysis suggests that two additional vicariant events in the speciation of <italic>Percocypris</italic> occurred after the split of the two paleo-drainages (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s002">Figure S2</xref>). These were the speciation of <italic>P. pingi</italic> and <italic>P. regani</italic>-<italic>P</italic>. sp1 by the isolation between Upper Yangtze River and Upper Pearl River, and the speciation of <italic>P. retrodorslis</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. sp2 by the separation of Mekong and Salween rivers. According to our estimated separation time, the first vicariant event most likely occurred during the initiation age of rapid river erosion and capture in eastern Tibetan Plateau, and the subsequent vicariant events of Mekong and Salween rivers appear compatible with the formation of Salween River. The fluvial erosion and river capture leading to isolation events in <italic>Percocypris</italic> presumably reacted to the uplift of the Southeastern Tibetan Plateau during the Miocene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Clark2">[65]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Zhao2">[66]</xref>.</p>
<p>Large paleo-drainages may have acted as barriers to terricolous animals (e.g. <italic>Nanorana yunnanensis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Zhang1">[69]</xref>; <italic>Apodemus ilex</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Liu2">[70]</xref>) and plants (e.g. <italic>Terminalia franchetii</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Zhang2">[71]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Zhang3">[72]</xref>), which invoked the paleo-Red River hypothesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Clark1">[60]</xref>. The paleo-Red River hypothesis was also tested by other fish biogeographic studies (e.g. Badidae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Rber1">[14]</xref>; Glyptosternoidae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Peng1">[15]</xref>; Sisoridae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Guo1">[16]</xref>; <italic>Schizothorax</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-He2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Yang2">[73]</xref>). However, the divergence time of <italic>Schizothorax</italic> of Upper Yangtze River and Mekong River + Salween River (6.8 Mya –6.2 Mya; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-He2">[17]</xref>) was much later than those in <italic>Percocypris</italic> (13.73 Mya; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g005">Figure 5</xref>). This may imply that Upper Yangtze River and Mekong River + Salween River were connected for some time by small-scale tributaries after the main river split. The discrepancy of the divergence times may be attributable to the different ecological niche between <italic>Schizothorax</italic> and <italic>Percocypris</italic>. <italic>Percocypris</italic> inhabit large bodies of water (large rivers or lakes); smaller bodies of water seem to act as barriers to the species of <italic>Percocypris</italic>. Therefore, <italic>Percocypris</italic> should be sensitive to the change of large-scale morphologies of paleo-drainages basins.</p>
<p>In summary, this study indicates that geological vicariance based on the changes in the large-scale morphologies of the paleo-drainage basins in the Southeastern Tibetan Plateau has played an important role in the speciation of <italic>Percocypris</italic>. The biogeographic relationships of <italic>Percocypris</italic> (as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g005">Figure 5</xref>) could test the paleo-Red River hypothesis more simply and clearly. With the specific distribution pattern of only one species in each drainage and specific ecological niche, <italic>Percocypris</italic> seem to be an ideal system for testing the hypotheses of the morphologies of the paleo-drainage basins of the Southeastern Tibetan Plateau. Clearly, similar biogeographic results for additional taxa and detailed paleogeographic evidences are needed to fully understand the influence of the paleo-drainage basin morphologies surrounding the Southeastern Tibetan Plateau on the speciation of the organisms inhabiting this area.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Trait divergence in <italic>Percocypris</italic> from lake and river</title>
<p>Two main habitat types are found among the species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> in this study: (1) the lake type of <italic>P. regani</italic> in Fuxian Lake; (2) the river type of <italic>P</italic>. sp1, <italic>P. pingi P. retrodorslis</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. sp2 inhabiting Upper Pearl, Upper Yangtze, Mekong and Salween rivers. As the result of the PCA indicates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061827-g004">Figure 4</xref>), the individuals from the lake habitat (Fuxian Lake) formed a separate cluster from those from the riverine habitats (Upper Pearl, Upper Yangtze, Mekong and Salween rivers). The differences were reflected in the length of the fins, the distance between the origin of each fin base and the snout, the proportions of the head (head depth and head width) and the length of barbels (maxillary and rictal barbels).</p>
<p>Morphological divergence associated with lentic and lotic habitat was observed in many kinds of fishes. Different species reflect different aspects of traits divergence. In the well-investigated threespine stickleback (<italic>Gasterosteus aculeatus</italic>) it was found that the lake ecotypes displayed more developed gill structures (more numerous gill rakers) and more streamlined bodies (deeper bodies, shorter pelvic, dorsal spines, deeper caudal peduncles) than the stream counterparts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Aguirre1">[74]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Sharpe1">[83]</xref>. Two Neotropical fish (<italic>Bryconops caudomaculatus</italic>; <italic>Biotodoma wavrini</italic>) showed morphological divergence in of maximum body depth and mouth orientation between lotic channels and lentic lagoons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Langerhans1">[84]</xref>. <italic>Cyprinella venusta</italic> in rivers and reservoirs exhibited differences in the proportions of the head, the position of eye, the position of dorsal fin and the length of dorsal fin base <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Haas1">[85]</xref>. In the study of the rainbow fishes (<italic>Melanotaenia eachamensis</italic> and <italic>M. duboulayi</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-McGuigan1">[86]</xref>, trait divergence between lake and stream habitats was found in the position first dorsal and pelvic fins, the length of second dorsal fin bases. The lentic–lotic divergences in morphological traits have been observed in many other fish (e.g. <italic>Cyprinella lutrensis</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Franssen1">[87]</xref>; <italic>Phoxinus phoxinus</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Collin1">[88]</xref>; <italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Taylor1">[89]</xref>; <italic>Oncorhynchus nerka</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Pavey1">[90]</xref>; <italic>Osteochilus hasseltii</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Roesma1">[91]</xref>).</p>
<p>In this study, <italic>P. regani</italic> inhabiting lakes have more anterior fins and smaller heads than the other species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> inhabiting rivers. The divergence of the position of the dorsal fin could also be observed in the number of neural spines before the pterygiophore (see the result of bivariate correlation analysis). These findings are congruent with the morphological differences between reservoirs and rivers observed in the two species of <italic>Cyprinella</italic> (<italic>C. venusta</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Haas1">[85]</xref>; <italic>C. lutrensis</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Franssen1">[87]</xref>). Cui &amp; Chu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Cui1">[6]</xref> suggested that the posterior placement of the dorsal fin may be an adaptive trait related to the predatory nature of the species of this genus. In addition, we found that the positions of the fins (except the caudal fin) may also be related to the habitat type; that is, the position of each fin is more posteriorly situated in the species from the rivers than those from the lake. Strikingly, compared with the rainbow fishes <italic>Melanotaenia eachamensis</italic> and <italic>M. duboulayi</italic> (McGuigan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-McGuigan1">[86]</xref>), the dorsal fin position of <italic>Percocypris</italic> appears to diverge in the opposite direction relative to lentic and lotic habitat. The rainbow fishes in the lake had a more posteriorly positioned first dorsal fin than those in the streams <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-McGuigan1">[86]</xref>. McGuigan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-McGuigan1">[86]</xref> hypothesized that the posterior shift in the first dorsal fin of the rainbow fish was driven by selection with the change of different water velocity habitat, but they could not provide firm evidence that selection drove the evolution of the relative fin positions in their system. The effect of water velocity on the position of pterygiophore/dorsal fin and associated traits might be highly variable in different systems. Further and deeper ecological and kinematic studies may help to elucidate the correlation between the water velocity and the position of pterygiophore/dorsal fin. Cui &amp; Chu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Cui1">[6]</xref> hypothesized that the narrow head enabled broader vision in <italic>P. regani</italic>, which provided an advantage while hunting in the clearer waters of Fuxian Lake. In the stickleback, changes in head size and eye position may be related to the shifts in prey type <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Hendry3">[92]</xref>. The head of <italic>Percocypris</italic> inhabiting the rivers with turbid water was wider than those in the lake, and this may indicate that vision is less important in prey acquisition in this environment. The maxillary and rictal barbels of <italic>Percocypris</italic> in rivers are longer than those in the lake, and this may also be correlated with more limited vision in the turbid waters of the rivers. In addition, for the differences in the lengths of fins between lacustrine and riverine species, we support the hypothesis that riverine fishes have longer pectoral, anal and dorsal fins for the stability and manoeuvrability in the water flow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Beacham1">[93]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Swain1">[94]</xref>. Drinan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Drinan1">[95]</xref> found that <italic>Salmo trutta</italic> from high-gradient (rapid water flow) rivers have longer pectoral fins than those from low-gradient rivers to increase stability and manoeuvrability.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Conservation implications for genus <italic>Percocypris</italic></title>
<p>The IUCN Red List for China lists <italic>P. pingi</italic> (using Cui &amp; Chu's <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Cui1">[6]</xref> arrangement of three subspecies) as “Vulnerable” (VU). However, according to the results of our phylogenetic analyses, <italic>Percocypris</italic> should be reclassified as six species. Our suggestion of this reclassification may be helpful in developing conservation strategies for the species of this genus, based on the views of Amato &amp; Schaller <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Amato1">[96]</xref> and Vogler &amp; DeSalle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061827-Vogler1">[97]</xref> that phylogenetic information can provide data useful for prioritizing conservation strategies. Within this new classificatory framework, the conservation status of each of the six species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> requires reassessment. Therefore, conservation efforts should be directed to the six species and their relevant habitats.</p>
<p>The fishes of Upper Yangtze, Upper Pearl, Mekong, Salween and Red rivers have been extensively sampled since 1977; our field records covering several decades and the information provided by local people show that populations of all of the species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> have decreased in recent years.</p>
<p><italic>Percocypris pingi</italic> in Upper Yangtze River, <italic>P. regani</italic> in Fuxian Lake, <italic>P. retrodorslis</italic> in Mekong River and <italic>P</italic>. sp2 in Salween River were difficult to find, especially in recent years, as our field records and the information from the local people demonstrate. Even worse, the number of <italic>P</italic>. sp1 in Upper Pearl River is very low probably due to pollution produced by heavy-metal enterprises along the river. Noticeably, <italic>P. tchangi</italic> in Red River has not been found since the species was described in 1936, a period of 77 years. Unfortunately, the species of this genus are threatened due to habitat destruction by water pollution as well as other factors such as overfishing and illegal fishing. As predators of other fishes, the species of <italic>Percocypris</italic> are keystone species in the relevant drainages, which have a significant impact on the maintenance of the ecological community structure. As a group of highly endemic species, immediate specific conservation strategies and additional studies on conservation for this genus are urgently needed.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0061827.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>The results of divergence time using the Bayesian relaxed clock method (A). Chronogram of </bold><bold><italic>Percocypris</italic></bold><bold> (B).</bold></p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0061827.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Primary BPA taxa/area cladogram of </bold><bold><italic>Percocypris</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> A – Upper Yangtze River, B – Upper Pearl River, C – Fuxian Lake, D – Mekong River, E – Salween River. The numbers “1–9” refer to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0061827.s007">Table S5</xref>.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0061827.s003" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Samples of species, with voucher number, locality and drainage information for the specimens sampled, including the GenBank accession numbers.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0061827.s004" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>PCR primers (names, sequences and references) to amplify three mitochondrial and one nuclear DNA genes.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0061827.s005" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Summary of partitioned substitution models (BIC) for the phylogenetic analyses and divergence time estimation.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0061827.s006" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>The statistics of the counts of meristic characters and osteological traits.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0061827.s007" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061827.s007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S5</label><caption>
<p><bold>Primary BPA matrix listing the distribution of </bold><bold><italic>Percocypris</italic></bold><bold>, along with the binary codes representing the phylogenetic relationships among the genus.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We appreciate very much the helpful and insightful comments and suggestions of two anonymous reviewers for this manuscript. We are thankful to Dr. Rick Winterbottom for his insightful and professional suggestions and improvements on this manuscript. We thank Kai He, Wan-Sheng Jiang, Feng Dong and Rui Min for the useful comments on the draft of this manuscript. We appreciate the assistance of Zai-Yun Li, Gui-Hua Cui, Xiao-Fu Pan, David Catania, William Polly and Wei-Ying Wang in samples accumulation collection in the field, and thank Li Jia for the help with laboratory work.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Chu1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name> (<year>1935</year>) <article-title>Comparative studies on the scales and on the pharyngeals and their teeth in Chinese cyprinids, with particular reference to taxonomy and evolution. Biological Bulletin, St</article-title>. <source>John's University</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Tchang1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tchang</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name> (<year>1930</year>) <article-title>Description de Cyprinidés nouveaux de Se-Tchuan</article-title>. <source>Bulletin du Muséum National d'Histoire Naturelle (Série 2)</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Tchang2"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tchang</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name> (<year>1935</year>) <article-title>Two new species of <italic>Barbus</italic> from Yunnan</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of the Fan Memorial Institute of Biology, Peiping (Zoological Series)</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Wu1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wu XW, Lin RD, Chen JX, Chen XL, He MJ (1977) Zhongguo like yulei zhi. [The cyprinid fishes of China]; Wu XW, et al., editors. Shanghai: People's Press. 265–268 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Chu2"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chu XL, Cui GH (1989) The fishes of Yunnan, Part 1 Cyprinidae; Chu XL, Chen YR, et al., editors. Beijing: Science Press. 177–180 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Cui1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Differentiation and distribution of the cyprinid fish <italic>Percocypris pingi</italic> (Tchang)</article-title>. <source>Dong Wu Fen Lei Xue Bao</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Shan1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Shan XH, Lin RD, Yue PQ, Chu XL (2000) Fauna Sinica. Osteichthyes. Cypriniformes III; Yue PQ, Shan XH, Lin RD, Chu XL, Zhang E, et al., editors. Beijing: Science Press. 47–51 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Kottelat1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kottelat M (2001) Freshwater Fishes of Northern Vietnam: A Preliminary Check-list of the Fishes Known Or Expected to Occur in Northern Vietnam: with Comments on Systematics and Nomenclature. Washington, DC: The World Bank, Environment and Social Development Unit, East Asia and Pacific Region. 35 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Pellegrin1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pellegrin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chevey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1936</year>) <article-title>Poissons nouveaux ou rares du Tonkin et de l'Annam</article-title>. <source>Bulletin de la Société Zoologique de France</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>379</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Wang1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular evidence for the monophyly of East Asian groups of Cyprinidae (Teleostei: Cypriniformes) derived from the nuclear recombination activating gene 2 sequences</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Kong1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships of Cyprinidae (Teleostei: Cypriniformes) inferred from the partial <italic>S6K1</italic> gene sequences and implication of indel sites in intron 1</article-title>. <source>Sci China C Life Sci</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>780</fpage>–<lpage>788</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Li1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Variation patterns of the mitochondrial 16S rRNA gene with secondary structure constraints and their application to phylogeny of cyprinine fishes (Teleostei: Cypriniformes)</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>472</fpage>–<lpage>487</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-He1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogeny of the specialized schizothoracine fishes (Teleostei: Cyprinidae), with their implications for the uplift of the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau</article-title>. <source>Chin Sci Bull</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Rber1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rüber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Britz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kullander</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zardoya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Evolutionary and biogeographic patterns of the Badidae (Teleostei: Perciformes) inferred from mitochondrial and nuclear DNA sequence data</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1010</fpage>–<lpage>1022</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Peng1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Uplift of the Tibetan plateau: Evidence from divergence times of glyptosternoid catfishes</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Guo1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny and biogeography of Chinese sisorid catfishes re-examined using mitochondrial cytochrome <italic>b</italic> and 16S rRNA gene sequences</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-He2"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Biogeography and molecular phylogeny of the genus <italic>Schizothorax</italic> (Teleostei: Cyprinidae) in China inferred from cytochrome <italic>b</italic> sequences</article-title>. <source>J Biogeogr</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>1448</fpage>–<lpage>1460</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-He3"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogeny and biogeography of the highly specialized grade schizothoracine fishes (Teleostei: Cyprinidae) inferred from cytochrome <italic>b</italic> sequences</article-title>. <source>Chin Sci Bull</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>788</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Zhao1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zhao Y, Zhang C (2009) Endemic Fishes of <italic>Sinocyclocheilus</italic> (Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae) in China. Beijing: Science Press. 255–257 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Sambrook1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sambrook J, Fritsch EF, Maniatis T (1989) Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual. Cold Spring Harbor, NY: Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Thompson1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plewniak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeanmougin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The CLUSTAL_X windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple equence alignment aided by quality analysis tools</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>4876</fpage>–<lpage>4882</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Tamura1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MEGA5: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis using Maximum Likelihood, Evolutionary Distance, and Maximum Parsimony Methods</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2731</fpage>–<lpage>2739</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Edgar1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1792</fpage>–<lpage>1797</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Schwarz1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>Estimating the Dimension of a Model</article-title>. <source>Ann Stat</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Darriba1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darriba</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taboada</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doallo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>jModelTest 2: more models, new heuristics and parallel computing</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>772</fpage>–<lpage>772</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Tanabe1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Kakusan4 and Aminosan: two programs for comparing nonpartitioned, proportional and separate models for combined molecular phylogenetic analyses of multilocus sequence data</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>914</fpage>–<lpage>921</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Luo1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Performance of criteria for selecting evolutionary models in phylogenetics: a comprehensive study based on simulated datasets</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>242</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Abdo1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minin</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Accounting for Uncertainty in the Tree Topology Has Little Effect on the Decision-Theoretic Approach to Model Selection in Phylogeny Estimation</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>703</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Posada1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crandall</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Selecting the Best-Fit Model of Nucleotide Substitution</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>580</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Ripplinger1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripplinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Does Choice in Model Selection Affect Maximum Likelihood Analysis?</article-title> <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Yang1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Maximum-likelihood models for combined analyses of multiple sequence data</article-title>. <source>J Mol Evol</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>596</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Jobb1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jobb</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strimmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>TREEFINDER: a powerful graphical analysis environment for molecular phylogenetics</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Nylander1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nylander</surname><given-names>JAA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieves-Aldrey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Bayesian Phylogenetic Analysis of Combined Data</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Brandley1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandley</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reeder</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Partitioned Bayesian Analyses, Partition Choice, and the Phylogenetic Relationships of Scincid Lizards</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Brown1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemmon</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The Importance of Data Partitioning and the Utility of Bayes Factors in Bayesian Phylogenetics</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>643</fpage>–<lpage>655</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Rambaut1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rambaut A, Drummond AJ (2007) Tracer v1.5. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer" xlink:type="simple">http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 July 23.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Kass1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kass</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raftery</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Bayes Factors</article-title>. <source>J Am Stat Assoc</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>773</fpage>–<lpage>795</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Huelsenbeck1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Mrbayes: bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>754</fpage>–<lpage>755</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Nylander2"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nylander</surname><given-names>JAA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilgenbusch</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swofford</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>AWTY (are we there yet?): a system for graphical exploration of MCMC convergence in Bayesian phylogenetics</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Zwickl1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zwickl DJ (2006) Genetic algorithm approaches for the phylogenetic analysis of large biological sequence datasets under the maximum likelihood criterion. Ph.D. dissertation, The University of Texas at Austin.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Swofford1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Swofford DL (2002) Paup*. Phylogenetic analysis using parsimony (* and other methods), version. 4.0b10. Sinauer Associates, Sunderland, MA.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Kimura1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>A simple method for estimating evolutionary rates of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences</article-title>. <source>J Mol Evol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Drummond1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Relaxed Phylogenetics and Dating with Confidence</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e88</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Drummond2"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Bayesian phylogenetics with BEAUti and the BEAST 1.7</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1969</fpage>–<lpage>1973</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Ferreira1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>MAR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bayesian analysis of elapsed times in continuous-time Markov chains</article-title>. <source>Can J Stat</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>368</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Bhme1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Böhme M, Ilg A (2003) fosFARbase. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wahre-staerke.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.wahre-staerke.com</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 August 8.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Tsigenopoulos1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsigenopoulos</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ünlü</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berrebi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Rapid radiation of the Mediterranean <italic>Luciobarbus</italic> species (Cyprinidae) after the Messinian salinity crisis of the Mediterranean Sea, inferred from mitochondrial phylogenetic analysis</article-title>. <source>Biol J Linn Soc Lond</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Levin1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freyhof</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lajbner</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perea</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships of the algae scraping cyprinid genus <italic>Capoeta</italic> (Teleostei: Cyprinidae)</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>542</fpage>–<lpage>549</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Schnhuth1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schönhuth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shiozawa</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dowling</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayden</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Molecular systematics of western North American cyprinids (Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae)</article-title>. <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>3586</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Chen1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arratia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Oldest known <italic>Mylopharyngodon</italic> (Teleostei: Cyprinidae) from the Mongolian Plateau and its biogeographical implications based on ecological niche modeling</article-title>. <source>J Vert Paleontol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Tao1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayden</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Remarkable phylogenetic resolution of the most complex clade of Cyprinidae (Teleostei: Cypriniformes): A proof of concept of homology assessment and partitioning sequence data integrated with mixed model Bayesian analyses</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>603</fpage>–<lpage>616</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-He4"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayden</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogenetics of the family Cyprinidae (Actinopterygii: Cypriniformes) as evidenced by sequence variation in the first intron of S7 ribosomal protein-coding gene: Further evidence from a nuclear gene of the systematic chaos in the family</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>818</fpage>–<lpage>829</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Liu1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A new Eocene catostomid (Teleostei: Cypriniformes) from northeastern China and early divergence of Catostomidae</article-title>. <source>Sci China Ser D Earth Sci</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Mayden1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayden</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bart</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doosey</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Reconstructing the phylogenetic relationships of the earth's most diverse clade of freshwater fishes – order Cypriniformes (Actinopterygii: Ostariophysi): A case study using multiple nuclear loci and the mitochondrial genome</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Harris1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayden</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetic Relationships of Major Clades of Catostomidae (Teleostei: Cypriniformes) as Inferred from Mitochondrial SSU and LSU rDNA Sequences</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Bart1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bart</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reneau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doosey</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Evolutionary Divergence of Duplicate Copies of the Growth Hormone Gene in Suckers (Actinopterygii: Catostomidae)</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1090</fpage>–<lpage>1102</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Near1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Near</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eytan</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dornburg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Resolution of ray-finned fish phylogeny and timing of diversification</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>13698</fpage>–<lpage>13703</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Rambaut2"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rambaut A (2009) Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/" xlink:type="simple">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/</ext-link>.Accessed 2012 July 23.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Brooks1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Historical ecology: a new approach to studying the evolution of ecological associations</article-title>. <source>Ann Mo Bot Gard</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>660</fpage>–<lpage>680</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Clark1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenbohm</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Royden</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whipple</surname><given-names>KX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burchfiel</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Surface uplift, tectonics, and erosion of eastern Tibet from large-scale drainage patterns</article-title>. <source>Tectonics</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>TC1006</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Fang1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lü</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Loess in Kunlun Mountains and its implications on desert development and Tibetan Plateau uplift in west China</article-title>. <source>Sci China Ser D Earth Sci</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Ge1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Uplift dynamics of Qinghai–Tibet Plateau and Altun fault</article-title>. <source>Geol China</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>346</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Sun1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sun HL (1996) Science monographic series: formation and evolution of Qinghai-Xizang Plateau. Shanghai Science and Technology Press, Shanghai. 104–106 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Shi1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Uplift of the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau and East Asia environmental change during late Cenozoic</article-title>. <source>Acta Geographical Sinica</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Clark2"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>House</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Royden</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whipple</surname><given-names>KX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burchfiel</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Late Cenozoic uplift of southeastern Tibet</article-title>. <source>Geology</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>525</fpage>–<lpage>528</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Zhao2"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Discovery of Neogene Gravels and Dammed – Lake Sediments in Nujiang (Salween) River Valleys, Yunnan Province, China, and Their Implications</article-title>. <source>Acta Geol Sin</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>1963</fpage>–<lpage>1976</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Ming1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The tentative inquiry on the formation time in the region of three parallel rivers, Yunnan</article-title>. <source>Yunnan Geographic Environment Research</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Nanjing1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Nanjing Institute of Geography and Limnology CAS, Lanzhou Institute of Geology CAS, Institute of Geochemistry CAS, Paleontology NIoGa (1989) Enviroments and Sedimentation of Fault Lakes, Yunnan Province. Science Press. xiii p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Zhang1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Che</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genealogy and palaeodrainage basins in Yunnan Province: phylogeography of the Yunnan spiny frog, <italic>Nanorana yunnanensis</italic> (Dicroglossidae)</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>3406</fpage>–<lpage>3420</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Liu2"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kilpatrick</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Phylogeographic Study of <italic>Apodemus ilex</italic> (Rodentia: Muridae) in Southwest China</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e31453</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Zhang2"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Phylogeographic structure of <italic>Terminalia franchetii</italic> (Combretaceae) in southwest China and its implications for drainage geological history</article-title>. <source>J Plant Res</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Zhang3"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Comes</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Chloroplast phylogeography of <italic>Terminalia franchetii</italic> (Combretaceae) from the eastern Sino-Himalayan region and its correlation with historical river capture events</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Yang2"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A re-examination of the molecular phylogeny and biogeography of the genus <italic>Schizothorax</italic> (Teleostei: Cyprinidae) through enhanced sampling, with emphasis on the species in the Yunnan–Guizhou Plateau, China</article-title>. <source>J Zoolog Syst Evol Res</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Aguirre1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Microgeographical diversification of threespine stickleback: body shape–habitat correlations in a small, ecologically diverse Alaskan drainage</article-title>. <source>Biol J Linn Soc Lond</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Berner1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grandchamp</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendry</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Natural selection drives patterns of lake–stream divergence in stickleback foraging morphology</article-title>. <source>J Evol Biol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1653</fpage>–<lpage>1665</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Berner2"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grandchamp</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendry</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Variable progress toward ecological speciation in parapatry: stickleback across eight lake-stream transitions</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>1740</fpage>–<lpage>1753</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Berner3"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaeuffer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grandchamp</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raeymaekers</surname><given-names>JAM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Räsänen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Quantitative genetic inheritance of morphological divergence in a lake–stream stickleback ecotype pair: implications for reproductive isolation</article-title>. <source>J Evol Biol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1975</fpage>–<lpage>1983</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Hendry1"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendry</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Räsänen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genetic divergence in morphology–performance mapping between Misty Lake and inlet stickleback</article-title>. <source>J Evol Biol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Hendry2"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendry</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>How much of the variation in adaptive divergence can be explained by gene flow? An evaluation using lake-stream stickleback pairs</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>2319</fpage>–<lpage>2331</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Kaeuffer1"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaeuffer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peichel</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bolnick</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendry</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Parallel and nonparallel aspects of ecological, phenotypic, and genetic divergence across replicate population pairs of lake and stream stickleback</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Lavin1"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavin</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McPhail</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Parapatric lake and stream sticklebacks on northern Vancouver Island: disjunct distribution or parallel evolution?</article-title> <source>Can J Zool</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Reimchen1"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reimchen</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stinson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Multivariate differentiation of parapatric and allopatric populations of threespine stickleback in the Sangan River watershed, Queen Charlotte Islands</article-title>. <source>Can J Zool</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>2944</fpage>–<lpage>2951</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Sharpe1"><label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharpe</surname><given-names>DMT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Räsänen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendry</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Genetic and environmental contributions to the morphology of lake and stream stickleback: implications for gene flow and reproductive isolation</article-title>. <source>Evol Ecol Res</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>849</fpage>–<lpage>866</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Langerhans1"><label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langerhans</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Layman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langerhans</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dewitt</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Habitat-associated morphological divergence in two Neotropical fish species</article-title>. <source>Biol J Linn Soc Lond</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>689</fpage>–<lpage>698</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Haas1"><label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heins</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Morphological responses of a stream fish to water impoundment</article-title>. <source>Biol Lett</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>803</fpage>–<lpage>806</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-McGuigan1"><label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGuigan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blows</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Adaptation of rainbow fish to lake and stream habitats</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Franssen1"><label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franssen</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Anthropogenic habitat alteration induces rapid morphological divergence in a native stream fish</article-title>. <source>Evol Appl</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>791</fpage>–<lpage>804</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Collin1"><label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fumagalli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evidence for morphological and adaptive genetic divergence between lake and stream habitats in European minnows (<italic>Phoxinus phoxinus</italic>, Cyprinidae)</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>4490</fpage>–<lpage>4502</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Taylor1"><label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamkee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keeley</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Conservation prioritization in widespread species: the use of genetic and morphological data to assess population distinctiveness in rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) from British Columbia, Canada</article-title>. <source>Evol Appl</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Pavey1"><label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavey</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>MacKas</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamon</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breden</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Contrasting Ecology Shapes Juvenile Lake-Type and Riverine Sockeye Salmon</article-title>. <source>Trans Am Fish Soc</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1584</fpage>–<lpage>1594</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Roesma1"><label>91</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roesma</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santoso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Morphological divergences among three sympatric populations of Silver Sharkminnow (Cyprinidae: <italic>Osteochilus hasseltii</italic> C.V.) in West Sumatra</article-title>. <source>Biodiversitas</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Hendry3"><label>92</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendry</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McPhail</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Adaptive divergence and the balance between selection and gene flow: Lake and stream stickleback in the Misty System</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1199</fpage>–<lpage>1216</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Beacham1"><label>93</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beacham</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Withler</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Age, Morphology, and Biochemical Genetic Variation of Yukon River Chinook Salmon</article-title>. <source>Trans Am Fish Soc</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Swain1"><label>94</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holtby</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Differences in Morphology and Behavior between Juvenile Coho Salmon (<italic>Oncorhynchus kisutch</italic>) Rearing in a Lake and in its Tributary Stream</article-title>. <source>Can J Fish Aquat Sci</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1406</fpage>–<lpage>1414</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Drinan1"><label>95</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drinan</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGinnity</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coughlan</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>SSC</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Morphological variability of Atlantic salmon <italic>Salmo salar</italic> and brown trout <italic>Salmo trutta</italic> in different river environments</article-title>. <source>Ecol Freshw Fish</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>420</fpage>–<lpage>432</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Amato1"><label>96</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Amato G, Schaller GB (1998) Phylogeny of the Tibetan steppe bovids: morphological and molecular comparisons; Schaller GB, editor. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. 245–249 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Vogler1"><label>97</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desalle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Diagnosing units of conservation management</article-title>. <source>Conserv Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Li2"><label>98</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ortí</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Optimal Data Partitioning and a Test Case for Ray-Finned Fishes (Actinopterygii) Based on Ten Nuclear Loci</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>539</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0061827-Lanfear1"><label>99</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanfear</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calcott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>PartitionFinder: Combined Selection of Partitioning Schemes and Substitution Models for Phylogenetic Analyses</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1695</fpage>–<lpage>1701</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>