<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-31262</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053957</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Microbial ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Microbiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Bacterial pathogens</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Escherichia coli</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Bacteriology</subject>
              <subject>Microbial ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Model organisms</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal models</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Mouse</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Infectious diseases</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Bacterial diseases</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Escherichia coli</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Nutrition</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Infectious Diseases</subject>
          <subject>Microbiology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Nutritional Basis for Colonization Resistance by Human Commensal <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> Strains HS and Nissle 1917 against <italic>E. coli</italic> O157:H7 in the Mouse Intestine</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Colonization Resistance to <italic>E. coli</italic> O157:H7</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Maltby</surname>
            <given-names>Rosalie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Leatham-Jensen</surname>
            <given-names>Mary P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gibson</surname>
            <given-names>Terri</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cohen</surname>
            <given-names>Paul S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Conway</surname>
            <given-names>Tyrrell</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Microbiology and Plant Biology, University of Oklahoma, Norman, Oklahoma, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Cell and Molecular Biology, University of Rhode Island, Kingston, Rhode Island, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ibekwe</surname>
            <given-names>A. Mark</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>U. S. Salinity Lab, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">tconway@ou.edu</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RM MPL PSC TC. Performed the experiments: RM MPL TG. Analyzed the data: RM MPL PSC TC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RM MPL TG PSC TC. Wrote the paper: RM PSC TC.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>e53957</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>9</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Maltby et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> is a single species consisting of many biotypes, some of which are commensal colonizers of mammals and others that cause disease. Humans are colonized on average with five commensal biotypes, and it is widely thought that the commensals serve as a barrier to infection by pathogens. Previous studies showed that a combination of three pre-colonized commensal <italic>E. coli</italic> strains prevents colonization of <italic>E. coli</italic> O157:H7 in a mouse model (Leatham, et al., 2010, Infect Immun 77: 2876–7886). The commensal biotypes included <italic>E. coli</italic> HS, which is known to successfully colonize humans at high doses with no adverse effects, and <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917, a human commensal strain that is used in Europe as a preventative of traveler's diarrhea. We hypothesized that commensal biotypes could exert colonization resistance by consuming nutrients needed by <italic>E. coli</italic> O157:H7 to colonize, thus preventing this first step in infection. Here we report that to colonize streptomycin-treated mice <italic>E. coli</italic> HS consumes six of the twelve sugars tested and <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 uses a complementary yet divergent set of seven sugars to colonize, thus establishing a nutritional basis for the ability of <italic>E. coli</italic> HS and Nissle 1917 to occupy distinct niches in the mouse intestine. Together these two commensals use the five sugars previously determined to be most important for colonization of <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933, an O157:H7 strain. As predicted, the two commensals prevented <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 colonization. The results support a model in which invading pathogenic <italic>E. coli</italic> must compete with the gut microbiota to obtain the nutrients needed to colonize and establish infection; accordingly, the outcome of the challenge is determined by the aggregate capacity of the native microbiota to consume the nutrients required by the pathogen.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This research was supported by Public Health Service grants AI48945 and GM095370 to TC and PSC. The funders had no role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The gastrointestinal (GI) tract is home to a complex microbial community that has been implicated in both human health and disease. The GI tract is comparable to a chemostat in that the contents constantly turn over and to be successful in this highly competitive environment, an organism must reproduce at least as fast as the turnover rate or it will fail to colonize <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Freter1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Tilman1">[2]</xref>. Freter noted several factors that contribute to colonization success, and concluded that the most important is competition for resources, which led to the nutrient-niche hypothesis: in order to successfully colonize in the absence of adhesion to the mucosal surface an organism must use at least one limiting nutrient better than all other competitors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Freter1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Freter2">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Freter3">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Freter4">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Freter5">[6]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Collectively, the human gut microbiota consists of 1,000 to 36,000 different species of bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Frank1">[7]</xref>, although the number in any one individual is thought to be between 500 and 1,000 species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Turnbaugh1">[8]</xref>. The gut microbiota is predominately comprised of anaerobic bacteria, mostly in the Firmicutes and Bacteriodetes phyla. <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> is the predominant facultative anaerobe in the mammalian GI tract, although other facultatives are present <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Chang1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Hentges1">[10]</xref>. Recent work from our laboratories suggests that <italic>E. coli</italic> exists in a symbiotic relationship with the anaerobic members of the gut microbiota. Through normal nutrient processing the anaerobes degrade complex polysaccharides, releasing the mono- and disaccharides <italic>E. coli</italic> needs for growth. In return, <italic>E. coli</italic> helps create an anaerobic environment by scavenging oxygen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Jones1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Jones2">[12]</xref>. This may explain why <italic>E. coli</italic> and other facultative anaerobes are the first colonizers of the infant gut <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Palmer1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Mackie1">[14]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Once established, the gut microbiota is very stable, such that invading organisms often fail to colonize. This barrier effect is predicted by Freter's nutrient-niche hypothesis and is termed colonization resistance (CR) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Hentges1">[10]</xref>. In a recent review, Stecher and Hardt explain that while the mechanisms of CR are incompletely understood, it is thought that they include direct inhibition of pathogens, the stimulation of host defenses, and nutrient depletion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Stecher1">[15]</xref>. However, CR is not always effective, and invading species are sometimes able to compete with the microbiota, grow to sufficient numbers for colonization of the intestine, and cause disease. For example, <italic>E. coli</italic> pathogens infect humans, despite an average of 5 commensal strains of <italic>E. coli</italic> colonizing a human at any given time <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-ApperlooRenkema1">[16]</xref>. The disease burden of <italic>E. coli</italic> in the world is high and mostly carried by children in developing nations, where infantile diarrhea is a major factor in childhood mortality and up to 60% of cases can be attributed to two pathotypes of <italic>E. coli</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Nataro1">[17]</xref>. In developed nations, <italic>E. coli</italic> is not endemic, but disease outbreaks do occur, with approximately 5,000 cases of Shiga toxin-producing <italic>E. coli</italic> infection reported in the United States in 2011 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-1">[18]</xref>. In addition to enteric infections, disruptions in the gut microbiota have been indicated in inflammatory bowel disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Nell1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Strober1">[20]</xref>, and overgrowth of certain adherent and invasive <italic>E. coli</italic> has been associated with Crohn's disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Lapaquette1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-DarfeuilleMichaud1">[22]</xref>. It is becoming increasingly apparent that a better understanding of the role of the commensal microbiota in CR is needed in order to effectively treat and prevent disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Frank2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Stecher2">[24]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Previously, we showed that <italic>E. coli</italic> MG1655, a commensal strain, and <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933, an O157:H7 strain, use different sugars to colonize the streptomycin-treated mouse intestine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Fabich1">[25]</xref>. Furthermore, we recently showed incomplete CR amongst different commensal <italic>E. coli</italic> strains to <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 invasion in the streptomycin-treated mouse model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham1">[26]</xref>. Although pre-colonization of individual commensal strains did not prevent colonization by <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933, a combination of three commensal strains was effective <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham1">[26]</xref>. On the basis of these findings, we hypothesized that a potential strategy for preventing colonization by enterohemorrhagic <italic>E. coli</italic> would be to pre-colonize mice with a combination of commensal strains that would fill the sugar-defined nutritional niches normally available to invading <italic>E. coli</italic> pathotypes. However, the sugar-defined niche of only one commensal strain has been characterized to date (16).</p>
      <p>In order for such probiotic measures to be effective, the nutritional niches of both pathogenic and commensal strains must first be understood. The three commensal strains found to be the most effective at filling the nutritional niche of <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933, in combination, were <italic>E. coli</italic> MG1655 (a K-12 human commensal strain), <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 (a probiotic strain), and <italic>E. coli</italic> HS (a normal human commensal strain) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham1">[26]</xref>. <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 was first isolated from an uninfected soldier during an outbreak of <italic>Shigella</italic> in 1917. The strain has been marketed for treatment of infectious diarrhea <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Nissle1">[27]</xref>, and has shown to be as effective as current antibiotic treatments for the remission of ulcerative colitis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Schultz1">[28]</xref> with no adverse effects reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Kruis1">[29]</xref>. <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 lacks many of the virulence factors of pathogenic strains, but has several “fitness factors”, including anti-inflammatory properties, enhancement of host barrier function, and induction of the expression of human beta-defensins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Zyrek1">[30]</xref>. <italic>E. coli</italic> HS was first isolated in 1958 from a healthy human volunteer during a study of <italic>Shigella flexneri</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Formal1">[31]</xref>. It is considered a true human commensal, colonizing humans strongly (10<sup>10</sup> CFU/g feces) with no sign of disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Levine1">[32]</xref>. Its genome recently was sequenced <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Rasko1">[33]</xref>. <italic>E. coli</italic> HS has been used extensively as a non-pathogenic control for human and animal studies of pathogenic <italic>E. coli</italic>, although little is known about the nature of <italic>E. coli</italic> HS <italic>in vitro</italic> or <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p>
      <p>Despite its myriad benefits, the safety of <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 as a probiotic has been questioned. Gronback <italic>et al</italic> showed that when both the host gut microbiota and adaptive immunity are defective in mice, <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 was able to translocate through the epithelial layer, leading to dissemination, septicemia, and death of the animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Gronbach1">[34]</xref>. The authors noted that although patients with incomplete gut microbiota have been the successful targets for probiotic treatment, cases have arisen where probiotics were associated with sepsis and other adverse effects, especially in immunocompromised patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Ledoux1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Bleich1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Bjarnason1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Besselink1">[38]</xref>. Also, when mice pre-colonized with only <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 are fed a low dose of <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933, the pathogenic strain is able to grow, albeit marginally, and persist in the intestine for the 11 day duration of the experiment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham1">[26]</xref>. Clearly, a greater understanding is needed of the physiology of commensal <italic>E. coli</italic> strains, keeping in mind that any positive effect against colonization of a pathogen may need to include multiple strains. In this study we determined the sugar-defined niches of <italic>E. coli</italic> strains HS and Nissle 1917, and compared them to those of the previously characterized strains, <italic>E. coli</italic> MG1655 and <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Generation of sugar-negative strains</title>
        <p>To determine which carbon sources are utilized for colonization by <italic>E. coli</italic> HS and Nissle 1917, mutants were constructed that were unable to utilize specific sugars for growth (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t001">Table 1</xref>). <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 deletions were constructed via Lamda Red allelic replacement, as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Datsenko1">[39]</xref>. Mutation frequency in <italic>E. coli</italic> HS by the routine Datsenko-Wanner method was low, as has been reported by others for non-K12 <italic>E. coli</italic> strains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Murphy1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Bryan1">[41]</xref>. We found an alternative Lambda Red plasmid, pKM208, which previously was shown to increase recombination efficiency in enterohemorrhagic strains of <italic>E. coli</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Murphy1">[40]</xref>, to be superior for allelic replacement in <italic>E. coli</italic> HS.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0053957-t001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Bacterial strains and plasmids used in this study.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0053957-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain or Plasmid</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype or phenotype<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">1</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild type</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Rasko1">[33]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HS Str<sup>R</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spontaneous Str<sup>R</sup> mutant of HS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HS Str<sup>R</sup>Nal<sup>R</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spontaneous Nal<sup>R</sup> mutant of HS Str<sup>R</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nissle 1917 Str<sup>R</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spontaneous Str<sup>R</sup> mutant of Nissle 1917</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Autieri1">[45]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EDL933 Str<sup>R</sup>Rif<sup>R</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spontaneous Rif<sup>R</sup> mutant of EDL933 Str<sup>R</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Miranda1">[46]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Strains derived from HS Str<sup>R</sup>:</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>araBAD</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>(araB-araD)::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>araBAD+</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HS <italic>araBAD</italic>+ (restored to WT)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>fucK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>fucK::kan</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>galK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>galK::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>galK+</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HS <italic>galK</italic>+ (restored to WT)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>gntK ΔidnK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>gntK</italic> Δ<italic>idnK::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>lacZ</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>lacZ::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>manA</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>manA::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nagE</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nagE::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nanAT</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nanAT::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>rbsK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>rbsK::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>uxaC</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>uxaC::kan</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Strains derived from Nissle 1917 Str<sup>R</sup>:</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>agaWEFA</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>(agaW- agaA)::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>araBAD</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic> (araB-araD)::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>fucK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>fucK::kan</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>galK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>galK::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>gntK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>gntK::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>lacZ</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>lacZ::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>manA</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>manA::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nagE</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nagE::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nanAT</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nanAT::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>rbsK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>rbsK::cat</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>uxaC</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>uxaC::kan</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmids:</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKD46</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sup>s</sup> Amp<sup>r</sup> P<sub>araC</sub>-λ-red recombinase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Datsenko1">[39]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKM208</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sup>s</sup> Amp<sup>r</sup> <italic>lacI</italic> P<sub>tac</sub>-<italic>red-gam-lacI</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Murphy1">[40]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCP20</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sup>s</sup> Amp<sup>r</sup> FLP recombinase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Datsenko1">[39]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>1</label>
              <p>Str<sup>R</sup>, streptomycin resistance; Nal<sup>R</sup>, nalidixic acid resistance; Rif<sup>R</sup>, rifampicin resistance; Amp<sup>R</sup>, ampicillin resistance; T<sup>S</sup>, temperature sensitive replication.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Confirmation of sugar-negative phenotypes</title>
        <p>The goal of this study was to compare the in vivo (i.e., in the intestine) nutrition of <italic>E. coli</italic> commensal strains HS and Nissle 1917 with that of the pathogen <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933. We previously assessed the ability of <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 to use 12 different sugars in the intestine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Fabich1">[25]</xref>. We note that the hexuronates glucuronate and galacturonate are considered here to be one sugar because mutation of the hexuronate catabolism pathway eliminates growth on both sugars. Of these 12 sugars, neither <italic>E. coli</italic> HS nor Nissle 1917 have the genes for sucrose catabolism and <italic>E. coli</italic> HS also lacks the genes for N-acetylgalactosamine catabolism. Hence, mutations were constructed in the 11 sugar catabolism pathways possessed by <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 and 10 pathways in <italic>E. coli</italic> HS.</p>
        <p>All mutant genotypes were sequenced and the phenotypes confirmed by growth on MOPS minimal media and Biolog assays. Results of the phenotypic assays for the <italic>E. coli</italic> HS mutants are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g001">Figure 1</xref>. Only one of the <italic>E. coli</italic> HS mutants showed significant growth on the sugar targeted for mutation, <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Δ<italic>nagE</italic>, which lacks the N-acetylglucosamine phosphotransferase system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Postma1">[42]</xref>. This gene was chosen for mutation instead of <italic>nagA</italic>, as strains lacking <italic>nagA</italic> have been shown to accumulate N-acetylglucosamine-6-phosphate, which is toxic to <italic>E. coli</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Chang1">[9]</xref>. Strains lacking <italic>nagE</italic> are still able to transport N-acetylglucosamine via the mannose phosphotransferase system, ManXYZ, which has a broad substrate specificity that includes N-acetylglucosamine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Postma1">[42]</xref>. <italic>nagE</italic> deficient strains can also access N-acetylglucosamine through peptidoglycan recycling, although at lower levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Plumbridge1">[43]</xref>. Thus, deletion of <italic>nagE</italic> does not prevent growth on N-acetylglucosamine as the sole carbon and energy source, but the growth rate is significantly lowered. Comparison of growth curves on MOPS minimal medium with 0.2% N-acetylglucosamine showed that <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Δ<italic>nagE</italic> had a doubling time of 2.6 h, compared to 1 h doubling time for the wild type. We also found that <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Δ<italic>gntK</italic> Δ<italic>idnK</italic> retained the ability to grow, albeit poorly, on gluconate. With gluconate as the sole carbon and energy source <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Δ<italic>gntK</italic> Δ<italic>idnK</italic> reached a final O.D.<sub>600</sub> of 0.3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g001">Figure 1</xref>), compared to a final O.D.<sub>600</sub> of approximately 1.0 for wild type <italic>E. coli</italic> HS (data not shown). <italic>E. coli</italic> HS apparently possesses an alternative route for gluconate phosphorylation, despite deletion of the two known gluconate kinase genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Peekhaus1">[44]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0053957-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Phenotypic assay results for <italic>E. coli</italic> HS mutants.</title>
            <p><bold>A–L.</bold> Biolog GN2 (Gram negative carbon nutrition) plates were utilized to assess the overall metabolic capacity of the mutants constructed in <italic>E. coli</italic> HS to consume 95 individual carbon sources (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> for details). The kinetic curves plot substrate oxidation vs. time. Green represents carbon source utilization by the <italic>E. coli</italic> HS wild type strain, red represents the mutant strain, and yellow represents utilization by both strains. Mutant strains of <italic>E. coli</italic> HS: (<bold>A</bold>) Δ<italic>araBAD</italic>, (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>araBAD+</italic>, (<bold>C</bold>) Δ<italic>galK</italic>, (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>galK+</italic>, (<bold>E</bold>) Δ<italic>fucK</italic>, (<bold>F</bold>) Δ<italic>gntK</italic> Δ<italic>idnK</italic>, (<bold>G</bold>) Δ<italic>lacZ</italic>, (<bold>H</bold>) Δ<italic>manA</italic>, (<bold>I</bold>) Δ<italic>nagE</italic>, (<bold>J</bold>) Δ<italic>nanAT</italic>, (<bold>K</bold>) Δ<italic>rbsK</italic>, and (<bold>L</bold>) Δ<italic>uxaC</italic>. <bold>M.</bold> Sugar utilization was assessed in minimal media containing 0.2% carbon source. The final O.D.<sub>600</sub>'s following 12 hour incubations are shown. Note: the generation time of <italic>E. coli HS</italic> Δ<italic>nagE</italic> on N-acetylglucosamine is 2.6 h compared to 1 h for the wild type (see text for details). The sugars N-acetylneuraminate and ribose are not represented on the Biolog plate (NA).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Biolog assays confirmed the sugar-negative phenotypes of the remaining <italic>E. coli</italic> HS strains, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g001">Figure 1</xref>. Although not shown, the phenotypes of the <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 mutants were identical to those of the <italic>E. coli</italic> HS mutants with the exception of <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 Δ<italic>gntK</italic>, which was unable to grow on gluconate. For each sugar-negative mutant, Biolog assays indicated the use of other carbon sources was unaffected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title><italic>E coli</italic> HS Str<sup>R</sup> and HS Str<sup>R</sup> Nal<sup>R</sup> and <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 Str<sup>R</sup> and Nissle 1917 Str<sup>R</sup> Nal<sup>R</sup> are isogenic</title>
        <p>To ensure that spontaneous mutations conferring nalidixic acid resistance do not cause inherent growth defects, equal numbers of <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Str<sup>R</sup> and Str<sup>R</sup> Nal<sup>R</sup> were competed in the streptomycin-treated mouse model, as were <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 Str<sup>R</sup> and Str<sup>R</sup> Nal<sup>R</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Autieri1">[45]</xref>, as described previously for <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Miranda1">[46]</xref>. The <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Str<sup>R</sup> and Str<sup>R</sup> Nal<sup>R</sup> strains co-colonized for 15 days at approximately 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/g feces (data not shown) and thus are considered isogenic and can be regarded as wild type strains.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>The in vivo carbon nutrition of <italic>E. coli</italic> HS</title>
        <p>In order to test which carbon sources are important for intestinal colonization of <italic>E. coli</italic> HS, sugar-negative mutants were competed against their wild type parent strain in streptomycin-treated mice by feeding 10<sup>5</sup> CFU of both strains. Results for the initiation phase (Day 1) and maintenance phase (Day 9), which best reflects the outcome of competition following initiation of colonization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Chang1">[9]</xref>, are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t002">Table 2</xref>. Representative plots of mutations causing no colonization defect, or causing moderate or severe defects are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g002">Figure 2</xref>. For 6 of the 10 sugars tested, the mutation was shown to cause a statistically significant defect of the mutants compared to the wild type during the maintenance stage of colonization. The relative severity of the colonization defects of the <italic>E. coli</italic> HS mutants was galactose&gt;arabinose&gt;gluconate&gt;N-acetylglucosamine&gt;lactose&gt;ribose. N-acetylneuraminate, fucose, mannose, and hexuronates were found to be unnecessary for growth of <italic>E. coli</italic> HS in the intestine.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0053957-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Competitive colonization of <italic>E. coli</italic> HS mutants vs. wild type.</title>
            <p>Sets of three mice were fed 10<sup>5</sup> CFU of both the <italic>E. coli</italic> HS wild type strain and mutant strain. At the times indicated, fecal samples were homogenized, diluted, and plated as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>. Compiled data from at least two distinct experiments (6 mice) are shown. Standard errors of the log<sub>10</sub> means of CFU/gram feces are indicated with error bars. (<bold>A</bold>) Δ<italic>uxaC</italic>, which does not have a colonization defect; (<bold>B</bold>) Δ<italic>rbsK</italic>, which has a moderate colonization defect; (<bold>C</bold>) Δ<italic>galK</italic>, which has a severe colonization defect.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0053957-t002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>E. coli</italic> HS sugar utilization in the mouse intestine.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0053957-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Log10 difference on:</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutation</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p Value</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>araBAD</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8±0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5±0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.61×10<sup>−4</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>araBAD</italic>+</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0±0.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7±0.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>fucK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4±0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0±0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>galK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4±0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1±0.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1.13×10<sup>−3</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>galK+</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5±0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4±0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>gntK</italic> Δ<italic>idnK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1±0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4±0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.06×10<sup>−5</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>lacZ</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4±0.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0±0.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>4.56×10<sup>−2</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>manA</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6±0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3±0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.05×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nagE</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4±0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9±0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>8.42×10<sup>−5</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nanAT</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8±0.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3±0.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.62×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>rbsK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3±0.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8±0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1.78×10<sup>−2</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>uxaC</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0±0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1±0.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.45×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label/>
              <p>The difference between population density of the wild type and each mutant strain is shown at Day 1 and Day 9, plus or minus the standard error of the mean. Significant values (bold) indicate log difference &gt;0.8 and student's <italic>t</italic> test value P&lt;0.05 at Day 9.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Colonization defects are due to deletion of the targeted gene</title>
        <p>To ensure that inability to co-colonize with the wild type parent was in fact due to the genetic disruption of the specific sugar utilization pathway and not a deleterious mutation at an unintended second site, complemented strains were constructed. To save mice, only two mutations were complemented. Previously, we found that complementation restored the wild type phenotype and eliminated the colonization defect, confirming that the defect was caused by the mutation and not a second site mutation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-LeathamJensen1">[47]</xref>. In this study, <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Δ<italic>araBAD</italic> (arabinose negative) and <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Δ<italic>galK</italic> (galactose negative) were chosen for restoration of gene function because they showed the greatest defects when colonized against the wild type strain, a 2.5 and 3.1 log difference, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t002">Table 2</xref>). When these functions were restored by reintroduction of the wild type alleles, the complimented strains showed restoration of sugar utilization in Biolog assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g001">Figure 1</xref>), and no colonization defect in competition with the wild type (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>The in vivo carbon nutrition of <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917</title>
        <p>Analogous to the experiments described above for <italic>E. coli</italic> HS, a series of metabolism mutants was competed against the wild type <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 parent strain (Str<sup>R</sup> Nal<sup>R</sup>). The results for initiation (Day 1) and maintenance (Day 9) phases in competitive colonizations are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t003">Table 3</xref>. Representative plots of three colonization experiments are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g003">Figure 3</xref>. For 7 of the 11 sugars tested, mutation was shown to cause a statistically significant defect in the maintenance stage of colonization. The relative severity of the colonization defects of the <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 strains was arabinose&gt;fucose&gt;galactose&gt;gluconate&gt;N-acetylgalactosamine&gt;mannose = N-acetylneuraminate. Of the sugars tested, only lactose, N-acetylglucosamine, the hexuronates, and ribose were found to be unnecessary for growth of <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 in the intestine.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0053957-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Competitive colonization of <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 mutants vs. wild type.</title>
            <p>Data were collected as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g002">Figure 2</xref>. (<bold>A</bold>) Δ<italic>lacZ</italic>, which does not have a colonization defect; (<bold>B</bold>) Δ<italic>fucK</italic>, which has a moderate colonization defect; (<bold>C</bold>) Δ<italic>araBAD</italic>, which has a severe colonization defect.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0053957-t003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.t003</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 sugar utilization in the mouse intestine.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0053957-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Log10 difference on:</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutation</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p Value</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>agaWEFA</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1±0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0±0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>9.64×10<sup>−3</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>araBAD</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5±0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7±0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1.01×10<sup>−3</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>fucK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1±0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3±0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.33×10<sup>−9</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>galK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0±0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2±0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.74×10<sup>−3</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>gntK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6±0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1±0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>4.28×10<sup>−3</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>lacZ</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4±0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6±0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.85×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>manA</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4±0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9±0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>3.97×10−</bold>
                    <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">2</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nagE</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0±0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0±0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.77×10<sup>1</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nanAT</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3±0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9±0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>3.45×10<sup>−3</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>rbsK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.1±0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2±0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>uxaC</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">2</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.9±02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6±0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.92×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label/>
              <p>The difference between population density of the wild type and each mutant strain is shown at Day 1 and Day 9, plus or minus the standard error of the mean. Significant values (bold) indicate log difference &gt;0.8 and student's <italic>t</italic> test value P&lt;0.05 at Day 9.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label>2</label>
              <p>Significance refers to Nissle 1917Δ<italic>uxaC</italic> ability to outcompete wildtype.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title><italic>E. coli</italic> strains HS, Nissle 1917, MG1655, and EDL933 display different nutritional profiles in streptomycin-treated mice</title>
        <p>Previously we demonstrated that <italic>E. coli</italic> MG1655 and <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 display different nutritional profiles in the streptomycin-treated mouse intestine (16). <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t004">Table 4</xref> compares the <italic>in vivo</italic> carbon preferences of four <italic>E. coli</italic> strains: <italic>E. coli</italic> MG1655, the K12 strain; the enterohemorrhagic O157:H7 type strain <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933; <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917; and <italic>E. coli</italic> HS. Of the 12 sugars tested, <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 uses seven of them, in order of preference, ribose&gt;galactose&gt;sucrose&gt;mannose&gt;N-acetylglucosamine&gt;arabinose&gt;hexuronates (16). Therefore, <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 is able to use 2 sugars that are not used by the commensals: sucrose, which cannot be catabolized by the commensals because they lack the pathway, and the hexuronates, the loss of which has the least impact on colonization by <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933. The results in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t004">Table 4</xref> show that each strain displays a unique nutritional program in the streptomycin-treated mouse intestine.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0053957-t004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.t004</object-id>
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Sugar utilization in the intestine by <italic>E. coli</italic> strains.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0053957-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sugar-negative phenotype</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutation</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MG1655<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">3</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EDL 933<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">3</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nissle 1917<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">4</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HS<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">4</xref></td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arabinose</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>araBAD</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fucose</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>fucK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galactose</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>galK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gluconate</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>gntK</italic> Δ<italic>idnK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexuronates</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>uxaC</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactose</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>lacZ</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mannose</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>manA</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-acetylglucosamine</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nagE</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-acetylgalactosamine</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>agaWEFA</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">5</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-acetylneuraminate</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>nanAT</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribose</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>rbsK</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>sacH</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label/>
              <p>Results show the difference in population sizes of wild type verses mutant strains at Day 9. Yes indicates &gt;0.8 log<sub>10</sub> colonization difference and P&lt;0.05.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt106">
              <label>3</label>
              <p>Data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Fabich1">[25]</xref>. Fabich AJ, Jones SA, Chowdhury FZ, Cernosek A, Anderson A, et al. (2008) Comparison of carbon nutrition for pathogenic and commensal <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains in the mouse intestine. Infection and immunity 76: 1143–1152.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt107">
              <label>4</label>
              <p>This study.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt108">
              <label>5</label>
              <p>NA indicates that the pathway is not intact in this genetic background.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title><italic>E. coli</italic> HS and Nissle 1917 fill the sugar-defined niches occupied by EDL933</title>
        <p>Previously we showed that pre-colonization with three commensal strains for 10 days was sufficient to prevent subsequent challenge by <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933, which was completely eliminated from the intestine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham1">[26]</xref>. If the basis for exclusion of <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 in that experiment was because the commensals utilized the nutrients needed by <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 to compete and colonize, we reasoned that any commensal strain or combination of strains that effectively catabolizes the sugars used by <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 would prevent its colonization. Therefore, we tested the ability of <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 to colonize mice that were pre-colonized with <italic>E. coli</italic> HS and <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917, which the data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t004">Table 4</xref> indicated should be equally effective without MG1655 present. The two commensal strains were fed to mice at the beginning of the experiment, using nalidixic acid selection to enumerate <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Str<sup>R</sup>Nal<sup>R</sup> and chloramphenicol selection to enumerate <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 Δ<italic>lacZ::cat</italic> (as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t003">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g003">Figure 3</xref>, the <italic>lacZ</italic> mutation does not affect its colonization). The precolonized animals were challenged on day 10 with <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 Str<sup>R</sup>Rif<sup>R</sup> and the experiment was continued for 11 more days. The results of this experiment, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g004">Figure 4</xref>, indicated that pre-colonization for 10 days with the two commensal <italic>E. coli</italic> strains did indeed completely prevent challenge by <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933, which was eliminated 5 days following association. Thus, some but not all commensal <italic>E. coli</italic> strains exert CR against <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 in the mouse intestine.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0053957-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Mice precolonized with <italic>E. coli</italic> HS and <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 prevent colonization by <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL 933.</title>
            <p>Mice were fed 10<sup>5</sup> CFU of <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Str<sup>R</sup>Nal<sup>R</sup> and <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 Str<sup>R</sup> Δ<italic>lacZ::cat</italic>. Ten days later, mice were fed 10<sup>5</sup> CFU <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933. Data were collected as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g002">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0053957.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The results from this study show that the human commensals <italic>E. coli</italic> HS and <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 each occupy a unique nutritional niche in the mouse intestine (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t004">Table 4</xref>). Of the 12 sugars available in the mucus layer, <italic>E. coli</italic> HS has the genetic capacity to use 10 and actually utilizes 6 for colonization: galactose, arabinose, gluconate, N-acetylglucosamine, lactose, and ribose. Here, we also show that <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 uses a differing list of 7 carbon sources to support colonization, including arabinose, fucose, galactose, gluconate, N-acetylglucosamine, and N-acetylneuraminate, and mannose. Previously we showed that <italic>E. coli</italic> MG1655 utilizes 5 sugars, arabinose, fucose, gluconate, N-acetylglucosamine, and N-acetylneuraminate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Fabich1">[25]</xref>. Each of these commensals is capable of colonizing mice that were pre-colonized with one of the others <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham1">[26]</xref>, and each strain is capable of utilizing at least one sugar not used by the others in vivo, which suggests that differences in their in vivo sugar preferences allows them to occupy distinct nutrient-defined niches in the intestine.</p>
      <p>The intestinal niche occupied by pathogenic <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 is at least partially defined by utilization of arabinose, galactose, hexuronates, mannose, N-acetylglucosamine, ribose, and sucrose for colonization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Fabich1">[25]</xref>. Together, <italic>E. coli</italic> HS and <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 utilize all but two of these carbon sources. <italic>E. coli</italic> HS was found to be the only strain, besides <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933, which uses N-acetylglucosamine for colonization, whereas <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 was found to be the only strain, besides <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933, to use mannose (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t004">Table 4</xref>). Two sugars utilized by the pathogenic <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 but not utilized by the commensal strains tested are sucrose and the hexuronates. Only <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 has the genes necessary for sucrose catabolism. It is possible that <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 uses these sugars in order to initiate colonization, although the energy yield may not be enough to enable it to persist <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Fabich1">[25]</xref>. Leatham, et al., showed that when mice pre-colonized with three commensal <italic>E. coli</italic> strains were fed <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933, it dropped from a population of about 10<sup>5</sup> CFU/g feces to approximately 10<sup>2</sup> CFU/g feces by 48 hours, and down to &lt;10 CFU/g feces 10 days post association <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham1">[26]</xref>. However, individually none of these commensal strains could prevent colonization of EDL933 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham1">[26]</xref>. Since the in vivo substrate range of <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 and HS cover the same sugars without MG1655 in the mix, we predicted that the two strains would prevent EDL933 and found indeed this was the case (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g004">Figure 4</xref>). This result supports the hypothesis that nutrient consumption by certain <italic>E. coli</italic> strains can limit nutrient availability to other <italic>E. coli</italic> strains, supporting the idea that CR can be attributed, at least in part, to competition for nutrients.</p>
      <p>It was important in this study to establish that the observed colonization defects are due to the loss of gene function for sugar utilization, and not due to second site mutations. Our results showed that the two mutations that caused the largest colonization defects in <italic>E. coli</italic> HS prevented growth on arabinose and galactose, respectively. Genetic complementation of these mutations (wild type <italic>araBAD</italic> was recombined into <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Δ<italic>araBAD</italic> and wild type <italic>galK</italic> into <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Δ<italic>galK</italic>) restored both complemented strains to the wild type colonization phenotype (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t002">Table 2</xref>), proving that the mutant colonization defects were due solely to mutation of the specific sugar pathway.</p>
      <p>It is interesting that <italic>E. coli</italic> HS is the only <italic>E. coli</italic> strain found thus far to utilize lactose for colonization. This strain has often been used as a control during human and animal studies of pathogenic <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> strains due to its ability to consistently colonize the intestine in high numbers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Levine1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Formal2">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-RobinsBrowne1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Nataro2">[50]</xref>. While further studies are needed, perhaps utilization of lactose is the reason for such strong colonization shown by <italic>E. coli</italic> HS. The amount of lactose present in the human large intestine differs from person to person, based on their diet and the presence or absence of lactase, the enzyme that degrades lactose <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-2">[51]</xref>. It is well known that humans with decreased lactase production suffer from gastrointestinal symptoms such as bloating, gas, and diarrhea when excess lactose passes from the small intestine and is fermented by members of the gut microbiota <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-2">[51]</xref>. Human adults are unique among mammals in having the ability to produce lactase, which most mammals lose upon weaning <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Swallow1">[52]</xref>. The results of this study suggest that <italic>E. coli</italic> HS can compete with the native gut microbiota for lactose.</p>
      <p>The use of streptomycin treatment to remove native <italic>E. coli</italic> from the mice is required to overcome CR to experimentally introduced <italic>E. coli</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Hentges1">[10]</xref>. It is not possible to conduct the experiments in conventional mice, which are resistant to colonization by <italic>E. coli</italic>, nor would the experiments be possible in humans, who are colonized on average by five different commensal <italic>E. coli</italic> strains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-ApperlooRenkema1">[16]</xref>. However, with the native <italic>E. coli</italic> removed by streptomycin treatment, the system allows the determination of in vivo nutrient utilization by introduced <italic>E. coli</italic> strains. Despite alterations to the mouse microbiota caused by streptomycin treatment, there remains a large and diverse anaerobe population in the intestine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Hentges1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-LeathamJensen1">[47]</xref>. We contend that results of the experiments described here extend to a more complex native microbiota found in conventional animals, including humans, and that the aggregate capacity of the microbiota to consume nutrients needed by invading bacteria to colonize is a component of CR, which is central to the probiotic concept <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Araya1">[53]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Probiotics are defined as “live microorganisms which, when administered in adequate amounts, confer a health benefit on the host” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Araya1">[53]</xref>. In recent years, interest in their use to promote human health has increased dramatically. For almost a century, <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 has been used as a probiotic for the treatment of infectious diarrhea <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Nissle1">[27]</xref>. In addition to its ability to occupy a different nutritional niche from that of <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933, <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 also has several fitness factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Zyrek1">[30]</xref>. Nissle 1917 is also effective in maintaining remission in ulcerative colitis patients as traditional treatments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Schultz1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Kruis1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Rembacken1">[54]</xref>, possibly through the increased production of indole <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Schumann1">[55]</xref>. However, Leatham, et al., showed that in the streptomycin-treated mouse model, pre-colonization with <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 alone was insufficient to keep <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 from initiating colonization and persisting, albeit in low numbers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham1">[26]</xref>. This level of colonization may be high enough for <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 to reach the epithelium and express virulence factors. There has been no work, to date, to indicate that <italic>E. coli</italic> HS benefits humans. However, the strain has no adverse effects when fed to humans at high doses (10<sup>10</sup> CFU) and has been used extensively as a representative of a “normal” commensal strain in human studies, with no ill outcomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Levine1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Formal2">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-RobinsBrowne1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Nataro2">[50]</xref>. The new finding reported here, that <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 and HS prevent colonization by EDL933, supports the hypothesis that nutrient consumption by commensal <italic>E. coli</italic> can limit nutrient availability to pathogens, which in turn points to the potential of probiotics for preventing disease.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title>
        <p>Bacterial strains and plasmids used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053957-t001">Table 1</xref>. <italic>E. coli</italic> HS was obtained from David Rasko at the University of Maryland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Rasko1">[33]</xref>. Derivation of the <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 parent strains used in this study was described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Autieri1">[45]</xref>. The <italic>E. coli</italic> EDL933 parent strain used in this study also was described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Miranda1">[46]</xref>. Cultures were grown on Luria-Bertani (LB) broth at 250 RPM gyratory shaking or on LB agar. All cultures were incubated at 37°C, except those containing temperature-sensitive replicon plasmids, which were grown at 30°C. Antibiotics were supplemented as required to the following final concentrations: streptomycin, 100 µg/ml, nalidixic acid, 50 µg/ml, chloramphenicol, 30 µg/ml, kanamycin, 40 µg/ml, amplicillin, 100 µg/ml, rifampicin, 50 µg/ml.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Electroporation and gene replacement</title>
        <p>Null alleles were constructed in <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 by using the Lambda Red allelic replacement system, first described by Datsenko and Wanner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Datsenko1">[39]</xref>. In our hands, successful allelic replacement in <italic>E. coli</italic> HS by the Datsenko and Wanner approach was rare, so instead we used the approach of Murphy and Campellone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Murphy1">[40]</xref>, modified as follows. To increase recombination efficiency, null alleles previously constructed in <italic>E. coli</italic> MG1655 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Fabich1">[25]</xref> were used as a template for creating deletions in <italic>E. coli</italic> HS, which was possible because their genomes are highly conserved. The null alleles containing antibiotic resistance cassettes were PCR amplified from the genome of the appropriate <italic>E. coli</italic> MG1655 mutant, together with 500 to 700 base pairs of upstream and downstream flanking sequences, which increases recombination efficiency <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Bryan1">[41]</xref>. The PCR amplicons were purified using Qiagen PCR purification kit and electroporated into competent <italic>E. coli</italic> HS cells containing the Lambda Red pKM208 plasmid, according to the Murphy protocol <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Murphy1">[40]</xref>. Cells were recovered in super optimal broth (SOB) medium at 37°C with shaking for two hours and then plated on LB agar containing appropriate antibiotics. In this way the target genes on the <italic>E. coli</italic> HS genome were deleted and replaced with chloramphenicol or kanamycin resistance cassettes, which acted as selectable markers in colonization experiments. Single gene deletions began with deletion of the start codon and ended with the stop codon. Deletions of contiguous genes within an operon began with the start codon of the first gene and ended with the stop codon of the last gene deleted. Strains with multiple mutations at different loci were created by sequential allelic replacement. The first gene was replaced with a resistance cassette, which was removed using FLP recombinase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Datsenko1">[39]</xref>. The second gene was then replaced with a resistance cassette, leaving the selectable marker in place of the second gene deleted. All constructions were verified by DNA sequencing and phenotypic analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Phenotypic analysis</title>
        <p>For confirmation of phenotypes, putative mutant strains and their wild type parents were grown in 3-<italic>N</italic>-morpholino propanesulfonic acid (MOPS) defined minimal medium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Neidhardt1">[56]</xref> with 0.2% carbon source at 37°C with gyratory shaking for 12–14 hours. Cell growth was determined spectrophotometrically at OD<sub>600</sub>. To demonstrate the slower growth phenotype of the <italic>E. coli</italic> HS Δ<italic>nagE</italic> mutant, the growth rates in MOPS minimal medium plus 0.2% N-acetylglucosamine were measured for the mutant and the wild type. In addition, Biolog assays were used to determine the metabolic capacity of each deletion strain in <italic>E. coli</italic> HS, as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Jones3">[57]</xref>. Biolog GN2 (Gram negative carbon nutrition) plates were used according to manufacturer's instructions. In brief, strains were grown overnight on tryptic soy agar, suspended in Biolog inoculating fluid (gellan gum, 0.2 g/liter; NaCL, 4.0 g/liter; Pluronic F-68, 0.3 g/liter; 2.5 mM thioglycolate) to a final OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.2 to 0.3. Each well of the Biolog GN2 plate was inoculated with 150 µl cell suspension and incubated at 37°C for 24 hours in an Omnilog system. Tetrazolium violet dye reduction was measured at 15 min intervals and plotted vs. time, resulting in a kinetic curve. The area under the curve served as a measure of oxidation of each carbon source.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Mouse colonization experiments</title>
        <p>The streptomycin-treated mouse model was used to investigate the <italic>in vivo</italic> carbon nutrition of <italic>E. coli</italic> HS and Nissle 1917. This strategy for the study of intestinal colonization has been used extensively by our group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Chang1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Jones1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Jones2">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Fabich1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Autieri1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Miranda1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Jones3">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham2">[58]</xref>. Briefly, streptomycin treated water (5 g/L) was given to three male, six week old, CD-1 mice for 24 hours, clearing the intestine of native facultative anaerobic bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Hentges1">[10]</xref>. Streptomycin is an aminoglycoside antibiotic that inhibits protein synthesis, affecting terminal respiration pathways, carbohydrate metabolism, and cell division <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Barkulis1">[59]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Henry1">[60]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Paine1">[61]</xref>. Anaerobic bacteria apparently do not take up aminoglycosides, making them intrinsically resistant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Franklin1">[62]</xref>. Streptomycin is taken up by actively respiring cells and therefore selectively removes facultative anaerobic bacteria in the gut <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Umbreit1">[63]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Wells1">[64]</xref>. Thus, streptomycin treatment opens a niche for the colonization of experimentally introduced <italic>E. coli</italic> strains while leaving the general population of anaerobic bacteria essentially intact <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Hentges1">[10]</xref>. Recent work from our laboratory using 16S rRNA gene sequencing showed that, while streptomycin treatment alters the anaerobic gut microbiota, the resulting microbial community is highly diverse, more so than any other animal model currently available <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-LeathamJensen1">[47]</xref>.</p>
        <p>As described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Chang1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Jones1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Jones2">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Fabich1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Autieri1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Miranda1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Jones3">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053957-Leatham2">[58]</xref>, seed cultures were grown in LB liquid medium for eighteen hours prior to association. Food and water were withheld from the mice for fourteen hours prior to association. Mice were placed into separate cages and given 1 ml of a bacterial suspension prepared in 20% sucrose containing approximately 10<sup>5</sup> CFU of each strain. Mice took up the inoculum orally, after which food and streptomycin treated water were returned <italic>ad libidum</italic> for the remainder of the experiment. At 5 and 24 hours post association and every other day thereafter, 1 gram of feces was diluted in 10 ml of 1% tryptone, homogenized, serially diluted, and plated onto MacConkey agar supplemented with appropriate antibiotics (typically streptomycin and nalidixic acid for wild type strain and streptomycin and chloramphenicol or kanamycin for mutant strains). The limit of detection was 10<sup>1</sup> CFU/g feces. For experiments in which the challenge strain was associated with the mice on day 10, food and water again are withheld for 14 h and then 10<sup>5</sup> CFU of the challenge strain was fed as described above, at which time food and water were returned. When necessary to differentiate strains, 100 colonies were tooth-picked from MacConkey streptomycin plates to MacConkey streptomycin and nalidixic acid plates. Colonizations were replicated at least twice, and the average population sizes and standard error of the mean of six or more animals was calculated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Gene complementation</title>
        <p>To prove that selected colonization defects were in fact due to the targeted gene and not inadvertent second site mutations, the mutations were complemented in <italic>E. coli</italic> HS. Lambda Red plasmid pKM208 was electroporated into the mutated strain of choice, and a gene fragment containing the deleted allele was electroporated into competent cells as described above. Complemented strains were rescued by plating on MOPS minimal agar containing 0.2% of the appropriate carbon source. Strains were then verified via phenotypic and Biolog analysis, as described above. Complimented strains (streptomycin resistant) were colonized in the streptomycin-treated mouse model as above against the wild type strain (streptomycin and nalidixic acid resistant). Fecal samples were plated onto MacConkey agar supplemented with streptomycin. To distinguish the complemented strains from the wild type, 100 colonies were tooth-picked from the streptomycin plate to MacConkey agar containing streptomycin and nalidixic acid.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title>Ethics statement</title>
        <p>Animal experiments were conducted in accordance with the United States Department of Health and Human Services Office of Laboratory Animal Welfare. We used the minimum number of animals needed to obtain statistically significant results. To our knowledge, there is no in vitro experiment design that provides a reasonable alternative to animal experiments. The mice were cared for in a humane manner according to local, state, and federal regulations. During colonization experiments, there was no discomfort to the mice. Throughout the duration of the colonization experiments the cages were changed daily and the mice were provided food and water ad libitum. Mice were killed by CO<sub>2</sub> asphyxiation at the conclusion of colonization experiments, consistent with recommendations of the Panel on Euthanasia of the American Veterinary Medical Association. The University of Oklahoma IACUC Approval Number is A3240-01, approved 01/25/2008. The University of Rhode Island IACUC Approval Number is A3690-01, approved 03/19/2007.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors wish to thank Sal Rizzuto for assistance with the animal colonization experiment shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053957-g004">Figure 4</xref>.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Freter1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brickner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Botney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cleven</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aranki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms that control bacterial populations in continuous-flow culture models of mouse large intestinal flora</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>685</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Tilman1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tilman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Resource competition and community structure</article-title>. <source>Monographs in population biology</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Freter2">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brickner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fekete</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vickerman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Survival and implantation of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in the intestinal tract</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>686</fpage>–<lpage>703</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Freter3">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freter</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brickner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Experimental and mathematical models of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> plasmid transfer in vitro and in vivo</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Freter4">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Models for studying the role of bacterial attachment in virulence and pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Reviews of infectious diseases</source> <volume>5 Suppl 4</volume>: <fpage>S647</fpage>–<lpage>658</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Freter5">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stauffer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cleven</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holdeman</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Continuous-flow cultures as in vitro models of the ecology of large intestinal flora</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>666</fpage>–<lpage>675</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Frank1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>St Amand</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boedeker</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harpaz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular-phylogenetic characterization of microbial community imbalances in human inflammatory bowel diseases</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>13780</fpage>–<lpage>13785</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Turnbaugh1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turnbaugh</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quince</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faith</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McHardy</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yatsunenko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Organismal, genetic, and transcriptional variation in the deeply sequenced gut microbiomes of identical twins</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>7503</fpage>–<lpage>7508</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Chang1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smalley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leatham</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Carbon nutrition of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in the mouse intestine</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>7427</fpage>–<lpage>7432</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Hentges1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hentges</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Que</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>The influence of streptomycin on colonization resistance in mice</article-title>. <source>Microecology and Therapy</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Jones1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fabich</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiner</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Respiration of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in the mouse intestine</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>4891</fpage>–<lpage>4899</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Jones2">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maltby</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Anaerobic respiration of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in the mouse intestine</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>4218</fpage>–<lpage>4226</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Palmer1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bik</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiGiulio</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Relman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Development of the human infant intestinal microbiota</article-title>. <source>Plos Biology</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1556</fpage>–<lpage>1573</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Mackie1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackie</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sghir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaskins</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Developmental microbial ecology of the neonatal gastrointestinal tract</article-title>. <source>The American journal of clinical nutrition</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1035S</fpage>–<lpage>1045S</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Stecher1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardt</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms controlling pathogen colonization of the gut</article-title>. <source>Current opinion in microbiology</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-ApperlooRenkema1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Apperloo-Renkema</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Waaij</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Waaij</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Determination of colonization resistance of the digestive tract by biotyping of <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic></article-title>. <source>Epidemiology and infection</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Nataro1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nataro</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaper</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Diarrheagenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Clinical microbiology reviews</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><article-title>Notifiable Disease and Mortality Tables</article-title>. <source>MMWR Recommendations and reports : Morbidity and mortality weekly report Recommendations and reports/Centers for Disease Control</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1762</fpage>–<lpage>1775</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Nell1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suerbaum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Josenhans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The impact of the microbiota on the pathogenesis of IBD: lessons from mouse infection models</article-title>. <source>Nature reviews Microbiology</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>577</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Strober1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strober</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fuss</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mannon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The fundamental basis of inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>The Journal of clinical investigation</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>514</fpage>–<lpage>521</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Lapaquette1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lapaquette</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasser</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Darfeuille-Michaud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Crohn's disease-associated adherent-invasive <italic>E. coli</italic> are selectively favoured by impaired autophagy to replicate intracellularly</article-title>. <source>Cellular microbiology</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-DarfeuilleMichaud1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darfeuille-Michaud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boudeau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bulois</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neut</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasser</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>High prevalence of adherent-invasive <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> associated with ileal mucosa in Crohn's disease</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>421</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Frank2">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Gastrointestinal microbiology enters the metagenomics era</article-title>. <source>Current opinion in gastroenterology</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Stecher2">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardt</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The role of microbiota in infectious disease</article-title>. <source>Trends in microbiology</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Fabich1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabich</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cernosek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Comparison of carbon nutrition for pathogenic and commensal <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains in the mouse intestine</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>1143</fpage>–<lpage>1152</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Leatham1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leatham</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Autieri</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mercado-Lubo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Precolonized human commensal <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains serve as a barrier to <italic>E. coli</italic> O157:H7 growth in the streptomycin-treated mouse intestine</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>2876</fpage>–<lpage>2886</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Nissle1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nissle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1951</year>) <article-title>[Mutaflor and its medical significance]</article-title>. <source>Zeitschrift fur klinische Medizin</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Schultz1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Clinical use of <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 in inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Inflammatory bowel diseases</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1012</fpage>–<lpage>1018</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Kruis1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruis</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fric</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pokrotnieks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lukas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fixa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Maintaining remission of ulcerative colitis with the probiotic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> Nissle 1917 is as effective as with standard mesalazine</article-title>. <source>Gut</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>1617</fpage>–<lpage>1623</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Zyrek1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zyrek</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cichon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helms</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enders</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sonnenborn</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular mechanisms underlying the probiotic effects of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> Nissle 1917 involve ZO-2 and PKCzeta redistribution resulting in tight junction and epithelial barrier repair</article-title>. <source>Cellular microbiology</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>804</fpage>–<lpage>816</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Formal1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Formal</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dammin</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labrec</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1958</year>) <article-title>Experimental <italic>Shigella</italic> infections: characteristics of a fatal infection produced in guinea pigs</article-title>. <source>Journal of bacteriology</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>604</fpage>–<lpage>610</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Levine1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bergquist</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nalin</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hornick</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1978</year>) <article-title><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains that cause diarrhoea but do not produce heat-labile or heat-stable enterotoxins and are non-invasive</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1119</fpage>–<lpage>1122</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Rasko1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasko</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosovitz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mongodin</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fricke</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The pangenome structure of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: comparative genomic analysis of <italic>E. coli</italic> commensal and pathogenic isolates</article-title>. <source>Journal of bacteriology</source> <volume>190</volume>: <fpage>6881</fpage>–<lpage>6893</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Gronbach1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gronbach</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eberle</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olschlager</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrindt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Safety of probiotic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain Nissle 1917 depends on intestinal microbiota and adaptive immunity of the host</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>3036</fpage>–<lpage>3046</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Ledoux1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ledoux</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labombardi</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title><italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> bacteraemia after use of a probiotic in a patient with AIDS and Hodgkin's disease</article-title>. <source>International journal of STD &amp; AIDS</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Bleich1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bleich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sundberg</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smoczek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Wasielewski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Buhr</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Sensitivity to <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> Nissle 1917 in mice is dependent on environment and genetic background</article-title>. <source>International journal of experimental pathology</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Bjarnason1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjarnason</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bjarnason</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Probiotic prophylaxis in predicted severe acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>372</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Besselink1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Besselink</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Santvoort</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buskens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boermeester</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Goor</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Probiotic prophylaxis in predicted severe acute pancreatitis: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>371</volume>: <fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>659</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Datsenko1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Datsenko</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>One-step inactivation of chromosomal genes in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 using PCR products</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>6640</fpage>–<lpage>6645</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Murphy1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campellone</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Lambda Red-mediated recombinogenic engineering of enterohemorrhagic and enteropathogenic <italic>E. coli</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC molecular biology</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Bryan1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roesch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pellett</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Regulation of type 1 fimbriae by unlinked FimB- and FimE-like recombinases in uropathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain CFT073</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>1072</fpage>–<lpage>1083</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Postma1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lengeler</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Phosphoenolpyruvate:carbohydrate phosphotransferase systems of bacteria</article-title>. <source>Microbiological reviews</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>594</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Plumbridge1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plumbridge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>An alternative route for recycling of N-acetylglucosamine from peptidoglycan involves the N-acetylglucosamine phosphotransferase system in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Journal of bacteriology</source> <volume>191</volume>: <fpage>5641</fpage>–<lpage>5647</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Peekhaus1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peekhaus</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>What's for dinner?: Entner-Doudoroff metabolism in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Journal of bacteriology</source> <volume>180</volume>: <fpage>3495</fpage>–<lpage>3502</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Autieri1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Autieri</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lins</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leatham</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>L-fucose stimulates utilization of D-ribose by <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> MG1655 Δf<italic>ucAO</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic> Nissle 1917 Δf<italic>ucAO</italic> mutants in the mouse intestine and in M9 minimal medium</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>5465</fpage>–<lpage>5475</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Miranda1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leatham</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Glycolytic and gluconeogenic growth of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7 (EDL933) and E. coli K-12 (MG1655) in the mouse intestine</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>1666</fpage>–<lpage>1676</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-LeathamJensen1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leatham-Jensen</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frimodt-Moller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adediran</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mokszycki</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banner</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The streptomycin-treated mouse intestine selects Escherichia coli envZ missense mutants that interact with dense and diverse intestinal microbiota</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>1716</fpage>–<lpage>1727</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Formal2">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Formal</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hornick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Libonati</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>EXPERIMENTAL MODELS IN THE INVESTIGATION OF THE VIRULENCE OF DYSENTERY BACILLI AND <italic>ESCHERICHIA COLI</italic>*</article-title>. <source>Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>176</volume>: <fpage>190</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-RobinsBrowne1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robins-Browne</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Failure to detect conventional enterotoxins in classical enteropathogenic (serotyped) <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains of proven pathogenicity</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>798</fpage>–<lpage>801</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Nataro2">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nataro</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cookson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cravioto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Savarino</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Heterogeneity of enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> virulence demonstrated in volunteers</article-title>. <source>The Journal of infectious diseases</source> <volume>171</volume>: <fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-2">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">(2009) Lactose Intolerance. In: National Digestive Diseases Information Clearinghouse NIoH, editor, US Department of Health and Human Services. Bethesda, MD.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Swallow1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swallow</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Genetics of lactase persistence and lactose intolerance</article-title>. <source>Annual review of genetics</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Araya1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Araya M, Gopal P, Lindgren S, Lordi R, Oliver G, <etal>et al</etal>. (2001) Joint FAO/WHO expert consultation on evaluation of health and nutritional properties of probiotics in food including milk powder with live lactic acid bacteria. Cordoba, Argentina: WHO.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Rembacken1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rembacken</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snelling</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkey</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chalmers</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Axon</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Non-pathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> versus mesalazine for the treatment of ulcerative colitis: a randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>354</volume>: <fpage>635</fpage>–<lpage>639</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Schumann1">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schumann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engst</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>DSS-induced inflammation changes protein expression of intestinal <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in a gnotobiotic mouse model</article-title>. <source>Applied and environmental microbiology</source></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Neidhardt1">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neidhardt</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Culture medium for enterobacteria</article-title>. <source>Journal of bacteriology</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>736</fpage>–<lpage>747</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Jones3">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartline</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Glycogen and maltose utilization by <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7 in the mouse intestine</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>2531</fpage>–<lpage>2540</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Leatham2">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leatham</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gauger</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krogfelt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lins</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Mouse intestine selects nonmotile <italic>flhDC</italic> mutants of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> MG1655 with increased colonizing ability and better utilization of carbon sources</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>8039</fpage>–<lpage>8049</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Barkulis1">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barkulis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1952</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of the anaerobic pyruvate metabolism of <italic>Echerichia coli</italic> by dihydrostreptomycin</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Henry1">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Housewright</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1949</year>) <article-title>STUDIES ON STREPTOMYCIN VI. : The Effect of Streptomycin on the Metabolism of Multiplying Bacteria</article-title>. <source>Journal of bacteriology</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Paine1">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paine</surname><given-names>TF</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name> (<year>1953</year>) <article-title>The effect of streptomycin on oxygen uptake and viability of resting suspensions of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Franklin1">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Franklin T, Snow G (2005) Attack and defense: drug transport across cell walls and membranes. Biochemistry an Molecular Biology of Antimicrobial Drug Action. 6 ed. New York: Sringer Science+Business MEdia, Inc. pp. 121–134.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Umbreit1">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Umbreit</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1948</year>) <article-title>A site of action of streptomycin</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>177</volume>: <fpage>703</fpage>–<lpage>714</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053957-Wells1">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maddaus</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jechorek</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Role of anaerobic flora in the translocation of aerobic and facultatively anaerobic intestinal bacteria</article-title>. <source>Infection and immunity</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>2689</fpage>–<lpage>2694</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>