<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-15686</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Application of a Hybrid Forest Growth Model to Evaluate Climate Change Impacts on Productivity, Nutrient Cycling and Mortality in a Montane Forest Ecosystem</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Application of a Forest Model to Evaluate Climate Change Impacts</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Seely</surname>
<given-names>Brad</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Welham</surname>
<given-names>Clive</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Scoullar</surname>
<given-names>Kim</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Forest Resources Management, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Life Sciences Programming Incorporated, Naramata, British Columbia, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Silva</surname>
<given-names>Lucas C.R.</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of California Davis, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>One of the authors (KS) is employed by Life Sciences Programming, Inc. This does not alter the authors’ adherence to PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: BS CW KS. Performed the experiments: BS. Analyzed the data: BS CW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: KS. Wrote the paper: BS CW KS. Code development: KS BS.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">brad.seely@ubc.ca</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>12</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e0135034</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>10</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>16</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Seely et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<p>Climate change introduces considerable uncertainty in forest management planning and outcomes, potentially undermining efforts at achieving sustainable practices. Here, we describe the development and application of the FORECAST Climate model. Constructed using a hybrid simulation approach, the model includes an explicit representation of the effect of temperature and moisture availability on tree growth and survival, litter decomposition, and nutrient cycling. The model also includes a representation of the impact of increasing atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> on water use efficiency, but no direct CO<sub>2</sub> fertilization effect. FORECAST Climate was evaluated for its ability to reproduce the effects of historical climate on Douglas-fir and lodgepole pine growth in a montane forest in southern British Columbia, Canada, as measured using tree ring analysis. The model was subsequently used to project the long-term impacts of alternative future climate change scenarios on forest productivity in young and established stands. There was a close association between predicted sapwood production and measured tree ring chronologies, providing confidence that model is able to predict the relative impact of annual climate variability on tree productivity. Simulations of future climate change suggest a modest increase in productivity in young stands of both species related to an increase in growing season length. In contrast, results showed a negative impact on stemwood biomass production (particularly in the case of lodgepole pine) for established stands due to increased moisture stress mortality.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This study was supported by the Future Forest Ecosystems Scientific Council (FFESC) of British Columbia (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.for.gov.bc.ca/hfp/future_forests/council/index.htm" xlink:type="simple">https://www.for.gov.bc.ca/hfp/future_forests/council/index.htm</ext-link>) (to BS), Cumulative Environmental Management Association (CEMA) of Alberta, Canada (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cemaonline.ca/index.php/about-us" xlink:type="simple">http://www.cemaonline.ca/index.php/about-us</ext-link>) (to CW), Alberta Environment (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://esrd.alberta.ca/" xlink:type="simple">http://esrd.alberta.ca/</ext-link>) (to CW), Life Sciences Programming (to KS). Other than Life Sciences Programming, the funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. Life Sciences Programming, on the other hand, provided support in the form of salaries for author KS, but did not have any additional role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. The specific roles of the authors are articulated in the ‘author contributions’ section.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="14"/>
<table-count count="4"/>
<page-count count="25"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Worldwide, forest health and productivity are being affected by anthropogenic climate change. The frequency and intensity of catastrophic natural disturbance agents, for example, are rising [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Moreover, evidence suggests that unusually severe drought events have triggered a significant rise in mortality rates in forested regions throughout the world [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Climate change is expected to influence long-term forest productivity through its effect on moisture availability [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], temperature-limited net photosynthetic rates [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and nutrient cycling [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. After litter quality, temperature and soil moisture are the key determinants of heterotrophic respiration and nutrient mineralization rates in temperate forests [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p>
<p>Efforts at modeling the impact of climate on forests can be divided into three broad categories: dynamic global vegetation models (DGVMs), statistical models derived from climate envelope analysis, and stand-level, process-based models. The overall objective of DGVMs is to evaluate the influence of climate on the biogeochemical and hydrological processes regulating vegetation growth dynamics [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Although they can be detailed with respect to process simulation, these models are designed to predict general patterns of vegetation development over large spatial and temporal scales [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and have limited application for evaluating alternative forest adaptation strategies (see, for example, [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]). In general, DGVMs may be best suited to evaluating the impact of changing climate regimes on regional patterns of forest productivity and hydrology.</p>
<p>Models based on the climate envelope approach rely on detailed statistical analyses of historical climate data collected from a species’ observed range. Deviations from climate normals are calculated for future climate scenarios and then used to project changes in growth rates, mortality, and species distributions. Examples include a modified version of the Forest Vegetation Simulator (FVS) model [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and adjustments to site index based on anticipated changes in growing-degree days [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The strength of this approach is that it provides a method for predicting climate change impacts with relatively small calibration data requirements. Challenges with the approach include, 1) limited insight with respect to the underlying mechanisms of response, 2) an assumption that current species distributions are dictated exclusively by climate, and 3) the issue that if the range of variation in future climate exceeds the historical climate regime then applications of the model are beyond the scope of its statistical foundations.</p>
<p>The third category of model is the stand-level, process-based models. These models employ physiological and physical principles in conjunction with simulated edaphic conditions to project forest development and productivity under a changing climate. They vary widely in their complexity and application, from comprehensive, research-oriented ecosystem models (e.g. Ecosys; [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]) to less complex, management-oriented models such as CABALA [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] to relatively simplified models designed for broad application such as 3PG [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The more complex models can be difficult to calibrate because they usually comprise many site and species-specific parameters. This can necessitate expensive, multi-year field research programs to support their application (e.g. [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]). Highly simplified process models usually have lower calibration requirements but they often cannot adequately address the complexity of forest management in the face of climate change. A compromise approach is embodied in ‘hybrid’ process-based models, in which empirical data inputted to the model are used to ‘self-calibrate’ at least some of the algorithm parameters associated with ecosystem processes (see [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]). This makes it possible to retain adequate model complexity while minimizing the calibration load [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p>
<p>Climate change introduces considerable uncertainty into forest management planning and outcomes, potentially undermining efforts at achieving sustainable practices [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. There is a need for models capable of projecting the potential impact of climate change on long-term patterns of forest growth and development while being reasonably accessible to forest managers. Ideally, such models should: 1) be capable of representing the effects of climate change on forest productivity and drought-related mortality, 2) include the ability to simulate a variety of forest management options to allow for an evaluation of adaptive management strategies, 3) provide broad outputs relevant to multi-objective forest management, and 4) be relatively straightforward to calibrate.</p>
<p>Here we describe the development and application of the hybrid simulation model FORECAST Climate. The model is evaluated with respect to its ability to reproduce the effects of historic annual climate variability on the annual variation of Douglas-fir and lodgepole pine growth in a montane forest located in southern British Columbia, Canada as measured using tree ring analysis. Simulations of the long-term impacts of alternative future climate change scenarios on forest productivity in young and established stands were conducted with the verified model.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>2.1. Model Description</title>
<p>FORECAST Climate was developed as an extension of FORECAST [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] which is a stand-level, management-oriented forest growth simulator. FORECAST was designed to accommodate a wide variety of harvesting and silvicultural systems in order to compare and contrast their effect upon forest productivity, stand dynamics and a series of biophysical indicators of non-timber stand values. The model has been used in a wide variety of applications and has been evaluated against field data for growth, yield, ecophysiological and soil variables [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p>
<p>FORECAST is a ‘hybrid’ model and many of its parameters are calibrated using historical bioassay data inputted to the model. As with any model of this type, a fundamental assumption with respect to its successful calibration and application is that the past climate regime constitutes a faithful representation of future climate conditions. The validity of this assumption is now questionable given anticipated trends in greenhouse gas emissions and their associated impacts on future temperature and precipitation patterns [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The FORECAST model simulates the effect of light and nutrient availability on forest productivity but it has no explicit representation of moisture or temperature on ecosystem processes. Thus, the rationale in developing FORECAST Climate was to incorporate these two factors. The foundation for FORECAST Climate was established through the creation of a dynamic linkage with a forest hydrology model including direct feedback to the core processes driving forest ecosystem production.</p>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>2.1.1. The basic FORECAST model</title>
<p>In FORECAST, the rates of key ecosystem processes are combined with data describing rates of decomposition, nutrient cycling, light competition, and other ecosystem properties to simulate annual changes in forest growth (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). Plant populations can be initiated from seed and/or vegetatively, and stand development can occur with or without competition from non-target tree species and understory populations. Decomposition and dead organic matter dynamics are simulated using a method in which specific biomass components (eg. foliage, fine roots, branches, etc.) are transferred at the time of tissue death to one of a series of independent litter types. Residual litter mass and its associated nutrient content are transferred to active and passive humus pools when the mass remaining is within 15–20% of the original litter mass. Typically, mean residence times for active and passive humus types are 50 and 600 years, respectively. See [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] for further details.</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Schematic illustration of the key ecosystem processes and flows represented in FORECAST (after [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]).</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>2.1.2. The ForWaDy Model</title>
<p>The Forest Water Dynamics (ForWaDy; [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]) model simulates the hydrologic dynamics of a forest stand on a daily time step for a given set of climatic and vegetation conditions. The model was specifically designed with a structure to facilitate its linkage to FORECAST [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. It has been shown to perform well for predicting the effect of forest management on evapotranspiration [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and temporal patterns in soil moisture content under field conditions [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The model represents potential evapotranspiration (PET) using an energy balance approach based on a modified version of the Priestly-Taylor equation [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. This equation is effective in predicting evapotranspiration under a wide variety of forest types and conditions [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Net shortwave solar radiation interception is used to drive the PET calculations. It is calculated for each tree and plant species from a light competition submodel built into FORECAST (see [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]) and surface albedo. ForWaDy includes a representation of the vertical flow of water through canopy and soil layer compartments (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Movement of water through each soil layer is regulated by its physical properties that dictate moisture holding capacity, permanent wilting point moisture content, and infiltration rate.</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Schematic diagram of the ForWaDy model indicating water flow pathways and storage compartments.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Water stress is calculated for each species separately on a daily time step and is expressed as a transpiration deficit index (TDI). The TDI is the relative difference between potential energy-limited transpiration demand and actual transpiration:
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e001">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e001g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M1" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>TDI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CanT</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Demand</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CanT</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Actual</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CanT</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Demand</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(1)</label>
</disp-formula>
where:</p>
<p>CanT<sub>Demand, i,d</sub> = energy-driven transpiration demand for species <italic>i</italic> (mm) on day <italic>d</italic>, as a function of leaf area index, intercepted short-wave radiation, canopy albedo, and canopy resistance,</p>
<p>CanT<sub>Actual, i,d</sub> = actual tree transpiration for species <italic>i</italic> (mm) on day <italic>d</italic>, as a function of CanT<sub>Demand i,d</sub>, root occupancy, and available soil moisture.</p>
<p>A detailed description of the ForWaDy model is provided in the <xref rid="pone.0135034.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 File</xref>. Its general data requirements are listed in <xref rid="pone.0135034.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0135034.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>General data requirements for the ForWaDy model.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Climate data (daily)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetation data</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest floor &amp; soil data</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean, max and min air temperature (°C)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">seasonal conifer and hardwood LAI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fine litter mass (kg/ha)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">solar radiation<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>1</sup></xref> (MJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">seasonal understory % cover</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">humus layer depth (cm) and bulk density (g/cm<sup>3</sup>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">total precipitation (mm)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rooting depths for trees (cm)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">depth of mineral soil layers (cm)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">snow fraction</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rooting depths for understory (cm)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">soil texture<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>3</sup></xref> (by layer)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">atmospheric [CO<sub>2</sub>]<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>2</sup></xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">canopy resistance and albedo (by species)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">coarse fragment content (% by layer)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p><sup>1</sup> Solar radiation may be estimated from max and min air temperature, elevation, latitude, slope and aspect using published radiation models.</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p><sup>2</sup> Only annual data required.</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn003"><p><sup>3</sup> Standard texture classes used to estimate clay content.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>2.1.3. Simulating the effect of increasing CO2 on forest growth</title>
<p>Higher atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations (c<sub>a</sub>) are associated with lower stomatal water vapour conductance [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and greater water use efficiency [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. These processes are represented in ForWaDy using a function that modifies canopy resistance in each species in relation to projected changes in c<sub>a</sub> [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The functional curve is derived from the physiological relationship between relative net assimilation rate and changes in c<sub>a</sub> relative to a reference atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<xref rid="pone.0135034.e002" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 2A</xref>). The impact of c<sub>a</sub> on stomatal conductance is given in <xref rid="pone.0135034.e002" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 2B</xref> [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], and stomatal conductance in relation to canopy resistance in <xref rid="pone.0135034.e004" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 3</xref> (see <xref rid="pone.0135034.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3B</xref>, for an example).
<fig id="pone.0135034.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Relationships between atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (c<sub>a</sub>) and (A) relative stomatal conductance and (B) canopy resistance.</title>
<p>(A) Observations of relative stomatal conductance of water vapour (g<sub>w(rel)</sub>) under changing atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations (c<sub>a</sub>; data from [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] re-plotted). The solid line is derived from <xref rid="pone.0135034.e003" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 2B</xref> where c<sub>a(rel)</sub> = c<sub>a</sub>/c<sub>a0</sub>, c<sub>a0</sub> is 360 ppm, and An<sub>(rel)</sub> is obtained from <xref rid="pone.0135034.e002" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 2A</xref>. (B) An example of the calculation of adjusted canopy resistance (R<sub>Can,adj</sub>) as a function of c<sub>a</sub>, using a reference canopy resistance (R<sub>Can,ref</sub>) value of 0.3.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e002">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e002g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M2" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>rel</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.1em"/><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.1em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(2A)</label>
</disp-formula>
where:</p>
<p>A<sub>n(rel)</sub> = relative net assimilation rate</p>
<p>c<sub>a</sub> = current atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (ppm)</p>
<p>c<sub>a0</sub> = reference atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (determined from reference climate data, ppm)</p>
<p>r’ = CO<sub>2</sub> compensation point = 40 ppm</p>
<p>and the relative stomatal conductance for water vapour (g<sub>w(rel)</sub>; dimensionless) is
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e003">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e003g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M3" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>w</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>rel</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>rel</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>rel</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(2B)</label>
</disp-formula>
where:</p>
<p>c<sub>a(rel)</sub> = relative atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> conc = c<sub>a</sub>/c<sub>a0</sub> (dimensionless)</p>
<p>Adjusted canopy resistance (R<sub>Can,adj</sub>; dimensionless) is
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e004">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e004g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M4" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Can</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>adj</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Can</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>ref</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Can</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>ref</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.1em"/><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>w</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>rel</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(3)</label>
</disp-formula>
where:</p>
<p>R<sub>Can,ref</sub> = reference canopy resistance (dimensionless)</p>
<p>Many models incorporate a representation of the direct effect of CO<sub>2</sub> fertilization on tree growth [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] based on evidence from short-term studies [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. There is little evidence, however, supporting the long-term impacts of CO<sub>2</sub> fertilization on forest growth [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. As such, the FORECAST Climate model does not presently include this as a control on growth.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>2.1.4. Linkage of FORECAST and ForWaDy</title>
<p>The ForWaDy—FORECAST linkage couples forest water availability directly with ecosystem process simulation. Furthermore, this linkage is dynamic in that the respective functions from each model are continuously updated in response to the iterative sharing of information encoded within a series of feedback loops (see <xref rid="pone.0135034.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). One aspect of this linkage is reconciling FORECAST’s annual time step with the daily time step used in ForWaDy, the latter of which is required to properly capture short-term moisture limitations. This was accomplished by aggregating the daily ForWaDy output into an annual index that was then used as input to FORECAST (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). FORECAST, in turn, supplies input to ForWaDy at the beginning of each growing season with respect to vegetation and forest floor conditions (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>A schematic diagram illustrating feedback loops and data transfer pathways between FORECAST and ForWaDy.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>2.1.5. Accounting for climate impacts on productivity</title>
<p>The impact of climate on tree and plant growth in FORECAST Climate is focused primarily on the relationships between growth rate, temperature and water stress. These relationships are represented using species-specific, curvilinear response functions simulated on a daily time step. The net daily growth response index of species i on day d (GRIDay,i,d) is derived as the product of two indices, calculated as temperature and water stress response functions:
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e005">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e005g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M5" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>GRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Day</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Growth</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.1em"/><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Growth</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(4)</label>
</disp-formula>
where:</p>
<p>T<sub>Growth,i,d</sub> = The temperature response index (range 0–1; dimensionless) for species <italic>i</italic> on day <italic>d</italic>. Specified in the model as a user-defined graphical function of daily mean air temperature (see Section <xref rid="sec014" ref-type="sec">2.2.3</xref>).</p>
<p>S<sub>Growth,i,d</sub> = The water stress response index (range 0–1; dimensionless) for species <italic>i</italic> on day <italic>d</italic>. Specified in the model as a user-defined graphical function of the daily mean water stress index (see Section <xref rid="sec014" ref-type="sec">2.2.3</xref>).</p>
<p>The temperature response index is designed to encapsulate the complex physiological growth processes governing tree and understory response to variations in mean daily temperature. It is intended to represent net effect of variations in temperature on primary productivity (NPP) by accounting for the impact of temperature on both photosynthesis and respiration. Data for calibrating the index can be derived from greenhouse studies and/or <italic>in situ</italic> measurements of seasonal primary productivity (eddy covariance, for example; see [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]).</p>
<p>The water stress response index is calculated from TDI (see section <xref rid="sec005" ref-type="sec">2.1.2</xref>). The daily TDI value represents the degree to which a species was able to meet its energy-driven transpiration demands (a higher TDI value indicates greater moisture stress). Plants typically respond to water stress by closing stomata to conserve water, leading to an associated reduction in photosynthetic production (see [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]). A negative relationship between S<sub>Growth</sub> and TDI is therefore expected.</p>
<p>The net daily growth response index is summed to calculate an annual growth response index for year, <italic>y</italic> (GRI<sub>Year,i,y</sub>; <xref rid="pone.0135034.e006" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 5</xref>).
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e006">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e006g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e006" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M6" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>GRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Year</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>365</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mtext>GRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Day</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(5)</label>
</disp-formula>
</p>
<p>This index is used as a weighting factor that reflects the ‘quality’ of a given climate year relative to an expected growth rate (further details below).</p>
<p>The climate response functions within FORECAST Climate are calibrated using historical daily climate data. A ‘reference’ daily climate series must be compiled with data derived from a climate station near the forest area to be modeled, and should span a minimum 20-year time period. A summary of the climate data required is provided in <xref rid="pone.0135034.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<p>Using the reference data set, a calibration run is conducted from which the annual growth response index is calculated (<xref rid="pone.0135034.e006" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 5</xref>). By averaging the annual values for the length of the reference climate period, a normalized growth response index is derived for each species (<xref rid="pone.0135034.e007" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 6</xref>) that reflects growth conditions in an average historical climate year. This index is used in subsequent calculations.
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e007">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e007g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e007" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M7" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>NGRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mtext>GRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Year</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(6)</label>
</disp-formula>
where:</p>
<p>NGRI<sub>,i</sub> is the normalized growth rate index for species <italic>i</italic> derived from the reference climate data set (dimensionless)</p>
<p>GRI <sub>Year,i,y</sub> is the annual growth response index for species <italic>i</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0135034.e006" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 5</xref>).</p>
<p>n = the number of years in the historical climate data set</p>
<p>Simulation of growth response to climate in FORECAST Climate is achieved by modifying base growth rates (as determined in the underlying FORECAST model–section 2.1.1) according to the climate relationships described in section 2.1.4. A climate-limited growth rate is calculated by multiplying the base growth rate (<xref rid="pone.0135034.e008" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 7A</xref>) by a climate response factor (<xref rid="pone.0135034.e009" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 7B</xref>).
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e008">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e008g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e008" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M8" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CGR</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>BGR</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CRF</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(7A)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e009">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e009g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e009" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M9" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CRF</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>GRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Year</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>NGRI</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>NGRI</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(7B)</label>
</disp-formula>
where:</p>
<p>CGR<sub>,i,y</sub> is the climate-limited growth rate for species <italic>i</italic> in year <italic>y</italic> (tons ha<sup>-1</sup>),</p>
<p>BGR<sub>,i,y</sub> = the base growth rate for species <italic>i</italic> and year <italic>y</italic> determined in FORECAST as the light and nutrient-limited growth rate (tons ha<sup>-1</sup>),</p>
<p>CRF<sub>,i,y</sub> is the climate response factor for species <italic>i</italic> in year <italic>y</italic> (dimensionless), and GRIyear<sub>i,y</sub> and NGRI<sub>i</sub> are as defined in Eqs <xref rid="pone.0135034.e006" ref-type="disp-formula">5</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0135034.e007" ref-type="disp-formula">6</xref>, respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>2.1.6. Climate and decomposition rates</title>
<p>The decomposition of dead organic matter in FORECAST is represented based upon user-defined mass loss rates associated with litter quality and derived from field incubation experiments. A maximum of 40 dead organic matter types may be defined and simulated within the model [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In FORECAST Climate, decomposition rates are modified by soil moisture content and air temperature with the calculation of a daily decomposition response index (<xref rid="pone.0135034.e010" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 8</xref>). The model does not include any representation of the potential effects of mixing different litter types on mass loss rates.
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e010">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e010g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e010" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M10" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>DRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Day</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Decomp</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>M</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Decomp</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(8)</label>
</disp-formula>
where:</p>
<p>DRI<sub>Day,l,d</sub> = daily decomposition response index (range 0–1; dimensionless) for soil layer <italic>l</italic> on day <italic>d</italic></p>
<p>T<sub>Decomp,d</sub> = Temperature decomposition response (range 0–1; dimensionless). Specified in the model as a user-defined graphical function of daily mean air temperature (see <xref rid="pone.0135034.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>).</p>
<p>M<sub>Decomp,l,d</sub> = Moisture decomposition response (range 0–1; dimensionless). Specified in the model as a user-defined graphical function of daily moisture content (see <xref rid="pone.0135034.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title>Daily decomposition index in relation to (A) daily air temperature, and (B) relative daily moisture content.</title>
<p>(A) The realtionship with mean daily air temperature is based upon a Q<sub>10</sub> function where Q<sub>10</sub> = 2. (B) Moisture content relationships are shown for litter, humus, and mineral soil (see text for details).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Assuming moisture is not a limiting factor, the decomposition rate of dead organic matter is generally faster in warmer environments [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The default temperature response function is shown in <xref rid="pone.0135034.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>, and is based upon a Q<sub>10</sub> factor of 2 [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The moisture response functions for litter, humus, and soil, are shown in <xref rid="pone.0135034.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>.</p>
<p>The climate impact on decomposition rates is represented using the same procedure as the growth response index calculation (section 2.1.5). First, a normalized decomposition response index (NDRI<sub><italic>l</italic></sub>) is calculated for each soil layer <italic>l</italic> using the reference climate series:
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e011">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e011g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e011" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M11" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>NDRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mtext>DRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Year</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(9)</label>
</disp-formula>
where:</p>
<p>NDRI<sub>,l</sub> is the normalized decomposition response index for layer <italic>l</italic> derived from the climate calibration data (dimensionless)</p>
<p>DRI <sub>Year,l,y</sub> is the summed annual decomposition response index for each soil layer <italic>l</italic></p>
<p>n = the number of years in the reference climate data set</p>
<p>A climate decomposition factor (CDF<sub>x,y</sub>; <xref rid="pone.0135034.e012" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 10A</xref>) is then calculated as the relative difference between the current and normalized decomposition response indices (<xref rid="pone.0135034.e011" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 9</xref>). Climate feedback is represented by a climate decomposition rate index (CDR<sub>,l,y</sub>) for each soil layer <italic>l</italic> and year <italic>y</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0135034.e013" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 10B</xref>).
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e012">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e012g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e012" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M12" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CDF</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>x</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.1em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>DRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Year</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>NDRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>NDRI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(10A)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pone.0135034.e013">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.e013g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.e013" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M13" overflow="scroll">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CDR</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>x</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.1em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>BDR</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>x</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CDF</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>x</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(10B)</label>
</disp-formula>
where:</p>
<p>CDF<sub>x,y</sub> is the climate decomposition factor for litter type <italic>x</italic> in year <italic>y</italic> (dimensionless)</p>
<p>DRI<sub>Year,l,y</sub> and NDRI,<sub>l</sub>, are as defined above (<xref rid="pone.0135034.e011" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 9</xref>),</p>
<p>CDR<sub>,x,y</sub> is the expected climate decomposition rate for litter type <italic>x</italic> and year <italic>y</italic> (tons ha<sup>-1</sup>)</p>
<p>BDR<sub>,x,y</sub> is the base decomposition rate for litter type <italic>x</italic> in year <italic>y</italic> determined as a function of litter quality (tons ha<sup>-1</sup>)</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>2.1.7. Representation of drought-related mortality</title>
<p>Extended periods of drought can lead to plant mortality, either directly or by increasing vulnerability to biotic disturbance agents [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. FORECAST Climate includes a drought mortality function in which a two-year running-average TDI is used to predict annual mortality. The two-year running average reflects the negative impact of consecutive years of drought (see, for example, [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]). The drought mortality relationship is specified in the model as a user-defined graphical function of species-specific, two-year running average TDI (see Section <xref rid="sec014" ref-type="sec">2.2.3</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>2.2. Evaluating model performance using tree-ring analysis</title>
<p>FORECAST Climate was calibrated for a montane forest in south central British Columbia. The model was used to predict annual sapwood production (a proxy measure of tree ring growth), which was then compared against measured 30-year ring chronologies.</p>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>2.2.1. Study area</title>
<p>The study area was located in south central British Columbia, Canada near the city of Kamloops (50°40'00" N, 120°20'00" W), and is classified as a dry cool subzone of the Interior Douglas-fir biogeoclimatic zone [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. The site, located in crown-owned forest land, is dominated by stands of interior Douglas-fir (<italic>Pseudotsuga mensziesii</italic> var. <italic>glauca</italic>) and lodgepole pine (<italic>Pinus contorta</italic>). Theses species are common in montane regions in the southern interior of British Columbia, ranging from 900 to 1400m in elevation. The closest local climate station with a complete climate record (Red Lake: Elevation = 1162m, 50°56’06” N, 120°48’00” W) was selected from which 30 years of daily data (spanning the years 1975–2004) were obtained. Average monthly temperature and precipitation for Red Lake are shown in <xref rid="pone.0135034.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g006</object-id>
<label>Fig 6</label>
<caption>
<title>Average monthly temperature and precipitation from the Red Lake climate station (1975–2004).</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>2.2.2. Tree-ring analysis</title>
<p>A total of 5 plots were randomly selected from a series of candidate stands identified using forest inventory data from the study site. Plots were split with 3 Douglas-fir and 2 lodgepole pine-dominated stands. Stands with clear signs of fire scars or damage from biotic agents that could have masked a climate signal were avoided. Plot centers were established using a variable radius to define plot area such that a total of 20 dominant and/or co-dominant trees were identified within the plot area. Species, elevation, slope, aspect, and slope position were recorded for each plot. The stands ranged in age from 36 to 150 years (<xref rid="pone.0135034.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0135034.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Characteristics of sample plot locations from which trees were harvested for tree-ring analysis and chronology statistics.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.t002g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plot ID</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AverageAge (y)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevation (m)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope(%)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspect (deg.)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope Position</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean sensitivity</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serial correlation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fd</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1250</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mid</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.288</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.836</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fd</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">978</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mid</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.275</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.812</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fd</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1125</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mid</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.812</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pl</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1300</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.946</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pl</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1356</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">322</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flat</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.159</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.846</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>A total of 20 trees per plot were sampled. Fd = Douglas fir, Pl = lodgepole pine.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Within each plot, a total of 20 dominant or co-dominant trees were cut down and a slice (cookie) approximately 4 cm thick removed from the base of each stem, within 20 cm of the soil surface. The cookies were prepared for analysis in the Tree-Ring Laboratory at the University of Northern British Columbia, using standard procedures [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Annual tree ring width was measured to the nearest 0.01mm using a Windendro system. The ARSTAN software [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] was used to prepare and cross-date the final chronologies. All series were de-trended by fitting a spline of 50% frequency response across 67% of the series length to remove the low frequency age trend. Slight modifications were made to spline stiffness for two of the series to improve their fit to the data. De-trended data were used to isolate the impacts of year-to-year climate variability on relative tree productivity. Chronologies for each plot were constructed using the final ARSTAN tree ring index. Each chronology was restricted to the 1975–2004 period and normalized by dividing by the average ring index. Typically, tree rings are compared against two consecutive years of climate data (current and previous year) [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. This is because early season wood growth is partly a function of climate suitability in the previous year and its impact on carbohydrate reserves [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>2.2.3. FORECAST Climate calibration</title>
<p>Detailed descriptions of FORECAST calibration data requirements are provided in [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The base FORECAST model was calibrated with an existing data set from the Interior Douglas-fir dry cool subzone [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. The data set includes both Douglas-fir and lodgepole pine, and two minor vegetation functional groups (grasses and shrubs) common to the area. Calibration of the climate response functions in FORECAST Climate is described in the following sections.</p>
<p>The hydrological submodel requires data describing characteristics of the soil profile (<xref rid="pone.0135034.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) and characteristics of simulated trees and minor vegetation with respect to the calculation of daily evapotranspiration and water stress (<xref rid="pone.0135034.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Average soil characteristics were inferred from soil pits dug in each of the plots.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0135034.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Parameter values in the hydrological submodel specific to the simulation of plant-available water within soil layers.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.t003g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil layer</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil Texture Class</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coarse Fragment Content (%)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil Depth<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>1</sup></xref> (cm)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field Capacity Moisture Content <xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>2</sup></xref></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Humus</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mineral A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silt loam</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mineral B</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silt loam</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mineral C</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silt loam</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p><sup>1</sup> The starting humus depth is shown, but humus depth can change over time depending on rates production and decomposition.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p><sup>2</sup> Volumetric water content above which drainage occurs.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0135034.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>Parameter values in the hydrological submodel specific to the simulation of evapotranspiration and water stress for trees and minor vegetation.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0135034.t004g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th>
<th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Canopy Parameters</th>
<th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Permanent Wilting Point<xref rid="t004fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>3</sup></xref></th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum Root Depth</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albedo<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>1</sup></xref></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resistance<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>2</sup></xref></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Humus</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mineral Soil</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(cm)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Trees</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Douglas-fir</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lodgepole pine</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Minor vegetation</italic></bold></td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Calamagrostis</italic> grass</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vaccinium</italic> shrub</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p><sup>1</sup> Estimated values.</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn002"><p><sup>2</sup> Reference relative canopy resistance to water loss through stomata (R<sub>Can,i</sub>) [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Higher values indicate greater resistance.</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn003"><p><sup>3</sup> Relative volumetric moisture content (proportion of total volume) at which soil water uptake is suspended [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>].</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Calibration of the climate response functions was completed as follows. Daily temperature and water-stress growth response curves were developed for Douglas-fir [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] and lodgepole pine [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] based upon literature reviews of climate-growth relationships (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7A and 7B</xref>). The sharp increase in growth beginning around 5°C for both species is indicative of the heat sum required to break dormancy. Each curve varies with respect to the optimal temperature range for growth and the relative rate of decline beyond the optimum, depending on a plant’s tolerance characteristics. The decline at higher temperatures represents the increase in respiration associated with elevated temperatures [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g007" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g007</object-id>
<label>Fig 7</label>
<caption>
<title>Climate response functions showing the effect of temperature and water stress on growth (A,B) and mortality (C).</title>
<p>(A) Relationships between mean daily temperature and the T<sub>growth</sub> parameter, and (B) daily water stress and S<sub>growth</sub> parameter used in <xref rid="pone.0135034.e005" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 4</xref>. (C) The drought-related mortality rate as a function of the 2-year running average water stress index.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>A relative drought mortality curve was developed for each tree species based on its ecological characteristics within the subzone (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7C</xref>). Douglas-fir was assumed to be slightly more tolerant of drought stress relative to lodgepole pine. Each species-specific mortality function was evaluated using provincial forest health survey data (not shown) to verify that it produced realistic mortality projections when the model was run with the historical reference climate data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>2.2.4. Growth simulation using historical climate data</title>
<p>To evaluate the capability of FORECAST Climate to reproduce the measured, climate-related annual variation in tree ring growth, the model was run using the historical climate data from the period of 1975–2004. The 30-year climate data set was cycled 5 times to generate 150 years of daily data. Model projections of annual sapwood production were subsequently compared against the normalized tree ring indices for the corresponding climate years using regression analysis. However, because annual ring growth is fueled both by carbohydrates stored from the previous year and the current year’s production, each ring index was compared against a normalized average of the previous and current year’s simulated sapwood production.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>2.3. Simulation of long-term climate change impacts</title>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>2.3.1. Development of climate change scenarios</title>
<p>To illustrate the potential of FORECAST Climate to simulate the impacts of climate on the growth and development of forests within the study area, climate change projections were derived from two established general circulation models (GCMs) included as part of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change AR5 analysis [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], HadGem2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.enes.org/models/earthsystem-models/metoffice-hadley-centre/hadgem2-es" xlink:type="simple">www.enes.org/models/earthsystem-models/metoffice-hadley-centre/hadgem2-es</ext-link>) and CanESM2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cccma.ec.gc.ca/data/cgcm4/CanESM2/rcp45/index.shtml" xlink:type="simple">www.cccma.ec.gc.ca/data/cgcm4/CanESM2/rcp45/index.shtml</ext-link>). A medium range emissions pathway was selected for the two models (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8A</xref>). It is based on a representative CO<sub>2</sub> concentration pathway that generates a radiative forcing of 4.5 Wm<sup>-2</sup> (RCP 4.5, [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]). These models and scenario were selected to be representative of the middle of the range of potential climate change scenarios. It should be noted that other scenarios could generate different results. Atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration for the reference climate scenario was constrained to 2005 values (380 ppm). The regional monthly output from the GCMs for the 2020s, 2050s and 2080s was downscaled to daily data using a direct approach based upon the Red Lake daily climate data series from the years 1975–2004. The resulting data set spanned a 100-year period (2012–2111). Projected changes in mean growing season temperature and precipitation are shown in <xref rid="pone.0135034.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8B and 8C</xref>. Mean growing season temperature is predicted to increase from approximately 12.5°C in 2013 to 16–17°C by 2111. In contrast, both GCMs predicted only a very gradual declining trend in growing season precipitation during the same period. It should be noted that the interannual variability in temperature and precipitation characteristic of the base reference data is retained as a result of the direct downscaling process.</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g008" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g008</object-id>
<label>Fig 8</label>
<caption>
<title>Reference climate data and projected atmospheric [CO<sub>2</sub>] (A), growing season temperature (B), and precipitation (C).</title>
<p>(A) Projected increase in atmospheric [CO<sub>2</sub>] (c<sub>a</sub>) for the RCP 4.5 emissions scenario, (B) projected growing season (MAY–SEP) mean daily air temperature, and (C) projected total growing season precipitation for the next 100 years based on two downscaled climate change projections (see text). Lines represent the 10-year moving average for each series in panels B and C.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>2.3.2. Model application for climate change simulation</title>
<p>FORECAST Climate was used to simulate the long-term impact of climate change on stand growth and development for both Douglas-fir-dominated and lodgepole pine-dominated stand types. Growth in newly planted (age = 1 year) and established stands (starting age = 60 years) was simulated for a 100-year period. In the newly planted stands, the climate began to change immediately (see <xref rid="pone.0135034.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>). For established stands, however, the 30-year historical climate data were copied and appended to create 60 years of data before the climate change period began at age 61. A total of eight runs were completed (2 climate scenarios * 2 species * 2 age classes).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec020">
<title>3.1. Model evaluation against tree ring data</title>
<p>Sapwood production predictions were concordant with 48% to 73% of the variation in measured annual ring widths in 4 of the 5 plots (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>). One Douglas-fir plot (Plot #9) showed no significant correlation with the other plots suggesting that annual variation in tree growth in this plots was likely a consequence of factors other than climate. This plot was therefore excluded from subsequent analysis. The average slopes of the regression lines were 1.04 and 1.05, for the remaining Douglas-fir (#4 &amp; #14) and pine (#71 &amp; #34) plots, respectively.</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g009" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g009</object-id>
<label>Fig 9</label>
<caption>
<title>Comparison of the simulated sapwood production index with the measured ring width index.</title>
<p>Data are shown for Douglas-fir (Fd) and lodgepole pine (Pl) plots for the 30-year climate reference period. Average tree age is shown for each plot.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec021">
<title>3.2. Climate change impacts on tree growth</title>
<p>Both climate change scenarios had a net positive impact on growth rates for newly planted stands, as indicated by the climate response factor (CRF, <xref rid="pone.0135034.e008" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 7</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0135034.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig 10A</xref>). Ten-year running averages show that the CRF values under the historical (reference) climate oscillate around zero, while those for the climate change scenarios are consistently higher. The impact of climate change on stemwood biomass was generally positive for both tree species, except in pine stands 85 years and older (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig 10B</xref>). In Douglas-fir, stemwood biomass was 11 to 17% higher at rotation age (80 years), and 4 to 7% higher in pine. Climate change triggered more drought-related mortality (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig 10C</xref>), which was associated with an increase in both the frequency and intensity of water stress (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g011" ref-type="fig">Fig 11B and 11C</xref>). The increase in water stress in the climate change scenarios occurred despite an increase in canopy resistance associated with higher CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g011" ref-type="fig">Fig 11A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g010" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g010</object-id>
<label>Fig 10</label>
<caption>
<title>Impact of climate change on: (A) growth response (CRF), (B) stemwood biomass, and (C) drought-related mortality.</title>
<p>Simulations results for newly planted stands of Douglas-fir are shown on the left and for lodgepole pine on the right. Climate change simulation was initiated at year 1 of the simulation. Lines represent 10-year running averages of annual values. A CRF value near zero indicates that the simulated climate year was similar to the historical average year.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g011" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g011</object-id>
<label>Fig 11</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulated effect of c<sub>a</sub> on canopy resistance (A) and of climate change on tree water stress (B-C).</title>
<p>(A) Projected atmospheric [CO<sub>2</sub>] (c<sub>a</sub>) for the climate change scenarios is based on the RCP 4.5 emissions scenario while reference scenario levels were constrained at 2005 values (380 ppm). The impact of c<sub>a</sub> on canopy resistance (R<sub>Can,adj</sub>) is shown for both species and for both climate scenarios (see <xref rid="pone.0135034.e004" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 3</xref>). Lower panels show simulated water stress for newly planted stands of (B) Douglas-fir and (C) lodgepole pine. Water stress results represent the 10-year running averages of annual transpiration deficit index (TDI) values.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g011" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>In established (60 year-old) stands, the impact of climate change was projected to be positive in terms of the CRF (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g012" ref-type="fig">Fig 12A</xref>). This was not the case for stemwood biomass, however. For Douglas-fir, there was little difference among the historical and climate change scenarios, though biomass under the latter was lower when stands were very old (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g012" ref-type="fig">Fig 12B</xref>). In pine, however, climate change reduced stemwood biomass early in the simulation. This discrepancy became more pronounced over time. Lower stemwood biomass was associated with elevated drought-related mortality in both species but more so in pine (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g012" ref-type="fig">Fig 12C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g012" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g012</object-id>
<label>Fig 12</label>
<caption>
<title>The impact of climate change for on: (A) growth response (CRF), (B) stemwood biomass, and (C) drought-related mortality.</title>
<p>Simulation results for established (60 years old) stands of Douglas-fir are shown on the left and for lodgepole pine on the right. Climate change simulation was initiated at year 60 of the simulation. Lines represent 10-year running averages of annual values. A CRF value near zero indicates that the simulated climate year was similar to the historical average year.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g012" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Projected impacts in newly planted stands of the reference climate and climate change (CanESM2) scenarios on the daily growth response index are shown for three future climate periods (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g013" ref-type="fig">Fig 13</xref>). The daily growth response index (GRI<sub>Day</sub>) is determined as the product of the daily growth response to temperature (T<sub>Growth</sub>) and water stress (S<sub>Growth</sub>) (<xref rid="pone.0135034.e005" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 4</xref>) and is summed for the year to determine the annual growth response index (GRI<sub>Year</sub>). The model predicts a considerable lengthening of the temperature-limited growing season, as approximated by the number of calendar days where the value of T<sub>Growth</sub> ≥ 0.25 (data not shown). The average length of the temperature-limited growing season for both species increased by 42 days in the period from 2073–2102 relative to the reference period (1975–2004). The increase, however, was also accompanied by higher daily drought stress during the growing season leading to a mid-summer decline in average GRI<sub>Day</sub> (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g013" ref-type="fig">Fig 13</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g013" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g013</object-id>
<label>Fig 13</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulated impact of climate change on GRI<sub>Day</sub> for Douglas-fir (A) and lodgepole pine (B).</title>
<p>Results for mean daily growth response index (GRI<sub>Day</sub>) are shown for newly planted stands and reflect data from the 30-year historical time period (reference), and three sequential 30-year future climate periods (2013–2042, 2043–2072, and 2073–2102) based upon the CanESM2 climate scenario.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g013" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec022">
<title>3.3. Climate change impacts on decomposition</title>
<p>Over the first 30 years of the simulation, climate change led to reduced levels of litter mass due to increased mass loss rates (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g014" ref-type="fig">Fig 14A</xref>). Thereafter, total litter mass in the climate change scenarios increased to levels above that of the reference climate. Nitrogen (N) release was consistently higher under both climate change scenarios (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g014" ref-type="fig">Fig 14B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0135034.g014" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g014</object-id>
<label>Fig 14</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulated impact of climate change on (A) total litter mass, and (B) net N release.</title>
<p>Results are shown for established (60 years old at the start of the climate change simulation) Douglas-fir stands.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.g014" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec023" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="sec024">
<title>4.1. Model evaluation using tree-ring analysis</title>
<p>A variety of metrics have been useful in establishing the relationship between climate and plant productivity (see [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]). One metric used extensively is dendrochronology, in which changes in ring width are linked to annual variation in climate, particularly temperature and moisture [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Dendrochronology thus provides a means of assessing how well a forest model can project the impact of climate on plant performance (i.e., annual ring growth). If a model can successfully reproduce ring chronologies as a function of historical climate conditions, it should be reasonable to use these same relationships to predict the future growth response to a changing climate regime (see, for example, [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]).</p>
<p>Dendrochronological records indicate that, in general, annual tree growth in temperate regions tends to be more sensitive to variations in water stress than temperature [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. FORECAST Climate performed well in capturing the historical effect of climate on ring width indices in 4 of the 5 measured plots. Model output was consistent with years when measured radial growth rates were reduced due to water stress as well as years in which growth was above average.</p>
<p>The positive impacts of temperature on ring width were captured directly by FORECAST Climate as a lengthening of the growing season, and indirectly through the positive influence of enhanced nitrogen mineralization on site productivity.</p>
<p>One of the challenges in using tree ring data is that climate signals can be obscured by other factors that influence growth, such as abiotic and biotic disturbance agents, and competition for site resources from neighboring trees and/or other vegetation types [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. In our case, one of the two plots with lower R<sup>2</sup> values (Douglas-fir, plot #9; see <xref rid="pone.0135034.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) displayed unusual patterns whereby ring widths declined to near zero for a three-year period before returning to ‘normal’ levels (data not shown). The other Douglas-fir plots showed no such pattern suggesting that the decline was not climate related. Abrupt disruption and subsequent recovery in tree radial growth is indicative of insect attack. In Douglas-fir that might be from budworm or bark beetle [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Regardless of its source, the ring pattern was sufficiently skewed that it effectively obscured the climate signal.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec025">
<title>4.2. Effects of climate change on productivity and mortality</title>
<p>FORECAST Climate predicted an overall increases in annual growth rates under future climate conditions in both Douglas-fir and lodgepole pine (Figs <xref rid="pone.0135034.g010" ref-type="fig">10</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0135034.g012" ref-type="fig">12</xref>). An increase in growing season length was the dominant factor in this regard and served to counteract an increase in the frequency and intensity of summer moisture stress, the latter of which represented a downward pressure on growth (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g011" ref-type="fig">Fig 11</xref>). Summer moisture stress trended upwards under climate change despite simulated increases in canopy resistance associated with elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations (see <xref rid="pone.0135034.g011" ref-type="fig">Fig 11</xref>). [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] also reported an antagonistic effect of growing season length and moisture stress on forest productivity in the boreal forest. [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] found that Douglas-fir growth rates in warm-dry regions correlated well with annual precipitation while growth in populations from cooler and wetter regions was better correlated with temperature and other climatic variables. Summer moisture deficit was the key climatic factor limiting interior Douglas-fir growth rates in montane ecosystems in the northwestern US [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. In the Cascade Range, Washington, USA, [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] observed that growing season precipitation was the climate variable most strongly correlated with growth rates in mid-elevation lodgepole pine stands, indicating that summer water stress was a key limiting factor. They noted that temperature-regulated growing season length was the most important factor influencing growth rates in high elevation stands.</p>
<p>Higher drought-related mortality was predicted by FORECAST Climate in all climate change scenarios. This resulted in lower biomass production except for newly planted Douglas-fir stands. Established stands were vulnerable to the warmer and drier climate conditions due to a high leaf area. This is because older stands originated and developed under historical climate conditions, which can support a greater leaf area. The latter, however, is poorly adapted to an increasingly water-limited future environment. High evapotranspirational demand in older stands thus triggered widespread mortality during drought and a significant loss of live biomass. Although newly planted stands also incurred elevated mortality, the impact on long-term productivity was relatively low and surviving trees developed canopies with a lower leaf area. Finally, it should be noted that the intensity of predicted water stress declined after a mortality event. This was because mortality reduced stand leaf area (data not shown) resulting in a lower canopy water demand.</p>
<p>Evidence of increased drought-related mortality has been documented in forest ecosystems around the world [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Moreover, [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>] observed widespread growth decline despite increases in water use efficiency in temperate and boreal forests in a study combining standard dendrochronological techniques with isotopic analysis. The complex physiological response of vegetation to water stress, however, has made it difficult to represent accurately within forest ecosystem models [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Prolonged moisture stress increases mortality generally [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>] and both hydraulic failure and carbon starvation have been implicated as direct causal factors [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Trees suffering from water stress are also more vulnerable to abiotic and biotic disturbance, including fire and insect attack [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0135034.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. The water-stress mortality function employed in FORECAST Climate was designed to encapsulate both the direct and indirect aspects of drought-related mortality. It can be parameterized through an iterative process whereby modeled mortality derived using historical reference climate data is adjusted to achieve a reasonable match to measured rates.</p>
<p>It should be noted that the projections of the impact of climate change on long-term growth and productivity in these ecosystems do not include any impacts from extreme climate events nor the effect of climate on population dynamics of natural disturbance agents. Both of these factors have the potential to substantially impact forest productivity as the climate continues to change.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec026">
<title>4.3. Climate effects on decomposition and nutrient cycling</title>
<p>FORECAST Climate predicted a net increase in mass loss associated with litter decomposition over most years in the climate change scenarios and there was an increase in simulated litter mass over the long-term (<xref rid="pone.0135034.g014" ref-type="fig">Fig 14A</xref>). The latter was a result of the higher mortality rates that occurred under climate change relative to historical conditions (see Figs <xref rid="pone.0135034.g010" ref-type="fig">10C</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0135034.g012" ref-type="fig">12C</xref>). Though warmer temperatures had a positive impact on decomposition rates there were periods when litter water content was low, which exerted a downward pressure on rates. Nevertheless, the net increase in decomposition led to an associated increase in N mineralization and thus a positive benefit to tree productivity. [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] provided evidence that soil warming leads to pronounced increases in litter mass loss and net N mineralization rates. In an experimental manipulation of soil warming over 7-years, [<xref rid="pone.0135034.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>] showed enhanced biomass production relative to controls, which they attributed largely to increased N availability. The representation of such feedback loops in models is thus paramount to improving their capability to capture climate change impacts on forest growth and development.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec027">
<title>4.4. Hybrid modelling approach</title>
<p>FORECAST Climate employs a series of climate response functions to represent the impact of temperature and moisture stress on plant growth. The benefits of this approach are: 1) it represents a relatively simple and transparent approach to predicting the independent and combined effects of temperature and moisture stress on growth, 2) the shape of the response functions can be easily established and evaluated empirically, 3) it provides a convenient means of summarizing daily responses into annual indices, and 4) is easily calibrated using historical reference climate data. Further potential improvements to the model include a representation of the phenological responses of plants to climate, such as bud break or the onset of dormancy, and frost events.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec028">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0135034.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0135034.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 File</label>
<caption>
<title>A detailed description of the ForWaDy model, including key equations, algorithms, and references are provided within.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank Kathy Lewis for her assistance with the tree ring analysis conducted at the University of Northern British Columbia. We would also like to thank Hamish Kimmins for his guidance and inspiration.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dale</surname> <given-names>VH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joyce</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mcnulty</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neilson</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayres</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flannigan</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Climate change and forest disturbances</article-title>. <source>BioScience</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>723</fpage>–<lpage>734</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond-Lamberty</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peckham</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahl</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gower</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fire as the dominant driver of central Canadian boreal forest carbon balance</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>450</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17972883</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raffa</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aukema</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bentz</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hicke</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Cross-scale drivers of natural disturbances prone to anthropogenic amplification: the dynamics of bark beetle eruptions</article-title>. <source>Bioscience</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>517</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurz</surname> <given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dymond</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stinson</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rampley</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neilson</surname> <given-names>ET</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Mountain pine beetle and forest carbon feedback to climate change</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>452</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>–<lpage>990</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature06777" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature06777</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18432244</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macalady</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chenchouni</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bachele</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vennetier</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A global overview of drought and heat-induced tree mortality reveals emerging climate change risks for forests</article-title>. <source>For Ecol Manage</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>259</volume>: <fpage>660</fpage>–<lpage>684</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Mantgem</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephenson</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daniels</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franklin</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ful</surname> <given-names>E PZ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Widespread increase of tree mortality rates in the western United States</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>323</volume>: <fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1165000" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1165000</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19164752</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barber</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Juday</surname> <given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname> <given-names>BP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reduced growth of Alaskan white spruce in the twentieth century</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>405</volume>: <fpage>668</fpage>–<lpage>673</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10864320</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Running</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Drought-induced reduction in global terrestrial net primary production from 2000 through 2009</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>329</volume>: <fpage>940</fpage>–<lpage>943</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1192666" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1192666</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20724633</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemani</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keeling</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hashimoto</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jolly</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piper</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Climate driven increases in global terrestrial net primary production from 1982 to 1999</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>300</volume>: <fpage>1560</fpage>–<lpage>1563</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12791990</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McMahon</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname> <given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evidence for a recent increase in forest growth</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>E86</fpage>–<lpage>E87</lpage> 101073/pnas1002725107 <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20439700</object-id>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1002725107" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1002725107</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muraoka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Experimental warming studies on tree species and forest ecosystems: a literature review</article-title>. <source>J Plant Res</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>460</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10265-013-0565-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10265-013-0565-3</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23689840</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trofymow</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Titus</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prescott</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siltanen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Rates of litter decomposition over six years in Canadian forests: Influence of litter quality and climate</article-title>. <source>Can J For Res</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>789</fpage>–<lpage>804</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prescott</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blevins</surname> <given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staley</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Litter decomposition in BC forests: Controlling factors and influences of forestry activities</article-title>. <source>BC J Ecosys Manage</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kneeshaw</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larocque</surname> <given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>. <article-title>Drought-induced tree mortality: ecological consequences, causes and modeling</article-title>. <source>Enivron Rev</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quillet</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garneau</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Toward dynamic global vegetation models for simulating vegetation-climate interactions and feedbacks: recent developments, limitations, and future challenge</article-title>. <source>Environ Rev</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galbraith</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christoffersen</surname> <given-names>BO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imbuzeiro</surname> <given-names>HMA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rowland</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Confronting model predictions of carbon fluxes with measurements of Amazon forests subjected to experimental drought</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>200</volume>: <fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/nph.12390" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/nph.12390</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23844931</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crookston</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rehfeldt</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiskittel</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Addressing climate change in the forest vegetation simulator to assess impacts on landscape forest dynamics</article-title>. <source>For Ecol Manage</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>260</volume>: <fpage>1198</fpage>–<lpage>1211</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monserud</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tchebakova</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Potential change in lodgepole pine site index and distribution under climatic change in Alberta</article-title>. <source>Can J For Res</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaumont-Guaye</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Intercomparison of techniques to model water stress effects on CO<sub>2</sub> and energy exchange in temperate and boreal deciduous forests</article-title>. <source>Ecol Modell</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>196</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Battaglia</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sands</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mummery</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>A linked carbon, water and nitrogen model of forest growth for silvicultural decision support</article-title>. <source>For Ecol Manage</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>193</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landsberg</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waring</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name>. <article-title>A generalized model of forest productivity using simplified concepts of radiation-use efficiency, carbon balance, and partitioning</article-title>. <source>For Ecol Manage</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimmins</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seely</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welham</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scoullar</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Forecasting forest futures: a hybrid modelling approach to the assessment of sustainability of forest ecosystems and their values</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Earthscan Ltd.</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Girardin</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raulier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernier</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tardif</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Response of tree growth to a changing climate in boreal central Canada: A comparison of empirical, process-based, and hybrid modelling approaches</article-title>. <source>Ecol Modell</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>213</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spittlehouse</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adaptation to climate change in forest management</article-title>. <source>BC J Ecosys Manage</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Millar</surname> <given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephenson</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Climate change and forests of the future: managing in the face of uncertainty</article-title>. <source>Ecol Appl</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>2145</fpage>–<lpage>2151</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18213958</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimmins</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mailly</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seely</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Modelling forest ecosystem net primary production: the hybrid simulation approach used in FORECAST</article-title>. <source>Ecol Modell</source>.<year>1999</year>; <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimmins</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seely</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welham</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Yield decline in Chinese Fir plantations: A simulation investigation with implications for model complexity</article-title>. <source>Can J For Res</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>1615</fpage>–<lpage>1630</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seely</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welham</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimmins</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seebacher</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Testing the performance of FORECAST, a forest ecosystem model, against 29 years of field data in a Pseudotsuga menziesii plantation</article-title>. <source>Can J For Res</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>1808</fpage>–<lpage>1820</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seely</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welham</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimmins</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of a mechanistic approach to mixedwood modelling</article-title>. <source>For Chron</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seely</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welham</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Towards the application of soil organic matter as an indicator of forest ecosystem productivity: Deriving thresholds, developing monitoring systems, and evaluating practices</article-title>. <source>Ecol Indic</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>999</fpage>–<lpage>1008</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">IPCC</collab>. <chapter-title>Summary for Policymakers</chapter-title> In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Stocker</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plattner</surname> <given-names>G-K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tignor</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boschung</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>., editors. <source>Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Seely B, Arp P, Kimmins JP. A forest hydrology submodel for simulating the effect of management and climate change on stand water stress. In: Amaro A and Tomé M, editors. Proceedings of Empirical and Process-based models for forest, tree and stand growth simulation Oeiras, Portugal, 21–27, September 1997, Lisboa: Edições Salamandra; 1997. pp. 463–477.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Titus</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prescott</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maynard</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feller</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Post-harvest nitrogen cycling in clearcut and alternative silvicultural systems in a montane forest in coastal British Columbia</article-title>. <source>For Chron</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>844</fpage>–<lpage>859</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dordel</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seely</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simard</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Relationships between simulated water stress and mortality and growth rates in underplanted Toona ciliata Roem in subtropical Argentinean plantations</article-title>. <source>Ecol Modell</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>222</volume>: <fpage>3226</fpage>–<lpage>3235</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Priestley</surname> <given-names>CHB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>On the assessment of surface heat flux and evaporation using large-scale parameters</article-title>. <source>Monthly Weather Review</source>. <year>1972</year>; <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stagnitti</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parlange</surname> <given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Hydrology of a small wet catchment</article-title>. <source>Hydrol Process</source>. <year>1989</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Childs</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Use of the Priestly-Taylor evaporation equation for soil water limited conditions in a small forest clearcut</article-title> <source>Agric For Meteorol</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sumner</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Utility of Penman–Monteith, Priestley–Taylor, reference evapotranspiration, and pan evaporation methods to estimate pasture evapotranspiration</article-title>. <source>J Hydrol</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>308</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname> <given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vose</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Modeling potential evapotranspiration of two forested watersheds in the southern Appalachians</article-title>. <source>Biol Eng Trans</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>2067</fpage>–<lpage>2078</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ainsworth</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The response of photosynthesis and stomatal conductance to rising [CO<sub>2</sub>]: mechanisms and environmental interactions</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17263773</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keenan</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hollinger</surname> <given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohrer</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dragoni</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munger</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname> <given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Increase in forest water-use efficiency as atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations rise</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>499</volume>: <fpage>324</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature12291" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature12291</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23842499</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Battipaglia</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saurer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cherubini</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calfapietra</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname> <given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norby</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>ElevatedCO2 increases tree-level intrinsic water use efficiency: insights from carbon and oxygen isotope analyses in tree rings across three forest FACE sites</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>197</volume>: <fpage>544</fpage>–<lpage>554</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/nph.12044" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/nph.12044</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23215904</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname> <given-names>LCR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anand</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Probing for the influence of atmospheric CO2 and climate change on forest ecosystems across biomes</article-title>. <source>Glob Ecol Biogeogr</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franks</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amthor</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbour</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellsworth</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Sensitivity of plants to changing atmospheric CO2 concentration: from the geological past to the next century</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>197</volume>: <fpage>1077</fpage>–<lpage>1094</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/nph.12104" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/nph.12104</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23346950</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Medlyn</surname> <given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dursma</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeppel</surname> <given-names>MJB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Forest productivity under climate change: a checklist for evaluating model studies WIREs</article-title>. <source>Clim Change</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eamus</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jarvis</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name>. <article-title>The direct effects of increase in the global atmospheric CO2 concentration on natural and commercial temperate trees and forests</article-title>. <source>Adv Ecol Res</source>. <year>1989</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Norby</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wullschleger</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gunderson</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ceulemans</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Tree responses to rising CO2 in field experiments: implications for the future forest</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>714</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Körner</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asshoff</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bignucolo</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hättenschwiler</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keel</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peláez‐Riedl</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Carbon flux and growth in mature deciduous forest trees exposed to elevated CO<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>1360</fpage>–<lpage>1362</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16123297</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Girardin</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernier</surname> <given-names>PY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raulier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tardif</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conciatori</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>XJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Testing for a CO2 fertilization effect on growth of Canadian Boreal forests</article-title>. <source>J of Geophys Res</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>G01012</fpage>, 101029/2010JG001287.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barron-Gafford</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jenerette</surname> <given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamerlynck</surname> <given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huxman</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Temperature and precipitation controls over leaf- and ecosystem-level CO<sub>2</sub> flux along a woody plant encroachment gradient</article-title>. <source>Glob Chang Biol</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1389</fpage>–<lpage>1400</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pockman</surname> <given-names>WT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breshears</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cobb</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolb</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Mechanisms of plant survival and mortality during drought: why do some plants survive while others succumb to drought?</article-title> <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>178</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage>–<lpage>739</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2008.02436.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2008.02436.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18422905</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gholz</surname> <given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wedin</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smitherman</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harmon</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parton</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Long-term dynamics of pine and hardwood litter in contrasting environments: toward a global model of decomposition</article-title>. <source>Glob Chang Biol</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>751</fpage>–<lpage>765</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harmon</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of global change on litter decomposition in terrestrial ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Acta Ecologica Sinica</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1549</fpage>–<lpage>1563</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Factors influencing leaf litter decomposition: an intersite decomposition experiment across China</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>311</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniels</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maertens</surname> <given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stan</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCloskey</surname> <given-names>SPJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cochrane</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Direct and indirect impacts of climate change on forests: three case studies from British Columbia</article-title>. <source>Can J Plant Pathol</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogg</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michaelian</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impacts of regional drought on the productivity, dieback, and biomass of western Canadian aspen forests</article-title>. <source>Can J For Res</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1373</fpage>–<lpage>1384</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKinnon</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meidinger</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klinka</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Use of the biogeoclimatic ecosystem classification system in British Columbia</article-title>. <source>For Chron</source>. <year>1992</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stokes</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smiley</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>An introduction to tree-ring dating</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>; <year>1968</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krusic</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>ARSTAN v 41d: A tree-ring standardization program based on de-trending and autoregressive time series modeling, with interactive graphics</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Tree-Ring Laboratory, Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogg</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name>. <article-title>A simple soil moisture index for representing multi-year drought impacts on aspen productivity in the western Canadian interior</article-title>. <source>Agric For Meteorol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>178–179</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlowski</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pallardy</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Acclimation and adaptive responses of woody plants to environmental stresses</article-title>. <source>Bot Rev</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>270</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seely</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimmin</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welham</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scoullar</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ecosystem management models: defining stand-level sustainability, exploring stand-level stewardship</article-title>. <source>J For</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Nelson H, Zielke K, Bancroft B, Brown C, Cohen S, Davis R, et al. Validating Impacts, Exploring Vulnerabilities, and Developing Robust Adaptive Strategies under the Kamloops Future Forest Strategy. Final Report. 2011. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.symmetree.ca/ftp/Public/Climate%20Change/Kamloops%20TSA/K2%20FFESC%20Report%202011_Jan%2031-12%20FINAL.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.symmetree.ca/ftp/Public/Climate%20Change/Kamloops%20TSA/K2%20FFESC%20Report%202011_Jan%2031-12%20FINAL.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spittlehouse</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name>. <article-title>A growing season water balance model applied to two Douglas-fir stands</article-title>. <source>Water Resour Res</source>. <year>1981</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1651</fpage>–<lpage>1656</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flanagan</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Variation in water potential, hydraulic characteristics and water source use in montane Douglas-fir and lodgepole pine trees in southwestern Alberta and consequences for seasonal changes in photosynthetic capacity</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiol</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/treephys/tpr136" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/treephys/tpr136</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22318220</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meinzer</surname> <given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Domec</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Vertical stratification of soil water storage and release dynamics in Pacific Northwest coniferous forests</article-title>. <source>Agric For Meteorol</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lucash</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olszyk</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tingey</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Seasonal patterns of photosynthesis in Douglas fir seedlings during the third and fourth year of exposure to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> and temperature</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Case</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fine-scale variation in growth relationships of Douglas-fir, North Cascade Range, Washington</article-title>. <source>Can J For Res</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>2743</fpage>–<lpage>2755</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dykstra</surname> <given-names>GF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Photosynthesis and Carbon dioxide transfer resistance of Lodgepole pine seedlings in relation to irradiance, temperature and water potential</article-title>. <source>Can J For Res</source>. <year>1974</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coops</surname> <given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waring</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name>. <article-title>A process-based approach to estimate lodgepole pine (pinus contorta Dougl) distribution in the Pacific Northwest under climate change</article-title>. <source>Clim Change</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinshausen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calvin</surname> <given-names>KV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kainuma</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamarque</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The RCP greenhouse gas concentrations and their extension from 1765 to 2300</article-title>. <source>Clim Change</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boisvenue</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Running</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impacts of climate change on natural forest productivity–evidence since the middle of the 20th century</article-title>. <source>Glob Chang Biol</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>862</fpage>–<lpage>882</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritts</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Tree rings and climate</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>; <year>1976</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anchukaitis</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname> <given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaganov</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grissino-Mayer</surname> <given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Forward modeling of regional scale tree-ring patterns in the southeastern United States and the recent influence of summer drought</article-title>. <source>Geophys Res Lett</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>L04705</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lara</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maguire</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Modeling patterns between drought and tree biomass growth from dendrochronological data: A multilevel approach</article-title>. <source>Agric For Meteorol</source>. <volume>178–179</volume>: <fpage>140</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pederson</surname> <given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fagre</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graumlich</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Long-duration drought variability and impacts on ecosystem services: A case study from Glacier National Park, Montana</article-title>. <source>Earth Inter</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Littell</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name> <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tjoelkler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Douglas-fir growth in mountain ecosystems: water limits tree growth from stand to region</article-title>. <source>Ecol Monogr</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>368</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadley</surname> <given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veblen</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stand response to western spruce budworm and Douglas-fir bark beetle outbreaks, Colorado Front Range</article-title>. <source>Can J For Res</source>. <year>1993</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>479</fpage>–<lpage>493</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Griesbauer</surname> <given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regional and ecological patterns in interior Douglas-fir climate–growth relationships in British Columbia, Canada</article-title>. <source>Can J For Res</source>. <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Case</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Growth-climate Relations of Lodgepole Pine in the North Cascades National Park, Washington</article-title>. <source>Northwest Sci</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A drought-induced pervasive increase in tree mortality across Canada’s boreal forests</article-title> <source>Nat Clim Chang</source>. <year>2011</year>; 101038/NCLIMATE: <volume>1293</volume>, <fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>471</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname> <given-names>LCR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anand</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leithead</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Recent widespread tree growth decline despite increasing atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>5</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>e11543</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0011543" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0011543</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20657763</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Grady</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname> <given-names>PJM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinkard</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tissue</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Thirsty roots and hungry leaves: unravelling the roles of carbon and water dynamics in tree mortality</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>200</volume>: <fpage>294</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/nph.12451" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/nph.12451</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24050630</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell</surname> <given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sevanto</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Our limited ability to predict vegetation dynamics under water stress</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>200</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/nph.12450" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/nph.12450</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24050631</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0135034.ref085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melillo</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steudler</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lux</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Soil warming, carbon–nitrogen interactions, and forest carbon budgets</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>9508</fpage>–<lpage>9512</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1018189108" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1018189108</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21606374</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>